<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet  href="http://www.blogger.com/styles/atom.css" type="text/css"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:openSearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearchrss/1.0/" xmlns:blogger="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0"><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878</id><updated>2022-11-16T23:19:53.079-06:00</updated><title type="text">Siris</title><subtitle type="html">&lt;em&gt;Seiren chruseien ex ouranothen kremasantes&lt;/em&gt;</subtitle><link rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#feed" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/posts/default"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/"><link rel="hub" href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/"><link rel="next" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default?start-index=26&amp;max-results=25"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><generator version="7.00" uri="http://www.blogger.com">Blogger</generator><openSearch:totalResults>10945</openSearch:totalResults><openSearch:startIndex>1</openSearch:startIndex><openSearch:itemsPerPage>25</openSearch:itemsPerPage><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-7849988534063726581</id><published>2022-11-15T09:48:00.001-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-15T09:48:34.022-06:00</updated><title type="text">Doctor Universalis</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Today is the feast of St. Albert of Lauingen, Doctor of the Church; he is often known by the name he was given even in his own time, Albertus Magnus, Albert the Great. From his &lt;i&gt;De corpore domini&lt;/i&gt;, on the Eucharist:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;That it is nothing but grace is shown by the name, because it is and is named the Eucharist, which means &quot;good grace&quot;. Although we receive grace in all the sacraments, there is in this sacrament the whole of grace, which we see, touch, and taste. Thus Zechariah 4.7 says about this sacrament, &quot;And he will give equal grace to its grace.&quot; Whatever graces are scattered to be gathered in all the [other] sacraments and virtues, the whole is found here together in one grace. This is signified by the omer, which was the measure of the manna, which was sufficient for each one. [Exodus 16.16-17]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the measure which is sufficient for man's salvation can only be that which contains the grace in which the whole Christ is contained....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[Albert the Great, &lt;i&gt;On the Body of the Lord&lt;/i&gt;, Surmanski, OP, tr., CUA Press (Washington, DC: 2017) pp. 31-32.]&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/7849988534063726581/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/doctor-universalis.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/7849988534063726581"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/7849988534063726581"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/doctor-universalis.html" title="Doctor Universalis"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-2073511057174275423</id><published>2022-11-14T22:19:00.000-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-14T22:19:07.816-06:00</updated><title type="text">Two Poem Drafts</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;Knowing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The world flows in, I ball it up,&lt;br /&gt;I bounce it here and there;&lt;br /&gt;I play with it like string and cup&lt;br /&gt;and toss it in the air.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The world flows in, I shape it so,&lt;br /&gt;I build with it like clay,&lt;br /&gt;and then I outward let it flow,&lt;br /&gt;returned to light of day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Words of Ameny&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The collected words, the gathered verses,&lt;br /&gt;the heart-searching utterances &lt;br /&gt;of the priest of Elephantopolis,&lt;br /&gt;Ameny son of Ankhu:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The realm is destroyed and none care;&lt;br /&gt;none weep the end, nor do any speak it.&lt;br /&gt;None are free from evildoing, no, not one;&lt;br /&gt;all do it and all suffer it.&lt;br /&gt;Some are learned enough to understand it;&lt;br /&gt;none are roused enough to speak against it.&lt;br /&gt;Everyone only loves their own utterances;&lt;br /&gt;crooked of heart, all honest speech is abandoned.&lt;br /&gt;Each mouth says only, &quot;I want.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;What past ages built is torn and ruined;&lt;br /&gt;rebuke is answered with knife in the belly.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;May Thoth, the god-appeaser, vindicate me;&lt;br /&gt;may Khonsu, who reckons Truth, favor me;&lt;br /&gt;may Irdes in the holy place defend me!&lt;br /&gt;As for men, their hearts are selfish;&lt;br /&gt;as for men, their hearts are unsteady.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The brother is unveiled as an enemy;&lt;br /&gt;to find an honest man, one must find a stranger.&lt;br /&gt;Every face is set against every face.&lt;br /&gt;Evil roams the land; no end can be found to it.&lt;br /&gt;Where is found recover for the sick?&lt;br /&gt;Where is found wind for the sail?&lt;br /&gt;Where is found homecoming after long journey?&lt;br /&gt;Where is found the land where men are living gods?&lt;br /&gt;Seek out the answer, even if you weep;&lt;br /&gt;life is transitory, but the wise seek what endures.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/2073511057174275423/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/two-poem-drafts.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2073511057174275423"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2073511057174275423"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/two-poem-drafts.html" title="Two Poem Drafts"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-7783949372054810567</id><published>2022-11-13T19:11:00.002-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-14T16:31:51.834-06:00</updated><title type="text">Logres XI</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/logres-x.html&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;continuing Book II&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chapter 4&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the end of the tournament, Epiphany Eve having arrived, there gathered together all the great men of from around about, whether of the lay orders of knight and king or the holy orders of priest and bishop, for a trial of the sword. After the singing of &lt;i&gt;Te Deum Laudamus&lt;/i&gt;, many barons and lords tried their hand, and all failed, until Arthur stepped up to the sword and drew it easy, giving it over to Bishop Bedwin. Then the house of Sir Ector, the houses of Duke Corneus and Sir Don, the houses of Sir Ulfius and of Sir Brastias, and all their supporters, as well as all the common people, stood with Arthur, but the other lords and barons were in great shock and disbelief, and then in great anger, saying that no one of such low degree was deserving to be king.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Shall we be overgoverned by a boy of no blood?&quot; they said to each other in wrath. &quot;This is surely some trick.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But Bishop Bedwin said, with great hardness in his voice, &quot;Though he were even a shepherd-boy, younger than his brothers, the Lord might raise him up, and what man is there who could gainsay it? But I shall show you. Arthur, take the sword and return it to the stone.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arthur did as he was told. The barons and lords again tried to take it from the stone, but found it as fastly bound as it had been. Arthur, however, again drew it easily.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Will you then be against the Lord's will?&quot; said the bishop to the barons.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The barons and the lords were for the most part not moved, but wary of the influence of Sir Ector and of Duke Corneus, and not wanting to defy the Church directly in the presence of the common people, they said, &quot;Good sir, we are not against the Lord's will, but surely the boy is not old enough yet.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To this, Bishop Bedwin replied, &quot;The one who has chosen him knows who he is.&quot; But still the barons demanded that another trial be held at Candlemas. And some of the more clever among them added that by this means the trial could be witnessed by men from more distant lands. This was then agreed, and it was agreed as well that until then, ten knights should guard the sword, so that, day or night, there should always be five guarding it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After all of this, Sir Don came to Bishop Bedwin and Sir Ector, saying, &quot;We must take great care, or the boy may meet with a mishap that is not a mishap.&quot; From that moment on, Sir Kay, Sir Lucan, or Sir Bedivere was with Arthur, no matter the time and no matter the place. The three were the first of the Companions of Arthur.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus at Candlemas the trial was held again, with men coming from every part of every realm around. Again the barons and the lords attempted to draw the sword, and again Arthur drew it easily. The prelates and the common folk all shouted acclamation, saying, &quot;Who shall deny that Arthur is the choice of the Lord?&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the barons and the lords replied, &quot;Surely we must be sure that there is no better. Let the trial be held again, this time at Pascha, that any man who wishes to try may try it.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bishop Bedwin said in response, &quot;If we hold a trial yet again at Pascha, will you accept the choice?&quot; And when they affirmed this, he granted their request.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus the trial was held again on Easter Eve, and again Arthur alone drew the sword. Bishop Bedwin spoke at length of the sobriety and prudence he found in Arthur. Then the barons and lords consulted among themselves and came to the bishop.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;What impediment to the Lord's choice do you bring this time? Surely the boy should already be crowned,&quot; the bishop said.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;We do not impede it at all,&quot; said the representatives of the lords, &quot;but you have seen his character and we have not. Thus let him be crowned, if it be the Lord's will, but let it wait until Pentecost, that we may ourselves behold his character, and may also spend the time in prayer.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus Bishop Bedwin, having taken counsel with Arthur and Sir Ector, agreed that Arthur's crowning and sacring would be delayed until Pentecost. Then the barons and lords brought fine gifts to Arthur as tokens of good faith; but in reality, they wished to see if he could bought and bribed. However, all that they gave him, Arthur at the advice of Sir Ector gave away. Horses and fine tapestries he gave to knights, and jewels to merchants and their wives, and gold and silver to the poor, and his fame among the common people grew. And indeed, some of the lords and barons were won over by this, either because they themselves received gifts, or because they found him to be a noble young man in heart, or because they did not wish to cross directly one who was increasingly well liked.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chapter 5&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thus all things continued until Whitsuntide. Again on Whitsun Eve, the sword was tried, and again only Arthur could draw it from the stone. But this time the Bishop Bedwin had ready the crown and the scepter and holy oil. In the view of the people and with the consent of the barons, he knighted Arthur. Then he adorned Sir Arthur with royal vestments, and bringing him before all, he said, &quot;Here is the man God has chosen to be your king. But if any of you have reason why he should not be made king, let him now speak or else hold his peace.&quot; But none dared speak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then Bishop Bedwin, showing the sword to Sir Arthur, said,&amp;nbsp; &quot;This is the sword with which you will keep justice in defense of the holy Church and to maintain right and the Christian faith. If you will, here before all the orders of Christendom, swear to God, and to our Lady, Saint Mary, and to Saint Peter and to all the saints, to save and uphold truth and peace in the land, and to use your power to keep justice, come forth and take this sword of your election by God.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then Sir Arthur and many of the people were greatly affected and wept as Sir Arthur took the sword. He said, &quot;As truly as God is Lord over all, may he grant grace and power to do as you have said.&quot; Then he was led to the altar and laid it thereon. Bishop Bedwin crowned and anointed him with the same rite that Bishop Fastidius had used for King Uther Pendragon. Then High Mass was sung, the first Mass of the reign of King Arthur.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When the people left the church, they marveled, because there was nothing where the stone of the sword had been.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then King Arthur held court, and lords and barons and knights came to give their service. Many complaints were also brought to King Arthur of wrongs that had been done since the death of King Uther Pendragon, for many knights and ladies had been bereft of their lands. The king gave judgment in all such cases, and he became known for his fairness and impartiality. He also created the officers of his household; Sir Kay was made seneschal and steward, Sir Ulfius was made chamberlain, Sir Lucan was made butler, Sir Bedivere was made constable, and Sir Brastias was made warden of the north. Then King Arthur began establishing his magistracy over all the counties and lordships around Londinium, and even into Cambrian lands.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All things went well until the middle of August.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chapter 6&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the middle of August, King Arthur held a great feast and royal court at Caerleon, and invitations were sent far and wide. There came King Lot of Lothian, King Urien of Rheged and Gore, King Caradoc Strongarm of Stangore, known far and wide as the husband of Queen Tegau Goldenhearted, King Yder the Elder of Scotland, and the young King Anguish of Ireland. There also came a king named Malaguin or Maelgwn, but known more often as the Tall King or the King of a Hundred Knights; he was the king who is known elsewhere to have at first opposed St. Padarn and St. Tydecho, but who eventually gave them lands and became a great supporter to them. And each of these kings came with their knights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When they were all assembled, King Arthur showered gifts upon them and invited them to a great feast. But the kings, regarding him as being a beardless boy of low birth and not a suitable king for such a realm as Logres, held all that he gave them and all that he did in disdain. They refused his gifts, saying that they came instead to give him gifts, namely, a sharp sword between the neck and the shoulders. Then King Arthur withdrew to a strong tower in Caerleon and they besieged him. With King Arthur were five hundred good men. But with the six kings there were twenty-seven hundred knights.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For fifteen days the six kings besieged King Arthur, for the tower to which he had withdrawn was well victualed. And on the fifteenth day, Merlin came, showing himself with wonders and marvels in the town, so that rumor of him spread like fire all around. Hearing of this, the kings at the advice of King Urien sent for him. They met him at a palace on the banks of the river outside the town, in a tower that overlooked the water and had a view in the distance of the walls of Caerleon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;What do you think of this beardless boy,&quot; asked King Urien, &quot;whom the bishop of Trinovant has crowned a king without our license and without the assent of the people of the land? What do you propose as our best means of dealing with him?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But Merlin replied, &quot;Bishop Bedwin has done well, and could not have done better than he did.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The kings in turn responded, &quot;How can it possibly be as you say? Many there are who are of higher lineage or of greater experience, many who are stronger or wiser. No man knows whence this boy comes, for Sir Ector is merely his foster father.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;You say what you wish were true,&quot; said Merlin, &quot;but his lineage is higher than any of yours.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;King Lot replied, &quot;You have gone mad.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;This boy Arthur,&quot; said Merlin, &quot;is the son of Uther Pendragon by Igraine of Tintagel.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;You are saying he is a bastard,&quot; the kings replied.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Not so,&quot; said Merlin. &quot;He was begotten after Gorlois had died and he was born in wedlock after Uther had married Igraine. I will tell you more than this. Those who oppose him, he will defeat. Even to his dying day, no one who rises against him shall have victory against him, though they had many more men, and much better men, than any that you are able to bring. He is, by right, the King of Britain.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then some of the kings, such as King Urien and the King of a Hundred Knights, were disturbed. But King Lot, laughing in scorn, said to them all, &quot;He lies. Is he not often said to be the Devil's son? Like his father, he lies.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, Merlin persuaded the kings that an embassy should be received under truce so that the matter might be discussed. Thus he went to the tower, where he was received joyfully by Sir Ulfius and brought to the king.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Merlin told them all that had happened, and said, &quot;Do not fear, my king. The days before you are difficult, but you will triumph. Go forth boldly, as a king and not as a supplicant, and answer them in all things as their lord and chieftain. For they will kneel before you, whether they will or nill.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;to be continued&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/7783949372054810567/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/logres-xi.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/7783949372054810567"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/7783949372054810567"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/logres-xi.html" title="Logres XI"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-6447389244033723342</id><published>2022-11-12T10:22:00.000-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-12T10:22:04.488-06:00</updated><title type="text">Links of Note</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;* Christopher Kaczor, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wordonfire.org/articles/fellows/magical-thinking-free-will-is-an-illusion/&quot;&gt;Magical Thinking: Free Will Is an Illusion&lt;/a&gt;, at &quot;Word on Fire&quot;; a humorous story.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* David Corey, &lt;a href=&quot;https://comment.org/politics-friendship-and-the-search-for-meaning/&quot;&gt;Politics, Friendship, and the Search for Meaning&lt;/a&gt;, at &quot;Comment&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* There has been a fair amount of controversy recently over Pierre Manent's &lt;a href=&quot;https://compactmag.com/article/macintyre-s-flight-from-politics&quot;&gt;MacIntyre's Flight from Politics&lt;/a&gt;. I think MacIntyre has more resources for addressing the issue than Manent's summary suggests, but the MacIntyreans who are criticizing it are often glossing over the important (and, I think, deliberate) ways in which MacIntyre certainly is an 'Aristotelianism of the opposition' in contrast to what we find in Aristotle or Thomas Aquinas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Alice MacLachlan, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/MACFDA-3&quot;&gt;Fiduciary Duties and the Ethics of Public Apology&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Daniel McCarthy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://chroniclesmagazine.org/featured/remembering-michael-oakeshott/&quot;&gt;Remembering Michael Oakeshott&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* James Mumford, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newsweek.com/are-human-rights-merely-matter-perception-opinion-1753923&quot;&gt;Are Human Rights Merely a Matter of Perception?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Ed Lamb, &lt;a href=&quot;https://antigonejournal.com/2022/11/civil-disobedience-socrates-crito/&quot;&gt;Civil Disobedience: A Puzzle in Plato's Crito&lt;/a&gt;, at &quot;Antigone&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* James Franklin, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/FRARLP&quot;&gt;Resurrecting logical probability&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Oliver D. Crisp, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/scottish-journal-of-theology/article/infant-baptism-and-the-disposition-to-saving-faith/924A23BEC21F97B81C5071E8DA65F290&quot;&gt;Infant baptism and the disposition to saving faith&lt;/a&gt;, on the Reformed theology of infant baptism; this was a very interesting paper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Huaping Lu-Adler, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/LUAKOL-3&quot;&gt;Kant on Language and the (Self-)Development of Reason&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Jonas Faria Costa, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/philosophy/article/on-gregariousness/61DE330CB037355D41BA2939BA029766&quot;&gt;On Gregariousness&lt;/a&gt;, looks at human sociality in contexts in which we are not directly interacting, like at a coffee shop to which one might go to be around people, but in which one mostly does one's own thing. As the author notes, this is not considered very often, and most accounts of human sociality don't really shed any light on it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Jonathan Simon and Colin Marshall, &lt;a href=&quot;https://quod.lib.umich.edu/e/ergo/12405314.0004.029/--mendelssohn-kant-and-the-mereotopology-of-immortality?rgn=main;view=fulltext&quot;&gt;Mendelssohn, Kant, and the Mereotopology of Immortality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Giulia Martina, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/MARHWT&quot;&gt;How we talk about smells&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/6447389244033723342/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/links-of-note_12.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/6447389244033723342"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/6447389244033723342"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/links-of-note_12.html" title="Links of Note"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-931495232099524158</id><published>2022-11-11T12:27:00.003-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-11T23:43:44.681-06:00</updated><title type="text">Dashed Off XXVII</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This begins the notebook that was started in December 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;******&amp;nbsp;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;incipit/desinit as constructed by comparison of changes&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Metaphysics 1056b4-5: If 'many' is placed in contrariety to 'one', impossible things follow.&lt;br /&gt;1056b33-35: &quot;The one is opposed to the many as measure is to measurable.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the child &quot;guided by the inner teacher&quot; (Montessori)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the joy of strolling as a mild exercise in learning&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the charm of social life as diversity of people in harmonious interaction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Historically, secularization is always accompanied by (but not caused by) a kind of atrophy of reason.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the regrounding or re-radicating of passions and virtues as part of evangelism&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;barbarism as &quot;the absence of standards to which appeal can be made&quot; (Ortega y Gassett)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;beauty as something that invites thought&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Acts 4:31 -- filled with the Holy Spirit and spoke the Logos of God boldly&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Simple ethical actions are signs and symbols of greater ethical actions.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Faith may express itself in the midst of any and all of the passions.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Fortune favors the diversifier.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nothing can be discovered out of nothing.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;In scholarship as in all else, nothing is made from nothing.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sovereignty must itself be a kind of right, or it is not sovereignty.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To arbitrate disputes presupposes the authority of reason.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bentham's &quot;Anarchical Fallacies&quot; and &quot;The Necessity of an Omnipotent Legislature&quot; as laying out the real structure of utilitarianism&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the monitorial system of education&lt;br /&gt;the method of learning by teaching&lt;br /&gt;plastic platypus learning&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;teaching structures: professional, monitorial, democratic&lt;br /&gt;learning structures: receptive, apprenticed, autonomous ?&lt;br /&gt;-- a school is a combining of a teaching structure with a learning structure&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Athanasius Kircher gets a lot of flak, but it's often forgotten that Kircher's view was that hieroglyphics can't actually be translated -- his paraphrases are not intended as translations in the proper sense. And he did recognize that there could be a phonetic value for a hieroglyph, the foundation of later work, and he was the first to recognize that Coptic was related to demotic; both of these were elements necessary to the actual discovery of how to read hieroglyphs.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Hieroglyphs are complicated by the existence of honorific transposition -- divine things, like the solar sign, are elevated or moved to the front out of respect.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;progress as converting genius to method&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the 'link' between the I and the eye&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dates for the 'Fall of Rome'&lt;br /&gt;[Fall of Republic]&lt;br /&gt;31 BC -- Actium&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;27 BC -- Principate&lt;br /&gt;[Fall of Empire]&lt;br /&gt;---[Fall of Caesarean Empire]&lt;br /&gt;180 -- Death of Marcus Aurelius and Succession of Commodus&lt;br /&gt;312 -- Conversion of Constantine&lt;br /&gt;378 -- Adrianople and Death of Valens&lt;br /&gt;410 -- Sack of Rome by Visigoths&lt;br /&gt;455 -- Sack of Rome by Vandals&lt;br /&gt;476 -- Sack of Rome and Deposition of Romulus Augustulus by Odoacer&lt;br /&gt;---[Fall of Byzantine Empire]&lt;br /&gt;1204 -- Latin Sack of Constantinople in Fourth Crusade&lt;br /&gt;1453 -- Ottoman Conquest of Constantinople&lt;br /&gt;---[Utter End]&lt;br /&gt;1806 -- Last Holy Roman Emperor &lt;br /&gt;1917 -- Last Czar&lt;br /&gt;********&lt;br /&gt;All of these are right; Republics and Empires are many-layered things, and with each, something important was stripped away and sometimes replaced.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;All falls of nations are either defeat by external force, defeat by internal force, or moral corruption. Nothing else is actually any kind of fall at all. Declines are likewise multiplications of problems related to these.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;If we think of myth as meaning-making story, we can ask what the myth would be that is commensurate with human life.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;There are clearly multiple ways to assess disparate impact and no reason to think they would all agree; thus one should always ascertain the relevant standard.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Economies arise out of communications.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;visible shapes as color-dependent, tangible shape as resistance-dependent&lt;br /&gt;-- The key question: Do we perhaps link these by a sense of color (at least sometimes) being resistant to the eye? Or is it something else like constant conjunction or abstract analogy?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;acquired dispositions of institutions -&amp;gt; institutions having a quasi-character, and thus quasi-virtues and quasi-vices&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Anyone who truly loves virtue will love divinity, its exemplar.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;plot-focused ethical reasoning vs. episode-focused ethical reasoning&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nations rise from small springs and fall in cataracts small and great.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;trace-fossil formation and the major genera of trace fossils&lt;br /&gt;(1) left in soft-sediment surface: Cubichnia&lt;br /&gt;(2) dwelling structure formation (e.g., burrowing or boring): Domichnia&lt;br /&gt;(3) sediment disturbance in deposit-food search: Fodinichnia&lt;br /&gt;(4) surface disturbance in grazing-food search: Pascichnia&lt;br /&gt;(5) locomotion: Repichnia&lt;br /&gt;[These are Seiacher's and account for most trace fossis , but there are others, e.g., Colichnia, arising from making structures for breeding activities, like bee cells), and people propose others from time to time.]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the palaetiology of ideas&lt;br /&gt;arguments as environments of ideas&lt;br /&gt;ideas as undergoing selection within argumentational environments&lt;br /&gt;manifest contradictoriness or impossibility in a context // extinction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Multiplicity can in a certain fashion be attributed to the noncomposite by expression (how it is reflected, received, etc., or by assumption).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;geometrical diagram as speech act: locution (line and circle), illocutionary force (interpretation), perlocutionary effect (for illustration or for proof)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tengwar and Lodwick's Universal Alphabet&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;word, as quasi-form, structuring world, as quasi-material&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The ebook is a more fragile, not a less fragile, technology, than a codex or scroll, and whether it is more or less accessible depends on environmental factors, not itself.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the 'practical minimum of concession' as a key idea in planning&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Skepticism requires that we be able to say that such-and-such does not appear to have sufficient ground or reason.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;One often finds in theology that one doctrine serves as an allegory for another.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Poorly analyzed experiments are worse evidence than trustworthy anecdotes.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;arrow of time // dominance of matter over antimatter&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The meaning of a myth depends in part on its ritual context.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the economy of myths -- myths are one of the things we exchange&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Academic papers are not primarily research instruments but career instruments.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;pandemics and defense-in-depth&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Cuisines spread by 'fast-food-izing'.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the moral-juridical presence of Christ in the sacrament of reconciliation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;being married before God as the base for the presence of Christ in the sacrament of matrimony&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Christ's Baptism as a symbol of His Incarnation.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;repentance unto friendship&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;A martial nobility and stubborn commons, possessed of arms, tenacious of property, and collected into constitutional assemblies, form the only balance capable of preserving a free constitution against the enterprises of an aspiring prince.&quot; Gibbon&lt;br /&gt;&quot;The principles of a free constitution are irrecoverable, lost, when the legislative power is nominated by the executive.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;&quot;In elective monarchies, the vacancy of the throne is a moment big with danger and mischief.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;&quot;Wit and valour are qualifications more easily ascertained than humanity or the love of justice.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;&quot;But the power of instruction is seldom of much efficacy, except in those happy dispositions where it is almost superfluous.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;&quot;Of all our passions and appetites, the love of power is of the most imperious and unsociable nature, since the pride of one man requires the submission of the multitude.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;All lovers are fighters.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;symbolism &amp;amp; allegory : virtue ethics :: critical exegesis : deontology :: x : consequentialism&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;'artfully to collect in his own person all the scattered rays of civil jurisdiction'&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;consular powers&lt;br /&gt;(1) superintendance of ceremony&lt;br /&gt;(2) levy and command of legions&lt;br /&gt;(3) reception of ambassadors&lt;br /&gt;(4) presidence in assembly, both senatorial and popular&lt;br /&gt;tribunitian powers&lt;br /&gt;(1) veto&lt;br /&gt;(2) convene plebeian assembly&lt;br /&gt;(3) summon senate&lt;br /&gt;(4) propose legislation&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;One of the most important goals in constitutional law is to force things into visibility -- literally anything can be abused by human ingenuity, but it is harder to abuse them in full light of day.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;emperor (imperator): general + consul + tribune + censor + pontiff&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;One cannot properly understand the Church as People of God without understanding it as societas perfecta.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Solidarity primarily works by other routes than obligation.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;immersed life, study, reparative reconstruction&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Genesis creation story places God before all the cosmogonical origins and supposed divinities of pagan myth.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the Shabaka Text ('Memphite Theology'): thought -&amp;gt; word -&amp;gt; world&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;grace as participation in divine missions&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Law intrinsically applies a higher rational order than itself.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;law as humanitarian tradition -&amp;gt; human common good -&amp;gt; God as primal good&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;'this rational and bloodless sacrifice, for our own sins and for the ignorance of the people'&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Empathy can be valuable, but it is not itself good judgment.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Boredom sometimes repulses us more than pain.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;constant polynomial : s orbital :: linear polynomial : p orbital :: quadratic polynomial : d orbital :: cubic polynomial : f orbital&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the transcendental unity of the history of philosophy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Forgiveness is not a release of resentment; the latter is sometimes a removal of an impediment to forgiveness, but one can forgive where there is no resentment at all, and release resentment without forgiveness.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Nobody confines their forgiveness to people who deserve it, if only because we are often not well positioned for assessing whether they deserve it.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;No one has a right to be forgiven, but no one can be charitable without a willingness to forgive.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Forgiving is never condoning -- they are completely opposed acts.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;One reason to be ready to forgive is to avoid self-righteousness, which is one of the worse things that can befall a person.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Philosophy is per aliud wisdom participating per se wisdom, contingent wisdom participating necessary wisdom, etc.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Note that in Psalm 148, the angels and host are put before sun, moon, and stars. (Compare Turretin on this.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ps 148:5 -- &quot;he commanded and they were created&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the sentiments of the people vs the professions of the people&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Moving from sets to categories emphasizes functions over membership/inclusion.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the classic problem of organizational ethics: good intentions deteriorating the ethically constrained functioning of the system&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Marriage is not a commitment but a union.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;finality as a transcendental&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Possibilities are represented in myths as other places or other times.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;Had it not been love which is the basis of all relationships, it was impossible to promote peace, respect others. In fact, meaningful life on earth would have been impossible.&quot; Mawere&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;fantasy and the literalization of striking metaphors&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A very great deal of Chinese Imperial history seems to consist of the Confucians losing whenever they were most clearly and inconveniently right.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;generic experience, structured experience, directed experience, participative experience&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Every giving creates signs: giving as the root of semiosis.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;As the Incarnation was made possible by the Virgin's Yes, so too every Eucharist morally depends on her Yes.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;As Israel in suffering was sign of Christ in Passion, it therefore was also the sign of Christ in Eucharist.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Crucifixion - Session - Mass as one act of sacrifice (morally, juridically, and really)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;'deism of the Cross' in certain accounts of Christ's sacrifice&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;contracts as agreeing on ways to express one's rights&lt;br /&gt;-- this is the correct idea that social contract theory misplaces&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The senses do not distinguish substance and accident at all; when we recognize that accidents require substances, we are not starting with an experience of accidents and concluding to substances beyond them, but starting with an experience of accidents-in-substances and concluding to substance within it.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;partial substance (hand)&lt;br /&gt;substance (man)&lt;br /&gt;supersubstance (cosmos)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Aquinas's use of mereological terminology to organize virtues works because the part-whole relation is relativity without separation.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;incomplete induction as credibility-lending&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;more-and-less as hypercategorical&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;hypercategorical transcendental : convertible transcendental :: change (incomplete act) : actuality (complete act)&lt;br /&gt;-- this is a conjoined rather than separate analogy, because change is hypercategorical and actuality is convertible&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;three kinds of evidence:&lt;br /&gt;actuality anticipative of actuality&lt;br /&gt;actuality reminiscent of actuality&lt;br /&gt;actuality suggestive of actuality&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;common good : Matthew :: subsidiarity : Mark :: human dignity : Luke :: solidarity : John&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Freedom of conscience does not have to be asserted and vindicated for everybody because matters to which conscience is applied are not all the same in their relations either to conscience or to freedom; a finer-grained analysis is necessary.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the right to religious freedom (Dignitatis Humanae)&lt;br /&gt;(1) all should have [some kind of] immunity from coercion in religious matters&lt;br /&gt;(2) that no one should be forced to act against conscience in religious matters within due limits [i.e., as long as due public order is preserved]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Human dignity, solidarity, subsidiarity, and common good are four ways human beings are not separate from each other.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Because of Adam's sin, our dignity is mixed with baseness, our solidarity with discord, our subsidiarity with rebellion, and our common good with mutual temptation.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Parenthood begins prior to birth; this is much more important than usually recognized.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;If mathematics or logic are ever explanatory, there must be real formal causes.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To deny the principle of sufficient reason is to hold that there are possibilities that are not any kind of possibility, and are thus unspecifiable.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Liberty is protected by mediating institutions.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;choices as pure formal means&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/931495232099524158/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/dashed-off-xxvii.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/931495232099524158"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/931495232099524158"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/dashed-off-xxvii.html" title="Dashed Off XXVII"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-5143874646410373931</id><published>2022-11-10T10:27:00.001-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-10T10:32:12.662-06:00</updated><title type="text">Lion of the Latin Church</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Today is the feast of St. Leo I the Great, Pope and Doctor of the Church. From one of his Easter sermons (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newadvent.org/fathers/360372.htm&quot;&gt;Sermon 72&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt; Because therefore there is no place for ignorance in faithful ears, the seed of the Word which consists of the preaching of the Gospel, ought to grow in the soil of your heart, so that, when choking thorns and thistles have been removed, the plants of holy thoughts and the buds of right desires may spring up freely into fruit. For the cross of Christ, which was set up for the salvation of mortals, is both a mystery and an example : a sacrament where by the Divine power takes effect, an example whereby man's devotion is excited: for to those who are rescued from the prisoner's yoke Redemption further procures the power of following the way of the cross by imitation. For if the world's wisdom so prides itself in its error that every one follows the opinions and habits and whole manner of life of him whom he has chosen as his leader, how shall we share in the name of Christ save by being inseparably united to Him, Who is, as He Himself asserted, the Way, the Truth, and the Life? the Way that is of holy living, the Truth of Divine doctrine, and the Life of eternal happiness.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/5143874646410373931/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/lion-of-latin-church.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/5143874646410373931"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/5143874646410373931"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/lion-of-latin-church.html" title="Lion of the Latin Church"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-7136001866772932591</id><published>2022-11-09T19:37:00.004-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-09T19:43:27.798-06:00</updated><title type="text">High Tea</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Every so often, you get accidental clusters of similar events and, as it happens, in three different places in the past two weeks I have come across people getting the usage of 'high tea' wrong. This is, after confusing peerage titles and feudal titles, one of the most common Americanisms that seems to spread everywhere. So a few quick points related to 'high tea'.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(1) The first and most important is that high tea is not fancy. High tea gets its name from being 'high' in the afternoon or even into the evening; it was originally a working-class tea for people who had to work until 5 pm or later. Despite its working class origins, it become common in general, because almost everybody has situations where they can't take tea until late, and because travelers and guests would often arrive fairly late in the day, so it became a common form of quick-bite-to-eat hospitality. As such, it's usually a simple tea meal, consisting basically of tea with both a savory (like ham salad sandwich) and a sweet (like bread and jam) snack.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(2) The fancy tea can sometimes be called low tea, but is usually just called afternoon tea. It usually has a nice spread of tea sandwiches, scones, cakes, tea biscuits, and the like. It's a nicer tea than high tea in the sense that it is more social and less utility-driven, but, strictly speaking, it does not have to be formal. A cream tea, for instance, is basically just tea and some scones (with clotted cream or Devonshire cream, hence the name). However, when people talk about 'high tea' in American movies, television shows, and novels, they almost always mean formal afternoon tea. Formal afternoon tea is a tea for a tea party, a special-occasion light meal for a group; for the past century, it's almost always something taken at a hotel. You typically have to dress up for it. The most common formal afternoon tea in the United States is the debutante tea occasionally hosted by women's organizations for younger women.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(3) The fanciest form of afternoon tea, though, is arguably not formal afternoon tea but dancing tea, or tea dance, which is a full-scale party with music and dancing. Just as a tea is a light meal, so a dancing tea is a light dancing party, well short of a formal dance; you'd do the dancing in a garden or drawing room rather than a ballroom, and the tea meal itself would be handled like a buffet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, there can be, and have been, all sorts of variations. The kettle drum, for instance, was a form of very informal afternoon tea party that became popular for a while in the eighteenth century; it was basically just a dropping-in kind of tea, as people would come by without much formality, mingle and talk a bit, and then leave when they felt like it. Lots of other variations exist, particularly if you look at local modifications throughout the Commonwealth. But a high tea is an informal tea for after work or at the end of a long day.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/7136001866772932591/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/high-tea.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/7136001866772932591"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/7136001866772932591"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/high-tea.html" title="High Tea"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-993280814840527438</id><published>2022-11-08T21:49:00.001-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-08T21:49:15.172-06:00</updated><title type="text">The Religion of the Day</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&amp;nbsp;In every age of Christianity, since it was first preached, there has been what may be called a religion of the world, which so far imitates the one true religion, as to deceive the unstable and unwary. The world does not oppose religion as such. I may say, it never has opposed it. In particular, it has, in all ages, acknowledged in one sense or other the Gospel of Christ, fastened on one or other of its characteristics, and professed to embody this in its practice; while by neglecting the other parts of the holy doctrine, it has, in fact, distorted and corrupted even that portion of it which it has exclusively put forward, and so has contrived to explain away the whole;for he who cultivates only one precept of the Gospel to the exclusion of the rest, in reality attends to no part at all. Our duties balance each other; and though we are too sinful to perform them all perfectly, yet we may in some measure be performing them all, and preserving the balance on the whole; whereas, to give ourselves only to this or that commandment, is to incline our minds in a wrong direction, and at length to pull them down to the earth, which is the aim of our adversary, the Devil.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Henry Newman, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newmanreader.org/works/parochial/volume1/sermon24.html&quot;&gt;&quot;The Religion of the Day&quot; (Sermon 24)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Parochial Sermons&lt;/i&gt;, Volume 1.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/993280814840527438/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/the-religion-of-day.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/993280814840527438"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/993280814840527438"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/the-religion-of-day.html" title="The Religion of the Day"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-5224640123121057484</id><published>2022-11-07T12:55:00.003-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-07T13:44:28.409-06:00</updated><title type="text">Two New Poem Drafts</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Cathedral of Immerath&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sorrow, mortal children, cast the dust of time upon your head;&lt;br /&gt;all your fairest works are crumbled; soon they will be dead;&lt;br /&gt;this soldier-building, wounded once by guns of blood and death,&lt;br /&gt;was left unheeded, unregarded, rasping in its breath;&lt;br /&gt;unloved and lonely veteran, it kept the watch of years&lt;br /&gt;where its ancestors broke the ground; it fought the things of fear.&lt;br /&gt;But God and holy Lambert's way no longer find respect,&lt;br /&gt;for Mammon is this age's god, and all things does direct.&lt;br /&gt;So strip the village! Strip the church! And strip the very earth!&lt;br /&gt;Those things a people will destroy will measure their unworth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Now&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The future is out of reach; the present now&lt;br /&gt;is running swiftly past; hope is now&lt;br /&gt;as memory, however cut and shaped, is now,&lt;br /&gt;and both are running swiftly past; so now&lt;br /&gt;be patient with the day; for only now&lt;br /&gt;are you and I here, and we know no fate but now,&lt;br /&gt;when we are as we are before God's eternal now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/5224640123121057484/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/two-new-poem-drafts.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/5224640123121057484"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/5224640123121057484"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/two-new-poem-drafts.html" title="Two New Poem Drafts"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-362096720018964487</id><published>2022-11-06T16:52:00.001-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-06T19:06:45.718-06:00</updated><title type="text">Fortnightly Book, November 6</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;The next fortnightly book will be &lt;i&gt;The Tale of Sinuhe and Other Ancient Egyptian Poems, 1940-1640 BC&lt;/i&gt;, one of the Oxford World's Classics books. It is edited by R. B. Parkinson and purports to include all surviving literary works of Ancient Egypt that are still relatively complete and relatively intelligible. &lt;i&gt;The Tale of Sinuhe&lt;/i&gt;, of course, is the most famous. It tells of a courtier (Za-Nehet or Sinuhe) who flees the Egyptian court on the death of Pharaoh Amenemhat I and ends up in the court of a king in Retjenu, which is roughly the Egyptian name for Syria and Canaan, but eventually in his old age returns home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The works that are included in this edition:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tales&lt;br /&gt;1. The Tale of Sinuhe&lt;br /&gt;2. The Tale of the Eloquent Peasant&lt;br /&gt;3. The Tale of the Shipwrecked Sailor&lt;br /&gt;4. The Tale of King Cheops' Court&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discourses&lt;br /&gt;5. The Words of Neferti&lt;br /&gt;6. The Words of Khakheperreseneb&lt;br /&gt;7. The Dialogue of a Man and his Soul&lt;br /&gt;8. The Dialogue of Ipuur and the Lord of All&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Teachings&lt;br /&gt;9. The Teaching of King Amenemhat&lt;br /&gt;10. The Teaching for King Merikare&lt;br /&gt;11. The 'Loyalist' Teaching&lt;br /&gt;12. The Teaching of the Vizier Ptahhotep&lt;br /&gt;13. The Teaching of Khety&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It also ends with a selection of some of the fragments we have of other Egyptian literary works from the period.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/362096720018964487/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/fortnightly-book-november-6.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/362096720018964487"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/362096720018964487"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/fortnightly-book-november-6.html" title="Fortnightly Book, November 6"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-2597177365166919544</id><published>2022-11-06T11:24:00.000-06:00</published><updated>2022-11-06T11:24:10.666-06:00</updated><title type="text">Dorothy L. Sayers, Striding Folly</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/fortnightly-book-october-23.html&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Opening Passages:&lt;/b&gt; From &quot;Striding Folly&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Shall I expect you next Wednesday for our game as usual?' asked Mr Mellilow.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Of course, of course,' said Mr Creech. 'Very glad there's no ill feeling, Mellilow. Next Wednesday as well. Unless...' his heavy face darkened for a moment, as though at some disagreeable recollection. (p. 35)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From &quot;The Haunted Policeman&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Good God!' said his lordship. 'Did I do that?'&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'All the evidence points that way,' replied his wife.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Then I can say that I never knew so convincing a body of evidence produce such an inadequate result.'&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nurse appeared to take this reflection personally. She said in a tone of rebuke:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'He's a &lt;b&gt;beautiful&lt;/b&gt; boy.' (p. 59)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From &quot;Talboys&quot;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Father!'&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Yes, my son.'&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'You know those peaches of Mr Puffett's, the whacking great big ones you said I wasn't to take?'&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Well?'&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Well, I've tooken them.' (p. 93)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Summary: &lt;/b&gt;&quot;Striding Folly&quot; is a story of Mr Mellilow and Mr Creech, who regularly meet for a chess match. Mr Creech is extremely unpopular, having bought a significant quantity of highly scenic and universally visible land (originally owned by the Striding family and marked by a stone tower known as the Folly) in the area simply in order to the Electrical Power Company to build a large power-plant as the area begins to be electrified. Mr Mellilow is the only person who is still polite to him, because of their regular chess matches, although even he is very unhappy about Mr Creech's actions. In this state of mind, Mr Mellilow has a dream in which he is missing his goloshes and chased by a pair of towers across a chessboard-like land lit by flashes of lightning, ending with seeing a dead black crow. When next he is supposed to meet Mr Creech, however, Mr Creech does not show and instead a stranger comes by asking to play; afterward, Mr Mellilow, looking for his goloshes, wanders up to the Folly, where he does indeed find his goloshes, right by a murdered Mr Creech. Mr Mellilow is of course the primary suspect for the murder until Lord Peter Wimsey, a friend of the Chief Constable's, shows up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In &quot;The Haunted Policeman&quot;, Lord Peter and Harriet have just had their firstborn son, and Lord Peter, having just seen off the doctor, meets a worried and distracted policeman just off duty, whom he spontaneously asks to help him celebrate. The policeman tells Lord Peter the source of his distraction. Walking a beat, the policeman had turned into Merriman's End and noticed a suspicious character when someone began shouting about a murder. The policeman goes to Number 13 and sees a curious sight through the letter-flap. Inside there is a black-and-white marble floor and a staircase with a red carpet. A nude woman at the bottom of the staircase is carrying a pot of blue and yellow flowers. He sees a number of other things, all quite vividly, but the most serious is a large man on the floor with a knife in his throat. He blows his whistle, and has to leave the house temporarily to make sure people don't run into the street, and soon is met by another policeman, who was coming to take over for the night. They discover a problem. There is no Number 13 (all the streets are even-numbered), and Number 12 and Number 14 (and, indeed, all the others) look nothing like what the policeman had seen through the letter-flap. He is accused of having been drinking and might well lose his job, if Lord Peter cannot solve the&amp;nbsp; mystery of the disappearing house.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In &quot;Talboys&quot;, the oldest son of Lord Peter and Harriet, Bredon, is in trouble for having stolen a couple of prize peaches from Mr Puffett. Mr Puffett is fairly affable about it, and Lord Peter whips Bredon. A visitor, Miss Quirk, a friend of Harriet's sister, is staying and takes a dark view of corporal punishment as only encouraging delinquency, and takes herself to be vindicated when all of Mr Puffett's peaches are stolen, since Bredon is the likeliest suspect. Lord Peter and Mr Puffett investigate the scene of the crime, while Miss Quirk follows up her suspicion of Bredon, who is certainly hiding something.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All three stories are that particular form of mystery story in which someone is falsely accused, whom we know from having 'met' them probably to be falsely accused, but on grounds that seem unimpeachable, and therefore all have a structure of building up evidence in order to show that the evidence's apparent direction is not what it seems. &quot;Talboys&quot; is best of the three, and on its own is a reason to read this short collection. It has the most natural set-up for the crime and the most natural reason for Lord Peter to be involved; it has the most distinctive characterization; and it is a very funny story, being in part a send-up of modern views of education and parenting, embodied in Miss Quirk. It perhaps helps the story that Miss Quirks have become more, rather than less, common; being judgmental about other people's approach to parenting seems a common sport in our day and, as with Miss Quirk, it is a sport that anyone can play, even the childless. But while it's true enough that parents make their share of mistakes, sometimes even serious ones, it's only in the most extreme cases true that another person in their place would certainly do better. As in war, no plan survives contact with the enemy, so too in parenting, no scheme of how it should be done ever survives contact with actual children. At the very least, all parenting requires some custom-tailoring. Sayers's skewering of Miss Quirk's refusal to recognize this is very well done, and makes for an enjoyable story throughout.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;My past two weeks have been for the most part extraordinarily busy, but listening to audiobooks is something I can occasionally do even when my reading is itself taking a hit -- more places I can do it -- so I also listened to two audiobooks -- the audiobook version of &lt;i&gt;Striding Folly&lt;/i&gt;, put out by Blackstone Publishing and narrated by Ian Carmichael, and Colin Duriez's &lt;i&gt;Dorothy L. Sayers: A Biography of Death, Dante, and Lord Peter&lt;/i&gt;, published by Oasis&amp;nbsp; Audio and narrated by Simon Vance. Both were quite good. &quot;Talboys&quot; in particular works quite well in audio form; I did notice that the audio script toned down some of the policeman's crudeness in &quot;The Haunted Policeman&quot;. Duriez's biography struck me as probably better in audiobook form that it would be in book form; it's more a conversational introduction than a deep dive into Sayers's life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Favorite Passage:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;'I wish,' said Harriet, a little irritably, for she strongly disliked being lectured about her duties and being thus prevented from attending to them, 'you wouldn't always talk about &quot;a&quot; child, as if all children were alike. Even my three are all quite different.'&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'Mothers always think their own children are different,' said Miss Quirk. 'But the fundamental principles of child-psychology are the same in all, I have studied the subject. Take this question of punishment. When you punish a child -- '&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;'&lt;b&gt;Which&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp;child?' (p. 115)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Recommendation:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt; Recommended.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;*********&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dorothy L. Sayers, &lt;i&gt;Striding Folly&lt;/i&gt;, New English Library (London: 1977).&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/2597177365166919544/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/dorothy-l-sayers-striding-folly.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2597177365166919544"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2597177365166919544"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/dorothy-l-sayers-striding-folly.html" title="Dorothy L. Sayers, Striding Folly"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-6392431989967088754</id><published>2022-11-04T16:54:00.002-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-04T16:54:14.820-05:00</updated><title type="text">Beneath the Boughs of Yggdrasil</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lignum Vitae&lt;br /&gt;by Dorothy Sayers&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;And the leaves of the Tree were for the healing of the nations.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I am grown so weary, my hands can keep no hold &lt;br /&gt;Of the heavy water of living, in its jar of mortal gold, &lt;br /&gt;And it slips and spills in the ocean; then I shall sink to sleep &lt;br /&gt;Beneath the boughs of Yggdrasil, where the sea-ways are deep, &lt;br /&gt;Or peer from slumberous eyelids to see the smooth, black stem &lt;br /&gt;Stretch up to the world's foundations, and know that it beareth them; &lt;br /&gt;While dim through the roofs of water I shall hear, and hardly hear &lt;br /&gt;How the birds of Bran the Blessed sing Aves all the year. &lt;br /&gt;The waves of God will go over me, the waves and the great, green flood, &lt;br /&gt;Where the ash-buds break to blossom in a red gleam like blood. &lt;br /&gt;Yggdrasil, Yggdrasil! . . . the branches sweep and spread &lt;br /&gt;Till the Tree of the whole world's sorrow shadows my dreaming head; &lt;br /&gt;And never a wind comes near it, but the leaves swing quietly &lt;br /&gt;Night and day to the swinging of the sea, of the salt sea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/6392431989967088754/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/beneath-boughs-of-yggdrasil.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/6392431989967088754"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/6392431989967088754"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/beneath-boughs-of-yggdrasil.html" title="Beneath the Boughs of Yggdrasil"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-9159950632711249148</id><published>2022-11-03T11:51:00.001-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-10T22:57:48.417-06:00</updated><title type="text">Links of Note</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;* Keith Burgess-Jackson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scirp.org/journal/paperinformation.aspx?paperid=100016&quot;&gt;The Whole Truth about Partial Truth Tables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Corbin K. Barthold, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.city-journal.org/can-sludge-kill-societies&quot;&gt;Sludge Kills&lt;/a&gt;, at &quot;City Journal&quot;, discusses the problems of increasing bureaucratic and administrative friction and impediment&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Boaz Faraday Schuman, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/SCHSHR-3&quot;&gt;Scholastic Humor: Ready Wit as a Virtue in Theory and Practice&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* &lt;a href=&quot;https://thonyc.wordpress.com/2022/10/26/the-jesuits-and-science-in-the-seventeenth-century/&quot;&gt;Thony Christie reviews Michael John Gorman's &lt;i&gt;The Scientific Counter-Revolution&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, on Jesuit work in science in the early modern period&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Andrew Lambert, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/LAMFIT-4&quot;&gt;Friendship in the Confucian Tradition&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Tom Metcalf, &lt;a href=&quot;https://1000wordphilosophy.com/2022/10/26/modal-logic/&quot;&gt;Modal Logic: Axioms and and Systems for Modal Logic&lt;/a&gt;, at &quot;1000-Word Philosophy&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* David Polansky, &lt;a href=&quot;https://unherd.com/2022/10/stop-talking-about-american-fascism/&quot;&gt;Stop talking about American 'fascism'&lt;/a&gt;, discusses the problems of substantive concepts degenerating into mere rhetoric&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Hrishikesh Joshi, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/JOSTES-2&quot;&gt;The Epistemic Significance of Social Pressure&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Elizabeth Steere, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/advice/2022/11/02/plagiarism-and-use-text-spinners-class-assignments-opinion&quot;&gt;Text Spinners and the Problem of Paraphrase Plagiarism&lt;/a&gt;, at &quot;Inside Higher Education&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Andree Hahmann &amp;amp; Michael Vazquez, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/HAHC_A-5&quot;&gt;Ciceronian Officium and Kantian Duty&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/9159950632711249148/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/links-of-note.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/9159950632711249148"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/9159950632711249148"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/links-of-note.html" title="Links of Note"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-6681851618703067417</id><published>2022-11-02T05:05:00.001-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-02T05:05:00.236-05:00</updated><title type="text">All Souls</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Today is the Feast of All Souls, more formally known as the Commemoration of All the Faithful Departed. The following song comes to mind, a classic from long-ago days of my youth:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/chIGGBeyOqI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; width=&quot;560&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bebo Norman &amp;amp; Rich Mullins, &quot;Sometimes by Step&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/6681851618703067417/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/all-souls.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/6681851618703067417"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/6681851618703067417"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/all-souls.html" title="All Souls"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://img.youtube.com/vi/chIGGBeyOqI/default.jpg" height="72" width="72"/><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-2758309926288100177</id><published>2022-11-01T05:00:00.006-05:00</published><updated>2022-11-01T10:51:23.256-05:00</updated><title type="text">All Saints</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Then I heard what seemed to be the voice of a great multitude, like the sound of many waters and like the sound of mighty thunderpeals, crying out,  Hallelujah! For the Lord our God     the Almighty reigns.&amp;nbsp; Let us rejoice and exult     and give him the glory, for the marriage of the Lamb has come,     and his bride has made herself ready; to her it has been granted to be clothed     with fine linen, bright and pure--for the fine linen is the righteous deeds of the saints. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Revelation+19%3A6-8&amp;amp;version=NRSVCE&quot;&gt;Rev 19:6-8 NRSV&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Gildas the Wise&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gweltaz, known usually by the Latin form of his name, Gildas, was born in the sixth century. According to a longstanding legend, he was born in Scotland somewhere around modern-day Glasgow, but it is often held that he was actually born much farther south. According to himself, he was born in the same year as the Battle of Mount Badon. The battle was later attributed to King Arthur; St. Gildas does not say who fought at it, but the later attribution led to Gildas occasionally showing up in Arthurian legend. Unfortunately, we don't know exactly when the Battle of Mount Badon took place; Gildas is the first person we know to mention it, but he takes it as a reference point his original readers would already know. It is generally held to have occurred around 500. Gildas became a monk, and is traditionally thought to have been educated in the school run by St. Illtud in Wales. At the age of forty-four, he wrote the work for which he is famous, &lt;i&gt;On the Ruin and Conquest of Britain.&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;The work is a scathing polemic attacking the morals of several kings and the clergy of his day, but has since become most important for historical purposes because it was the only surviving extended near-contemporary discussion of figures and events at the time, and was influential on the development of several other important historians, like St. Bede and Alcuin. St. Gildas also became a recurring symbol of political and ecclesiastical reform in British contexts. At some point, Gildas founded an abbey at Rhuys, in Brittany, and died there, perhaps in 569 or 570. His feast day is celebrated on January 29.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Clelia Barbieri&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clelia Rachele Maria Barbieri was born in 1847 in Bologna to a poor working-class family. She herself began to work very young. When she was eight years old, her father died, and to maintain her family Clelia had to spend much of her day spinning hemp into rope. The family lived near a little church, and the girl spent her time when not working or sleeping at the church. In 1861 she joined a group devoted to Christian catechesis and soon became an active teacher in the parish's catechetical programs. In 1868, she founded her own group, the Little Sisters of Our Lady of Sorrows, to minister to the local poor and sick. She contracted tuberculosis, however, and died on July 13, 1870. She was beatified in 1968 by Bl. Paul VI and canonized in 1989 by St. John Paul II; her feast day is July 13.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Marguerite Bourgeoys&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Born in 1620 in Troyes in the County of Champagne, Marguerite Bourgeoys lived a relatively uneventful life until in 1652 Paul de Chomedey, Sieur de Maisonneuve, the governor of the French colony at Fort Ville-Marie (later known as Montreal), visited his sister, a local canoness.&amp;nbsp; Maisonneuve happened to be looking for people to start schools, and Marguerite was one of the people he asked. So in 1653, Bourgeoys arrived in Quebec and set to work. She helped organize the fundraising and building for the first church in Fort Ville-Marie, Notre-Dame-de-Bonsecours, and set up a school. She and her fellow workers helped educate orphan girls who were sent to the colony and also interviewed male settlers who came to Quebec looking for fortune and a wife. A small community of women grew up around Bourgeoys's work, and this eventually became the Congregation of Notre Dame of Montreal. Bourgeoys herself often returned to France to raise funds, recruit help, and petition for royal support for various projects; one of the most important such projects was keeping the Congregation uncloistered. There was a strong push to cloister most religious congregations at the time, which was seen as necessary for religious reform; Marguerite recognized that this was utterly unsuitable both to the nature of the Congregation itself and the needs of the population they served, and kept petitioning until she met King Louis XIV and obtained his support in keeping her community a community of sisters out in the world. The king seems to have been fairly impressed with her, and noted that she was a major contributor to the building of the colony both educationally and materially. Royal patronage in hand, the Congregation built schools all over Quebec. This kept Bourgeoys busy, although she had to spend a fair amount of time fending off the attempts of bishops to make the Congregation cloistered in the misguided belief that in doing so they were aiding in the reform of the Church rather than impeding it. She died on January 12, 1700. She was beatified in 1950 by Pius XII and canonized in 1982 by John Paul II. Her feast is January 12.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Charles Eugene de Foucauld de Pontbriand&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Charles Eugene de Foucauld de Pontbriand was born September 15, 1858 in Strasbourg, but both of his parents died in 1864 from different ailments; he and his sister were given over to the care of their paternal grandmother, but she died shortly after, as well, so they were raised by their maternal grandparents. Their grandfather did a great deal to encourage Charles's education, but Charles was often sick and not a cooperative or sociable child at all. The family had to flee in 1870 due to the Franco-Prussian War, and they eventually ended up in Nancy. Charles was confirmed, but he shortly afterward began to doubt his faith, became an agnostic, and stopped all of his religious practices. Finishing his education up in military schools, he eventually joined the French cavalry and spent time posted in Algeria, Morocco, the Sahara, and Palestine. The time in North Africa, and subsequent return to France, slowly brought him back to his faith, and in 1890, despite having lived a quite dissolute lifestyle before, he became a Trappist monk, and later, feeling called to something different from what the Trappists offered, became a hermit. He was ordained in 1900, and set out for Algeria to found a new congregation, but that project was a complete failure. Instead, he simply lived among the Berbers, studying Tuareg culture and creating the first Tuareg-French dictionary. His life came to an end on December 1, 1916, when a bunch of raiders broke into his hermitage and kidnapped him, probably hoping for a ransom; however, when the raiders ran into French cavalry, they panicked and shot Foucauld in the head. He was beatified by Pope Benedict XVI and was canonized by Pope Francis I in 2022; his feast day is December 1.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lazaros the Iconographer&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lazaros, often known as Lazaros Zagraphos ('the Painter' or 'the Iconographer') was a ninth-century Armenian who became a monk and studied at the great Stoudios Monastery in Constantinople, where he was ordained. He was discovered to have a talented for painting, and his frescos were especially impressive, so he was set with the task of restoring old icons. In another time, this might have been quiet minor work, but in Lazaros's day Constantinople was in the grip of the iconoclastic movement, and the emperor, Theophilos, was a major supporter of the iconoclasts. Thus restoring icons was potentially dangerous work, particularly since one of Lazaros's task was repairing icons that had been vandalized by the iconoclasts. Lazaros was eventually dragged before the emperor who, discovering that Lazaros could not be bribed to stop, threatened him with death; when he discovered that Lazaros was a priest, Theophilos instead threw him in prison, where he was tortured in the attempt to get him to stop. Instead, he began painting icons on the prison walls using makeshift materials. Eventually the torture put Lazaros on his deathbed. Since he was dying anyway, the empress, Theodora the Armenian, who was sympathetic to the iconodoules, was able to get him released. Lazaros took shelter at a church near the shores of the Bosporus, where he recovered, and in fact outlasted the Emperor Theophilos. As Theodora brought the iconoclastic persecution to an end, Lazaros was free to paint again. He was also sent on a couple of diplomatic missions to Rome in the attempt to heal the damage that had been caused between Rome and Constantinople during the iconcolastic period, dying in Rome on the second such mission. His feast is usually celebrated November 17 on Orthodox calendars and February 23 on the Roman calendar.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Arialdo and Erlembaldo&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arialdo lived in the eleventh century; he became a canon in Milan, which was still one of the major sees of the West. It was not a great time for Milan, whose clergy were infamous for a long list of immoralities. However, times were changing, and Arialdo was the beginning of it. He began preaching against the tendency of the clergy to keep concubines, probably taking advantage of the fact that the bishop of Milan was away at the time. The clergy of Milan, alarmed, sent envoys to Pope Stephen IX, suggesting that Arialdo was a troublemaker trying to stir up the people of Milan against the clergy. Arialdo heard about this, however, and went to Rome himself to explain his own position. The pope was convinced that, at the very least, further investigation was required, so he sent two envoys, Anselm of Baggio and Hildebrand of Sovana, to look into the matter further. The result was that Arialdo could continue to preach, although there were occasional attempts to kill him and his associates. One of those killed was a man named Landulf Cotta. The violence was inconsistent. However, Arialdo had to return to Rome in 1059 because things were getting out of hand. The pope again sent envoys, Anselm of Baggio and St. Peter Damian, but the envoys were unable to get the city under control. A full-scale reform movement, known as the Pataria, had grown up around Arialdo, and the Patarines and their opponents, led by the bishop, Guido de Velate, were increasingly in direct conflict. The Patarines had an unexpected opportunity when Anselm of Baggio became Pope Alexander II in 1061. The new pope had quite a bit on his plate, but he actively supported the Pataria. In 1063, Landulf Cotta's brother, Erlembaldo Cotta returned from a pilgrimage and was convinced by Arialdo to become an active member of the Pataria, despite being a soldier rather than a cleric; Erlembaldo received the papal banner in 1864. This guaranteed that the fundamental showdown was now not between the See of Milan and the Pataria but between the See of Milan and the Holy See of Rome. Bishop Guido was excommunicated, and the Pataria began moving directly against the Milanese hierarchy, with Arialdo imposing an interdict on the diocese. This led to a revolt, and Arialdo had to flee; he was caught, however, and killed. Things continued to heat up, as Erlembald had to deal with the meddling of Emperor Henry IV, who was backing opponents of Pope Alexander II. As the pope's representative in Milan, Erlembald, despite being a layman, effectively governed the church, deciding appointments and doing what was required to support them, but his opponents were many, and when backed by the Emperor, Erlembald was sometimes limited in what he could do. However, the Pataria had another stroke of luck when Alexander II, who had died in 1073, was succeeded by Hildebrand of Sovana, now Gregory VII, who was also a supporter of the Pataria, with the result that the Pataria, backed by Rome, was able to outlast the Emperor, who was having problems elsewhere in his empire. Nonetheless, problems were not over, as the Pataria continued to be controversial, and when the cathedral of Milan was set on fire by a lightning storm in 1075, many of the people of Milan took it as a sign of divine judgment against the Pataria. A major revolt rose up. Erlembald was able to put it down, but at a cost, since he died from wounds in the battle. After his death, the Pataria began to dissolve, although tensions between the popes and the emperors over Milan continued. Ariald's feast is June 27 and Erlembald's feast is July 27.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Devashayam Pillai&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neelakandan Pillai was born in 1712 in Tamil Nadu to a Brahmin father and a non-Brahmin mother; because of this, he was outcaste and therefore was raised entirely by his mother's family, his father not being ritually able to play a role in his education. His mother's family had important connections in the court of the maharaja of Travancore, so Neelekanden eventually became an important official. So things would probably have remained, except that in 1741, the Dutch East India Company tried by force to establish a trading post in Travancore, at Colachel. The Dutch were resoundingly defeated at the Battle of Colachel, and the commander of the Dutch military forces, Eustachius Benedictus de Lannoy, was taken prisoner. He was later pardoned by the maharaja on the condition that he would assist the development of the Travancore military, particularly when it came to European tactics and weaponry. He did so well that he was eventually made commander, and in this position, Neelakandan Pillai interacted with him to a considerable degree, and became curious about his Christianity. As a result of these interactions, Pillai was baptized in 1745, taking the baptismal name Lazar, although the version of the name he came to use most, and was known most by, was a Tamil translation of the name, Devashayam. Many other members of Devashayam Pillai's family followed him into the Church. The Brahmin priests eventually brought charges against Devashayam for rejecting traditional beliefs and practices, and he was imprisoned. For diplomatic reasons, due to relations between Travancore and European nations, he was eventually sent to exile in the nearby Pandya kingdom; he spent some time in the forests near Aralvaimozhy, where he gained a reputation as a holy man. The exact circumstances of his death are difficult to determine, but he seems to have been shot by soldiers, perhaps at the instigation of local Brahmin priests. He was beatified by Benedict XVI in 2012 and canonized by Francis I in 2022. His feast day is January 14.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Gerard Majella&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gerardo Maiella was born in southern Italy in 1726. He was apprenticed as a tailor, but his career was somewhat rocky because his health was always frail. His fragile health also prevented him from joining a religious order as he wished to do, but in 1749 he was allowed into a relatively new religious order devoted to missionary work, the Congregation of the Most Holy Redeemer, or Redemptorists, as a lay brother. He did a large number of odd jobs for the Redemptorist community, and things were for the most part quiet. However, in 1753, he was accused by a local woman of having fathered her child; the scandal was serious enough that St. Alphonsus Liguori, the head of the Redemptorists, investigated the matter himself. Maiella refused to speak in his own defense, and therefore St. Alphonsus imposed sanctions on him. Later the woman confessed that she had lied, and Maiella's name was cleared. He died of tuberculosis in 1755. After his death, he became popular among pregnant mothers in Italy because devotion to him was associated with easing labor due to some of the miracles attributed to him; for this reason, he is often referred to as the patron saint of expectant mothers. He was beatified in 1893 by Leo XIII and canonized in 1904 by St. Pius X. His feast day is October 16.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;David Uribe-Velasco&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;David Uribe-Velasco was born in 1889 in Buenavista de Cullar in Mexico. He was ordained as a priest in 1913. It was an uneasy time for the Catholic Church in Mexico; the Constitution at that time was anticlericalist, although its anti-Catholic provisions were only very lightly enforced. However, in 1914 there was a coup which put into place a regime that used the provisions to engage in an active persecution of Catholics. Fr. David at one point had to relocate in the hope of avoiding a direct crackdown. Political struggles eventually led to the persecutions being lightened up temporarily, but the way the Church was treated see-sawed back and forth depending on who was in power. This was unstable, and it all exploded in 1926 with the Cristero War, in which parts of the rural Catholic population of Mexico rose in rebellion after the regime attempted to close Catholic churches. Meanwhile, Catholic priests often had to say Mass and give confessions in secret. The Mexican army eventually became aware of a secret Mass celebrated by Uribe-Velasco. The Mexican government had established its own schismatic alternative to the Catholic Church, the&amp;nbsp;Iglesia Catlica Apostlica Mexicana, and tried to recruit him to it. When he refused, he was shot. He was beatified in 1992 and canonized in 2000 by St. John Paul II as one of the Martyrs of the Mexican Revolution. His feast day is April 12, the anniversary of his death in 1927.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Incio de Azevedo and the Martyrs of Tazacorte&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incio de Azevedo de Atade Abreu e Malafaia was born in Porto, Portugal, in 1526; he was an illegitimate son, but as his family was nobility, he was legitimized and began to be trained for a life at court. However, after he began attending sermons by a Jesuit missionary, he gave that career up and became a Jesuit priest instead. He was put in charge of several Jesuit schools, eventually doing extensive work in raising funds for the construction of the Roman College (now known as the Gregorian). In 1565, St. Francis Borgia named him Visitor to Brazil; he arrived in Brazil the next year to oversee Jesuit schools and missions. It was tricky business, because he had to keep working around the war between France and Portugal that was happening at the time, but within two years he had visited every Jesuit mission in Brazil. He returned to Lisbon and then Rome to report, and asked to have more volunteers to help meet the needs of the Brazilian missions. He was given full authority to arrange such a mission to Brazil as he thought appropriate and he and the volunteers set out in June of 1570. On July 15, shortly after leaving Tazacorte, the small fleet of which the mission was a part was sailing near La Palma in the Canary Islands, when they were attacked by the fleet of the French pirate, Jacques de Sores. The ships were captured. Many of the passengers were allowed to escape, but Jacques do Sore, who was a French Huguenot, ordered the Catholic priests and seminarians to be executed. Forty of them, including Fr. Incio were stabbed and thrown overboard. They were beatified in 1854 by Pius IX as the Forty Martyrs of Brazil. Their feast day is July 17.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Angelus of Jerusalem&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Angelus and his twin brother John were born to a Jewish family in Jerusalem in 1185, but their mother converted to Catholicism not long after, and so they were both baptized. As their parents died when they were children, they were raised in the household of the Patriarch of Jerusalem. At the age of 18, they joined the relatively new order, the Order of the Brothers of the Blessed Virgin Mary of Mount Carmel, usually known as the Carmelites. Angelus, unlike his brother, wanted to be a hermit, so he began the eremitic life in the wilderness, but had some difficulty because people kept hearing about him and seeking him out. In 1218, he set out for Italy. We don't quite know why, as different stories give different reasons. But he seems to have done so with the permission of his superiors, because he was authorized to petition Pope Honorius III for confirmation of a new rule for the order. While in Rome, he is said to have preached in St. John Lateran and to have met both St. Francis and St. Dominic. We don't know for sure whether this is true, but according to the story, St. Angelus predicted that St. Francis would share the wounds of Christ, and St. Francis predicted that St. Angelus would die fairly young. Angelus made his way to Sicily, where he spent his time preaching. On May 1, 1220, he was stabbed to death by a Cathar knight, supposedly for having convinced the knight's mistress to leave him. He died a few days later, and his burial place in Licata became a major Carmelite pilgrimage site. His feast day is May 5.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Laura of Saint Catherine of Siena&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mara Laura de Jess Montoya Upegui was born in&amp;nbsp;Jeric, Colombia in 1874. Her father's death in the Colombian Civil War of 1876 left the family nearly destitute, so she was raised first by her grandmother and then sent to an orphanage run by her maternal aunt. With her aunt's help and support, she trained to be a schoolteacher, and began teaching in 1893. Beginning in 1908, she started working with indigenous communities. She had been wanting for a while to become Carmelite nun, but one thing that kept her was that Carmelites were cloistered and she found that evangelism was what actually interested her. So in 1917 she started the Congregation of Missionary Sisters of the Immaculate Virgin Mary and Saint Catherine of Siena and with a few other women began doing missionary work in the little indigenous community of Dabeiba. She took the religious name of Laura of Saint Catherine of Siena and was active in missionary work the rest of her life. Toward the end of her life she suffered from a prolonged illness that kept her in a wheelchair. She died in 1949. She was beatified in 2004 by St. John Paul II and canonized in 2013 by Francis I. Her feast day is October 21.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jean-Baptiste de la Salle&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jean-Baptiste de la Salle was born to a wealthy and noble family in Reims, France, in 1651; his mother's family, in fact, was a major winemaking family, the Mots, whose name is still associated with high-quality champagne. La Salle was destined for religious life from his teenage years, and he was given an excellent education, culminating in attendance at the Seminary of Saint-Sulpice. Both of his parents died shortly afterward, however, so he had to leave school to look after his younger brothers and sisters. While this slowed him down a bit, it did not stall him, and he was ordained a priest in 1678. One of his earliest tasks was to help establish the Sisters of the Child Jesus, recently founded to look after the education of poor and sickly girls. This would be formative, because while he was serving as confessor to the order, he met Adrian Nyel. Nyel was a civil educator, founding schools for poor children throughout Rouen, and La Salle began working with Nyel to found schools that were properly integrated into the local communities. La Salle began overseeing the schools founded by Nyel in and around Reims. He immediately ran into the problem that the teachers at these schools often faced nearly insuperable impediments. They were poor and had little training, and often only a very basic education themselves, and they had difficulty working together with a common aim. To help remedy this La Salle started inviting them to dinner, which at the time was scandalous because they belonged to a much lower class than he did. Having inherited a very large amount of money, he began thinking of using it to found a series of high-quality schools for the poor and working class. As it happens, he ended up donating almost all of the money to help during a famine, but he went ahead with the school project, anyway. Thus began the Institute of the Brothers of the Christian Schools. It had a very rocky start. The bishops were wary of this (at the time) very unusual approach to religious life; secular authorities were very suspicious of this unusual approach to schools. But he did not stop and in 1685 founded a school specializing in the training of teachers. His work in education turned out to be extremely successful, but it was also extremely time-consuming and exhausting, and the stress of it is often thought to have been a contributing cause of his death on Good Friday in 1719. He was canonized by Leo XIII in 1900, and his current feast day is April 7.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Damien of Molokai&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jozef de Veuster was born in 1840 in Tremelo, Belgium. His parents intended him for the mercantile life, training him to work in the family farm and the little grain business they owned, but he became fascinated by the Redemptorists and began looking into the possibility of religious life. He eventually decided to join the Congregation of the Sacred Hearts of Jesus and Mary and took the religious name of Damien. He wanted to be a missionary priest. He got very little encouragement from his superiors, because the farmboy was very, very far from being polished in manners or scholarly in interests. He was an intelligent young man, however, and although he never stopped being a bit rough in manners, when he showed that he could learn Latin fairly easily, he was allowed to proceed with a seminary education and was ordained. Shortly before his ordination, in 1864, he was sent to Hawaii on a mission, because the previous priest had become too sick to go. The Kingdom of Hawai'i at that time was in a state of severe crisis; unemployment was rampant, crime was increasing, illness was spreading everywhere. Leprosy was becoming worryingly common, so that King Kamehameha V signed into effect a law to quarantine all lepers at the colony of Kalawao. However, the Kingdom struggled to pay for the expenses of such a quarantine, and the whole project was teetering on the edge of humanitarian disaster. At this time, the bishop in Honolulu decided that more needed to be done for the leper colony, and Damien de Veuster was one of the priests who volunteered. He established a church and became very well known throughout the colony for his willingness to help any of the residents with any of the practical problems that they might have; he helped dress wounds, lay down roads, repair houses, till farms, found hospitals, build furniture, dig graves. He himself rarely took a primary supervisory role, but he could always be counted on to help those who did. His work came to the attention of King David Kalakaua and Princess Lydia Lili'uokalani, and after they recognized him officially, he became internationally famous, to such an extent that his work was no longer merely supported by Catholics but by a wide range of Protestant churches, as well, although locally Christian churches were often highly critical of him, as he was widely regarded as an uncouth and coarse man, lacking all polished respectability. In 1884, he accidentally put his foot into water scalding enough to blister his skin, and feeling nothing, knew that he had contracted leprosy. Recognizing that the clock was ticking on his mission, he threw himself into his work as much as his medical condition would allow, trying to finish projects that had started and set up for success those projects he could not finish. He died on April 15, 1889. Shortly afterward, Robert Louis Stevenson was in Hawaii, suffering from tuberculosis, and, curious about Fr. Damien's story, investigated and wrote up a defense of him from his critics that made him even more internationally famous. He was beatified by Pope John Paul II in 1995 and canonized by Pope Benedict XVI in 2009. His feast day is May 10.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;************&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2021/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2021 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Niklaus von Flue, Contardo of Este, Peter of Verona, Virginia Centurione Bracelli, Fulrad, Ivan of Rila, Austregisilus, Sulpitius the Pious, Desiderius, Amandus, Remaclus, Theodard, Lambert, The Martyrs of Shanxi,&amp;nbsp;Tma Khung, Maria Teresa Goretti, Lidwina of Schiedam, Oliver Plunkett, Mariam Baouardy, Marinus, Nunzio Sulprizio&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;    &lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2020/10/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2020 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Andr de Soveral, Domingos Carvalho, and the Martyrs of Cunhau,&amp;nbsp;Henry of Uppsala and Eric IX the Holy, Adelaide of Burgundy, Junpero Serra y Ferrer, Maria Restituta Kafka, Venantius Fortunatus, Radegund, Junian of Maire, and Gregory of Tours, Magdalene of Nagasaki, Jeanne-Antide Thouret, Louis IX, Peter Nolasco, Tarasios of Constantinople, Albert Chmielowski&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2019/11/all-saints-iii.html&quot;&gt;2019 All Saints Post, Part III&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mariam Thresia Chiramel Mankidiyan, Gregory II and Gregory III, Katarina Ulfsdotter, Marko Stjepan Krizin, Istvn Pongrcz, Melchior Grodziecki, Amandus and Bavo of Ghent, Zhang Huailu, Colette of Corbie, Alphonsus Rodriguez, Marie-Margeuerite d'Youville, Anthony of the Caves, Teresa of Calcutta&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2019/11/all-saints-ii.html&quot;&gt;2019 All Saints Post, Part II&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bartolomeu dos Mrtires, Manuel Moralez, Apollonius the Apologist, Henry II the Exuberant and Cunigunde of Luxembourg, Ramon Nonat, Francis Xavier Cabrini, Juliana of Lige, Aelia Pulcheria, John Henry Newman, Anna Schffer, Ivo of Chartres, Paul I of Constantinople&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2019/11/all-saints-i.html&quot;&gt;2019 All Saints Post, Part I&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Matteo Correa Magallanes, Nicholas Owen, Knud IV and Knud Lavard, Mariana de Jess de Paredes, Joseph Vaz, Zdislava Berka, Caterina Fieschi Adorno, Pietro I Orseolo, aminh H Trng Mu, Jeanne-Franoise Frmiot de Chantal, Stephen Min Kk-ka, Rabanus Maurus Magnentius&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2018/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2018 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gianna Beretta Molla, Margaret of Scotland, Yu Tae-chol Peter, Justa and Rufina of Seville, Giuseppe Moscati, Kazimierz Jagielloczyk, Marie-Alphonsine Danil Ghaas, Salomone Leclerq, Arnulf of Metz, scar Arnulfo Romero y Galdmez, Frumentius of Tyre, Jeanne Jugan, Joseph Zhang Dapeng, Maroun and Abraham of Harran, Magnus Erlendsson, Callixtus I, Hippolytus, Urban I, Pontian, Anterus, Fabian, Jean de Brbeuf&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2017/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2017 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;John Ogilvie, Leo IV, Andrew Stratelates and the 2593 Martyrs, Theodore the Studite, The Martyrs of Gorkum, Margaret Ward and John Roche, Mesrop Mashtots, Jos Mara Robles Hurtado, Genevieve of Paris, Pedro Calungsod, Isaac of Nineveh, George Preca, Denis Ssebuggwawo Wasswa, Anthony of Padua&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2016/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2016 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Theodore of Tarsus, Nilus the Younger, Anne Line, Mark Ji Tianxiang, Maria Elisabetta Hesselbad, Sergius of Radonezh, Anna Pak Agi, Jeanne de Valois, Vigilius of Trent, Claudian, Magorian, Sisinnius, Martyrius, Alexander, Euphrasia Eluvathingal, Jos Sanchez del Rio, Andrew Kaggwa, Roberto Bellarmino&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2015/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2015 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Margaret Clitherow, Kaleb Elasbaan of Axum, Louis Martin and Marie-Azlie Gurin Martin, Gertrude of Nivelles, Pius V, Clare and Agnes of Assisi, Kuriakose Elias Chavara, Scholastica, Vinh Sn Phm Hiu Lim, Thorlak Thorhallson, John Damascene&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2014/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2014 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Marie Guyart, Alphonsa Muttathupadathu, John Neumann, Hildegard von Bingen, Pedro de San Jos Betancurt, Benedict the Moor&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2013/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2013 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Mara Guadalupe Garca Zavala, Antonio Primaldi, Nimatullah Kassab Al-Hardini, Gabriel-Taurin Dufresse and Augustine Zhao Rong, Josephine Margaret Bakhita, John Chrysostom&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2012/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2012 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Jadwiga of Poland, Kateri Tekakwitha, Andr Bessette, Rafqa Pietra Choboq Ar-Rays, Alberto Hurtado Cruchaga&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2011/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2011 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bonifacia Rodrguez de Castro, Celestine V, Olga of Kiev, Cyril of Jerusalem, Joseph Mukasa and Charles Lwanga&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://branemrys.blogspot.com/2010/11/all-saints.html&quot;&gt;2010 All Saints Post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Moses the Black of Ethiopia, Micae H nh Hy, Katherine Mary Drexel, Robert Southwell, Lojze Grozde, Andrew Kim Tae Gon&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/2758309926288100177/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/all-saints.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2758309926288100177"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2758309926288100177"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/11/all-saints.html" title="All Saints"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-2761371808486329730</id><published>2022-10-31T11:38:00.003-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T11:38:31.293-05:00</updated><title type="text">Tombs and Cities Rotting in the Sun</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;The Mummy&lt;br /&gt;by Clark Ashton Smith&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From out the light of many a mightier day, &lt;br /&gt;From Pharaonic splendour, Memphian gloom, &lt;br /&gt;And from the night aeonian of the tomb &lt;br /&gt;They brought him forth, to meet the modern ray, &lt;br /&gt;Upon his brow the unbroken seal of clay, &lt;br /&gt;While gods have gone to a forgotten doom, &lt;br /&gt;And desolation and the dust assume &lt;br /&gt;Temple and cot immingling in decay.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;From out the everlasting womb sublime &lt;br /&gt;Of cyclopean death, within a land &lt;br /&gt;Of tombs and cities rotting in the sun, &lt;br /&gt;He is reborn to mock the might of time, &lt;br /&gt;While kings have built against Oblivion &lt;br /&gt;With walls and columns of the windy sand.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/2761371808486329730/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/tombs-and-cities-rotting-in-sun.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2761371808486329730"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2761371808486329730"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/tombs-and-cities-rotting-in-sun.html" title="Tombs and Cities Rotting in the Sun"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-4994054507791426417</id><published>2022-10-30T14:04:00.005-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-31T11:32:17.457-05:00</updated><title type="text">'Theology Without Anathemas'</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Steven Nemes has a Cambridge Core Element, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/elements/orthodoxy-and-heresy/50689A55E19FDEC6B45FF3F3DAE2BBC2&quot;&gt;Orthodoxy and Heresy&lt;/a&gt;, that is temporarily open access (until November 3). The work is a critique of the concepts in the title, advocating instead a 'theology without anathemas' and has some interesting parts, but involves, I think, a fundamental and largely fatal structural flaw. The flaw can be roughly summarized in the following terms. Nemes assumes that orthodoxy and heresy are primarily terms that get their meaning, function, and value within theology as a field of intellectual inquiry; his primary criticism is that they fail to serve that field well in a number of ways. But this is simply an error. Orthodoxy and heresy are not primarily terms from theology as a field; they are terms concerned with the practical matter of communion or, to use a common Protestant term, church order. Their justification, structure, and practical implementation all derive from this, not from purely theological concerns. Theology as a field is only relevant to them insofar as they require the use of theological criteria. Therefore Nemes's discussion, which is focused almost entirely on the theological criteria considered in isolation from their ecclesiastical context, and mostly only discusses the social and political criteria to criticize their existing at all, repeatedly fails to address properly, or even at times to consider, the issues that would actually be relevant to assessing orthodox and heresy, which would have to look not at pure rational theory but at the practical issues involved in evaluating and handling the problem of counterfeits or of deviations so great that they seem to involve leaving the common social project in favor of another project entirely.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nemes's entire argument is an &lt;i&gt;ignoratio elenchi&lt;/i&gt;, in other words. It's as if you advocated a 'philosophy of law without censures' on the ground that legal licensing and practice requirements were distorting discussions of philosophy of law so that the latter were disproportionately focused on matters concerned with the ways you can legally practice and implement law, rather than floating free and considering every possible kind of legal matter in light of practical reason and empirical evidence. Simply considering philosophy of law as a field in complete isolation, there is indeed no particular reason why you couldn't specialize in vigilante law or warlord justice or the laws that might pertain to purely hypothetical fantasy societies. But most people are not interested in philosophy of law for these things; they want to discuss the kind of law that is in fact legally structured and restricted by the actual legal system, and thus it is very important to them to know what kind of laws and legal practice are actually legal or constitutional themselves. This is not in any way surprising, and it is if anything less surprising that people want to discuss the kind of theology relevant to participating in particular ecclesial communities. Further, whatever might be said of philosophy of law as a field, philosophy of law also serves as a means of assisting the actual legal practices and systems. This is a common pattern in 'philosophy of X' fields. But revealed theology, as opposed to natural theology, is very much like a philosophy of X field; it's also a means assisting ecclesial communities. Most people are not doing theology as a private little game or hobby; they want among other things to become more informed about what's involved in participating in their favored church community.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Criticizing 'orthodoxy' and 'heresy' for not having purely theoretical value in the context of purely theoretical investigations is thus missing the point. What Nemes would really have to argue, because it is the real controversy between him and almost everyone else, is that the ecclesial functions associated with the concepts of orthodoxy and heresy are irrelevant to salvation. That he does hold something like this is clear from his comments about belief-in versus belief-that, e.g., &quot;Christian belief-in Jesus is a matter of growing toward Him, whatever the more precise details of the theoretical context in which this takes place.&quot; Almost everyone else is skeptical about the &quot;whatever&quot; here; most people hold that growing toward Christ is something we do as communities, i.e., as churches and thus presupposes these communities being able to function as communities; almost everyone else holds that whether precise details of the theoretical context matter is a &lt;i&gt;practical&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;not a &lt;i&gt;theoretical&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;question, that has to be determined on a &lt;i&gt;case-by-case basis&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;and not as a &lt;i&gt;general rule for every situation&lt;/i&gt;. Nemes has confused a question of the doctrinal conditions for ecclesial practice for a question of the epistemological questions for a purely theoretical exploration of doctrine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All communities assess whether people are actually participating in the communal project; for communities where particular principles are involved, this may involve assessing whether people are using community offices, community resources, or community time to spread principles subversive or destructive of the communal project. Communities have authority over who can participate in the community, and in what way. Every community privileges certain views as valuable to the communal project and depreciates views that cause problems for the communal project; depending on the community, this may sometimes be backed by exhortation, rebuke, or formal penalties involving censure, removal of office, restriction of resource use, or expulsion. That churches are communities is undeniable, that they in fact back their communal projects with exhortation, rebuke, or penalty is undeniable, so the only question, really, is that of what should be included in the appropriate practical powers of churches given their nature and goals, of whether they should be doing these things. This is a practical question that has more in common with ethics than with epistemology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I regard this as the fundamentally fatal objection to Nemes's argument. There are some others, more minor. For instance, I was struck by this passage:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&amp;nbsp;A person first confronted with the notion of a theology without anathemas might immediately think of Pauls anathema against those who preach another gospel in Gal. 1:89. If Paul could do this, why shouldnt the practice of anathematization be permissible or even necessary at times in the present day? By way of response, one could first note that it is not clear that Paul is in fact offering a formal anathema rather than simply engaging in extreme rhetoric. But it is also worth noting that the case is not the same in later theology. The Gentiles had received the Holy Spirit, proof that God had chosen them, and yet were told that they had to submit to circumcision in order to be proper members of the people of Gods Messiah. There was an empirical disproof of the alternative position at hand, and Paul does not hesitate to use it (Gal. 3:23). &lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Part of the issue here intersects with what is noted above. I don't really know what Nemes thinks a &quot;formal 'anathema'&quot; is, if not a declaration of something as anathema in a public document (as Galatians, intended like most of the New Testament epistles to be read in public, is) put forward as authoritative for guiding action. Nemes comes close to recognizing the distinction between practical acts in a community (such as formal anathemas) and rhetorical presentations of doctrine, but this is not really consistent with his argument, which is all about the latter -- if Paul is engaging even in &quot;extreme rhetoric&quot;, then he is doing something analogous to what Nemes has actually been criticizing. But more than this, referring to Paul's rhetorical questions in Galatians 3:2-3 as &quot;empirical disproof&quot; is such a bizarre stretching of the term 'empirical' that I no longer know what it is supposed to mean. The passage including the immediately preceding and following verses for context:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;You foolish Galatians! Who has bewitched you? Before your very eyes Jesus Christ was clearly portrayed as crucified. I would like to learn just one thing from you: Did you receive the Spirit by the works of the law, or by believing what you heard? Are you so foolish? After beginning by means of the Spirit, are you now trying to finish by means of the flesh? Have you experienced so much in vainif it really was in vain? So again I ask, does God give you his Spirit and work miracles among you by the works of the law, or by your believing what you heard? So also Abraham believed God, and it was credited to him as righteousness. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=galatians%203&amp;amp;version=NIV&quot;&gt;Gal. 3:1-5 NIV&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We have a reference in 3:1 to Jesus being clearly portrayed as crucified &quot;before your eyes&quot;, but this is related to the immediately preceding verse, the last verse in Galatians 2, which says that if righteousness is through the law, Christ died for nothing; it is emphasizing that the message that was publicly announced (another way we could translate 'clearly portrayed') was one of Christ crucified. Galatians 3:4, here translated 'experience', might be thought to suggest empirical disproof, but the word is actually &lt;i&gt;epathete&lt;/i&gt;, which means 'endured' or 'suffered', and thus is clearly referring to the common Pauline theme that our own sufferings for Christ are connected to Christ's suffering for us. It extends the point that Paul is already making -- the Galatians are treating Christ's crucifixion as in vain, they are lacking in understanding and 'bewitched' so that they have deviated from the gospel of Christ crucified that was actually preached to them, they are ignoring that what made them part of the faithful was believing the doctrine, they are making their own suffering for Christ crucified to be in vain. None of this is &quot;empirical disproof&quot; of the thesis in question. And the point of the miracles in Galatians 3:5 is not that the miracles are empirical signs of what is being proven but just to reiterate the same rhetorical question. Paul is not assuming that the Galatians have to check their experience of miracles to see if he's right; he's making the point that their interpretation is foolish because it would make their lives as Christians pointless. This is a practical argument, not an empirical one.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And guess what rhetoric comes up historically when people are talking about orthodoxy and heresy? That such-and-such position is without understanding of the gospel that was actually received, that it makes Christ's sacrifice in vain, that it makes pointless the sufferings of the martyrs, that it would make nonsense of the actual doctrine and practice of the Church or of Christian life. Whether or not one regards this as true in any given case, it doesn't take much work at all to find these practical arguments being made through the centuries, and, indeed, being made on the model of St. Paul. But this is, of course, the problem with a 'theology without anathemas'; Nemes thinks that Paul is exploring a theological topic by reason and empirical evidence. In reality, the Apostle is directing a church. A theology without anathemas is an invention of theologians to free themselves from churches, because it is nothing other than theology without regard for the actual life in a church.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/4994054507791426417/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/theology-without-anathemas.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/4994054507791426417"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/4994054507791426417"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/theology-without-anathemas.html" title="'Theology Without Anathemas'"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-364191952809656523</id><published>2022-10-30T09:32:00.001-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-30T09:32:31.199-05:00</updated><title type="text">I of My Joy Have Had No Dearth</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hymn in Contemplation of Sudden Death&lt;br /&gt;by Dorothy Sayers&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lord , if this night my journey end, &lt;br /&gt;I thank Thee first for many a friend, &lt;br /&gt;The sturdy and unquestioned piers &lt;br /&gt;That run beneath my bridge of years.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;And next, for all the love I gave &lt;br /&gt;To things and men this side the grave, &lt;br /&gt;Wisely or not, since I can prove &lt;br /&gt;There always is much good in love.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Next, for the power thou gavest me &lt;br /&gt;To view the whole world mirthfully, &lt;br /&gt;For laughter, paraclete of pain, &lt;br /&gt;Like April suns across the rain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Also that, being not too wise &lt;br /&gt;To do things foolish in men's eyes, &lt;br /&gt;I gained experience by this, &lt;br /&gt;And saw life somewhat as it is.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Next, for the joy of labour done &lt;br /&gt;And burdens shouldered in the sun; &lt;br /&gt;Nor less, for shame of labour lost, &lt;br /&gt;And meekness born of a barren boast.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;For every fair and useless thing &lt;br /&gt;That bids men pause from labouring &lt;br /&gt;To look and find the larkspur blue &lt;br /&gt;And marigolds of a different hue;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;For eyes to see and ears to hear, &lt;br /&gt;For tongue to speak and thews to bear, &lt;br /&gt;For hands to handle, feet to go, &lt;br /&gt;For life, I give Thee thanks also.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;For all things merry, quaint and strange, &lt;br /&gt;For sound and silence, strength, and change, &lt;br /&gt;And last, for death, which only gives &lt;br /&gt;Value to every thing that lives;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For these, good Lord that madest me, &lt;br /&gt;I praise Thy name; since, verily, &lt;br /&gt;I of my joy have had no dearth &lt;br /&gt;Though this night were my last on earth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/364191952809656523/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/i-of-my-joy-have-had-no-dearth.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/364191952809656523"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/364191952809656523"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/i-of-my-joy-have-had-no-dearth.html" title="I of My Joy Have Had No Dearth"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-499532535644482947</id><published>2022-10-29T11:17:00.003-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-29T19:19:51.395-05:00</updated><title type="text">The Ordered Beauty of Thy Face</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;War-Time&lt;br /&gt;by Dorothy Sayers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The splendour of the year, no less &lt;br /&gt;Is on thy loveliness, &lt;br /&gt;The light in no less glory falls &lt;br /&gt;On thy unchanging walls &lt;br /&gt;Now, than in other days; &lt;br /&gt;No sorrow can displace &lt;br /&gt;The ordered beauty of thy face; &lt;br /&gt;Yet thou dost watch the water-ways &lt;br /&gt;For thy lost lovers, with a grave and panoplied distress;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Like Iseult looking over-sea &lt;br /&gt;With wan face wearily &lt;br /&gt;Under the coils of braided gold &lt;br /&gt;Resplendent fold on fold, &lt;br /&gt;And girded queenliwise &lt;br /&gt;With jewels of rich price, &lt;br /&gt;With vair, and scarlet of fine dyes, &lt;br /&gt;But still with shadow-haunted eyes &lt;br /&gt;Straining to Tristram hard bested in far-off Brittany.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/499532535644482947/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/the-ordered-beauty-of-thy-face.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/499532535644482947"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/499532535644482947"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/the-ordered-beauty-of-thy-face.html" title="The Ordered Beauty of Thy Face"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-5446759200116491239</id><published>2022-10-28T10:42:00.006-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-28T22:04:42.093-05:00</updated><title type="text">Dashed Off XXVI</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;This ends the notebook that was completed in December 2021.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;rule of law: Plato, Laws IV 715d&lt;br /&gt;Aristotle, Politics III.16 1287a&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Lewis's principle of recombination obviously fails to respect any links between causation and modality.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;What we love we take as a kind of end.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Confucius thinks we should practice ritual and music like rustics, in the sense that rustics perform their ritual and music with a view to their purpose, not to show.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Taxonomies are products of liberal and have grammatical, logical, and rhetorical features.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;algebra as a structure of measurements, calculus as a structure of measurement processes&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;In general, empires fall from their successes.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Steno's Principles&lt;br /&gt;I: &quot;If a solid body is enclosed on all sides by another solid body, of the two bodies that one first became hard which in the mutual contact expresses on its own surface the properties of the other surface.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;II: &quot;If a solid substance is in every way like another solid substance, not only as regards the conditions of surface, but also as regards the inner arrangement of parts and particles, it will also be like it as regards the manner and place of production, if you except those conditions of place which are found time and again in some place to furnish neither any advantage or disadvantage to the production of body.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;III: &quot;If a solid body has been produced according to the laws of nature, it has been produced from a fluid.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;-- &quot;If, therefore, every solid has its accretions, at any rate, from a fluid, if bodies similar to one another in all respects were also produced in a similar way, and if of two contiguous solids that one first became hard which exhibits on its surface the characeristics of the other's surface, it will be easy, granted a solid and the place in which it is, to affirm something definite about the place of its production. And this, indeed, is the general question of a solid contained within a solid.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Steno's Principles of Crystalline Matter&lt;br /&gt;I: &quot;A crystal grows while new crystalline matter is being added to the external planes of the crystal already formed.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;II: &quot;This new crystalline matter is not added to all the planes but, for the most part, to the planes of the apex only, or to the terminal planes....&quot;&lt;br /&gt;III: &quot;The crystalline matter is not added to all the terminal planes at the same time, nor in the same amount.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;IV: &quot;An entire plane is not always covered by crystalline matter, but exposed planes are left sometimes toward the angles, sometimes toward the sides, and sometimes in the centre of the plane.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;Whatever contributes anything to the production of any substance, does this either as place, or as matter, or as the agent.&quot; Steno, Prodromus&lt;br /&gt;&quot;There are no other means in order to enjoy the real human happiness in this world than those taught by Our Lord, namely, to constantly live before God's eyes and to eradicate our vices with the help of a confessor.&quot; Steno, Op. Sp.&lt;br /&gt;&quot;God does not ask us for lofty or difficult things, but for love.&quot; Steno, Ep. to Cosimo III, 21 June 1672&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gladiatorial combat seems to have arisen in the context of funerary rites.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;FIND-SELECT games vs FIND-AVOID games&lt;br /&gt;FIND-MATCH games vs. FIND-FIND-MATCH games vs. FIND-MATCH-FIND games&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;sport as ethical toy model&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;race as a distortion of the concept of tribe&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;In Etruscan paintings, men and women are often distinguished not by physical characteristics but by color -- women are pained white and men are painted red.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;We partly measure special occasions by the work we put into them.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;An ethics not conveyable in a story would be a very defective ethics.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Folk taxonomy is often more rigorous for its particular practical purposes than any taxonomy built for theoretical purposes.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;kinds of classification&lt;br /&gt;(1) placement under a label&lt;br /&gt;(2) placement in a division&lt;br /&gt;(3) placement in a hierarchy&lt;br /&gt;(4) placement in a system of distinct hierarchies&lt;br /&gt;-- all of these admit of simple or graded versions.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Torah is never abrogated, only accomplished in that of which it is a sign. It never fails, but is fulfilled in Christ.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Geometry plays a large role in the ancient world in part because the notational system of geometry was vastly more flexible and powerful than an arithmetic notation without place value.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Geometrical lines must lack breadth or it massively complicates congruency.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Language is constantly emerging on the model of prior language.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The usefulness of language, like that of a physical tool, lies in its combination of mutability and stability.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;-ly as a suffix in English was originally -like&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;'Do', 'go', and 'come' can cover practically every situation.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;'Canons' in the literary sense arise from pedagogical bottlenecks.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A cause is like a genus for its effect.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;John Mitchell, letter to Cavendish, 27 Nov 1783, read before the Royal Society, gives an early clear statement of something like a black hole (body with escape velocity greater than light) -- differs from relativistic conception in that it would still be escapable with sufficient acceleration.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;categorical vs transcendental causes (w/ intellectual beings being examples of the latter)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The clicks of click languages are thought by some to be a form of avoidance/respect -- etiquette in a broad sense, in which one replaces by click or clicks over a name or word that should not be merely spoken; this is at least very likely in later emergences, like Bantu languages.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Languages mix by nature because communication itself is usually a mixing.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Everybody's knowledge of language is impressionistic.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Forms of advertising are driven more by what the seller fears than anything to do with the product or service.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;a Christian approach to other religions&lt;br /&gt;(1) identify analogies&lt;br /&gt;(2) use allegorically&lt;br /&gt;(3) qualify excesses&lt;br /&gt;(4) repair deficiencies&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Humility is hierarchical by nature, and has three aspects: willingness to be purified, willingness to be enlightened, willingness to be united with another (and ultimately God).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;ren : seeking good :: yi : avoiding evil&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;All Christian papyrus manuscripts from the second-century are codices. (This is one of the reasons to think that the Christian community is a major cause of the spread of the format.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;making sense&quot; = reducible to a usable rule of thumb&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Ejectives are often associated with mountain languages.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;characteristic classification -&amp;gt; type classification -&amp;gt; prototype classification&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;writing as a symbiotic system with speech: writing allows revival, extends shelf-life of some linguistic features, etc.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;forms of business ethics&lt;br /&gt;(1) management ethics&lt;br /&gt;(2) workplace ethics&lt;br /&gt;(3) labor ethics&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Julio-Claudian Formation -- solved Julius Caesar's problems&lt;br /&gt;Year of Four Emperors -- problems unsolved by Julio-Claudians become unmanageable&lt;br /&gt;Flavian Consolidation -- solved Julio-Claudian problems&lt;br /&gt;The Five Good Emperors -- solved problems shown by Domitian, but could not establish solutions as stable&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A fossil captures an interaction between an organism and its environment. This is most clear with trace fossils, but it is also true of body fossils; the interaction is just of a different kind.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;For real wisdom does not merely cause us to know: it makes us 'be' in a different way.&quot; Hadot&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Simia Qian on the Spring and Autumn Annals: &quot;It distinguishes what is suspicious and doubtful, clarifies right and wrong, and settles points which are uncertain. It calls good good and bad bad, honors the worthy, and condemns the unworthy. It preserves states which are lost and restores the perishing family. It brings to light what was neglected and restores what was abandoned.&quot;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&quot;Order is the arrangement of graded elements in which each is given its due.&quot; Grosseteste&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Tidy schemes of grammatical gender always get broken by analogical extensions.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Things do not appear merely as present, but as traces of the past with potential for the future.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the sacraments qua signs of Christ's passion as pedagogy against the capital vices: e.g., Christ's sacrifice shows the remedy of humility, aspects of which are expressed in different sacraments -- the self-sacrifice in the eucharist, the compassion (solidarity) in matrimony, the patience in unction, the appeal to mercy in penance, etc.; and thus together they make a pedagogy against pride. And so with all others -- the remedy of self-giving against envy, the remedy of mortification against lust and gluttony, etc.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Study of the historical development of language is hampered by having no pre-writing analogue to fossilization.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;standard language order (McWhorter)&lt;br /&gt;SOV -- about 45% -- e.g., Bengali, Malayalam, Urdu, Latin&lt;br /&gt;SVO -- about 42% -- e.g., Chinese, Dutch, English, Malay&lt;br /&gt;OSV -- vanishingly small -- e.g., Warao, Xavante, Iamamadi&lt;br /&gt;VSO -- about 9% -- e.g., Irish, Welsh&lt;br /&gt;VOS -- about 3% -- e.g., Malagasy&lt;br /&gt;OVS -- about 1% -- e.g., Apulas, Hixkaryana&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;the Wedding at Cana as the structure of Marian intercession: she intercedes with Christ, then directs us to Him&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Lk 1:41 -- As an unborn baby, Jesus is first recognized by an unborn baby, John. The Word is incarnate of the Virgin Mary; Christianity begins in the womb.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Juxtaposing signs in and of itself raises the question of how they are related.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;perceptual evidence: causal principle&lt;br /&gt;inferential evidence: causal + abstract principle&lt;br /&gt;testimonial evidence: causal + abstract + personal/ethical principle&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Every effect implies a source (causation) not itself (remotion) more than adequate to explain it (eminence). (Merely adequate would just be direct transformation or continuity.)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To decipher an ancient writing is to rebuild, at least in model and idea, what makes a script useful and producible.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;All known natural writing systems have phonetic signs, which are integratable with other signs when such signs are used.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;A science like paleontology requires a very large amount of abstract infrastructure -- extant taxonomies, scientific theories from other sciences, ready chronologies, counterfactuals, etc. -- on which it must draw, often more directly than other sciences (which might, e.g., construct them on the fly).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/5446759200116491239/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/dashed-off-xxvi.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/5446759200116491239"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/5446759200116491239"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/dashed-off-xxvi.html" title="Dashed Off XXVI"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-613533606679485459</id><published>2022-10-26T21:18:00.001-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-26T21:18:55.673-05:00</updated><title type="text">Fallacies of Distribution</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;William Stanley Jevons, in his &lt;i&gt;Elementary Lessons in Logic&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;(Chapter XIX), notes that certain fallacies concerned with conditionals in propositional logic correspond to certain fallacies in syllogistic logic. For instance, one such conditional fallacy is the &lt;i&gt;fallacy of affirming the consequent&lt;/i&gt;, e.g.,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the iron is impure, the iron is brittle.&lt;br /&gt;The iron is brittle.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore the iron is impure. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This corresponds as an argument to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All the impure iron is brittle iron.&lt;br /&gt;The iron is brittle iron.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore the iron is impure iron. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The categorical syllogism is guilty of a specific fallacy, &lt;i&gt;the fallacy of the undistributed middle&lt;/i&gt;. And this will be found to be quite general: Whenever the hypothetical syllogism is guilty of the the fallacy of affirming the consequent, the categorical syllogism is guilty of the fallacy of the undistributed middle, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we find this works with the &lt;i&gt;fallacy of denying the antecedent&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the iron is impure, the iron is brittle.&lt;br /&gt;It is not true that the iron is impure.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore it is not true that the iron is brittle. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This corresponds to:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All the impure iron is brittle iron.&lt;br /&gt;The iron is not impure iron.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore The iron is not brittle iron. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this case, the categorical syllogism suffers from the &lt;i&gt;fallacy of the illicit process of the major&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;nbsp; This too will be found to be general: When the hypothetical syllogism involves the fallacy of denying the antecedent, the corresponding categorical syllogism involves the fallacy of illicit major.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jevons doesn't pursue this matter further, but there is another correspondence. Here is an example of a conditional fallacy that doesn't usually have a name, although we might call it the &lt;i&gt;fallacy of false chaining&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the iron is impure, the iron is brittle.&lt;br /&gt;If the iron is impure, the iron is unsuitable.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore if the iron is brittle, the iron is unsuitable. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The categorical fallacy corresponding to false chaining is well known; it is the &lt;i&gt;fallacy of the illicit process of the minor&lt;/i&gt;. Thus:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All the impure iron is brittle iron.&lt;br /&gt;All the impure iron is unsuitable iron.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore all the brittle iron is unsuitable iron. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The correspondence is quite general: Whenever the hypothetical syllogism commits false chaining, the corresponding categorical syllogism commits illicit minor, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These correspondences arise from the general correspondence of conditional propositions with universal affirmative propositions. As Jevons notes, any conditional proposition can be reduced to a universal affirmative proposition (although we have to be careful sometimes about interpretation). Indeed, the correspondence is essential to the predicate calculus, although the predicate calculus goes the opposite direction of Jevons and reduces universal affirmative propositions to conditional propositions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The three categorical fallacies are all fallacies of distribution. According to the principles of distribution, universal affirmative propositions all have distributed subjects and undistributed predicates. In any categorical syllogism, (1) the middle term must be distributed at least once; (2) if a term is distributed in the conclusion, it must be distributed in the premises. Violating the first rule gives you undistributed middle; violating the second rule gives you either illicit minor (if the term distributed in the conclusion is the subject term) or illicit major (if the distributed term in the conclusion is the predicate term).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've mentioned all this before. However, it's also true that, since conditional propositions can be converted to disjunctive propositions, if we are interpreting the former as material conditions, so we can find corresponding fallacies with disjunctive syllogisms. One common disjunctive fallacy is the &lt;i&gt;fallacy of affirming a disjunct&lt;/i&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Either the box is on the shelf or the store was closed.&lt;br /&gt;The box is on the shelf.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore it is not true that the store was closed. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;Either the box is on the shelf or the store was closed&quot; is translated into conditionals as &quot;If it is not true that the box is on the shelf, the store was closed; and if it is not true that the store was closed, the box is on the shelf.&quot; In this case the corresponding conditional argument is:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If it is not true that the box is on the shelf, the store was closed.&lt;br /&gt;The box is on the shelf.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore it is not true that the store was closed. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This means affirming a disjunct corresponds to denying an antecedent, and thus corresponds to the fallacy of illicit process of the major. However, notice that, because you actually translate the disjunction into two conditionals, affirming a disjunct &lt;i&gt;also&lt;/i&gt; corresponds to affirming the consequent and thus to the fallacy of undistributed middle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The disjunctive fallacy corresponding to illicit process of the minor seems not to have a name. An example:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Either the box is on the shelf or the store was closed.&lt;br /&gt;Either the box is on the shelf or Christmas is coming.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore, either Christmas is coming or it is not true that the store was closed. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;That sounds quite odd, but the conclusion is equivalent to 'If the store was closed, Christmas is coming', and one can imagine making the error in this form:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Either the box is on the shelf or the store was closed.&lt;br /&gt;Either the box is on the shelf or Christmas is coming.&lt;br /&gt;Therefore if the store was closed, Christmas is coming. [INVALID]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, distribution has usually been understood as indicating whether a term is in a position that requires it to cover the whole of that which it indicates. For instance, in &quot;All human beings are mortal&quot;, &quot;human beings&quot;, by being made a subject term in a universal proposition, is made to apply to every human being. We could reverse that and say that every human being is relevant. However, &quot;mortal&quot; isn't being made to apply to everything mortal (mortal cats are irrelevant to the proposition, for instance). Since propositions don't have extensions in this way, this doesn't carry over. But the original idea for distribution seems to have been mereological. To say &quot;All human beings are mortal&quot; was seen as corresponding to something like &quot;The extension of 'human being' is part of the extension of 'mortal'&quot;. Likewise, the conditional, &quot;If it's a human being, it's mortal&quot;, would correspond to &quot;The situations described by &quot;it's a human being&quot; are part of the situations described by &quot;it's mortal&quot;&quot;. A universal subject term is like a part of a whole; an antecedent in a conditional is also like a part of a whole. The affirmative predicate term is like a whole to which a part is assigned -- that on its own doesn't require that the part includes everything in the whole. Likewise with the consequent of the conditional.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/613533606679485459/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/fallacies-of-distribution.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/613533606679485459"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/613533606679485459"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/fallacies-of-distribution.html" title="Fallacies of Distribution"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-2582224572756967716</id><published>2022-10-25T15:31:00.003-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-25T22:28:04.752-05:00</updated><title type="text">Three Poem Re-Drafts</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Examen&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;O God, you are thrice holy as you dwell in endless light;&lt;br /&gt;send down your flawless splendor to your children in the night,&lt;br /&gt;for if you do not aid us, how empty is our song!&lt;br /&gt;How clearly all our virtue but a mask to hide our wrong!&lt;br /&gt;When I think upon my life, Lord, I should weep with tears of shame:&lt;br /&gt;each moment hides a weakness in which I've failed your name:&lt;br /&gt;when nations look upon me they should see Christ Crucified,&lt;br /&gt;yet often how it seems that I am nothing but a lie!&lt;br /&gt;Should I not become a sign of endless, holy grace?&lt;br /&gt;My life is more a symbol of the failing of our race.&lt;br /&gt;With your sanguine power flowing, Lord, cast out this sin in me&lt;br /&gt;as the music of your Spirit moves in psalmic melody.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;O God, you are most holy with your goodness ever-same,&lt;br /&gt;and who would stand before you if you chose to render blame?&lt;br /&gt;Not I, my King, most surely I would drown beneath the sea&lt;br /&gt;of times when I have fallen short of where our hearts should be.&lt;br /&gt;The love that I have given has not always come from you;&lt;br /&gt;my hope is streaked with cowardice that runs it through and through;&lt;br /&gt;in all my faith how truly rare are glory's little gleams;&lt;br /&gt;and prudence in me shifts around like faces in a dream;&lt;br /&gt;my courage, not a martyr's, is but mostly comfort tame;&lt;br /&gt;and moderation flees away, and justice just the same.&lt;br /&gt;With your sanguine power flowing, Lord, cast out this sin in me&lt;br /&gt;as the music of your Spirit moves in psalmic melody.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;One Moment in Time&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I fell in love&lt;br /&gt;with a girl sweet and shy,&lt;br /&gt;bright as spring&lt;br /&gt;when the birds sing,&lt;br /&gt;with stars in her eye.&lt;br /&gt;She looked at me&lt;br /&gt;and my senses were caught,&lt;br /&gt;with my breath &lt;br /&gt;taken away&lt;br /&gt;in entranced thought.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Someday, I know,&lt;br /&gt;at the back of the night,&lt;br /&gt;when all darknesses are gone,&lt;br /&gt;there will be light.&lt;br /&gt;Someday I dream&lt;br /&gt;all the moments now past&lt;br /&gt;will be found,&lt;br /&gt;all safe and sound,&lt;br /&gt;this time to last.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Never before my clear eye&lt;br /&gt;for such a vision has tried;&lt;br /&gt;never before has my soul&lt;br /&gt;known such a promise to be whole.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I fell in love&lt;br /&gt;with a girl sweet and shy,&lt;br /&gt;filled with joy&lt;br /&gt;enough for a boy&lt;br /&gt;to taste till he dies.&lt;br /&gt;She looked at me;&lt;br /&gt;the sun broke the cloud&lt;br /&gt;as dawn &lt;br /&gt;takes a scissor&lt;br /&gt;to night's shroud.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Never before has the light&lt;br /&gt;poured from the sky to sight,&lt;br /&gt;never again will the sky&lt;br /&gt;look the same to the seeking eye.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ever and again, I recall&lt;br /&gt;the sun in its rise and fall;&lt;br /&gt;Hear but the name,&lt;br /&gt;the world is never the same.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I fell in love&lt;br /&gt;with a girl sweet and shy,&lt;br /&gt;bright as sun's ray&lt;br /&gt;in blazing day&lt;br /&gt;as it pours from the sky.&lt;br /&gt;Someday, I know,&lt;br /&gt;a future far and fair&lt;br /&gt;this moment returns&lt;br /&gt;from memory burned,&lt;br /&gt;and erased &lt;br /&gt;of all care.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then it seems to me&lt;br /&gt;that my soul rises free:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I fall in love&lt;br /&gt;with a girl sweet and shy,&lt;br /&gt;bright as spring&lt;br /&gt;when the birds sing,&lt;br /&gt;and starry of eye.&lt;br /&gt;She looks at me&lt;br /&gt;and my senses are caught,&lt;br /&gt;with my breath &lt;br /&gt;taken away,&lt;br /&gt;in entranced thought.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;So It Goes&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There is love,&lt;br /&gt;there are lies,&lt;br /&gt;there is lying in love,&lt;br /&gt;there is living a lie&lt;br /&gt;(and loving it too),&lt;br /&gt;there is love like to hate&lt;br /&gt;and hate like to love,&lt;br /&gt;there is lying in wait,&lt;br /&gt;then surprise in their eyes&lt;br /&gt;when shots ring out.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;She hates and she loves,&lt;br /&gt;he hates and he loves,&lt;br /&gt;at times all the same in a jumbling game&lt;br /&gt;where the prize is a heart,&lt;br /&gt;or a life,&lt;br /&gt;or a death,&lt;br /&gt;and the sudden exhaling of everyone's breath&lt;br /&gt;when shots ring out.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And so --&lt;br /&gt;the gun's in her hand&lt;br /&gt;and the shots ring out,&lt;br /&gt;and how it ends who can tell?&lt;br /&gt;I suppose no one knows&lt;br /&gt;who has not been there,&lt;br /&gt;feeling it happen.&lt;br /&gt;So it goes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And so --&lt;br /&gt;the gun's in her hand&lt;br /&gt;and the life-lines are tangled with lies&lt;br /&gt;and soon somebody dies,&lt;br /&gt;and death is an untensing of breath.&lt;br /&gt;And so it goes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The dark is a friend,&lt;br /&gt;the dark is a foe,&lt;br /&gt;the tears on her cheek cannot recall&lt;br /&gt;even a memory tracing the path she has gone,&lt;br /&gt;wandering in darkness&lt;br /&gt;before hint of dawn;&lt;br /&gt;just the sound stays&lt;br /&gt;as shots ring out.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;He is dead.&lt;br /&gt;There -- it's said.&lt;br /&gt;He lied;&lt;br /&gt;let him lie.&lt;br /&gt;It cannot be recalled.&lt;br /&gt;So it goes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And so --&lt;br /&gt;the gun's in her hand;&lt;br /&gt;who can tell&lt;br /&gt;who it is&lt;br /&gt;who suffers the more?&lt;br /&gt;I guess to understand&lt;br /&gt;we would need to be there,&lt;br /&gt;feeling overcome.&lt;br /&gt;So it goes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And so --&lt;br /&gt;the gun's in her hand,&lt;br /&gt;and when love is a lie,&lt;br /&gt;or a lie is a love,&lt;br /&gt;there is lying in wait a doom and a fate&lt;br /&gt;that cannot end well.&lt;br /&gt;And so it goes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We are fools for our loves,&lt;br /&gt;we fall for their lies,&lt;br /&gt;and so --&lt;br /&gt;the gun's in her hand:&lt;br /&gt;like spilled milk, spilled blood&lt;br /&gt;now pointless to cry over;&lt;br /&gt;the tears were already shed,&lt;br /&gt;and she works out a fate&lt;br /&gt;she chose long ago.&lt;br /&gt;So it goes.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And so --&lt;br /&gt;the gun's in her hand;&lt;br /&gt;what's past has passed --&lt;br /&gt;and yet we would love to recall&lt;br /&gt;the lies of the past&lt;br /&gt;and not let them lie.&lt;br /&gt;It makes no sense;&lt;br /&gt;it cannot be reasoned away.&lt;br /&gt;And so it goes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/2582224572756967716/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/three-poem-re-drafts.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2582224572756967716"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/2582224572756967716"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/three-poem-re-drafts.html" title="Three Poem Re-Drafts"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-6900636234340826292</id><published>2022-10-24T11:18:00.000-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-24T11:18:12.234-05:00</updated><title type="text">And You Shall Tell the Next to Me</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;Matter of Brittany &lt;br /&gt;by Dorothy Sayers&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Draw to the fire, and let us weave a web &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Of sounds and splendours intertwined-- &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Of warriors riding two by two &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;In silken surcoats stitched with blue, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;To seek and strive the whole world through &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;For a scarlet fruit with silver rind; &lt;br /&gt;Of unsteered ships that drift for miles on miles &lt;br /&gt;Amid the creeks of myriad magic isles &lt;br /&gt;Over enchanted seas, that leave at ebb &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;A beach of glittering gold behind.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Hark! how the rain is rippling over the roofs &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;And knocking hard on the window-pane! &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;It rattles down the gutter-spout &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;And beats the laurel-leaves about; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;So let us tell of a kempy stout &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;With bells upon his bridle-rein-- &lt;br /&gt;How, as he rode beneath the chattering boughs, &lt;br /&gt;He clashed the iron visor over his brows, &lt;br /&gt;Hearing upon his heel the hurried hoofs &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Of Breunor, Breuse or Agravaine.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Of names like dusky jewels wedged in gold &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;The tale shall cherish goodly store, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Of Lionel and Lamorak &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;And of Sir Lancelot du Lak, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;And him that bore upon his back &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Arms for the Lady Lyonor; &lt;br /&gt;Persant, Perimones and Pertolepe, &lt;br /&gt;And Arthur laid in Avalon asleep, &lt;br /&gt;Dinas and Dinadan and Bors the bold, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;And many a mighty warrior more.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;And grimly crouched in every woodland way &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;A dragon with his emerald eyes &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Shall sit and blink on passing knights; &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;In the deep dells, old eremites, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Victors once of a thousand fights, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Shall sing their masses at sunrise; &lt;br /&gt;And weary men shall stumble unaware &lt;br /&gt;On damsels dancing in a garden fair, &lt;br /&gt;And there, like Meraugis of Portlesguez, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Dance, cheated of their memories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;To towns where we shall feast at Pentecost, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Carlion or Kynke Kenadon, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Each day shall come a faery dame, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Or else a giant with eyes of flame &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Shall bid to the beheading game &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Knights that the king sets store upon; &lt;br /&gt;And some shall find, at hour of day's decline, &lt;br /&gt;The house beside the fountain and the pine, &lt;br /&gt;And learning much of marvel from their host, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Shall hasten greatly to begone.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Some, by the help of charmd steeds shall-- just-- &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Leap through the whirling barriers &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;That guard about the pleasant bower &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Where every moment is an hour, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;And with an elfin paramour &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Drowse and dream for a hundred years, &lt;br /&gt;But setting foot again on Middle Earth, &lt;br /&gt;Or tasting wheaten bread in hour of dearth, &lt;br /&gt;Shall crumble to a little cloud of dust &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Blown by the wind across the furze.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;Or sometimes through the arches of the wood &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;The sad Good Friday bells will ring &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Loud in the ear of Percivale, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Through many a year of ban and bale &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Yet questing after the Sangraal &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;For comfort of the Fisher King; &lt;br /&gt;And suddenly across a vault of stars &lt;br /&gt;Shall drive a network of enchanted spars, &lt;br /&gt;And Lancelot and Galahad the good &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Behold the ship of hallowing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;And first of all I'll tell the tale to you, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;And you shall tell the next to me: &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;How gentle Enid made complaint &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;While riding with her lord Geraint, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Or how the merry Irish Saint &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Went ever westward oversea; &lt;br /&gt;While your dim shadow moving on the wall &lt;br /&gt;Might be Sir Tristram's, as he harped in hall &lt;br /&gt;Before Iseult of Ireland, always true, &lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;Or white Iseult of Brittany.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you can recognize all of the names in this poem, I salute you on your Arthurian knowledge. I had completely forgotten Dinas (King Mark's seneschal) and Persant, Perimones and Pertolepe (enemies of the Round Table), and had to look up Kynke Kenadon (a city mentioned only once, in Malory's tale of Geraint), which I don't think I ever knew. Meraugis of Portlesguez I only recognized because I have been reading up on various tales of Sir Gawain; he shows up in passing in a number of places, but has a major role in a Gawain-focused story by Raoul de Houdenc that is named after him.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/6900636234340826292/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/and-you-shall-tell-next-to-me.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/6900636234340826292"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/6900636234340826292"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/and-you-shall-tell-next-to-me.html" title="And You Shall Tell the Next to Me"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-93194497721866412</id><published>2022-10-23T19:59:00.000-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-23T19:59:03.051-05:00</updated><title type="text">Fortnightly Book, October 23</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;My next few weeks are going to going to be quite busy, so I don't want anything terribly long for the fortnightly book. I will be doing Dorothy Sayers's &lt;i&gt;Striding Folly&lt;/i&gt;. This is a Lord Peter Wimsey book made well after Sayers's death, a collection of short stories first published posthumously in 1972; it contains two stories that were published in 1939 and one story that had not ever been published. (It's one of those collections that's clearly meant to gather stories that otherwise were tending to fall between cracks in other collections.)The short stories are: &quot;Striding Folly&quot;, a chess-themed mystery; &quot;The Haunted Policeman&quot;, in which Lord Peter has to help a policeman who, because he has been dealing with strange and inexplicable happenings, is in danger of being dismissed on the accusation of being a drunk; and &quot;Talboys&quot;, the one that had not been published in Sayers's lifetime, when Lord Peter has to deal with a mystery close to home, as the family deals with an unwanted houseguest and his six-year-old son Bredon is accused of theft. The edition also has a long introduction by Janet Hitchman.&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/93194497721866412/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/fortnightly-book-october-23.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/93194497721866412"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/93194497721866412"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/fortnightly-book-october-23.html" title="Fortnightly Book, October 23"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry><entry><id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-7193878.post-7122858040188358884</id><published>2022-10-22T17:10:00.005-05:00</published><updated>2022-10-23T12:23:35.996-05:00</updated><title type="text">Evening Note for Saturday, October 22</title><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;b&gt;Thought for the Evening: Pseudoplots&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aristotle in the &lt;i&gt;Poetics&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;famously identifies six poetic parts of tragedy: plot (&lt;i&gt;mythos&lt;/i&gt;), character (&lt;i&gt;ethos&lt;/i&gt;), thought (&lt;i&gt;dianoia&lt;/i&gt;), diction (&lt;i&gt;lexis&lt;/i&gt;), melody (&lt;i&gt;melos&lt;/i&gt;), and spectacle (&lt;i&gt;opsis&lt;/i&gt;). Of these, plot is the fundamental to the narrative, the first principle and soul of tragedy, as Aristotle puts it. Indeed, Aristotle's word for plot, &lt;i&gt;mythos&lt;/i&gt;, just means 'story', particularly a story that clarifies or explains the nature of something. There are many things that can be called 'narrative' or 'story', but &lt;i&gt;mythos&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;is story in its purest and most perfect form. We have plot when we have the&amp;nbsp; plausible ordering of a complete action, with beginning, middle, and end, involving a complication that is turned into a resolution. In a tragedy, the&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;mythos&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;would literally be the myth of the gods or heroes that you are trying to tell. It is distinct from the chronological presentation of the narrative -- famously, the optimal way of beginning an epic is &lt;i&gt;in medias res&lt;/i&gt;, in the middle of the plot, in the midst of the substance of the story -- but to have a &lt;i&gt;mythos&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;you need an identifiable beginning, middle, and end, regardless of the order in which you happen to be presented them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plots in the proper sense are very, very, very difficult to construct in a sophisticated way. Many genuinely great literary works have a very minimal plot, relying mostly on episode, that is, the material with which one fills the structure of the story. Aristotle captures this in his analysis of the plot of the long, sprawling narrative of &lt;i&gt;The Odyssey:&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;A man has been abroad a long time; he is trying to get home but Poseidon is opposed to him; meanwhile at home, his wealth is being wasted and his son's death is being plotted by men trying to marry his wife; after terrible suffering, he finally comes home; there he reveals himself and saves himself by killing his enemies. &quot;All the rest,&quot; Aristotle says, in what I firmly believe is an example of the dry sense of humor that comes through even in lecture notes like the &lt;i&gt;Poetics&lt;/i&gt;, &quot;is episode.&quot; Homer had to pull together a very large number of episodes to construct a plot you can tell in a few lines.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I said above that there are uses of the term 'narrative' or 'story' that are not the same as &lt;i&gt;the&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;story that we find in plot, and one of the very common problems people today have in writing is that they are constantly confusing plots with something that is not a plot at all -- namely, a &lt;i&gt;character arc&lt;/i&gt;. Unsurprisingly, character arcs belong not to the plot but to the character element of the narrative, but they do have a narrative structure: the character starts out one way and through responses to events ends up another way. Character arcs are, as Aristotle would put it, episode, not plot. Indeed, we can describe a character arc as a series of episodes ordered in such a way as to make sense of a change in attitude or motivation. You can have very good stories with no character arcs at all, because plot does not depend on character arc. The reverse is closer to being true: a character arc is built by ordering the response of the character to actions and events, and thus in stories with a plot, the character arc just is the character's response to the action of the plot. You can indeed have character arcs that are detached from the plot, and these are not uncommon in highly episodic forms of narrative, like TV shows. Even such character arcs, if genuinely well constructed, suggest at least the ghost of a plot, however.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because a very large portion of the narrative art that people read and watch today is highly episodic, people today commonly confuse plot and character arc. This is one reason, I think, for the proliferation of badly constructed stories. Plot, again, is very difficult to construct properly; truly good writers sometimes struggle with it. If you can't tell the difference between plot and character arc, though, the task becomes literally impossible. On the other end, people who can't tell the difference between plot and character arc are practically shut out of an entire aspect of the narrative, which means that their judgments of the quality of a narrative are defective. They would contest that claim, of course, but in reality, you have only to look at the result of such writers and such an audience. In such narratives, events happen so that the character can do what the writer wants the character to do. If the narratives rely on a few events or on very ordinary events, this is not necessarily fatal -- your narrative, properly developed, still then has a chance of being an excellent character study, and that's not a small thing. You can have a great story, in a broad sense of the term, without much that is the story, in the sense of a proper plot.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, the bolder the events get, the more you court disaster. This results in the widely recognized problem of narratives that end up being a string of incoherent, implausible, impossible, or absurd events. A problem with the recent &lt;i&gt;Rings of Power&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;television series is precisely that Season 1 is held together not by a plot but by Galadriel's character arc, with the result that the events make no sense as a whole because a character arc simply cannot do what a plot does. This contrasts with, say, &lt;i&gt;Babylon 5&lt;/i&gt;, a work of art in which the distinction between plot and character arc is well respected. That series has a well-defined plot both by season and as a series, its episodes are tightly plotted (i.e., a very large portion of episodes contribute something to the construction of that plot), and, as an ensemble story, the responses of various characters to the action of the plot constitutes multiple character arcs moving through that well-defined structure. The character arc of (to take just one example) G'Kar is not the plot of &lt;i&gt;Babylon 5&lt;/i&gt;, but it is immensely satisfying because the plot guarantees that everything in the character arc makes complete sense; on the other side, the weaving of that character arc through a well-defined plot framework does a great deal to bring the story home and give us personal investment in it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Character arc, then, is a pseudoplot that arises from the interaction of one part of the narrative, character, with the plot, or at least the kinds of action or actions that in competent hands would serve as the materials of an actual plot. This raises the question of whether there are other kinds of plot-like non-plots, &lt;i&gt;pseudomythoi&lt;/i&gt;,&amp;nbsp;arising from the interaction of the other poetic parts with plot or at least the materials for plot. When we ask this question, I think it becomes obvious that there are, and indeed, we talk about them sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Melody (&lt;i&gt;melos&lt;/i&gt;) literally means something like musical phrasing, and obviously music is multifarious. However, we do speak of music narratively. That you can have music with narrative structure is knowledge so old we do not know when it was discovered; since the Viennese Golden Age, much of our music has been deliberately designed to have something like a narrative structure, to such an extent that music that definitely has no narrative structure sometimes sounds odd to our ears. This just means that music can easily be part of a narrative. But in being part of a narrative, &lt;i&gt;melos&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;can interact with &lt;i&gt;mythos&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;to create a pseudoplot. This is something with which we are very familiar, since one of our most popular modern arts, cinema, makes extensive use of it, and even gives us a name for it: &lt;i&gt;soundtrack&lt;/i&gt;. It consists in the musical response to the action or actions of the narrative. We are, thankfully, prevented by a number of things from confusing plots and soundtracks, although you can have narrative held together by soundtrack -- perhaps the most famous and successful example in cinema being Disney's 1940 film,&amp;nbsp;&lt;i&gt;Fantasia&lt;/i&gt;. In such a case your narrative doesn't hang together much as a story, but it can still be an excellent study of musical change and mood. As with character arcs, though, soundtrack achieves its perfection in subordination to plot, and for the same reason: the plot makes the soundtrack intelligible, the soundtrack makes the plot sensible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with melody, spectacle (&lt;i&gt;opsis&lt;/i&gt;), which literally means a view or appearance, interacts with action or actions to build a plot-like non-plot. Cinema is a field in which this has at times been taken almost to perfection. In a movie, we are not usually seeing events as we would see them; rather, we are getting fragmented showings of things -- scenes -- that are distinct of themselves. This makes the narrative more manageable as to time and space (a continual problem in cinema), and makes it possible to show things that are not amenable to straight viewing. However, sharp, jarring transitions between distinct scenes cause problems -- nobody has a problem with transition as such, but something has to bind both sides of the transition together. So competent directors attempt to create a visual narrative that is continuous through the scenes, or at least one that is conveyed by visual patterns and recurrences across scenes. The most basic are things like panning the camera; various fades and cuts give a way to make the transition in a way appropriate to the story; when scenes are set up visually, the end of one scene often has at least a token something-or-other that is visually in common with another scene. And of course, one does not merely use the visuals to maintain continuity, one uses them to support the story. Steven Soderbergh, when he tries to explain this, makes use of a version of &lt;i&gt;Indiana Jones and the Raiders of the Lost Ark&lt;/i&gt;, cutting out all the sound. When you do that, you still get a narrative, despite losing a lot of information about the plot: the visuals are at all times very clear and striking and the transitions are smooth and give a sense of being carried forward in a narrative despite the fact that the scenes are representing all sorts of different locations. &lt;i&gt;Raiders of the Lost Ark&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;would be a masterpiece of spectacle pseudoplot even if we lost the sound, did not know the plot beforehand, and only had extended fragments without context.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You'll notice I skipped two of the parts, thought (&lt;i&gt;dianoia&lt;/i&gt;) and diction (&lt;i&gt;lexis&lt;/i&gt;). Novels and television shows guarantee that we know about character arcs; cinema has proven conclusively that there are soundtracks and spectacle pseudoplots. But while thought is certainly part of all of these, arts with a clear and obvious dianoetic pseudoplot are somewhat difficult to find -- it just seems harder to see the thematic narrative than a character arc, for instance. Nonetheless, while it's not always obvious, we can with some care recognize them in novels, television shows, plays, and movies. Dianoetic pseudoplots have a problem-solution structure, and the plot-likeness comes from how these are broken up into stages. &lt;i&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;has a plot that is about taking the Ring to Mount Doom; it has a thematic narrative concerned with the problem of pride and its resolution in friendship and pity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Joe versus the Volcano&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;is a movie with an unusually robust dianoetic pseudoplot or thematic narrative: People who do not know who they are cannot make real personal connections, but knowing who you are seems to be something we develop through real personal connection. That is the thematic problem. The thematic solution is ultimately doing something great with our life in a way that overlaps with someone else's doing something great with their lives, and the full resolution of the problem -- two people knowing who they are in a real personal connection -- is symbolized by the actual jump into the volcano. But this solution and resolution is built in stages: Joe is shocked into recognizing that he can't bear to die without having done something truly bold, then he interacts with three women. The three women are all very similar -- the first two are the not-quite-rights in the personal connection for which he is searching -- and there is a building progression among them that corresponds to and reflects Joe's own building progression in solving the problem: the woman whose bold act is just to say yes to a date, the woman whose bold act is expressed in her (derivative) style and art, the woman who is sailing on the ocean, all of them facing the same problem as Joe at a given stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diction pseudoplots are harder yet, in part because I think diction is much more closely linked to character than to plot, but I think we do see them -- narratives sometimes shift in tone. I think this is most visible in epics, in part because they give us so much material to work with. We see this in &lt;i&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/i&gt;, again: we move back and forth from colloquial and sublime styles. Diction also helps express mood, so we get shifts of mood depending on the kinds of situation through which the action runs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently re-watched &lt;i&gt;The Expanse&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;and am currently going through audiobook versions of the books. The books have some advantages over the series, but one point on which the television series has so far done much better than the books is on the lexical narrative. There is some variation in the narrator-voice, presumably because of how the book was written -- James S. A. Corey is actual two co-authors who work out a basic story together, then divide it up into chapters with viewpoint characters, each author taking different characters, after which they revise cooperatively -- but it doesn't really progress at all, and the diction of the books is remarkably flat. One aspect of this that I find a little jarring is that characters rarely modulate their cursing according to situation. I don't care how far in the future we go, watching your language around people on whom your livelihood or status depends is universal. The only one who really noticeably does this, though, is Chrisjen Avasarala when talking to her superiors -- and since she doesn't have many superiors, that is not often. I know oil toughs and rednecks who have a better sense of when and how and in what company to swear than most of the characters. The series toned down the swearing, no doubt for practical reasons, and one of the results is that the lexical narrative makes much more sense -- people swear with people they know, they swear in moments of intensity, and while Avasarala still swears like a sailor in inappropriate situations, she's the only one who does, and it highlights both her status (she can get away with it) and her frankness (she speaks her mind) and the fact that she's often talking to people about extremely serious situations (the swearing makes sense in context). And because people aren't swearing so much, it's easier to distinguish manners of talking and how they relate to the events that are happening. That's a small lexical point in works that have a lot of speech, but it shows how the lexical narrative works: different ways people talk are like the conversational soundtrack.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are many complications that arise with all of these pseudoplots. But, in any case, this is enough to establish their existence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Various Links of Interest&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* &quot;The Neglected Books Page&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://neglectedbooks.com/?p=9271&quot;&gt;looks at Sigrid Undset's early novel, &lt;i&gt;Jenny&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Sacheen Littlefeather was famous as a Native American celebrity and activist, but information has come to light that suggests that she was not Native American at all. Jacqueline Keeler, a Navajo writer who has been investigating the phenomenon of non-Indians pretending to be Indian, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfchronicle.com/opinion/openforum/article/Sacheen-Littlefeather-oscar-Native-pretendian-17520648.php?utm_campaign=CMS%20Sharing%20Tools%20(Premium)&amp;amp;utm_source=t.co&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&quot;&gt;lays out the reasons to think this the case&lt;/a&gt;. She has family members who claim it was made-up, there is no record of her family having any connection with the Apache, and some of the claims she made don't seem to fit the facts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Amrouche Moktefi &amp;amp; Jens Lemanski, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/MOKOTO&quot;&gt;On the Origin of Venn Diagrams&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* David Landy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/LANISA-2&quot;&gt;Is Shepherd a Bundle Theorist?&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Greg Bamford, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/BAMFAF&quot;&gt;Function and Forethought in Design&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Eddy Keming Chen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/CHETSO-31&quot;&gt;The Simplicity of Physical Laws&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;* Boris Hennig, &lt;a href=&quot;https://philarchive.org/rec/HENAAM-3&quot;&gt;Aitiai as Middle Terms&lt;/a&gt; (PDF)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Currently Reading&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas Joseph White, OP, &lt;i&gt;The Trinity: On the Nature and Mystery of the One God&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;John C. Wright, &lt;i&gt;The Vindication of Man&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Christian Raab, OSB, &lt;i&gt;Understanding the Religious Priesthood: History, Controversy, Theology&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rod Girle, &lt;i&gt;Modal Logics and Philosophy&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;James S. A. Corey, &lt;i&gt;Caliban's War&lt;/i&gt;&amp;nbsp;(audiobook)&lt;/p&gt;</content><link rel="replies" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/feeds/7122858040188358884/comments/default" title="Post Comments"><link rel="replies" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/evening-note-for-saturday-october-22.html#comment-form" title="0 Comments"><link rel="edit" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/7122858040188358884"><link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.blogger.com/feeds/7193878/posts/default/7122858040188358884"><link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://branemrys.blogspot.com/2022/10/evening-note-for-saturday-october-22.html" title="Evening Note for Saturday, October 22"><author><name>Brandon</name><uri>http://www.blogger.com/profile/06698839146562734910</uri><email>noreply@blogger.com</email><gd:image rel="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005#thumbnail" width="16" height="16" src="https://img1.blogblog.com/img/b16-rounded.gif"/></author><thr:total>0</thr:total></entry></feed>