<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Super Good Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[We specialize in Solidus, Rails, and React]]></description><link>https://supergood.software</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 19:03:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Senior Developer]]></title><description><![CDATA[Software Developer (Senior) Location: 🇨🇦 We’re hiring for a senior-level full-stack Ruby on Rails developer position in Canada. About Us…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/senior-developer/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/senior-developer/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Software Developer (Senior)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location: 🇨🇦&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re hiring for a senior-level full-stack Ruby on Rails developer position in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About Us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re a remote-only development agency that focuses on eCommerce applications that use the open-source &lt;a href=&quot;https://solidus.io/&quot;&gt;Solidus&lt;/a&gt; platform. Because of our specialization we’re able to find fantastic clients who we build healthy, long-term relationships with. Don’t expect to find any fixed-bid projects on tight deadlines here; we only work on projects where our values are aligned with our clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our internal mission is to create a culture of learning where everyone is given the resources they need to develop their skills. This means investing in our team through internal education, knowledge sharing, conferences and other activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the many benefits you’ll enjoy here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competitive salary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit sharing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extended benefits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum 3 weeks vacation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible sick/personal days policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular pair programming sessions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conference trips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunities to do open-source work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular company updates regarding all aspects of the business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full transparency on company financials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About The Role&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a senior developer at Super Good, you’ll be working as part of a team to build new features, fix bugs, write documentation, design new systems, optimize code, help make technical decisions, create automated tests, triage issues, upgrade applications, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main technologies we work with are Ruby on Rails, Solidus, and React, but no two projects are the same, so expect opportunities to try new tools and technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The starting salary range for this position is $90,000-130,000/year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for developers who care about doing great work and improving at their craft. That doesn’t mean spending your nights and weekends hacking on side projects; we’re just looking for people who bring a desire to learn and improve to the work they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Qualifications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To us, a senior developer is someone who not only has a complete working understanding of the tools and techniques relevant to their expertise, but also understands the reasoning behind those techniques and is thoughtful in their application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for someone who has at least 5 years of experience working as a software developer and experience with either Spree/Solidus or significant experience with Ruby on Rails. On top of that, we’re looking for someone who has experience with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL and database design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technical planning and leading technical teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test-Driven Development and automated tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;deploying and monitoring web applications and infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;agile methodologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally we do a lot of work with the following technologies, so experience with any of them is an asset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;React.js and the React ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PostgreSQL and MySQL&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ElasticSearch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern JavaScript (ES2015+)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TypeScript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heroku&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AWS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Diversity, Inclusion, and Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe that creating a company culture of inclusion and building a team with diverse experiences and viewpoints is critical to our success. We encourage women, people of colour, indigenous people, people with disabilities, members of the LGBTQ+ community and members of other underrepresented groups to apply. We strive to offer a fair and accessible recruitment process to everyone. Please reach out if you have feedback or require accommodations to make our recruitment process more accessible to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How To Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send your resume (and optionally cover letter) to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:careers@super.gd&quot;&gt;careers@super.gd&lt;/a&gt; and include “Senior Developer” in the subject line so it’s clear which position you are applying for.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Intermediate Developer]]></title><description><![CDATA[Software Developer (Intermediate) Location: 🇨🇦 We’re hiring intermediate-level full-stack Ruby on Rails developers in Canada. About Us We…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/intermediate-developer/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/intermediate-developer/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Software Developer (Intermediate)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Location: 🇨🇦&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re hiring intermediate-level full-stack Ruby on Rails developers in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About Us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re a remote-only development agency that focuses on eCommerce applications that use the open-source &lt;a href=&quot;https://solidus.io/&quot;&gt;Solidus&lt;/a&gt; platform. Because of our specialization we’re able to find fantastic clients who we build healthy, long-term relationships with. Don’t expect to find any fixed-bid projects on tight deadlines here; we only work on projects where our values are aligned with our clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our internal mission is to create a culture of learning where everyone is given the resources they need to develop their skills. This means investing in our team through internal education, knowledge sharing, conferences and other activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the many benefits you’ll enjoy here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Competitive salary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit sharing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extended benefits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimum 3 weeks vacation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible sick/personal days policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular pair programming sessions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conference trips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunities to do open-source work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regular company updates regarding all aspects of the business&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Full transparency on company financials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About The Role&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a intermediate developer at Super Good, you’ll be working as part of a team to build
new features, fix bugs, write documentation, design new systems, optimize code, help make technical decisions, create automated tests, triage issues, upgrade applications, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main technologies we work with are Ruby on Rails, Solidus, and React, but no two projects are the same, so expect opportunities to try new tools and technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The starting salary range for this position is $70,000-90,000/year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;About You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re looking for developers who care about doing great work and improving at their craft. That doesn’t mean spending your nights and weekends hacking on side projects; we’re just looking for people who bring a desire to learn and improve to the work they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Qualifications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term “intermediate developer” can mean a lot of things. We’re looking
for someone who has at least 2 years of experience working as a software developer, but what’s really important is that you have a functional understanding of the tools and techniques relevant to your experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have experience building web applications and a good understanding of HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. Our ideal candidate has experience with Spree or Solidus or significant experience with Ruby on Rails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We work with the following technologies, so experience with any of them is an asset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;React.js and the React ecosystem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL (especially with PostgreSQL and MySQL)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ElasticSearch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern JavaScript (ES2015+)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TypeScript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heroku&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AWS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also expect some familiarity or experience with testing and test-driven development, agile methodologies, and object oriented software design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Diversity, Inclusion, and Accessibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe that creating a company culture of inclusion and building a team with diverse experiences and viewpoints is critical to our success. We encourage women, people of colour, indigenous people, people with disabilities, members of the LGBTQ+ community and members of other underrepresented groups to apply. We strive to offer a fair and accessible recruitment process to everyone. Please reach out if you have feedback or require accommodations to make our recruitment process more accessible to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How To Apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send your resume (and optionally cover letter) to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:careers@super.gd&quot;&gt;careers@super.gd&lt;/a&gt; and include “Intermediate Developer” in the subject line so it’s clear which position you are applying for.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Privacy Policy Last updated: April 04, 2022 This Privacy Policy describes Our policies and procedures on the collection, use and disclosure…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/privacypolicy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/privacypolicy/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Privacy Policy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last updated: April 04, 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Privacy Policy describes Our policies and procedures on the collection, use and disclosure of Your information when You use the Service and tells You about Your privacy rights and how the law protects You.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use Your Personal data to provide and improve the Service. By using the Service, You agree to the collection and use of information in accordance with this Privacy Policy. This Privacy Policy has been created with the help of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacypolicies.com/blog/privacy-policy-template/&quot;&gt;Privacy Policy Template&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interpretation and Definitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interpretation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The words of which the initial letter is capitalized have meanings defined under the following conditions. The following definitions shall have the same meaning regardless of whether they appear in singular or in plural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Definitions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this Privacy Policy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Account&lt;/strong&gt; means a unique account created for You to access our Service or parts of our Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company&lt;/strong&gt; (referred to as either “the Company”, “We”, “Us” or “Our” in this Agreement) refers to Super Good Software Inc., 105-1152 Johnson Street, Victoria V8V3N8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cookies&lt;/strong&gt; are small files that are placed on Your computer, mobile device or any other device by a website, containing the details of Your browsing history on that website among its many uses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Country&lt;/strong&gt; refers to: British Columbia, Canada&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Device&lt;/strong&gt; means any device that can access the Service such as a computer, a cellphone or a digital tablet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Data&lt;/strong&gt; is any information that relates to an identified or identifiable individual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the Website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service Provider&lt;/strong&gt; means any natural or legal person who processes the data on behalf of the Company. It refers to third-party companies or individuals employed by the Company to facilitate the Service, to provide the Service on behalf of the Company, to perform services related to the Service or to assist the Company in analyzing how the Service is used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Usage Data&lt;/strong&gt; refers to data collected automatically, either generated by the use of the Service or from the Service infrastructure itself (for example, the duration of a page visit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Website&lt;/strong&gt; refers to Super Good Software Inc., accessible from &lt;a href=&quot;https://supergood.software/&quot;&gt;https://supergood.software/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You&lt;/strong&gt; means the individual accessing or using the Service, or the company, or other legal entity on behalf of which such individual is accessing or using the Service, as applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Collecting and Using Your Personal Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Types of Data Collected&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Personal Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While using Our Service, We may ask You to provide Us with certain personally identifiable information that can be used to contact or identify You. Personally identifiable information may include, but is not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email address&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First name and last name&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phone number&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usage Data&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Usage Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usage Data is collected automatically when using the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usage Data may include information such as Your Device’s Internet Protocol address (e.g. IP address), browser type, browser version, the pages of our Service that You visit, the time and date of Your visit, the time spent on those pages, unique device identifiers and other diagnostic data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When You access the Service by or through a mobile device, We may collect certain information automatically, including, but not limited to, the type of mobile device You use, Your mobile device unique ID, the IP address of Your mobile device, Your mobile operating system, the type of mobile Internet browser You use, unique device identifiers and other diagnostic data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may also collect information that Your browser sends whenever You visit our Service or when You access the Service by or through a mobile device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tracking Technologies and Cookies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use Cookies and similar tracking technologies to track the activity on Our Service and store certain information. Tracking technologies used are beacons, tags, and scripts to collect and track information and to improve and analyze Our Service. The technologies We use may include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cookies or Browser Cookies.&lt;/strong&gt; A cookie is a small file placed on Your Device. You can instruct Your browser to refuse all Cookies or to indicate when a Cookie is being sent. However, if You do not accept Cookies, You may not be able to use some parts of our Service. Unless you have adjusted Your browser setting so that it will refuse Cookies, our Service may use Cookies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flash Cookies.&lt;/strong&gt; Certain features of our Service may use local stored objects (or Flash Cookies) to collect and store information about Your preferences or Your activity on our Service. Flash Cookies are not managed by the same browser settings as those used for Browser Cookies. For more information on how You can delete Flash Cookies, please read “Where can I change the settings for disabling, or deleting local shared objects?” available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://helpx.adobe.com/flash-player/kb/disable-local-shared-objects-flash.html#main_Where_can_I_change_the_settings_for_disabling__or_deleting_local_shared_objects_&quot;&gt;https://helpx.adobe.com/flash-player/kb/disable-local-shared-objects-flash.html#main_Where_can_I_change_the_settings_for_disabling__or_deleting_local_shared_objects_&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web Beacons.&lt;/strong&gt; Certain sections of our Service and our emails may contain small electronic files known as web beacons (also referred to as clear gifs, pixel tags, and single-pixel gifs) that permit the Company, for example, to count users who have visited those pages or opened an email and for other related website statistics (for example, recording the popularity of a certain section and verifying system and server integrity).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cookies can be “Persistent” or “Session” Cookies. Persistent Cookies remain on Your personal computer or mobile device when You go offline, while Session Cookies are deleted as soon as You close Your web browser. Learn more about cookies: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.privacypolicies.com/blog/privacy-policy-template/#Use_Of_Cookies_Log_Files_And_Tracking&quot;&gt;Cookies by PrivacyPolicies Generator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use both Session and Persistent Cookies for the purposes set out below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Necessary / Essential Cookies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type: Session Cookies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administered by: Us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose: These Cookies are essential to provide You with services available through the Website and to enable You to use some of its features. They help to authenticate users and prevent fraudulent use of user accounts. Without these Cookies, the services that You have asked for cannot be provided, and We only use these Cookies to provide You with those services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cookies Policy / Notice Acceptance Cookies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type: Persistent Cookies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administered by: Us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose: These Cookies identify if users have accepted the use of cookies on the Website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Functionality Cookies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type: Persistent Cookies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Administered by: Us&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purpose: These Cookies allow us to remember choices You make when You use the Website, such as remembering your login details or language preference. The purpose of these Cookies is to provide You with a more personal experience and to avoid You having to re-enter your preferences every time You use the Website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information about the cookies we use and your choices regarding cookies, please visit our Cookies Policy or the Cookies section of our Privacy Policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Use of Your Personal Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Company may use Personal Data for the following purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To provide and maintain our Service&lt;/strong&gt;, including to monitor the usage of our Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To manage Your Account:&lt;/strong&gt; to manage Your registration as a user of the Service. The Personal Data You provide can give You access to different functionalities of the Service that are available to You as a registered user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For the performance of a contract:&lt;/strong&gt; the development, compliance and undertaking of the purchase contract for the products, items or services You have purchased or of any other contract with Us through the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To contact You:&lt;/strong&gt; To contact You by email, telephone calls, SMS, or other equivalent forms of electronic communication, such as a mobile application’s push notifications regarding updates or informative communications related to the functionalities, products or contracted services, including the security updates, when necessary or reasonable for their implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To provide You&lt;/strong&gt; with news, special offers and general information about other goods, services and events which we offer that are similar to those that you have already purchased or enquired about unless You have opted not to receive such information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To manage Your requests:&lt;/strong&gt; To attend and manage Your requests to Us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For business transfers:&lt;/strong&gt; We may use Your information to evaluate or conduct a merger, divestiture, restructuring, reorganization, dissolution, or other sale or transfer of some or all of Our assets, whether as a going concern or as part of bankruptcy, liquidation, or similar proceeding, in which Personal Data held by Us about our Service users is among the assets transferred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For other purposes&lt;/strong&gt;: We may use Your information for other purposes, such as data analysis, identifying usage trends, determining the effectiveness of our promotional campaigns and to evaluate and improve our Service, products, services, marketing and your experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may share Your personal information in the following situations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With Service Providers:&lt;/strong&gt; We may share Your personal information with Service Providers to monitor and analyze the use of our Service, to contact You.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For business transfers:&lt;/strong&gt; We may share or transfer Your personal information in connection with, or during negotiations of, any merger, sale of Company assets, financing, or acquisition of all or a portion of Our business to another company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With Affiliates:&lt;/strong&gt; We may share Your information with Our affiliates, in which case we will require those affiliates to honor this Privacy Policy. Affiliates include Our parent company and any other subsidiaries, joint venture partners or other companies that We control or that are under common control with Us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With business partners:&lt;/strong&gt; We may share Your information with Our business partners to offer You certain products, services or promotions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With other users:&lt;/strong&gt; when You share personal information or otherwise interact in the public areas with other users, such information may be viewed by all users and may be publicly distributed outside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With Your consent&lt;/strong&gt;: We may disclose Your personal information for any other purpose with Your consent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Retention of Your Personal Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Company will retain Your Personal Data only for as long as is necessary for the purposes set out in this Privacy Policy. We will retain and use Your Personal Data to the extent necessary to comply with our legal obligations (for example, if we are required to retain your data to comply with applicable laws), resolve disputes, and enforce our legal agreements and policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Company will also retain Usage Data for internal analysis purposes. Usage Data is generally retained for a shorter period of time, except when this data is used to strengthen the security or to improve the functionality of Our Service, or We are legally obligated to retain this data for longer time periods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Transfer of Your Personal Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your information, including Personal Data, is processed at the Company’s operating offices and in any other places where the parties involved in the processing are located. It means that this information may be transferred to — and maintained on — computers located outside of Your state, province, country or other governmental jurisdiction where the data protection laws may differ than those from Your jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your consent to this Privacy Policy followed by Your submission of such information represents Your agreement to that transfer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Company will take all steps reasonably necessary to ensure that Your data is treated securely and in accordance with this Privacy Policy and no transfer of Your Personal Data will take place to an organization or a country unless there are adequate controls in place including the security of Your data and other personal information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Disclosure of Your Personal Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Business Transactions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the Company is involved in a merger, acquisition or asset sale, Your Personal Data may be transferred. We will provide notice before Your Personal Data is transferred and becomes subject to a different Privacy Policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Law enforcement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under certain circumstances, the Company may be required to disclose Your Personal Data if required to do so by law or in response to valid requests by public authorities (e.g. a court or a government agency).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Other legal requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Company may disclose Your Personal Data in the good faith belief that such action is necessary to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comply with a legal obligation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protect and defend the rights or property of the Company&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prevent or investigate possible wrongdoing in connection with the Service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protect the personal safety of Users of the Service or the public&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Protect against legal liability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Security of Your Personal Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The security of Your Personal Data is important to Us, but remember that no method of transmission over the Internet, or method of electronic storage is 100% secure. While We strive to use commercially acceptable means to protect Your Personal Data, We cannot guarantee its absolute security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Children’s Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Service does not address anyone under the age of 13. We do not knowingly collect personally identifiable information from anyone under the age of 13. If You are a parent or guardian and You are aware that Your child has provided Us with Personal Data, please contact Us. If We become aware that We have collected Personal Data from anyone under the age of 13 without verification of parental consent, We take steps to remove that information from Our servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If We need to rely on consent as a legal basis for processing Your information and Your country requires consent from a parent, We may require Your parent’s consent before We collect and use that information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Links to Other Websites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Service may contain links to other websites that are not operated by Us. If You click on a third party link, You will be directed to that third party’s site. We strongly advise You to review the Privacy Policy of every site You visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have no control over and assume no responsibility for the content, privacy policies or practices of any third party sites or services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Changes to this Privacy Policy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may update Our Privacy Policy from time to time. We will notify You of any changes by posting the new Privacy Policy on this page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will let You know via email and/or a prominent notice on Our Service, prior to the change becoming effective and update the “Last updated” date at the top of this Privacy Policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are advised to review this Privacy Policy periodically for any changes. Changes to this Privacy Policy are effective when they are posted on this page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contact Us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this Privacy Policy, You can contact us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:contact@super.gd&quot;&gt;contact@super.gd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><description><![CDATA[Terms and Conditions Last updated: April 04, 2022 Please read these terms and conditions carefully before using Our Service. Interpretation…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/terms/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/terms/</guid><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Terms and Conditions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last updated: April 04, 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please read these terms and conditions carefully before using Our Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interpretation and Definitions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Interpretation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The words of which the initial letter is capitalized have meanings defined under the following conditions. The following definitions shall have the same meaning regardless of whether they appear in singular or in plural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Definitions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of these Terms and Conditions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Affiliate&lt;/strong&gt; means an entity that controls, is controlled by or is under common control with a party, where “control” means ownership of 50% or more of the shares, equity interest or other securities entitled to vote for election of directors or other managing authority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Country&lt;/strong&gt; refers to: British Columbia, Canada&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company&lt;/strong&gt; (referred to as either “the Company”, “We”, “Us” or “Our” in this Agreement) refers to Super Good Software Inc., 105-1152 Johnson Street Victoria V8V3N8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Device&lt;/strong&gt; means any device that can access the Service such as a computer, a cellphone or a digital tablet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the Website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terms and Conditions&lt;/strong&gt; (also referred as “Terms”) mean these Terms and Conditions that form the entire agreement between You and the Company regarding the use of the Service. This Terms and Conditions agreement has been created with the help of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.termsfeed.com/terms-conditions-generator/&quot;&gt;Terms and Conditions Generator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third-party Social Media Service&lt;/strong&gt; means any services or content (including data, information, products or services) provided by a third-party that may be displayed, included or made available by the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Website&lt;/strong&gt; refers to Super Good Software Inc., accessible from &lt;a href=&quot;https://supergood.software/&quot;&gt;https://supergood.software/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You&lt;/strong&gt; means the individual accessing or using the Service, or the company, or other legal entity on behalf of which such individual is accessing or using the Service, as applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Acknowledgment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the Terms and Conditions governing the use of this Service and the agreement that operates between You and the Company. These Terms and Conditions set out the rights and obligations of all users regarding the use of the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your access to and use of the Service is conditioned on Your acceptance of and compliance with these Terms and Conditions. These Terms and Conditions apply to all visitors, users and others who access or use the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By accessing or using the Service You agree to be bound by these Terms and Conditions. If You disagree with any part of these Terms and Conditions then You may not access the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You represent that you are over the age of 18. The Company does not permit those under 18 to use the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your access to and use of the Service is also conditioned on Your acceptance of and compliance with the Privacy Policy of the Company. Our Privacy Policy describes Our policies and procedures on the collection, use and disclosure of Your personal information when You use the Application or the Website and tells You about Your privacy rights and how the law protects You. Please read Our Privacy Policy carefully before using Our Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Links to Other Websites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Service may contain links to third-party web sites or services that are not owned or controlled by the Company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Company has no control over, and assumes no responsibility for, the content, privacy policies, or practices of any third party web sites or services. You further acknowledge and agree that the Company shall not be responsible or liable, directly or indirectly, for any damage or loss caused or alleged to be caused by or in connection with the use of or reliance on any such content, goods or services available on or through any such web sites or services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We strongly advise You to read the terms and conditions and privacy policies of any third-party web sites or services that You visit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Termination&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may terminate or suspend Your access immediately, without prior notice or liability, for any reason whatsoever, including without limitation if You breach these Terms and Conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon termination, Your right to use the Service will cease immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Limitation of Liability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding any damages that You might incur, the entire liability of the Company and any of its suppliers under any provision of this Terms and Your exclusive remedy for all of the foregoing shall be limited to the amount actually paid by You through the Service or 100 USD if You haven’t purchased anything through the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the maximum extent permitted by applicable law, in no event shall the Company or its suppliers be liable for any special, incidental, indirect, or consequential damages whatsoever (including, but not limited to, damages for loss of profits, loss of data or other information, for business interruption, for personal injury, loss of privacy arising out of or in any way related to the use of or inability to use the Service, third-party software and/or third-party hardware used with the Service, or otherwise in connection with any provision of this Terms), even if the Company or any supplier has been advised of the possibility of such damages and even if the remedy fails of its essential purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some states do not allow the exclusion of implied warranties or limitation of liability for incidental or consequential damages, which means that some of the above limitations may not apply. In these states, each party’s liability will be limited to the greatest extent permitted by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“AS IS” and “AS AVAILABLE” Disclaimer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Service is provided to You “AS IS” and “AS AVAILABLE” and with all faults and defects without warranty of any kind. To the maximum extent permitted under applicable law, the Company, on its own behalf and on behalf of its Affiliates and its and their respective licensors and service providers, expressly disclaims all warranties, whether express, implied, statutory or otherwise, with respect to the Service, including all implied warranties of merchantability, fitness for a particular purpose, title and non-infringement, and warranties that may arise out of course of dealing, course of performance, usage or trade practice. Without limitation to the foregoing, the Company provides no warranty or undertaking, and makes no representation of any kind that the Service will meet Your requirements, achieve any intended results, be compatible or work with any other software, applications, systems or services, operate without interruption, meet any performance or reliability standards or be error free or that any errors or defects can or will be corrected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without limiting the foregoing, neither the Company nor any of the company’s provider makes any representation or warranty of any kind, express or implied: (i) as to the operation or availability of the Service, or the information, content, and materials or products included thereon; (ii) that the Service will be uninterrupted or error-free; (iii) as to the accuracy, reliability, or currency of any information or content provided through the Service; or (iv) that the Service, its servers, the content, or e-mails sent from or on behalf of the Company are free of viruses, scripts, trojan horses, worms, malware, timebombs or other harmful components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some jurisdictions do not allow the exclusion of certain types of warranties or limitations on applicable statutory rights of a consumer, so some or all of the above exclusions and limitations may not apply to You. But in such a case the exclusions and limitations set forth in this section shall be applied to the greatest extent enforceable under applicable law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Governing Law&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The laws of the Country, excluding its conflicts of law rules, shall govern this Terms and Your use of the Service. Your use of the Application may also be subject to other local, state, national, or international laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Disputes Resolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If You have any concern or dispute about the Service, You agree to first try to resolve the dispute informally by contacting the Company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;For European Union (EU) Users&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If You are a European Union consumer, you will benefit from any mandatory provisions of the law of the country in which you are resident in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;United States Legal Compliance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You represent and warrant that (i) You are not located in a country that is subject to the United States government embargo, or that has been designated by the United States government as a “terrorist supporting” country, and (ii) You are not listed on any United States government list of prohibited or restricted parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Severability and Waiver&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Severability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If any provision of these Terms is held to be unenforceable or invalid, such provision will be changed and interpreted to accomplish the objectives of such provision to the greatest extent possible under applicable law and the remaining provisions will continue in full force and effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Waiver&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Except as provided herein, the failure to exercise a right or to require performance of an obligation under these Terms shall not effect a party’s ability to exercise such right or require such performance at any time thereafter nor shall the waiver of a breach constitute a waiver of any subsequent breach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Translation Interpretation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These Terms and Conditions may have been translated if We have made them available to You on our Service. You agree that the original English text shall prevail in the case of a dispute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Changes to These Terms and Conditions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We reserve the right, at Our sole discretion, to modify or replace these Terms at any time. If a revision is material We will make reasonable efforts to provide at least 30 days’ notice prior to any new terms taking effect. What constitutes a material change will be determined at Our sole discretion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By continuing to access or use Our Service after those revisions become effective, You agree to be bound by the revised terms. If You do not agree to the new terms, in whole or in part, please stop using the website and the Service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contact Us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about these Terms and Conditions, You can contact us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:contact@super.gd&quot;&gt;contact@super.gd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Welcoming Adam Mueller to the Solidus Core Team]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’m excited to announce that our very own Adam Mueller has joined the Solidus Core Team! The Solidus Core Team  is responsible for the…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/welcoming-adam-mueller-to-solidus-core/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/welcoming-adam-mueller-to-solidus-core/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to announce that our very own &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adammathys&quot;&gt;Adam Mueller&lt;/a&gt; has joined the &lt;a href=&quot;https://solidus.io/core-team/&quot;&gt;Solidus Core Team&lt;/a&gt;! The Solidus Core Team  is responsible for the technical direction of Solidus and has the final say on what code makes it into Solidus itself. The Core Team meets weekly to discuss pull requests, issues, and ensure that Solidus is headed in the right direction. Adam brings his incredible depth of experience to the Solidus Core Team and expands Super Good’s ability to represent the interests of our clients in the ongoing development of Solidus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam began his journey in the ecosystem when he joined FreeRunning Technologies in 2012, quickly proving himself to be a talented and capable Rails developer. Having honed his skills on a variety of established Spree stores, his experience and advice was indispensable as the company (now called Stembolt) forked Spree to create Solidus. When JUUL Labs (a major user of Solidus) acquired Stembolt, Adam took on a senior position where he led B2B software development within the company. Having made his impact there, he then returned to the consulting world to join us here at Super Good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adam’s long tenure in the community and impact on Solidus made him an easy choice for the core team. While he’s got &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/pulls?page=1&amp;#x26;q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed+author%3Aadammathys&quot;&gt;a couple of pages&lt;/a&gt; of contributions merged already, it’s worth highlighting a couple of big ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, he implemented the configurable tax calculator interface that makes computing taxes using third party APIs (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.avalara.com/us/en/products/calculations.html&quot;&gt;Avatax&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.taxjar.com/&quot;&gt;TaxJar&lt;/a&gt;) a breeze. Prior to this change, integrating with these services was difficult and required jumping through hoops to avoid making dozens of duplicate API requests when recalculating tax for an order. Adam’s interface makes building third party tax integrations trivial, and also allows developers to easily design their own custom tax rules. We’re especially thankful for this interface because it made building &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SuperGoodSoft/solidus_taxjar&quot;&gt;our TaxJar extension&lt;/a&gt; much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, Adam introduced &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/pull/4477&quot;&gt;order-level taxes&lt;/a&gt; to Solidus in order to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/pull/4491&quot;&gt;add support&lt;/a&gt; for Colorado’s new &lt;a href=&quot;https://tax.colorado.gov/retail-delivery-fee&quot;&gt;retail delivery fee&lt;/a&gt;. It can be tough for global brands to stay on top of sales tax compliance and this tax introduced some unique challenges, so it’s awesome that Adam was able to add support for this style of tax and make it easy for stores to start collecting the tax right way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of ten years of experience in the community, Adam brings a calm and level-headed demeanor, an eye for simplicity, and an uncanny ability to delete large swaths of code to the Core Team. Adam’s addition to the Core Team is a win for Solidus and its community.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Solidus Roadmap Update Q2 2020 Released]]></title><description><![CDATA[With the second quarter of 2020 in the rear view mirror, it’s time to revisit the progress being made on the Solidus eCommerce platform…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/solidus-roadmap-update-q2-2020/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/solidus-roadmap-update-q2-2020/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;With the second quarter of 2020 in the rear view mirror, it’s time to revisit the progress being made on the Solidus eCommerce platform. Alessandro Desantis has just published &lt;a href=&quot;https://solidus.io/blog/2020/07/09/solidus-roadmap-update-q2-2020.html&quot;&gt;the roadmap update&lt;/a&gt; over on the Solidus blog and there’s lots to be excited about. Two of the new extensions stand out to us as big steps forward for Solidus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Headless CMS Integration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nebulab/solidus_content&quot;&gt;solidus_content&lt;/a&gt; streamlines the process of integrating with the ecosystem of headless CMS systems that have become very popular for managing all kinds of content for eCommerce storefronts. Integrating with these platforms is a really great way to provide your marketing and merchandising teams with flexible tools that help them be more effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;GraphQL Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re really pleased to see that &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio-contrib/solidus_graphql_api&quot;&gt;solidus_graphyql_api&lt;/a&gt; is ready for use. It brings a feature-complete GraphQL API to Solidus, enabling a host of new integrations and next-generation application architectures. GrahpQL is a great way to enable your frontend teams to build rich and dynamic frontends without relying on the backend developers to create additional endpoints. This is a real boon to the flexibility of the Solidus platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Much More&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The progress doesn’t stop there. There’s a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nebulab/solidus_importer&quot;&gt;importer extension&lt;/a&gt; for bringing large amounts of data in from other platforms. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio-contrib/solidus_klarna_payments&quot;&gt;Klarna extension&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio-contrib/solidus_subscriptions&quot;&gt;subscriptions extension&lt;/a&gt; have also both received lots of polish and updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third quarter should bring omnichannel improvements, improved support for Next.js, and more complete developer guides. For full details, check out the roadmap update &lt;a href=&quot;https://solidus.io/blog/2020/07/09/solidus-roadmap-update-q2-2020.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and don’t forget to join us &lt;a href=&quot;http://slack.solidus.io/&quot;&gt;on Slack&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Anonymous Struct Literals Might Be Coming To Ruby]]></title><description><![CDATA[There’s been some really interesting discussion in the Ruby community about
adding anonymous struct literals to the language. My Japanese…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/ruby-anonymous-struct-literals/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/ruby-anonymous-struct-literals/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;There’s been some really interesting discussion in the Ruby community about
adding anonymous struct literals to the language. My Japanese isn’t very good
(I don’t speak Japanese), but Koichi Sasada and Matz had a little Twitter
exchange about the idea and that’s now turned into &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugs.ruby-lang.org/issues/16986&quot;&gt;a
proposal&lt;/a&gt; on the Ruby tracker where
there’s been further discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;ja&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yukihiro_matz?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@yukihiro_matz&lt;/a&gt; just idea なんですが、無名Structを簡単に作る仕組みをいれるのはどうでしょうか。同じキーセットなら、同じ無名 Struct が返るような感じで。 &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/OfP6YigiYq&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/OfP6YigiYq&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; _ko1 (@_ko1) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/_ko1/status/1276055259241046016?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;June 25, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What’s a Struct?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruby provides &lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby-doc.org/core-2.7.1/Struct.html&quot;&gt;Structs&lt;/a&gt; as a
convenient way to create classes that group together a set of fields without
forcing you to explicitly define a class with all the accessor methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you needed to pass around a representation of a dog but didn’t
need any additional behaviour you might do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Dog &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Struct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:breed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:age&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Dog
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Dog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Roxie&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;whippet-cross&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#&amp;lt;struct Dog name=&quot;Roxie&quot;, breed=&quot;whippet-cross&quot;, age=4&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;name
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Roxie&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;breed
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;whippet-cross&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;age
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;age &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie2 &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Dog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Roxie&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;whippet-cross&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#&amp;lt;struct Dog name=&quot;Roxie&quot;, breed=&quot;whippet-cross&quot;, age=5&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; roxie2
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because instances of Structs are equal if their attributes are all equal, it makes them a great solution for defining &lt;a href=&quot;https://martinfowler.com/bliki/ValueObject.html&quot;&gt;value objects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does the proposal add?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s some disagreement on the syntax, but the idea is to add a syntax for defining anonymous instances of Structs in-line. Today, you might write this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;roxie &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Struct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:breed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Roxie&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;whippet-cross&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this proposal you’d be able to simply write something like this instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;roxie &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; $&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Roxie&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;breed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;whippet-cross&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This would create an instance of an anonymous Struct class without having to
explicitly define and instantiate the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why is that useful?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are actually a number of benefits to this, but let’s start with why
anonymous Structs are useful regardless of the syntax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Structs avoid typos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Ruby we often use hashes for passing around things like configuration
options and other structured data. Structs allow us to do this without allowing
arbitrary properties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our dog example above, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;roxie.breeed = &quot;pug&quot;&lt;/code&gt; will cause an error because we
spelled “breed” incorrectly and the Struct doesn’t have a member called
“breeed”. If were using a Hash instead then we’d be able to accidentally assign
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;roxie[:breeed] = &quot;pug&quot;&lt;/code&gt; without any errors, accidentally creating a new typoed
key in the Hash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many cases where you need arbitrary properties, but for those cases
you can use OpenStruct or a Hash. When accepting configuration from a user or
any other situation where you know the possible fields in advance Structs work
great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Anonymous Structs communicate intent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing code that communicates its own intent clearly is useful for helping
future developers understand and modify that code. Using an anonymous Struct
rather than a Hash or OpenStruct communicates to the person reading the code
that the fields the object is defined with are the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; fields that object
supports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Structs are simpler to access&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is admittedly a small improvement, but it’s simpler to type &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;roxie.breed&lt;/code&gt;
than &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;roxie[:breed]&lt;/code&gt;. In this example &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;roxie&lt;/code&gt; doesn’t represent an arbitrary
mapping of keys to values, but a dog, so if we’re following conventional
object-oriented design practices, then &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;roxie&lt;/code&gt; should be an object that
responds to messages about itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Structs over Hashes also means that refactoring the code to use a real
Class won’t mean you need to change everywhere its data is accessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;OpenStruct is slow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenStruct is another class in the standard library that provides the ability
to create objects that are basically like Structs, but are “open” to creating
new attributes like Hashes are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is extremely useful if you need to support arbitrary attributes on the
object, but if you don’t you’re just opening yourself up to the same issue as
using a Hash:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;OpenStruct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Roxie&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;breed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;whippet-cross&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#&amp;lt;OpenStruct name=&quot;Roxie&quot;, breed=&quot;whippet-cross&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;breeed &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;french bulldog&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;french bulldog&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; pry&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;main&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; roxie
&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#&amp;lt;OpenStruct name=&quot;Roxie&quot;, breed=&quot;whippet-cross&quot;, breeed=&quot;french bulldog&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, while OpenStructs are definitely great when you need their “open”
functionality, they are much slower than regular Structs. Koichi Sasada &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugs.ruby-lang.org/issues/16986#Performance&quot;&gt;notes
this&lt;/a&gt; in the performance
section of his proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But it says in the proposal that Hashes are faster!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting detail that the proposal brings up is that Hashes are currently
faster than Structs for this kind of usage. This is true, but Hashes have seen
plenty of optimization because of how heavily we rely on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would think that Structs would be faster than Hashes since their behaviour
is simpler. Well, that’s not the case but Koichi Sasada is confident that it
&lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; be the case with some optimization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This proposal also enables a whole new optimization that is only briefly
mentioned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to this spec, we can specify anonymous Struct classes at compile time.
We don’t need to find or create Struct classes at runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the attributes of the Structs is known at &lt;em&gt;parse&lt;/em&gt; time rather than
&lt;em&gt;run&lt;/em&gt; time, it is possible to define the anonymous classes at compile time so
that using this syntax incurs only the overhead of instantiating the anonymous
class without having to define it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What does it mean for you?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, not much. We can’t use this in our programs yet, but we are free to
use anonymous Structs in our code without the special syntax. If you’re
creating value objects, want to limit the attributes on your object, or just
want to make refactoring easier, this isn’t a bad idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, keep an eye on this proposal. Switching to this syntax in your
applications when it becomes available could have performance benefits, save on
typos, and make your code clearer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think about this new syntax? Let me know &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SuperGoodJared/status/1280509476861288449&quot;&gt;on Twitter!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[I've joined the Solidus Core Team!]]></title><description><![CDATA[I’m happy to announce that a few weeks ago I joined the Solidus Core Team, a group of talented developers who manage the technical side of…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/jared-joins-solidus-core-team/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/jared-joins-solidus-core-team/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to announce that a few weeks ago I joined the Solidus Core Team, &lt;a href=&quot;https://solidus.io/community/#core-team&quot;&gt;a group of talented developers&lt;/a&gt; who manage the technical side of the &lt;a href=&quot;/services/solidus&quot;&gt;Solidus&lt;/a&gt; eCommerce platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been involved in Solidus since its inception. I’ve seen the project grow from an idea at the first informal Solidus Conf in Whistler to what it is today and I’m excited to see where it goes next. My renewed efforts on the open-source side of the project have landed me the opportunity to help steer the development of Solidus and make sure it remains an excellent platform for both &lt;strong&gt;Super Good&lt;/strong&gt;’s clients and the broader Solidus community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know what’s coming next, but with eCommerce playing an increasingly important role in the world today I’m excited to continue doing great work on the most flexible eCommerce framework out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking for help with a Solidus or eCommerce project, don’t hesitate to reach out. &lt;strong&gt;Super Good&lt;/strong&gt;’s involvement in both the Core Team on the technical side of the project and the Stakeholders team on the organizational side makes us a great partner for anyone doing business on Solidus.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Solidus v2.10 Released]]></title><description><![CDATA[There’s been some great development work done on Solidus since the v2.9 release. The community continues to do fantastic work and there’s a…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/solidus-v2-10-released/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/solidus-v2-10-released/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;There’s been some great development work done on Solidus since the v2.9 release. The community continues to do fantastic work and there’s a lot to show for it in this release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rails 6 Support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the big things that the new version brings is support for Rails 6. Rails 6 includes many great improvements including multiple database support, a big win for stores that are scaling up and facing database bottlenecks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solidus v2.10 also deprecates Rails 5.1 support. While this release still supports Rails 5.1, that version has hit its maintenance end-of-life and is no longer receiving security fixes. If you’re still running Rails 5.1 you should consider upgrading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;State Machine Customization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have heavy customizations to the Solidus state machines, you’ll like this one: state machines have been extracted from their respective models and can be completely replaced (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/pull/3356&quot;&gt;#3356&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shouldn’t directly impact any stores as this is a backwards-compatible change, but if you’re brave you can now completely replace any of the state machines in your app rather than being forced to hack in your customizations another way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lots More!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were &lt;em&gt;hundreds&lt;/em&gt; of changes merged that I’ve not mentioned here: bug fixes, improvements to the admin interfaces, lots of documentation updates and more!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite small changes is that the configurable tax system that was built by Adam Mueller (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/pull/1892&quot;&gt;#1892&lt;/a&gt;) has been made official (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/pull/3354&quot;&gt;#3354&lt;/a&gt;)! It had been marked as “experimental” for some time, but it’s a stable API that we’ve built great stuff with, like our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/SuperGoodSoft/solidus_taxjar&quot;&gt;Solidus TaxJar extension&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://solidus.io/blog/2020/01/15/solidus-v2-10.html&quot;&gt;official release announcement&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/blob/master/CHANGELOG.md&quot;&gt;changelog on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Working Around ActiveRecord Callbacks]]></title><description><![CDATA[Working on applications that overuse ActiveRecord callbacks can be painful. Saving or updating any given record might cause a cascade of API…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/working-around-activerecord-callbacks/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/working-around-activerecord-callbacks/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Working on applications that overuse ActiveRecord callbacks can be painful. Saving or updating any given record might cause a cascade of API calls and business logic that’s totally irrelevant to what you’re trying accomplish. I’ve got a great trick for working around troublesome callbacks by allowing you to easily prevent them from running as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that business logic shouldn’t be implemented using ActiveRecord callbacks. Callbacks are great for data normalization and caching computed values. Sending e-mails, making API calls, and other side-effects should be implemented using some other programming pattern that untangles the logic from your persistence layer. Excessive use of callbacks leads to slow test suites, brittle systems, and unintended changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I run into many applications with complex third-party API integrations that are fueled by these cascades of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;after_save&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;after_create&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;after_commit&lt;/code&gt; callbacks and are difficult to understand and debug. Ideally I’d love to untangle these messes and pull out the business logic into classes that can easily be understood and tested separately from the persistence layer, but I don’t always have the time to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine this situation: you’ve got an &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Address&lt;/code&gt; model with a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;before_save&lt;/code&gt; callback that fetches and sets the latitude and longitude for that address. You’re on a deadline and don’t have the time to refactor every location in the code where you create an address. The callback is also slowing down your test suite because it’s making slow requests out to the geolocation API every time you create an address. What’s more, you’ve found some locations in the app where you create addresses and already know the coordinates. In these scenarios you don’t need to do the lookup, but the lookup is being performed anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could address the test suite speed issue by using something like VCR, but with a few hundred tests creating addresses, that’ll generate &lt;em&gt;a ton&lt;/em&gt; of cassettes and doesn’t solve the problem of the unnecessary API calls anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a solution that alleviates both these problems with minimal effort. Let’s say our address class looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Address&lt;/span&gt;
  before_save &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:set_geolocation&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;set_geolocation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Hit some API or something...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we can do is add an &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;attr_accessor&lt;/code&gt; to control whether we want to perform geolocation and then condition the callback on that attribute. (&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;attr_accessor :disable_geolocation&lt;/code&gt; is a handy shorthand for defining a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;disable_geolocation&lt;/code&gt; reader method and a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;disable_geolocation=&lt;/code&gt; writer method.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Address&lt;/span&gt;
  attr_accessor &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:disable_geolocation&lt;/span&gt;
  before_save &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:set_geolation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;unless&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:disable_geolocation&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;set_geolocation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Hit some API or something...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now when updating or creating our addresses we can pass in this attribute to control whether geolocation is performed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# This one will still cause geolocation:&lt;/span&gt;
address &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; Address&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;create&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;line1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;910 Government St&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;city&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Victoria&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;province&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;British Columbia&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;country&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Canada&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Here we prevent geolocation from running:&lt;/span&gt;
address&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;update&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;disable_geolocation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;line1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;1328 Douglas St&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works because ActiveRecord methods like &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;create&lt;/code&gt; basically just assign the values you pass in, so it doesn’t matter that &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;disable_geolocation&lt;/code&gt; isn’t backed by a database column. This also means that you can update your factory definitions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;FactoryBot&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;define &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  factory &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:address&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    name &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Jardo Namron&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    sequence&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:street_address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;n&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token interpolation&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token delimiter punctuation&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token content&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token delimiter punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt; Fake St.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    city &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Vancouver&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    province &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;British Columbia&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    country &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Canada&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    disable_geolocation &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token boolean&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you create addresses using the factory you won’t get geolocation by default, but can opt in as needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# No geolocation!&lt;/span&gt;
address1 &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; FactoryBot&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;create&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Yes geolocation!&lt;/span&gt;
address2 &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; FactoryBot&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;create&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:address&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;disable_geolocation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token boolean&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern comes in really handy when you don’t have the time to make the larger architectural changes to remove the offending callbacks altogether. It’s definitely a hack; externally controlling an object’s behaviour like this is an antipattern by my standards, but it extends well to more complex situations and cleanly addresses the immediate problem, so I hope you find it useful.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Solidus Conf 2019 In Review]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last week, the Solidus community gathered in Salt Lake City to discuss the future of the platform and ecosystem. Over the course of four…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/solidus-conf-2019-in-review/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/solidus-conf-2019-in-review/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last week, the Solidus community gathered in Salt Lake City to discuss the future of the platform and ecosystem. Over the course of four days, we discussed where we’re at, where we’re headed, and laid the groundwork for moving the platform forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The History of Solidus Conf&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solidus Conf has existed in some form since the very beginning of the project. In the spring of 2015, developers from Stembolt and Bonobos disappeared into the forest near Whistler, BC and emerged after a week with a plan and a direction for the new platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year since there’s been another conference: 2016 we invaded Toronto, 2017 was across the pond in London, and last year we found ourselves talking Solidus over the best barbecue that Memphis has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s fair to say that this is a big year for the conference and the platform, though. Last year in Memphis it was announced that Stembolt had been acquired by Juul and would no longer be stewarding the platform in their previous capacity. This meant a lot of change was coming and while we did our best to plan for the future, it was really hard to understand what this might mean for the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year’s conference took the same format as most previous years: two days of conference talks and two days of hack days. The presenters this year all did a fantastic job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day One&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ThomasSample&quot;&gt;Thomas Sample&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://karmacreative.io/&quot;&gt;Karma Creative&lt;/a&gt; kicked things off, jamming more than one hundred SEO tips into a single talk. It was an awesome way to start the conference. Thomas does a ton for Solidus and his energy was a great way to start the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next was one of my favourite talks; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cromwellryan&quot;&gt;Ryan Cromwell&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&quot;https://seesparkbox.com/&quot;&gt;Sparkbox&lt;/a&gt; spoke about “Making the Leap to Tech Lead”. At Super Good, levelling up our developers is one of our main focuses and Ryan had a lot of great advice around organizing streams of work and making space for team members to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third talk was focused on how consultants might improve our ability to gauge the quality of the codebases we’re jumping into. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/etagwerker&quot;&gt;Ernesto Tagwerker&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ombulabs.com/&quot;&gt;OmbuLabs&lt;/a&gt; presented on his new tool &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fastruby/skunk&quot;&gt;skunk&lt;/a&gt; which provides an integrated code smell/test coverage heuristic, so you can identify major code liabilies when stepping into a new project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/skukx&quot;&gt;Taylor Scott&lt;/a&gt; gave us a complete breakdown of the continuous integration and deployment process they use at &lt;a href=&quot;https://deseretbook.com&quot;&gt;Deseret Book&lt;/a&gt;. Having run Solidus (and Rails) apps on a few of Amazon’s different hosting offerings, it was interesting to see how they’re leveraging &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/elasticbeanstalk/&quot;&gt;Elastic Beanstalk&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/&quot;&gt;GitLab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the final talk of the first day, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pberkenbosch&quot;&gt;Peter Berkenbosch&lt;/a&gt; went over some of the lesser known extension points in Solidus, and some cool uses for them. A lot of work goes into making Solidus more extensible, so it was great for someone to help raise up some of the lesser used extension points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 648px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/80043e1bf43fb8b16d8d3d9c80785d48/d2602/ryan.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 66.66666666666666%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAANABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIEAQP/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABh6S4LiEf/8QAGhAAAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAhEAEgEDEP/aAAgBAQABBQIAeT1ilLS3P//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8BP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8BP//EABkQAAEFAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABICEiMf/aAAgBAQAGPwKcKq3/xAAbEAEAAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABEQITFRcf/aAAgBAQABPyEykCxO8PBNjgl33P/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQ0P8A/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECH/2gAIAQMBAT8Qh//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAh/9oACAECAQE/EKf/xAAaEAEAAwEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAABABExQSFx/9oACAEBAAE/EEBB2vIYwZTmxYo7FA0TyiiLEq80gBbT4z//2Q=='); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Ryan Cromwell addressing the Solidus Conf audience&quot;
        title=&quot;Ryan Cromwell addressing the Solidus Conf audience&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/80043e1bf43fb8b16d8d3d9c80785d48/6e52e/ryan.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/80043e1bf43fb8b16d8d3d9c80785d48/4254c/ryan.jpg 162w,
/static/80043e1bf43fb8b16d8d3d9c80785d48/033fb/ryan.jpg 324w,
/static/80043e1bf43fb8b16d8d3d9c80785d48/6e52e/ryan.jpg 648w,
/static/80043e1bf43fb8b16d8d3d9c80785d48/95c6e/ryan.jpg 972w,
/static/80043e1bf43fb8b16d8d3d9c80785d48/b3058/ryan.jpg 1296w,
/static/80043e1bf43fb8b16d8d3d9c80785d48/d2602/ryan.jpg 4032w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 648px) 100vw, 648px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
        decoding=&quot;async&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What’s Next For Solidus Extensions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Peter’s talk, we got a talk that deserves a little more attention. &lt;a href=&quot;https://alessandro.codes/&quot;&gt;Alessandro Desantis&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://nebulab.it/&quot;&gt;Nebulab&lt;/a&gt; presented on the state, direction, and plan for the Solidus’s many extensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before, this was the first Solidus Conf since Stembolt stepped back from their role as the primary directors of the Solidus platform. As such, everyone was curious to see what Nebulab has been doing to continue to maintain and grow the platform. Alessandro stepped up to outline everything they were doing to keep our extension ecosystem healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, they’re moving all the non-core extensions into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio-contrib&quot;&gt;Solidus Contrib organization&lt;/a&gt;. The core team of Solidus is responsible for the extensions and main gems, now all housed under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio&quot;&gt;main organization&lt;/a&gt;. The broader community is responsible for the maintenance of everything under the contrib organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before Stembolt was acquired by Juul Labs and merged into their development team, Stembolt had adopted an internal policy that all employees working at the company would be responsible for one or more Solidus extensions. This was to ensure that even lesser-used extensions had someone directly responsible for them who would respond to pull request and issues and keep them up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nebulab has implemented the same policy. While they welcome support from the community in supports the extensions in Contrib, each extension has a Nebulab developer responsible for it’s maintenance. While this policy was only somewhat successful at Stembolt, Nebulab has set themselves up for success with it. Nebulab dedicates Fridays to non-client work: writing blog posts, working on internal tools, and open source work. Time of this kind of open-source work is baked into their process and it’s great to see that kind of commitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of committing to keeping the ecosystem maintained, they’ve done some great work to make that easier for everyone. They’ve updated &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio-contrib/solidus_cmd&quot;&gt;solidus_cmd&lt;/a&gt; to make various maintenance tasks easier and adopted a consistent README format for Solidus extensions to make it easier for those new to Solidus to understand what the extension ecosystem has for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They’re using &lt;a href=&quot;https://dependabot.com/&quot;&gt;dependabot&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pullreminders.com/&quot;&gt;Pull Reminders&lt;/a&gt; to stay on top of updates, as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/github-changelog-generator/github-changelog-generator&quot;&gt;GitHub Changelog Generator&lt;/a&gt; to make sure that it’s as easy as possible to upgrade all the extensions your store is using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, they’re committed to addressing the issues we’ve talked about for a long time in the Solidus (and Spree) communities: &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;class_eval&lt;/code&gt; is bad and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Module#prepend&lt;/code&gt; isn’t much better. The success of the extension ecosystem is contingent on becoming less dependent on these methods of modifying Solidus’s core and providing the configuration options and extension points that real stores need. It’s great to see them continuing that effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really glad to see that some serious thought is going into how we’re handling extensions and that Nebulab is doing their part to keep the ecosystem up to date. That said, they’re only one member of this community and they need the assistance of the rest of us to make Solidus as awesome as it can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day Two&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day two featured talks from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.joelsaupe.com/&quot;&gt;Joel Saupe&lt;/a&gt; on the Solidus API, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/knitcodemonkey&quot;&gt;Jen Luker&lt;/a&gt; on how we can make sure not just our products, but our companies are accessible to everyone, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/braidn&quot;&gt;Braden Douglass&lt;/a&gt; on breaking up monoliths with microservices, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codewithjason.com/&quot;&gt;Jason Swett&lt;/a&gt; on how to confidently modify legacy code, something everyone work on Solidus has to do on a day-to-day basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also had a lightning talk section that provided some really great insight into what the community is working on. &lt;a href=&quot;https://eric.sau.pe/&quot;&gt;Eric Saupe&lt;/a&gt; from the core team described the architecture of the point-of-sale system he’s working on. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.matthewbass.com/&quot;&gt;Matthew Bass&lt;/a&gt; showed off an awesome shipping rate estimator that sidesteps the unreliable APIs they’d normally use, but still makes sure you’re charging your customers the right amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the final lightning talk &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gmacdougall&quot;&gt;Gregor Macdougall&lt;/a&gt; of Juul Labs and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AlbertoVena&quot;&gt;Alberto&lt;/a&gt; of Nebulab (both on the Solidus core team) outlined all the work that’s gone into putting together a roadmap for the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They went over the community survey results, reviewed independent market research, examined alternative eCommerce platforms, and used common sense to outline a laundry list of what Solidus needs to continue to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are tons of stores on Solidus today, but the more stores we can bring to the platform, the more open source contributions we can leverage to make this a better platform for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roadmap is public and can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://trello.com/b/RHPGLLy3/solidus-roadmap&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a work in progress, so there’ll be more prioritization and consultation to come, but it represents the next steps for the Solidus platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Community Driven Solidus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final talk of the conference (and what a talk to end on) was from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Seanphden&quot;&gt;Sean Denny&lt;/a&gt;. Sean is a member of the stakeholders team and did a ton of work to make this year’s conference (and last years) happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sean started by outlining the history of the project and how the organization functions now, before diving into his thoughts on the next steps for Solidus. He’s done a ton for this community, so when he talks about the need for greater diversity and calls on everyone to “take responsibility” for moving Solidus forward, it carries a lot of weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage everyone in the community to go give his talk a listen once it gets posted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Hack Days&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hack days are a staple of Solidus Conf. They help capture the energy and enthusiasm that builds around the conference and turn that into real contributions. Having everyone in the same room helps facilitate broader discussions and provides opportunities for newcomers to the platform to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year we saw everything from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/pull/3392&quot;&gt;optimizations that leverage new Rails 6 features&lt;/a&gt; to some of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/pull/3394&quot;&gt;oldest issues closed&lt;/a&gt;. I spent my time getting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jhawthorn/discard/&quot;&gt;discard project&lt;/a&gt; cleaned up to enable us to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/issues/3393&quot;&gt;complete the migration away from paranoia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Open Stakeholders Meeting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Solidus stakeholders team meets weekly to manage the project, so this week we held our meeting at the hack days and made it open to anyone who was present. Everyone at the hack day was able to voice their opinion and get a look at how things are run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This facilitated discussions around the material in the roadmap, what might be missing, and how to best prioritize that. There’ll be more to come on that as the stakeholders team continues to refine the roadmap process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 648px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/c2a9a3fb83ee9c3df3cc4175695d439f/d2602/alberto.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.17283950617284%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAALABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIFAwT/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABdePQrpGB/8QAGxAAAQQDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQACAxIREzL/2gAIAQEAAQUCcLlmN6saxdFf/8QAFhEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABIx/9oACAEDAQE/AdS//8QAFxEBAAMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAESIf/aAAgBAgEBPwGMWf/EABsQAAEEAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAhARITJB/9oACAEBAAY/ArclIY4bQ6P/xAAbEAADAQADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhYXGBof/aAAgBAQABPyGD2Bl4VJQTl4aFcPmY2n//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEGTf/8QAFhEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAER/9oACAEDAQE/EG4IP//EABgRAAIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABETFR/9oACAECAQE/EEoieH//xAAdEAEAAgICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAABESEAMVGxYXGh/9oACAEBAAE/EJUQtAojxieKgVJSXiFlWeQHWKvaopvWsJpNn3Eh6Os//9k='); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Alberto speaking about the Solidus roadmap&quot;
        title=&quot;Alberto speaking about the Solidus roadmap&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/c2a9a3fb83ee9c3df3cc4175695d439f/6e52e/alberto.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/c2a9a3fb83ee9c3df3cc4175695d439f/4254c/alberto.jpg 162w,
/static/c2a9a3fb83ee9c3df3cc4175695d439f/033fb/alberto.jpg 324w,
/static/c2a9a3fb83ee9c3df3cc4175695d439f/6e52e/alberto.jpg 648w,
/static/c2a9a3fb83ee9c3df3cc4175695d439f/95c6e/alberto.jpg 972w,
/static/c2a9a3fb83ee9c3df3cc4175695d439f/b3058/alberto.jpg 1296w,
/static/c2a9a3fb83ee9c3df3cc4175695d439f/d2602/alberto.jpg 4032w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 648px) 100vw, 648px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
        decoding=&quot;async&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What’s Next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solidus is a community made up of store owners, consultancies, individual developers, and more. Part of our strength is that so many businesses are build on the platform and are invested in its success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest next step for the stakeholders team, the core team, and other members of the community is to finish to fleshing out the roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re also focused on increasing the funding of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencollective.com/solidus&quot;&gt;Solidus Open Collective&lt;/a&gt; in order to hire a full time maintainer. Many of the tasks to support that are on the roadmap, but if you run a business on Solidus, consider a recurring contribution. If you look back on the everything that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.johnhawthorn.com/&quot;&gt;John Hawthorn&lt;/a&gt; did for the platform, it’s clear that a small investment can pay massive dividends here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The community at large is focused on improving the extension ecosystem. Extensions enable new stores to jump onto the platform with minimal friction, so continuing to build on our robust suite of extensions is critical to the continued growth of the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, expect to see more regional meetups and events around Solidus. The team and community are both aligned that these events do wonders for bringing us together and helping grow the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solidus started when a bunch of developers wandered off into the mountains in British Columbia to try to improve the state of eCommerce on Ruby on Rails. While the locale has changed, we’re still here, we’re still making eCommerce better, and you better bet we’re still hiking off into the woods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 648px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/696921de5e58b81b573205fbeb8d625a/9568a/hiking.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 133.33333333333331%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAbABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQFAQP/xAAVAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAf/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAB6MxcLZKCvMpKiwmR/8QAHRAAAgMAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQIAAwQREhMUM//aAAgBAQABBQJNKmNaqKlwdTU4ARmnr2ziaB0arR40mn5AT//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACD/2gAIAQMBAT8BH//EABURAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEg/9oACAECAQE/AWP/xAAfEAACAQIHAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEQECMRASICEikaH/2gAIAQEABj8C5kVXYxzAoXZb3CmadhZXo//EAB4QAAICAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABESExYRBBUXHR/9oACAEBAAE/IaxIpXsxEfB1xpmPD2RrWeYGoEkObTFq8tF5a0zPCpy8NCmrP//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQIAB+/8QAFREBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAESD/2gAIAQMBAT8QI//EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEf/aAAgBAgEBPxDTara//8QAHhABAQEAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAREAITFBUWFxsaH/2gAIAQEAAT8QVHsKOb0X66cW0Ugj2iZ+YMS7FOnMgzOQMusSiB/WBOIfB05PgOnuqD4I0/cNM19nVzBAsD651iG33v/Z'); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;a group of Solidus Conf attendees hiking in the snow in Utah&quot;
        title=&quot;a group of Solidus Conf attendees hiking in the snow in Utah&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/696921de5e58b81b573205fbeb8d625a/6e52e/hiking.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/696921de5e58b81b573205fbeb8d625a/4254c/hiking.jpg 162w,
/static/696921de5e58b81b573205fbeb8d625a/033fb/hiking.jpg 324w,
/static/696921de5e58b81b573205fbeb8d625a/6e52e/hiking.jpg 648w,
/static/696921de5e58b81b573205fbeb8d625a/95c6e/hiking.jpg 972w,
/static/696921de5e58b81b573205fbeb8d625a/b3058/hiking.jpg 1296w,
/static/696921de5e58b81b573205fbeb8d625a/9568a/hiking.jpg 3024w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 648px) 100vw, 648px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
        decoding=&quot;async&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Solidus Conf 2019 Is Coming Up]]></title><description><![CDATA[Solidus Conf 2019 is only three weeks away. From October 21st to 24th, you’ll find the Solidus community gathered in Salt Lake City, Utah…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/solidus-conf-2019-is-coming-up/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/solidus-conf-2019-is-coming-up/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://conf.solidus.io/&quot;&gt;Solidus Conf 2019&lt;/a&gt; is only three weeks away. From October 21st to 24th, you’ll find the Solidus community gathered in Salt Lake City, Utah for two days of conference talks and two days of hack days. If you’re at all a part of the Solidus ecosystem, you’ll want to be there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salt Lake City itself has &lt;a href=&quot;https://conf.solidus.io/city-guide/&quot;&gt;a lot to offer&lt;/a&gt;, but that’s not why you should go. Whether you’re running a store yourself, building and maintaining stores for others, or working on the services that power eCommerce, our annual conference always has something for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year the speakers deliver talks showcasing impressive new possibilities for the platform, exciting new extensions, and strategies for building the best eCommerce experiences out there. If you run a store on Solidus, you’ll want to be there to see how others are leveraging the customizability of the Solidus platform to drive their businesses forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not just the speakers that have a lot to say, though. The conference is always a center for discussions with the core team, the stakeholders team, contributors and users about the direction of the platform. It’s amazing what can be accomplished with everyone in the same room, so it’s important to be there to make your voice heard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, the conference is where a lot of the connections happen that allow us to leverage the benefits of building on Solidus as an open source platform. Solidus moves forward the fastest when the community works together towards shared goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solidus Conf is a great place to collaborate. Get inspired. Learn how others solved the same problems you’re facing. Find someone who needs the same integration you do and work together. This community is full of really talented people, so if you’re not at the conference, you’re not getting the full value out of the Solidus ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t picked up tickets for you or your team yet, do that &lt;a href=&quot;https://opencollective.com/solidus/events/solidusconf-2019-21928ev&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. If cost is an issue, reach out! We run these events to continue building a stronger community around the platform and we don’t want people missing out for financial reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a company that works in the ecosystem or provides services to eCommerce stores, it’s not too late to sponsor! You’ll be getting visibility in front of both store owners and agencies, and it’s a great place to drive interest within the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to see all the cool new things people have built on the platform and help hash out the project’s direction! I hope to see you there!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A Ruby Gem Debugging Strategy]]></title><description><![CDATA[Is a gem you’re using not behaving the way you expect or giving a cryptic error you don’t understand? If you’re comfortable diving into the…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/a-ruby-gem-debugging-strategy/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/a-ruby-gem-debugging-strategy/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Is a gem you’re using not behaving the way you expect or giving a cryptic error you don’t understand? If you’re comfortable diving into the gems your app depends on, you’ll be able to track down and fix a whole new class of bugs that you might otherwise have to work around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no wrong way to debug an issue so long as you eventually figure out the problem. I’m going to outline how I go about tackling these kinds of issues, but if you have or find a way that works better for you, go for it. My goal is to show you how to get started debugging issues that fall outside of your application’s codebase so that you can expand the kinds of issues you can solve, as well as give you a path to start contributing back to the open source community. Where you take it from there is up to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prying Things Open&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do almost all my debugging with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pry/pry&quot;&gt;Pry&lt;/a&gt;. Pry is a great debugger for Ruby that gives you a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop&quot;&gt;REPL&lt;/a&gt; with super powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve added Pry to your project, put &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; somewhere in your code. When your app executes that line, it will open up the Pry REPL, which is similar to IRB (what the command &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;rails console&lt;/code&gt; uses by default.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you have a controller in Rails and you need to look at what’s happening inside its &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;index&lt;/code&gt; action, you’ll add a call to pry like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;ThingsController&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; ApplicationController
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;@things&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; Thing&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;all
    binding&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;pry
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in place, when you hit that action either with your browser or with an automated test (using something like RSpec or minitest), the execution of the program will stop and drop out to a Pry REPL. For example, when I visited &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;localhost:3000/things&lt;/code&gt; with my browser and switched back to my Rails server, I saw this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;From: /Users/jardo/Codes/thing_app/app/controllers/things_controller.rb @ line 4 ThingsController#index:

    2: def index
    3:   @things = Thing.all
 =&gt; 4:   binding.pry
    5: end

[1] pry(#&amp;lt;ThingsController&gt;)&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can type any Ruby you want to evaluate into this REPL, but unlike &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;rails console&lt;/code&gt;, it all evaluates as if you were running it right where the call to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; is. If you want to see the value of that instance variable, you can do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;[1] pry(#&amp;lt;ThingsController&gt;)&gt; @things
=&gt; []&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that wasn’t the value of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;@things&lt;/code&gt; that you expected, you might want to examine the SQL that was getting run when you ran &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Things.all&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;[2] pry(#&amp;lt;ThingsController&gt;)&gt; Thing.all.to_sql
=&gt; &quot;SELECT \&quot;things\&quot;.* FROM \&quot;things\&quot;&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If At First You Don’t Succeed, Try Pry Again&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far I’ve only shown you the features of Pry that IRB has too. Pry has four features that I find extremely handy and wouldn’t want to live without.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;. Typing &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; into Pry will list all the constants, methods, variables, and instances variables in the current context. If I run it inside the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; console inside my &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ThingsController&lt;/code&gt; I get a huge dump of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 648px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/10666911423c448c114cede8b395a225/3f2fa/controllerls.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 57.407407407407405%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url('data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAALCAYAAAB/Ca1DAAAACXBIWXMAABYlAAAWJQFJUiTwAAACFklEQVQoz1WR25KTQBCG83a+g+VT6Hqhb7HeaW1xrbc+gGXK2i0rBncTEhLCYZghECAZzhACE9qaCTl48VX/zAx//d090GZPbzZkarhoMtq6czmjulwllrxPkaDmZLbQh9yW2wLLTX6C654RK8kq9tX3A1V5/OCt57AmCgSeClGgQbrTBRk1II9OnHURm4IqseCQY2gKDKwk0O3XEG3mnwfK5Nc7bkbsSb3GCqOBxvLIYGVssn2KWFNgdshtAddn2gKzY+UIWEkOveE9N7xziQIYTRrPmXU7fwnxdgXJdiXqbaJ9igR1iuCQ29D26VhJ2t7w02D6cjIk9rTBaNLxtpOtDmViQcNbyvHtjxfd3uj/DEVCZyYSOngqDKNQ62dkwyE7UfdcNRKGx8rpDZ3bhFdD351D6C0gDleXRfA2zy1XvT53wI2OlXNNqC9+3/muyrfabDeLLgq0LqNGl+70rslxV0Sm0HVmi8rvytjqcmqIM14zarR825QbIv3PWz78Y0X2oae2RWyyjBos9FSWUV3U7WbB0p3OXKKwIjIYf0P9JaszxGiwZHGo1Xym1JvfD9TZ48fNeg6+t4Bgs4QiRpBFJtBgBTRcQbIzoEptKBMkvvPYurxpCiJmyIHahchXvwx+/vj+avo8/Pbyd/iwmD1JpjaSbGMsEVO+gPSxZOunM17P99gYS2trLDnm+MG15K/L6fD1P5LTF76GIJv4AAAAAElFTkSuQmCC'); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;A screenshot of my terminal showing the many methods, constants, and variables available in the ThingsController&quot;
        title=&quot;A screenshot of my terminal showing the many methods, constants, and variables available in the ThingsController&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/10666911423c448c114cede8b395a225/3996e/controllerls.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/10666911423c448c114cede8b395a225/8e581/controllerls.png 162w,
/static/10666911423c448c114cede8b395a225/67580/controllerls.png 324w,
/static/10666911423c448c114cede8b395a225/3996e/controllerls.png 648w,
/static/10666911423c448c114cede8b395a225/7ae9c/controllerls.png 972w,
/static/10666911423c448c114cede8b395a225/86a1e/controllerls.png 1296w,
/static/10666911423c448c114cede8b395a225/3f2fa/controllerls.png 4304w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 648px) 100vw, 648px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
        decoding=&quot;async&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you scan through it, you’ll see it lists all the methods, constants, and variables available in this context. They are organized by their source or type, and the methods are all shown in the order they appear in the inheritance chain of the current object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rails controllers contain many mixins and anonymous modules, so this can be somewhat overwhelming, but near the bottom you’ll see some more useful things, the method we defined (&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;index&lt;/code&gt;) and the instance variable we set (&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;@things&lt;/code&gt;). If we’d defined some more methods, variables, or instance variables, we’d see them all listed here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ThingsController#methods: index
instance variables: @_action_has_layout  @_action_name  @_config  @_lookup_context  @_request  @_response  @_response_body  @_routes  @marked_for_same_origin_verification  @things
locals: _  __  _dir_  _ex_  _file_  _in_  _out_  _pry_&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the tips at the end of the article for more useful ways to use the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another useful tool Pry includes is the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; command. It blew my mind the first time I used it. This allows you to change contexts completely, moving away from the context where you called &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; into any other object you want. Here’s an example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;[1] pry(main)&gt; class Cat
[1] pry(main)*   def initialize(name)
[1] pry(main)*     @name = name
[1] pry(main)*   end
[1] pry(main)*   def meow
[1] pry(main)*     puts &quot;meow!&quot;
[1] pry(main)*   end
[1] pry(main)*   def greet
[1] pry(main)*     puts &quot;Hi, I'm #{@name}.&quot;
[1] pry(main)*   end
[1] pry(main)* end
=&gt; :greet
[2] pry(main)&gt; wally = Cat.new(&quot;Wally&quot;)
=&gt; #&amp;lt;Cat:0x00007faf3c118738 @name=&quot;Wally&quot;&gt;
[3] pry(main)&gt; cd wally
[4] pry(#&amp;lt;Cat&gt;):1&gt; ls
Cat#methods: greet  meow
self.methods: __pry__
instance variables: @name
locals: _  __  _dir_  _ex_  _file_  _in_  _out_  _pry_
[5] pry(#&amp;lt;Cat&gt;):1&gt; @name
=&gt; &quot;Wally&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this example we define a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Cat&lt;/code&gt; class, create an instance of it (named “Wally”), &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; into that instance and finally examine the instance variables set inside that object. This can be useful for examining the internal states of objects and calling their private methods to better understand how they work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final two tools I use all the time are the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; operators. They will show you the documentation and source code of a method/class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, let’s look at the documentation for a class method that the Mail gem provides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;[1] pry(main)&gt; require 'mail'
=&gt; true
[2] pry(main)&gt; ? Mail.register_interceptor

From: /Users/jardo/.gem/ruby/2.6.3/gems/mail-2.7.1/lib/mail/mail.rb @ line 208:
Owner: #&amp;lt;Class:Mail&gt;
Visibility: public
Signature: register_interceptor(interceptor)
Number of lines: 7

You can register an object to be given every mail object that will be sent,
before it is sent.  So if you want to add special headers or modify any
email that gets sent through the Mail library, you can do so.

Your object needs to respond to a single method #delivering_email(mail)
which receives the email that is about to be sent.  Make your modifications
directly to this object.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That might be helpful, but what if the documentation is out of date, or the even having read the documentation we find that the method isn’t doing what we expect? We can use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; to look at the actual source of the method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;[3] pry(main)&gt; $ Mail.register_interceptor

From: /Users/jardo/.gem/ruby/2.6.3/gems/mail-2.7.1/lib/mail/mail.rb @ line 215:
Owner: #&amp;lt;Class:Mail&gt;
Visibility: public
Number of lines: 5

def self.register_interceptor(interceptor)
  unless @@delivery_interceptors.include?(interceptor)
    @@delivery_interceptors &amp;lt;&amp;lt; interceptor
  end
end&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t have much experience with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;mail&lt;/code&gt; gem, so I still don’t really know what this method is for, but I bet that if I was using the gem and this method wasn’t doing what I expected, this might help me start digging in. Using the tools I’ve shown here, I could &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; into the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Mail&lt;/code&gt; class, examine the value of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;@@delivery_interceptors&lt;/code&gt; class variable, and start to track down how it gets used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Opening Up Your Gems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of ways to manage gems. Some people use gemsets using tools like rvm and rbenv. I’m a minimalist (to a fault, sometimes) and prefer a “simpler” method. I install the gems for each project inside the project folder itself. &lt;a href=&quot;https://bundler.io/v2.0/bundle_install.html&quot;&gt;The bundler documentation&lt;/a&gt; shows that you can do this by running &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;bundle install --path=vendor/bundle&lt;/code&gt;. Instead of installing the gems in their default location (this will depend on your setup), they’ll get installed into the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;vendor/bundle&lt;/code&gt; directory inside your project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason I like to do this is two-fold:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it allows me to modify those gems as much as I like, potentially breaking them completely, and easily delete and reinstall them by running &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;rm -r vendor/bundle &amp;amp;&amp;amp; bundle install&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, &lt;strong&gt;it encourages me to think of the code in my project’s dependencies as part of my project&lt;/strong&gt;. While it may not be &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; code as far as licensing is concerned, it’s no less a part of my running application as the code that I write myself. I think this is important to remember.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you choose to install your gems inside your project too, just make sure you add &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;/vendor/bundle&lt;/code&gt; to your &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; so you don’t accidentally commit all the gems to your git repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of where your gems are installed, you can ask bundler where a specific gem is installed with &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;bundle show GEMNAME&lt;/code&gt;. Once you’ve got the location of a gem, you can open it up and see its source code!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With access to the source code, you’re free to browse, modify, and debug it. One good place to start is by adding a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; into a method that your app is calling that’s behaving unexpectedly. Just make sure you restart your application for the changes to take effect. Rails will reload code found in &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;app/&lt;/code&gt; in your project, but generally not in third party gems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Debugging Strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good REPL debugger and access to the source code of a gem is often all that you’ll need to track down the source of the problem you’re experiencing. Let’s assume that you’ve found a bug in your app, but as you try to track it down, you discover that some methods or classes from another gem aren’t behaving how you expected them to. Here’s the process I like to go through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. Isolate The Problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reproduction is the first step. You’ll want to either write a test that demonstrates the problem, or at least find a way to trigger the bug manually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. Start Digging Down&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve reproduced the unexpected behaviour, start inserting calls to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; in places you expect it to be called. There’s no wrong places to put them. If you put them in and they don’t get hit when you reproduce the bug, then you’ve just learned that the part of the code you put the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; in isn’t getting executed. If you find your &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; is getting hit, but when you look at all the local and instance variables at that point in the code and they all contain what you expect, then you’ve learned that the bug probably lies elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use Pry to view the source of the methods that are getting called, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; into those objects and examine what they’re doing. Use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;bundle show&lt;/code&gt; to open the gems and insert more calls to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; to try to uncover the cause of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you continue learn more and more about what your program (and its dependencies are doing), eventually you’re liable to find something that violates some assumption you’ve made about how the system behaves. This isn’t usually the “root cause”, but a symptom of something you don’t yet understand about how the system behaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here, you can work backwards to find the root cause. This is kind of like applying the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/5_Whys&quot;&gt;5 Whys&lt;/a&gt; technique, continuing to ask “why is the system behaving this way?” and moving upwards through the behaviour of the program to understand what’s happening at higher and higher levels until you have a root cause. Unfortunately, there’s no guarantee that a mere five “whys” will get you to the solution. Keep going until you’ve found the real root cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Fix The Bug&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the root cause in hand, there are a few different situations you might find yourself in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have found that you’ve been using a gem incorrectly. The solution here is usually to rework your application to fix the problem. It’s generally best to use gems the way they are intended to be used because it makes it less likely that future changes will be incompatible with your application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you might have found that there’s a bug in a gem you’re using. If so, you should have a look the gem’s issues to see if the bug has been reported. If it hasn’t, you should probably report the issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it has been reported and hasn’t been fixed yet, consider trying to fix the bug yourself! After all, you’ve been digging through the gem’s code, you’re qualified to take a stab at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, it’s possible you never really found the root cause. Hopefully this isn’t the case, but we’ve all been there. Unusual or complex code, metaprogramming, excessive indirection can all get in the way of debugging a gem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you end up here, you’ve probably got a ton more context on the bug than when you started. If there are people around who can help you, you’ll be in a much better position to communicate the problem to them, putting them in a better position to help you. All is not lost!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being comfortable jumping into code outside of your project will expand your ability to fix bugs, and open up new opportunities to contribute back to the open source community. While different employers have different policies when it comes to open source work, in my experience, most companies don’t care whether the commit that fixes a bug in their product goes into their codebase or some other gem, so long as the bug gets fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fixing bugs in dependencies might also be one of the few chances you get to read real production code written by people outside your project. I feel strongly that exposing yourself to lots of code written by different people is a great way to level up your programming skills. Tracking down bugs forces you to really understand the code that you’re reading, making the process even more valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Extra Tips&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a few more Pry tricks that I find useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting Your Bearings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The command &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;whereami&lt;/code&gt; shows you where your Pry session is executing. If you’ve just hit a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; it’ll show you the source code, and if you &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; into another object it’ll tell you what object you’re in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finding The Source Of Exceptions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;wtf&lt;/code&gt; command to print some information about the last exception that was raised. Adding questions marks to the command (like &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;wtf??????&lt;/code&gt;) will show more and more of the stack trace of the exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Filtering The Results From &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When dealing with controllers and models this can all be a little overwhelming because of the sheer amount of superclasses and concerns that Rails provides. If you have some idea of what you’re looking for, you can use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;-G&lt;/code&gt; to “grep” for the methods or variables you want. Only lines matching the string you provide will be printed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;[4] pry(#&amp;lt;ThingsController&gt;)&gt; ls -G thing
#&amp;lt;Module:0x00007fc27ce15ed8&gt;#methods: edit_thing_url  new_thing_url  thing_url  things_url
#&amp;lt;Module:0x00007fc27ce15eb0&gt;#methods: edit_thing_path  new_thing_path  thing_path  things_path
instance variables: @_action_has_layout  @_action_name  @_config  @_lookup_context  @_request  @_response  @_response_body  @_routes  @marked_for_same_origin_verification  @things&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Stack Explorer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pry/pry-stack_explorer&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;pry-stack_explorer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a gem that allows you to move up and down the call stack. It’s a little more advanced, but I find it extremely useful when working backwards to track down the root cause of an issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lots More!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These tips aren’t exhaustive, so check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pry/pry&quot;&gt;Pry GitHub page&lt;/a&gt; to learn about more useful things you can do like running shell commands with &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;, or sharing parts of your Pry session with the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;gist&lt;/code&gt; integration.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Statements and Expressions in Ruby]]></title><description><![CDATA[Recently, a reddit user was looking for an explanation for a very unusual piece of code: This code is from the Sequel gem. It’s a great gem…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/statements-and-expressions/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/statements-and-expressions/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Recently, a reddit user &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/8zzlsm/def_cloneopts_return_self_nil_what_does_this_code/&quot;&gt;was looking for an explanation&lt;/a&gt; for a very unusual piece of code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;clone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;opts &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This code is from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jeremyevans/sequel/blob/master/lib/sequel/dataset/query.rb#L84&quot;&gt;the Sequel gem&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a great gem for working with databases, but that’s a pretty strange looking default value. To understand exactly why it is the way it is, we need to understand the difference between statements and expressions in Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s worth noting that there are good explanations in the comments on Reddit too, if you want to piece together what’s going on from them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Statements and Expressions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most programming languages have a concept of “expressions” and “statements”. The main difference is this: expressions evaluate to a value, but statements do not. In Ruby, unlike JavaScript, all our conditional and looping structures are expressions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;a &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token boolean&quot;&gt;false&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:yay&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:nay&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#=&gt; :nay&lt;/span&gt;

b &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;when&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token builtin&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;when&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token builtin&quot;&gt;Hash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;then&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#=&gt; 10&lt;/span&gt;

c &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; loop &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:potato&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#=&gt; :potato&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruby programmers sometimes get tripped up in JavaScript where none of this is possible. I’ve heard Ruby programmers say that “everything is an expression”, but that’s not strictly true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Statements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruby does have a few pieces of syntax that are statements. As far as I know, these are the only statements in Ruby: &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;return&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;retry&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;redo&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;next&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;break&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;alias&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first five will all cause a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/code&gt; due to a “void value expression” if you attempt to use them in place of an expression:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;eval&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; void value expression&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;alias&lt;/code&gt; is slightly different, but also a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; boop puts
&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; unexpected keyword_alias&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction between these syntax errors is important. Whereas &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;alias&lt;/code&gt; has to be used in a class context, void value expressions can be used anywhere you’d use an expression, so long as the result isn’t accessible in any way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Default Argument Magic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to our unusual code snippet. When Ruby needs the default value of an optional argument, it evaluates the expression provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trick depends on the fact that the default value must be an expression, and that it will be evaluated every time it is needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;some_method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;x &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  x
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

some_method
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#=&gt; #&amp;lt;X:0x00007feba10331c8&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
some_method
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#=&gt; #&amp;lt;X:0x00007feb9ee8c8a8&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each call re-evaluates the default value, and gives us a new object. It turns out that those default values are evaluated in the same context as the rest of the method. Ruby’s syntax only requires that the default value be an expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can’t write &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;def clone(opts = return self)&lt;/code&gt; because &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; is a void value expression and we can’t try to use its return value. In order to trick the Ruby interpreter into letting us do something equivalent, we just put a second expression after it, which will never be reached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;clone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;opts &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Ruby encounters a call to this method with no arguments, it evaluates the valid expression &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;(return self; nil)&lt;/code&gt;, and immediately returns from the method after evaluating the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result is that this method returns the object itself when &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;clone&lt;/code&gt; is called with no arguments. Take a second to consider how else you might do that. You could use the splat operator (&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;def clone(*arguments)&lt;/code&gt;) and check the length of the error, but now you’re going to have raise &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;ArgumentError&lt;/code&gt; yourself if there are too many arguments. You could provide a default value of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt;, but then you’ll have no way of knowing if the user intentionally called &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;clone(nil)&lt;/code&gt; expecting the main body of the method to run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One Reddit user &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/ruby/comments/8zzlsm/def_cloneopts_return_self_nil_what_does_this_code/e2n8p9v/&quot;&gt;profiled this and similar approaches&lt;/a&gt; and found that this default value return is easily the most performant way to do this kind of early return. I’d never do it in my application code, but if it’s inside of a heavily used part of a gem (which it is) I think it’s justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely don’t start putting return statements in your default values; you’re just going to confuse everyone. I think we should all try to write “normal code”, and despite how vague that sounds, we can probably all agree this pattern isn’t normal. I’d probably use the phrase “extremely unconventional.” This is only reasonable here because it’s an optimization on a very heavily used method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real takeaway is that Ruby has a type of syntax that I haven’t seen in other languages, the “void value expression.” You can use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;return&lt;/code&gt; and the other void value expressions I listed above anywhere that you can use an expression, as long as the result of the expression is inaccessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Afterword&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I expected to discover that &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;raise&lt;/code&gt; was a void value expression, but it isn’t. Raise is just a method, but it’s impossible to get the return value of it. The return value of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;raise&lt;/code&gt; is actually marked as &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;UNREACHABLE&lt;/code&gt; in the C code, as the exception handling is initiated before we get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-c&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; VALUE
&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;rb_f_raise&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; argc&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; VALUE &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;argv&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    VALUE err&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    VALUE opts&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;raise_max_opt&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; cause &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;opts&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;raise_opt_cause&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    argc &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;extract_raise_opts&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;argc&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; argv&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; opts&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;argc &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;cause &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; Qundef&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;rb_raise&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;rb_eArgError&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;only cause is given with no arguments&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
        err &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;get_errinfo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;NIL_P&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;err&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
            argc &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
            argv &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;err&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;rb_raise_jump&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;rb_make_exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;argc&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; argv&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;cause&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    UNREACHABLE&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Don't Step on a Rake, Use Rake::DSL]]></title><description><![CDATA[Over the years I’ve noticed a common mistake where developers do some refactoring to remove duplication and make their Rake tasks readable…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/dont-step-on-a-rake/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/dont-step-on-a-rake/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Over the years I’ve noticed a common mistake where developers do some refactoring to remove duplication and make their Rake tasks readable, but end up causing some unintended side-effects. Let’s take a look at what’s going on, and how we can use a built-in feature of Rake to fix the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rake&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ruby/rake&quot;&gt;Rake&lt;/a&gt; is a general purpose make-like task runner for Ruby. Almost all Ruby projects use it as a task runner, and it comes baked into new Rails projects. Most applications will eventually need their own custom tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Rails app you might find some custom Rake tasks for running scheduled jobs like snapshots or nightly processing tasks. It’s also usually preferred to perform data migration in Rake tasks rather than Rails migrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a Ruby on Rails application, you put your new tasks in &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;lib/tasks&lt;/code&gt;. (You also have to add the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.rake&lt;/code&gt; extension instead of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.rb&lt;/code&gt;, which is &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; easy to forget.) Let’s say we need some tasks for generating example data to develop against in a music managment app. We might write something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# lib/tasks/dev_data.rake&lt;/span&gt;

namespace &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:dev_data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  desc &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Create some randomly generated music albums&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  task &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:generate_albums&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:environment&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Task code goes here.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  desc &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Create some randomly generated music artists&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  task &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:generate_artists&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:environment&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Task code goes here.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  desc &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Create some randomly generated music labels&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  task &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:generate_labels&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:environment&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Task code goes here.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This defines three tasks in a namespace called &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;dev_data&lt;/code&gt;, named &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;generate_albums&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;generate_artists&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;generate_labels&lt;/code&gt; respectively. These tasks all depend on another task (it will run before the custom task) called &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;environment&lt;/code&gt; which is provided by Rails and loads our application code so we will be able to access our models and other code in these tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Rake tasks like this is a little better than throwing scripts in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;bin&lt;/code&gt; folder because they’re easier to discover for new developers, as you can ask Rake for all the tasks that have descriptions. You’ll get all the tasks from Rails, any gems providing tasks, and your custom ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;$ bundle exec rake -T
[...]
rake dev_data:generate_albums   # Create some randomly generated music albums
rake dev_data:generate_artists  # Create some randomly generated music artists
rake dev_data:generate_labels   # Create some randomly generated music labels
[...]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Refactoring Test Setup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem I’ve been seeing happens when developers apply a common refactoring in RSpec or Minitest to their Rake tasks. Let’s say we have a class called &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Bicycle&lt;/code&gt; and to get it ready to ride, it needs some assembly or setup. In order to write some tests we’re going to need to do that assembly. In RSpec, the specs might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;RSpec&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;describe &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Bicycle&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  let&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:bicycle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Bicycle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  before &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Do some stuff to set up the bicycle.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;has two wheels&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;has brakes&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;has handlebars&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if we introduce some tests that don’t need to do the setup, then we have some decisions to make. We can use contexts, but for simplicity let’s just leave our spec flat and pull out the shared setup logic into a method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;RSpec&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;describe &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Bicycle&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  let&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:bicycle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Bicycle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;comes disassembled&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;has two wheels&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    put_the_bicycle_together
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;has brakes&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    put_the_bicycle_together
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;has handlebars&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    put_the_bicycle_together
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;put_the_bicycle_together&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Do some stuff to set up the bicycle.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this refactoring is fine, and I see it used relatively often. It works because if you’re using &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;minitest/spec&lt;/code&gt; or Rspec, then those &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;describe&lt;/code&gt; calls are actually creating classes under the hood, and the block we provided is being run in the context of those classes using &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;class_eval&lt;/code&gt;. Try running something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;RSpec&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;describe &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Bicycle&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  puts &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# It prints out:&lt;/span&gt;
RSpec&lt;span class=&quot;token double-colon punctuation&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;ExampleGroups&lt;span class=&quot;token double-colon punctuation&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;Bicycle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rake Doesn’t Do That&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The refactoring we just covered kept our tests clean, and gave a descriptive name to some shared test setup logic, so we might be inclined to do something similar in our Rake tasks. I’ve done it before, and I see people do it all the time. Unfortunately, it’s not a very safe thing to do, and could have unintended side effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look. If Rake behaved the same way RSpec behaves, we should be able to write something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# lib/tasks/bicycle&lt;/span&gt;

namespace &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:bicycle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  task &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:assemble&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    bicycle &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Bicycle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Assemble the bicycle:&lt;/span&gt;
    attach_wheels&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    attach_handlebars&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    attach_brakes&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;attach_wheels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;attach_handlebars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;attach_brakes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do try that out, you’ll find that it works. You might, satisfied with your new bicycle assembly Rake task, commit this and move on to more pressing matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Rake doesn’t do anything to change the context that these blocks are executed in, as we saw &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;minitest/spec&lt;/code&gt; and Rspec do. &lt;strong&gt;You just defined a bunch of private methods on the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt; class.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/ada3be373a7050bf2c0434281cb189ec/rake.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Sideshow Bob getting hit in the face with a rake repeatedly&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two important pieces to what makes up a given context in Ruby: the value of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; and the “current class”. When you use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;def&lt;/code&gt; in Ruby, methods get defined on the current class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the root context of a Ruby program the value of &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;self&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; (a special instance of the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt; class) and the current class is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;. That means any methods we define there end up on &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;, which nearly all classes inherit from. Specifically, they’ll end up as private methods on Object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;namespace &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:bicycle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  task &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:assemble&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;attach_handlebars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# These now all work:&lt;/span&gt;
bicycle &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Bicycle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;
attach_handlebars&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;a string&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;send&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:attach_handlebars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1337.&lt;/span&gt;send&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:attach_handlebars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token builtin&quot;&gt;Class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;send&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:attach_handlebars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s correct: every instance of almost every class, including the classes and modules themselves, now have a private &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;attach_handlebars&lt;/code&gt; method. Polluting almost every object in your system with unnecessary methods is a bad practice and could have a variety of consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One problem you could run into without even doing any metaprogramming would be a naming collision. If you happened to be assembling some motorcycles as well as bicycles, and those motorbikes needed their handlebars attached too, suddenly you might be trying to attach motorcycle handlebars to your bicycles or vice versa, because the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;attach_handlebars&lt;/code&gt; method that got defined second would overwrite the first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use Service Classes Instead&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, it’s good practice to pull the logic of your Rake tasks out into a class. This allows you to do all the normal refactoring you’d do in any other object, like extracting out methods without accidentally polluting the global scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it’ll be easier to write tests for the class, and even pull it into application code if you one day need to. Even if you’re just writing a throwaway task that you’re going to delete in a week, you can define the class inline in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.rake&lt;/code&gt; file for easy deletion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Better Yet: Rake::DSL&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for us, Rake actually provides a built-in facility for changing the scope of our tasks! It lives in the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Rake::DSL&lt;/code&gt; module. From &lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby-doc.org/stdlib-2.2.1/libdoc/rake/rdoc/Rake/DSL.html&quot;&gt;the docs&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DSL is a module that provides task, desc, namespace, etc. Use this when you’d like to use rake outside the top level scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Rake outside of top-level scope is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; what we need to do. We can create a class for our extra methods to live on, and instantiating that class can define our tasks for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# lib/tasks/bicycle.rake&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;BicycleTasks&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;include&lt;/span&gt; Rake&lt;span class=&quot;token double-colon punctuation&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token constant&quot;&gt;DSL&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;initialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    namespace &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:bicycle&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
      task &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:assemble&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
        bicycle &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Bicycle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Assemble the bicycle:&lt;/span&gt;
        attach_wheels&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        attach_handlebars&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        attach_brakes&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;attach_wheels&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;attach_handlebars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;attach_brakes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;bicycle&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Instantiate the class to define the tasks:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;BicycleTasks&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can define any methods we want, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;include&lt;/code&gt; other mixins, and do anything else we would normally do with a class, all without polluting &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Rake::DSL&lt;/code&gt; is your friend! It’s good for more than just isolating some methods, too. You can use it for more advanced techniques like dynamically generating tasks, making customizable tasks, and more. If you maintain any gems that provide Rake tasks to their users, consider making sure you’re not accidentally exporting methods on &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Object&lt;/code&gt;, and use &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Rake::DSL&lt;/code&gt; to fix it if you are!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rails Application Upgrades: Hard Mode]]></title><description><![CDATA[Last month Luke Francl published a great
article titled
“Upgrading a Rails application incrementally”. In it he lays out an
approach for…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/rails-application-upgrades-hard-mode/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/rails-application-upgrades-hard-mode/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last month &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lof&quot;&gt;Luke Francl&lt;/a&gt; published &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recursion.org/incremental-rails-upgrade/&quot;&gt;a great
article&lt;/a&gt; titled
“Upgrading a Rails application incrementally”. In it he lays out an
approach for performing Rails version upgrades, specifically
discussing his experience upgrading an app from Rails 3.2 to 4.2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot more to it, but his strategy hinges on parameterizing
the dependencies of the application so that both the application and
the test suite can run against multiple versions of Rails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application developers might not realize that having one codebase that
runs against multiple versions of a gem is an option to them. On the
other hand, gem maintainers are probably all aware of this. The
&lt;a href=&quot;http://extensions.solidus.io/&quot;&gt;Solidus extension ecosystem&lt;/a&gt; is an
awesome example of a suite of gems that work against a variety of both
Rails and Solidus versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;If you haven’t read &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recursion.org/incremental-rails-upgrade/&quot;&gt;Luke’s
article&lt;/a&gt; yet, you
should probably do so now before continuing. It’s a really great
read.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hard Upgrades&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://solidus.io/blog/2015/08/11/version-1-0-0.html&quot;&gt;Solidus 1.0&lt;/a&gt;
was released in the summer of 2015. The project sought to continue the
development of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/spree/spree&quot;&gt;Spree&lt;/a&gt; platform
after Spree Commerce was acquired by First Data and announced they
were stepping away from their maintenance role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While a dedicated team eventually stepped up to continue working on
Spree, Solidus gained great initial momentum and continues to be the
more active project by commit frequency. Because of the activity on
the platform and the backing from many respected community members
there’s been a steady stream of projects making the jump from Spree to
Solidus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people show up in the Solidus Slack channel asking questions
about migrating their application from Spree to Solidus they’re
immediately pointed at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/wiki/Upgrading-from-Spree&quot;&gt;a short upgrade
guide&lt;/a&gt;
on the Solidus wiki. Because Solidus forked from Spree around the
2.4 release, applications currently running Spree 2.2 to 2.4 are in
the best position to upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spree 2.2 depends on Rails 4.0, and 2.4 depends on Rails 4.1. The 1.0
release of Solidus requires Rails 4.2, so upgrading from either of
these relatively desirable (as far as ease of migration) Spree
versions requires upgrading both Rails and Spree/Solidus at the same
time. This introduces some trickiness into the upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest blocker in getting a Spree/Solidus app to run against
another version is that there are schema changes. Any two versions of
Spree/Solidus are going to expect a different database schema. I don’t
know of any reasonable way to handle this within Luke’s approach. I
can think of ways to accomplish it, but none that would be worth the
time and effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself in a situation where you can’t do an incremental
upgrade, don’t despair. A long-lived feature branch is a liability,
but there are some great strategies for reducing the risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s worth noting that Solidus has taken a strategy of cutting
releases that contain no changes other than a Rails major version bump
and associated fixes. As such any project upgrading within Solidus
(rather than from Spree to Solidus) should be able to use Luke’s
incremental upgrade strategy. In general, upgrades between Solidus
versions are quite easy and don’t require special planning or effort.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contribute Back To Master&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Try to frame every change you need to make as a chance to fix the
issue upstream.&lt;/strong&gt; Rather than adding conditionals based on which Rails
version you’re on, try to write code that will run on both versions.
Of course many (probably most) changes won’t be candidates for this,
but every time you make a change in master instead of the upgrade
branch you’re avoiding unnecessary divergence. (More on why divergence needs to be avoided later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Issues with ActiveRecord are prime candidates. You’ll almost certainly
run into queries on your upgrade branch that no longer produce valid
SQL due to changes in ActiveRecord. Take these as a chance to rework
the code so it works on both versions of ActiveRecord. Not only will
you be avoiding diverging from master unnecessarily, but you’ll also
be driving your project to use the more stable parts of the API,
potentially avoiding headaches further down the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rebase, Rebase, Rebase&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all team’s are comfortable with it, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Branching-Rebasing&quot;&gt;git’s rebase
feature&lt;/a&gt; allows
you to periodically rewrite your long-lived branch history on top of
the latest master, fixing conflicts as you go. This offers a variety
of benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It gives the upgrade team more visibility on any conflicting changes
that other teams are making.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It avoids additional divergence. As regular development continues,
master will be diverging from the upgrade branch (usually) faster
than the upgrade branch is diverging from master. This keeps that in
check my regularly bring the upgrade branch in sync with master.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re contributing changes back to master, it brings those
changes in your upgrade branch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It keeps related changes together in the right commits. If you merge
master into your upgrade branch instead, you’ll have to fix any
conflicts. Those “conflict fixes” are logically part of whatever
commit in your branch introduced the conflict, not the merge itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your team doesn’t want to use rebases, then regularly merging
master back into your upgrade branch will still offer some of the
benefits. In my experience with long-lived Ruby codebases it’s much
easier to follow and understand the history (something you’ll probably
spend a good amount of time doing while performing this kind of large
application upgrade) without all those unnecessary merge commits, but
it isn’t the end of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stay Visible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When performing these kinds of application upgrades, one of your
biggest liabilities will be the people continuing to make changes to
the application. &lt;strong&gt;Every change you make is a vector for new
conflicts.&lt;/strong&gt; The rest of the team isn’t going to be keeping your
“future” changes to the application in mind while they’re doing their
day-to-day coding. Even if they’re trying to be mindful of the upgrade
work, that’s not an easy task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upgrade team must regularly communicate about where they are
making changes to avoid unnecessary conflicts. They may even need to
sit in on meetings where upcoming features are being planned to steer
teams away from areas that the upgrade has changed significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course you won’t be able to avoid those situations altogether, but
do your best to help decision-makers understand the costs of
any overlapping work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Avoid Invasive Changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important way you can maximize the success of your upgrade is
to avoid making changes that are going to conflict with changes made
upstream. This also might be the hardest part of doing these
upgrades. There are two main objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t make any unnecessary changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the most dangerous changes last.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before, every change made on the upgrade branch is a
conflict waiting to happen. Given enough time someone will eventually
make a change upstream that will conflict with the upgrade branch and
the upgrade team needs to be mindful of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pull out stats on which files and classes change the most
frequently. Code change frequency is called “churn.” Files/classes
that churn a lot usually indicate deeper design issues, but in the
context of an upgrade they are just huge liabilities; changing them is
asking for conflict. If you can, avoid changing these files at all or
at least save changing them for last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It’s All About Risk&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running a long-lived upgrade branch is always a risk. Most projects
should avoid them at all costs. Unfortunately, sometimes they are the
only option. As with anything, once you’re forced into a bad situation
it becomes all about managing risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting through an upgrade efficiently is an exercise in minimizing
the friction from reconciling the two changing views of the
codebase. That means keeping those branches as close to each other as
you can for as long as you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope these strategies can help out teams that are facing hard
upgrades. If you’ve already kicked off an upgrade, it’s not too
late. Re-prioritize your work based on code churn and upcoming plans,
and look at your existing upgrade commits and contribute some back to
master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thoughts and feedback? Let me know &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/creepy_wizard/status/966000209229594624&quot;&gt;on Twitter!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fixing Your Test Suite: Class Methods and Memoization]]></title><description><![CDATA[This is the first post in a series about common mistakes that lead to
unreliable test suites in Ruby and how to fix them. Stay tuned for…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/class-methods-and-memoization/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/class-methods-and-memoization/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the first post in a series about common mistakes that lead to
unreliable test suites in Ruby and how to fix them. Stay tuned for
more.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memoization&quot;&gt;Memoization&lt;/a&gt; is a helpful
tool for optimization, but Rubyists use it for more than that. Take
this class for, example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;UserNotification&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;initialize&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;user&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;@user&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; user
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;account_frozen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;unless&lt;/span&gt; user&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;phone_number

    api_client&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;send&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
      user&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;phone_number&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Your account has been frozen due to suspicious activity.&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt;

  attr_reader &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:user&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;api_client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;@api_client&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;||=&lt;/span&gt; NotificationService&lt;span class=&quot;token double-colon punctuation&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;key&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token constant&quot;&gt;ENV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;fetch&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;'NOTIFICATION_SERVICE_API_KEY'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the class above, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;#api_client&lt;/code&gt; private method is memoized so
that it instantiates our notification service client when it’s called
the first time and always returns the same client on subsequent calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memoizing the setup for the API client isn’t strictly necessary. It
probably isn’t very expensive to perform this tasks multiple times, so
we could just remove the memoization altogether and reinstantiate the
client on every call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively we could just setup the API client in the
constructor. We’d be setting it up even if we didn’t end up using it,
but the penalty for doing so is insignificant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I regularly see Rubyists memoize things when it isn’t strictly
necessary, and I like it. In situations like this it keeps the
constructor clean, isolating the boring implementation details in a
private method at the very bottom of the class definition. &lt;strong&gt;A good
class tells a story about how to use it,&lt;/strong&gt; and this class tells you up
front about what it does, and allows you to keep reading if you need
to know how it does it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s very few situations where you’ll consider using memoization
and be wrong to do so. Memoization is reasonably sensible as long as
these two criteria are met:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The method is called a variable number of times over the life an instance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The method should always return the same result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your instinct is to compute some value lazily in your class, it’s
probably just fine to do that. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Haskell_(programming_language)&quot;&gt;Some
languages&lt;/a&gt;
lazy evaluate pretty much everything. Just remember that memoizing a
falsy value won’t do anything; it will be re-evaluated every
time. (You can get around this.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Lifecycle of an Object&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forgetting about “the life of the object” is how we introduce the
first test suite issue. Like everything in Ruby, classes are objects
too. Class methods are no different than methods on any other
instance. When you define a class method it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Example&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;foo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# or equivalently:&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;foo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to memoization the important difference between class
and instance methods is how long the object in question lives. Your
application will create and throw away thousands or millions of
instances of most classes over the course of one HTTP request/response
cycle. On the other hand, the classes themselves live for the length
of the Ruby process. &lt;strong&gt;This means memoization in class methods saves
the memoized value until your app is restarted.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;When It Works&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memoizing class methods is sometimes okay. Ignoring potential thread
safety issues (a topic for another day), sometimes you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; want to
save a computed value for the length of your Ruby process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you build a lookup table for tax rates from a CSV then
there’s no reason not to keep it around. You probably don’t want to
load it from disk and parse it every time you need to look up a tax
rate, and if you’re loading this data from a CSV then it’s probably
safe to assume that it doesn’t change very often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;When It Doesn’t&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where you get into trouble is when you memoize something that &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt;
change. A common one I see is memoizing some value that changes
&lt;em&gt;infrequently&lt;/em&gt; from the database. Not only will this almost assuredly
break your test suite, but it will probably cause bugs in your
application. Take a look:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;module&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;UserQueries&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;active_with_subscription&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;@active_and_subscribed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;||=&lt;/span&gt;
        User&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;active&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;joins&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:subscription&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;distinct
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a innocent looking piece of code, and in my experience people
often end up with something like this by refactoring the query out of
another class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is that once this query gets executed the result gets saved
forever (until the Ruby process terminates.) The first time this
method gets called in your test suite or application process the value
will be recorded and returned for all subsequent calls, no matter how
much the database changes. Consider this example RSpec spec:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;'rails_helper'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

RSpec&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;describe UserQueries &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  describe &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;.active_with_subscription&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    subject &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; described_class&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;active_with_subscription &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    context &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;when there are active users with subscriptions&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
      let&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:user_one&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; create &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:active&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:with_subscription&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
      let&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:user_two&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; create &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:active&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:with_subscription&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
      it &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; is_expected&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to contain_exactly&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;user_one&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; user_two&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

    context &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;when there are no active users with subscriptions&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
      before &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
        create &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:active&lt;/span&gt;
        create &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:inactive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:with_subscription&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
      it &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; is_expected&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to be_empty &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example that runs second will always fail when run against the
code above. &lt;strong&gt;The value returned by ActiveRecord will be saved and
reused for the lifetime of the process.&lt;/strong&gt; If the first example runs
first then the method will return the two active users we created for
that test when it gets called in the second example, even though
they’ve likely been scrubbed by the database. If the second example
runs first then the method will return an empty collection when the
first example gets run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll likely never want to memoize the result of a query for the life
of a process. Databases contain application state, and the point of
state is that it changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How To Fix It&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the easiest common mistakes to fix. Once you’ve
determined that you’ve got some memoization where you shouldn’t, you
simply remove the memoization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# Before:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;active_with_subscription&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token variable&quot;&gt;@active_and_subscribed&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;||=&lt;/span&gt;
    User&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;active&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;joins&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:subscription&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;distinct
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# After:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;active_with_subscription&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  User&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;active&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;joins&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:subscription&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;distinct
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Careful though, you’ll need to performance test your code after you
make a change like this. If you have some code that calls this a
thousand times in one request then you’re going to need to find a way
to cache the result at another level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memoization is a great technique for writing more readable and faster
code. Don’t hesitate to use it, but pay attention while refactoring
and don’t pull memoized logic out into the wrong context.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[You Can't Save Everyone: Some Exceptions Should Be Left Alone]]></title><description><![CDATA[While exceptions are an important tool in creating reliable programs,
they also introduce what is arguably the least intuitive form of…]]></description><link>https://supergood.software/you-cant-save-everyone/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://supergood.software/you-cant-save-everyone/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;While exceptions are an important tool in creating reliable programs,
they also introduce what is arguably the least intuitive form of
control flow in mainstream languages, including Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conventional control flow structures like loops and conditionals move
execution within some very limited context. Unlike exception handling,
they never leave you in another part of the call stack altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exceptions handling is itself an exception to what many would consider
“good language design.” Exceptions are like mystery
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goto&quot;&gt;goto&lt;/a&gt; statements, and in Ruby
they have substantially more complicated behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goto statements arbitrarily move execution from one place to
another. It’s a one-direction transfer of the flow of execution to
another explicitly stated place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exceptions are &lt;em&gt;far harder&lt;/em&gt; to reason about; they send execution up
the call stack until a caller is found in a context that defines
exception handling for that type of exception. &lt;strong&gt;The code raising an
exception is not tied to the code that will be handling it.&lt;/strong&gt; In a
dynamic language like Ruby, identifying how a given exception is going
to be caught can be super hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post &lt;em&gt;doesn’t&lt;/em&gt; seek to slander exceptions. They’re a
powerful tool that allows us to write our programs where our
high-level abstractions can ignore many of the potential low-level
exceptions that might be encountered. Alternative solutions like
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Callback_(computer_programming)&quot;&gt;callbacks&lt;/a&gt;
tend to force the intermediate layers to handle the lower-level
exceptions so that they can be communicated to the caller in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike callback-based approaches where errors must be passed around
and either handled or passed up to callers, exceptions give
application developers some freedom in which errors to handle and
where to handle them. Being too broad in what exceptions you choose to
handle can get you into trouble. &lt;strong&gt;Permissively catching all
exceptions is a dangerous pattern&lt;/strong&gt;, and can have unintended
results. You might have heard this before, but I encountered a very
unexpected result not too long ago that’s worth sharing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be Careful&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve done tons of work with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/spree/spree&quot;&gt;Spree&lt;/a&gt; and its successor
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/solidusio/solidus&quot;&gt;Solidus&lt;/a&gt;. They offer an
E-commerce platform as a mountable Rails engine. Once installed in
your Rails application, they serve up a storefront, admin interface,
and API to power it. It’s a great way to build a highly-customized
store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The controllers that power the API all share a superclass named
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Spree::Api::BaseController&lt;/code&gt;. It helps deal with nitty-gritty details
like authentication, authorization, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Content-Type&lt;/code&gt; handling, and
&lt;strong&gt;exception handling&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Spree::Api::BaseController&lt;/code&gt; was &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/spree/spree/blob/2-4-stable/api/app/controllers/spree/api/base_controller.rb#L21&quot;&gt;rescuing any
exception&lt;/a&gt;,
so that it could respond with a status code of 422 (Unprocessable
Entity). The code that did this was eventually &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/solidusio/solidus/commit/4c57b317004b17ff46dd97d1ac3d33e9f1661bd1#diff-72139884662b996fcc462020939b7807&quot;&gt;completely
removed&lt;/a&gt;,
but the old code looked basically like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;module&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Spree&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;module&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;Api&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token class-name&quot;&gt;BaseController&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; ActionController&lt;span class=&quot;token double-colon punctuation&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;Base
      &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;

      rescue_from &lt;span class=&quot;token builtin&quot;&gt;Exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;with&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:error_during_processing&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token method-definition&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;error_during_processing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;exception&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        Rails&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;logger&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;error exception&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;message
        Rails&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;logger&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;error exception&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;backtrace&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;join&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;\n&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

        error_notifier&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;call&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;exception&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; error_notifier

        render text&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;exception&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; exception&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;message &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to_json&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;422&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least the author was kind enough to log the details of the
exception. This made developing subclasses bearable, but rescuing
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Exception&lt;/code&gt; will still rescue pretty much everything and having to read
through your logs in development to diagnose a &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;NoMethodError&lt;/code&gt; because
of a typo seems excessive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out, this code can also lead to false positives in your
automated test suite, if you construct your tests just right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Perfect Test&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spree and Solidus both use &lt;a href=&quot;http://rspec.info/&quot;&gt;RSpec&lt;/a&gt; for their test
suites, and if you’re building Spree/Solidus based store, you’re
encouraged to use it too as they provide some nice testing support
facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In RSpec, if you’re stubbing a method on an object and you need to
some non-trivial verification of its arguments, you’ll need to do
something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;expect&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;PaymentStore&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to receive&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:save&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;payment&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
  expect&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;payment&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;order_id&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to eq order&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;id
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above code asserts that when we store a payment, that payment
must be associated with the right order. It’s a slightly contrived
example, but it happens occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you were writing a custom API controller for your Spree
application that inherited from &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Spree::Api::BaseController&lt;/code&gt;, and you
did something like this in one of the specs, &lt;strong&gt;the assertion in that
block would never fail&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that’s not exactly true. RSpec would never report that exception
as having failed. When RSpec assertions fail they raise exceptions,
and because exceptions travel up the call stack, and
&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;PaymentStore.save(payment)&lt;/code&gt; is presumably being called somewhere
inside your controller, the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;rescue_from Exception&lt;/code&gt; will kick in and
call the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;error_during_processing&lt;/code&gt; method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assertion would fail, but it would be handled by your controller
code, resulting in a response with a 422 status code. This means you
could write the following spec which would pass even if the payments
were getting associated with some other order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot;&gt;describe &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;POST #record_payment&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
  subject &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    post &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:record_payment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;params&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; order_id&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;payment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; payment_params &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  let&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:order_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
  let&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:payment_params&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;# ...&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; is_expected&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to have_http_status &lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:created&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;associates the payment with the correct order&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    expect&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;PaymentStore&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to receive&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token symbol&quot;&gt;:save&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;payment&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
      expect&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;payment&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;order_id&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to eq order&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;id
    &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
    subject
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;

  it &lt;span class=&quot;token string-literal&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;saves a payment&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
    expect &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; subject &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to change &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; Payment&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;count &lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;from&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;to&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;token keyword&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the stub is only defined in the one example, you would never
catch that the controller was erroneously responding with a 422
(Unprocessable Entity) status code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; If you’ve encountered issues with rescuing &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Exception&lt;/code&gt;
before, you might also know that the preferred strategy is to rescue
from &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;StandardError&lt;/code&gt; instead. This is true, and would protect you from
this particular bug (RSpec’s assertion-related exceptions inherit
directly from &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Exception&lt;/code&gt;), but would still expose you to potential
problems. &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;NoMethodError&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;NameError&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;NoMethodError&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;TypeError&lt;/code&gt;,
all inherit from &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;StandardError&lt;/code&gt; and often represent unexpected issues
you should be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You Can’t Expect The Unexpected&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sure the author meant well, but when it comes to exception
handling, &lt;strong&gt;you should only handle exceptions that you
understand&lt;/strong&gt;. All modern web application frameworks provide facilities
for exception reporting that can be configured to notify external
services that record and group the exceptions encountered by your
application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You, the application developer, should monitor the exceptions your
application encounters and decide how to handle them
individually. You’ll need to write handlers for some exceptions that
get reported, while others you can safely ignore or monitor. Sometimes
you’ll want to catch a whole class of exceptions (network errors when
contacting a third party service, for example). Just be as
conservative as you can in your error handling. Modern software
systems are simply too complex for blanket strategies like Spree
used. &lt;strong&gt;Reasoning about everything that could cause an exception in
any given part of your application is simply not possible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>