<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><updated>2021-09-01T09:30:01+00:00</updated><icon>https://www.redditstatic.com/icon.png/</icon><id>/r/talesfromtechsupport.rss</id><link rel="self" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport.rss" type="application/atom+xml"><link rel="alternate" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport" type="text/html"><logo>https://b.thumbs.redditmedia.com/vjnTCecCm4tO6tmHqheYNXHORjwzbOrhEbLX7HduMdw.png</logo><subtitle>Welcome to Tales From Tech Support, the subreddit where we post stories about helping someone with a tech issue. Did you try turning it off and on again?</subtitle><title>Tales From Tech Support</title><entry><author><name>/u/MagicBigfoot</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/MagicBigfoot</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hey, we can have two stickies now!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, something like 90% of the mod removals are posts that obviously don&amp;#39;t belong here.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When we ask if they checked the rules first, almost everyone says, &amp;quot;O sorry, I didn&amp;#39;t read the sidebar.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And when asked why they didn&amp;#39;t read the sidebar, almost everyone says, &amp;quot;B-b-but I&amp;#39;m on mobile!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So this sticky is for &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt;, dear non-sidebar-reading mobile users.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;First off, here&amp;#39;s a link to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/about/sidebar&quot;&gt;TFTS Sidebar&lt;/a&gt; for your convenience and non-plausible-deniability.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;Second, here is a hot list of the rules of TFTS:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 0&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_.2205_.3A_your_post_must_be_a_written_story_about_tech_support&quot;&gt;YOUR POST MUST BE A STORY ABOUT TECH SUPPORT&lt;/a&gt; - Just like it says. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 1&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_1_.3A_anonymize_your_info&quot;&gt;ANONYMIZE YOUR INFO&lt;/a&gt; - Keep your personal and business names out of the story. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 2&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_2_.3A_keep_your_posts_.26_comments_sfw&quot;&gt;KEEP YOUR POST SFW&lt;/a&gt; - People do browse TFTS on the job and we need to respect that. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 3&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_3_.3A_no_posts_that_ask_a_question&quot;&gt;NO QUESTION POSTS&lt;/a&gt; - Post here AFTER you figure out what the problem was. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 4&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_4_.3A_no_image_links&quot;&gt;NO IMAGE LINKS&lt;/a&gt; - Tell your story with words please, not graphics or memes. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 5&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_5_.3A_no_standalone_links&quot;&gt;NO OTHER LINKS&lt;/a&gt; - Do not redirect us someplace else, even on Reddit. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 6&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_6_.3A_no_customer_complaint_posts&quot;&gt;NO COMPLAINT POSTS&lt;/a&gt; - We don&amp;#39;t want to hear about it. Really. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 7&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_7_.3A_no_pranking_or_hacking_tales&quot;&gt;NO PRANKING, HACKING, ETC.&lt;/a&gt; - TFTS is about helping people, not messing with them. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule &amp;#8734;&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_.221E_.3A_don.27t_be_a_jerk&quot;&gt;DON&amp;#39;T BE A JERK.&lt;/a&gt; - You know exactly what I&amp;#39;m talking &amp;#39;bout, Willis. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index&quot;&gt;TFTS Wiki&lt;/a&gt; has more details on all of these rules and other notable TFTS info as well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For instance, you can review our list of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_what_tales_have_jumped_the_shark.3F&quot;&gt;Officially Retired Topics&lt;/a&gt;, or check out all of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_the_compleat_best_of_tfts&quot;&gt;Best of TFTS Collections&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading &amp;amp; welcome to &lt;a href=&quot;/r/TalesFromTechSupport&quot;&gt;/r/TalesFromTechSupport&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post has been locked, comments will be auto-removed.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=%2Fr%2Ftalesfromtechsupport&quot;&gt;message the mods&lt;/a&gt; if you have a question or a suggestion.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Remember you can hide this message once you have read it and never see it again!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;edit: fixed links for some mobile users.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/MagicBigfoot&quot;&gt; /u/MagicBigfoot &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/3dqlny/tfts_posting_rules_mobile_users_please_read/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/3dqlny/tfts_posting_rules_mobile_users_please_read/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_3dqlny</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/3dqlny/tfts_posting_rules_mobile_users_please_read/"><updated>2015-07-18T14:29:59+00:00</updated><published>2015-07-18T14:29:59+00:00</published><title>TFTS POSTING RULES (MOBILE USERS PLEASE READ!)</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Mission-Guard5348</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Mission-Guard5348</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if I deserve to post here,I don’t work tech support, I’m just a computer science major, that wants to learn more about computers and stuff so I try to help where I can, I also recently rebirthed an old computer (of mine) with Linux, I’m not great at this stuff, but hey the way to improve is practice&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So the projector was frozen on the first side of a power point&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I start by assuming the projector is a second monitors, I’ve had minor issues with a second monitor on the past, turns out the projector has the same signal, so they are both the same monitor, kind of like how two keyboards are treated&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I then tried to check the physical connections, and I thought I found the issue, there was a big wire that just wasn’t plugged in, I tried to figure out what it was, and asked the professor eventually (couldn’t at first, she was talking to the class while I was fixing it) as it turns out she has never seen that wire before, so I looked around, I then noticed it was plugged into something with a tag that says “laptop” which has a switch turned to “desktop” and a desktop is plugged in&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Turns out that’s incase you want a laptop to be plugged in, but you don’t have to unplug the main computer (teachers often teach in different rooms, so maybe it’s so they can avoid messing with a cool-workers set up)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So I decided to check the projector settings, grab the remote, and then just start cracking up Right below the main controls, I’m an easy place to accidentally press there’s a big button that says “freeze”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I press it, and suddenly it works&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I just continue laughing, and just show three teacher/class that there was a freeze button, one or two laugh a small amount,I was probably the only person am really found it funny (I was also the only one who spent 30 minutes on the problem)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thanks&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Mission-Guard5348&quot;&gt; /u/Mission-Guard5348 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pfobwi/apparently_projectors_have_a_freeze_button/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pfobwi/apparently_projectors_have_a_freeze_button/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pfobwi</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pfobwi/apparently_projectors_have_a_freeze_button/"><updated>2021-09-01T06:44:09+00:00</updated><published>2021-09-01T06:44:09+00:00</published><title>Apparently projectors have a freeze button</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Littlewing586</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Littlewing586</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to my professional career, I’m the family technician especially to my grandmother’s boyfriend. Feels like every time I come here, he’s calling me over to help him with something.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I come by once a week to do laundry and hang out with my grandmother and tonight was that night. My grandmother’s boyfriend, Hank, calls me into the other room where it’s &lt;em&gt;super&lt;/em&gt; warm, like I’m sweating in seconds of walking in, to ask me for tech support tonight.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hank: Can you check out the TV? Like reboot it or something? Channel 2 CBS is always going mute randomly and now it’s spreading to other rooms.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;I agree rebooting sounds like a good start so I unplug all of the fairly hot cable boxes around the house and leave them unplugged for a good 30 or so minutes while I talk with my grandmother.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I come back and plug in everything and they get to watching all these awful shows like Young Sheldon and whatever else was on while I browse Reddit and play mobile games. But I peek my head up every so often and start to notice what Hank was talking about. Randomly throughout commercial breaks, mostly, the sound just goes dead silent. Pretty wonderful to me, but I could understand this was &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; entertainment.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Then I started noticing that throughout all of these shows…there was this really weird narration. I thought it was a strange move by CBS to have so many shows from comedy to drama have this woman in the background describing what’s going on in each episode. Maybe their new trademark?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Then I started picking up on it during NCIS when it was clearly out of place and realize this is definitely not CBS’ doing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I asked Hank for the remote and checked the Accessibility settings and saw someone enabled some setting for narration that was only showing on CBS, not on any other channel we were watching. Disabled that setting and so far over the last few hours, all is good again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This isn’t uncommon at my grandmother’s house. Someone is always enabling some weird setting on the TV and everyone just puts up with it until I come around.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Littlewing586&quot;&gt; /u/Littlewing586 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pezm9f/cbs_randomly_mutes_itself/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pezm9f/cbs_randomly_mutes_itself/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pezm9f</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pezm9f/cbs_randomly_mutes_itself/"><updated>2021-08-31T05:34:03+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-31T05:34:03+00:00</published><title>“CBS randomly mutes itself”</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/iammandalore</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/iammandalore</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are the stories of the New Guy. All of what you are about to read is true. I write you these tales of mirth and woe, of entertainment and anger with as much accuracy and as little embellishment as I can manage. Many conversations are written as best I can remember them from my notes and memories about the incidents they describe, but the heart of what you are about to read is as true as I can make it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Names have been changed to protect the innocent. And the guilty.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The cast:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;Jordan - FNG&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Thomas - Me, the manager and network admin&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;John - The older of my two other reports, primarily responsible for server maintenance, major application upgrades, and supporting our smaller off-site locations and their specific applications&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;Daniel - The younger of my two original employees, though here for the same amount of time as John. Both longer than me, actually. Desktop and server support, document management and phone system support, phenomenal people skills.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DAY 10&lt;/strong&gt; - The Betrayal&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A little over a week has come and gone. Jordan remains steadfast in his attempts to drive me and my other two reports to the brink of insanity. Thus far he has failed a stunningly easy test I devised to assess his problem-solving skills, admitted to underage drinking, attempted to build camaraderie in a conversation with us all by saying &amp;quot;you guys know how hard it is to pull one over on my mom&amp;quot;, and argued with me about the importance of locking computers when leaving them unattended. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While he was away from his desk performing a task and I was talking idly with John and Daniel, I walked over to inspect the clutter Jordan had already amassed and noticed a password written on a sticky note. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ah, an opportunity to teach an important lesson. I mentioned it to John and Daniel, and then waited.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Jordan, what&amp;#39;s wrong with your desk?&amp;quot; I asked upon his return. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Uh, I forgot to lock my computer?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well yes, but there&amp;#39;s something else.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I don&amp;#39;t know,&amp;quot; he declared after looking around.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What&amp;#39;s on that sticky note?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh! That&amp;#39;s the password that Daniel gave me.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Daniel, who had been listening to the exchange from his desk, poked his head out from behind his monitors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m sorry, what?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yeah,&amp;quot; Jordan replied. &amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s that [anti-virus] management password you gave me. You told me to write it down so I wouldn&amp;#39;t forget it.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I didn&amp;#39;t tell you to write any password down.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yeah, you-&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I cut in, stopping the conversation and telling Jordan not to worry about it right then. I again explained the importance of locking unattended computers, and let the issue drop until later in the day when I called him into my office.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Close the door behind you. About that password.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Daniel gave me that password.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I spoke to Daniel and he said he doesn&amp;#39;t remember giving you that password and definitely wouldn&amp;#39;t have told you to write it down. You&amp;#39;re sure?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Absolutely. That&amp;#39;s not like me.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Intent on giving Jordan every opportunity to come clean I tried again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Like I said, I talked to Daniel and he&amp;#39;s certain that he didn&amp;#39;t give you that password. I have to agree; it wouldn&amp;#39;t be like him to tell you or anyone to write down a password.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m positive he gave it to me and told me to write it down so I wouldn&amp;#39;t forget.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;You&amp;#39;re sure?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;deep sigh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Jordan, I know for a fact that Daniel didn&amp;#39;t give you that password.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What do you mean?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; gave you that password. In an email, which also explained that you should change it when you log in the first time.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Listen, Jordan. I&amp;#39;ve known the whole time what was up and I&amp;#39;ve been trying to give you the chance to be honest, but you chose right from the start to throw Daniel straight under the bus. That&amp;#39;s not the way to build a good working relationship with your coworkers. If you keep that up no one is ever going to trust you.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;OK.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The conversation ended. No apology, no remorse, no assurances it wouldn&amp;#39;t happen again. I reported this chain of events to my director, knowing that such a claim of dishonesty on the part of the HR director&amp;#39;s son would best be handled between the two directors. My cries would fall upon deaf ears.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The chronicles would continue.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pcvl1s/the_new_guy_chronicles_episode_1/&quot;&gt;Episode 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/iammandalore&quot;&gt; /u/iammandalore &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pemwdf/the_new_guy_chronicles_episode_2_the_betrayal/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pemwdf/the_new_guy_chronicles_episode_2_the_betrayal/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pemwdf</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pemwdf/the_new_guy_chronicles_episode_2_the_betrayal/"><updated>2021-08-30T17:33:37+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-30T17:33:37+00:00</published><title>The New Guy Chronicles - Episode 2: The Betrayal</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Cyborg_Ninja_Cat</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Cyborg_Ninja_Cat</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m a full stack web dev, mostly working on developing and maintaining eCommerce sites using my company&amp;#39;s in-house platform. We do support and maintenance as well as new sites and features, but aren&amp;#39;t expected to support end users directly. However we occasionally (or in the case of the site that features in this story, not so rarely) get end user issues forwarded to us if the client&amp;#39;s helpdesk can&amp;#39;t fix it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This particular site is healthcare-adjacent. I&amp;#39;m not in the US so HIPAA doesn&amp;#39;t apply but data security is still a particularly big deal for this site compared to some of our other clients - and security of customer data is a big deal for everyone these days.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the far-off days before the pandemic, I&amp;#39;d been working for months on a Major New Feature that allowed customers to use the site in a different way than before. It touched almost every part of the site and presented some fairly unique problems. We had to request a new feature be added to the in-house platform just for this, which necessitated deferring the Major New Feature&amp;#39;s completion until after a separate project to migrate the site through a major version of the platform.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Finally, everything is completed, tested, and signed off. The big release goes fairly smoothly, the Major New Feature appears to be working, and we pat ourselves on the back and relax.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cut to shortly after we get in the following morning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A customer who placed a single order is receiving dozens, no, hundreds of order confirmation emails. He provides a screenshot of his flooded inbox.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Virtually all eCommerce sites have transactional emails - and this has more than many, along with optional text message notifications. One of the implications of the Major New Feature is that it&amp;#39;s no longer completely trivial to decide who should be notified by what method about updates to a given order or account. I&amp;#39;ve written a nice new piece of code that abstracts away all this decision making into one place.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Obviously, I&amp;#39;ve got something terribly wrong. Are we sending every email update to the same person, this guy? Worse*, are we sending every update to &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt;, and this guy is just the first to report it? Either way, it sounds like a significant data security breach, on the site that I would least like to have a data breach on, and it&amp;#39;s definitely my fault. It&amp;#39;s &lt;strong&gt;panic stations&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I start looking frantically at my new code and the database, while our senior dev gets into the logs. I&amp;#39;ve just found the mildly reassuring information that the number of emails the customer appears to have received doesn&amp;#39;t match up with orders taken since the release of the Major New Feature, when the senior reports that the order confirmation page for this customer&amp;#39;s single order is being requested ten times a minute.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He&amp;#39;s refreshing the page ten times a minute. For an hour. We assume that it&amp;#39;s some kind of browser extension or something.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A quick proof of concept confirms that you can indeed generate multiple confirmation emails by refreshing that page. Which I hasten to add is not ok, and we immediately put a ticket in to fix it. But this bug appears to have been in the site for years, since before I joined the company. &lt;em&gt;Of all the days for it to come to light...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*Actually, that probably wouldn&amp;#39;t be &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; worse, because at that time we had another issue in the system that would have caused nearly all emails to fail to send in that case.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Cyborg_Ninja_Cat&quot;&gt; /u/Cyborg_Ninja_Cat &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pepaox/a_case_of_impeccable_timing/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pepaox/a_case_of_impeccable_timing/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pepaox</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pepaox/a_case_of_impeccable_timing/"><updated>2021-08-30T19:31:12+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-30T19:31:12+00:00</published><title>A case of impeccable timing</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/blueskyn01se</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/blueskyn01se</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I work for a company that provides a cloud communications platform as a service — developers can use our web service APIs to do a lot of neato stuff. I’m a tier 3 technical support engineer/developer — usually when a ticket makes it to our queue, advanced troubleshooting is needed. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I suppose that’s how sometimes the team forgets to check off the basics of troubleshooting, and something like this goes over our heads. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Got a user who couldn’t get our programmable chat API to work. By the time I got the ticket, two of my team members had already done some troubleshooting which included verifying and updating their SDKs, combing through our backend logs, and attempting to debug a snippet of their code. So far, no luck. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I’m reading through the ticket history and one of the very first replies we got from this user was that everything had been working prior to their account being suspended. Now, I re-route a lot of account suspended tickets — I know that it happens a lot and usually account administration handles it without any fuss. It was totally fair to assume that they had gone through that team already and taken care of that puzzle piece. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I did think it was odd however that neither of my team members had responded to that bit of information or referenced it again. My brain starts churning the gears — what exactly happens to our API keys when an account is suspended? It makes sense to me that they would become invalid, which would prevent future attempts to generate access tokens or to use our API services. I run this by the team and, with none of us having tried it before, get the suggestion to suspend+reactivate my own test account and see for myself.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cool. We have a game plan! I start opening some browser tabs, pulling up my own account info as well as the users so that I had everything I needed …&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Right there. At the top. In huge, bold letters. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;‘ACCOUNT SUSPENDED’&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Welp. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mr. Owl, how many developers does it take to notice that an account is inactive? The world does know, unfortunately, and the answer is embarrassing LOL&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/blueskyn01se&quot;&gt; /u/blueskyn01se &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/peh3bj/never_forget_to_check_the_basics/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/peh3bj/never_forget_to_check_the_basics/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_peh3bj</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/peh3bj/never_forget_to_check_the_basics/"><updated>2021-08-30T12:27:54+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-30T12:27:54+00:00</published><title>Never forget to check the basics</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/EonThief</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/EonThief</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hello all, it has been some time since my last post on here. Since that last post I have left the service desk job that I had and thought my time at the help desk was over. However much like an ex texting you at 3 in the morning, you can&amp;#39;t help but get pulled back in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This particular day was my first real day out of training, and it should&amp;#39;ve been a fairly easy day being a Friday and all. However, the IT gods above did not seem to want to give me an easy day. Thus began a multiple call saga, that spilt over into today. So sit back, relax, and enjoy my suffering.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The characters in this story are:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Your storyteller for the moment, and the hero of this anime.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: My eternal rival, and the best/worst part of my day.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As our story begins I am just logging in for the day, and within a minute or so I get a call.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Hello, thank you for contacting the [insert company name here] service desk, I&amp;#39;m Eon can I have your username? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: *&lt;em&gt;provides username&lt;/em&gt;* &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Wonderful, how can I help you? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: Hi, I&amp;#39;m new user and I&amp;#39;m trying to setup my computer but I&amp;#39;m stuck. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Yeah no problem, what step are you stuck on? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: On step 3.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now before we go any further I should explain something. When a user is sent a computer we send them a fairly in depth list of instructions on setting up their device. These instructions are, in my opinion, very easy to follow with one or two issues that most users have. They are so easy in fact that the only thing that would make them easier is if they included pictures. With that little info dump out of the way lets continue.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Okay, step 3 should have you reset your password. There should be a website listed on that step as well. Do you see it? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: There isn&amp;#39;t any website listed. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Sir I can assure you there is a website listed there &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: No website, just this [insert web address here] at the end of the step. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: *&lt;em&gt;trying to stop my palm from colliding with my forehead&lt;/em&gt;* That&amp;#39;s the website sir... &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: No it&amp;#39;s not. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Type that into a web browser and it will take you to the website sir... &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: Why didn&amp;#39;t it say that? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: *&lt;em&gt;internally &amp;quot;I shouldn&amp;#39;t have to say it&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;* It just assumes that users would know what to do in that circumstance. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: Yeah, well I don&amp;#39;t mess with computers none. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Most of our new users don&amp;#39;t sir.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;From this point the call goes on and I get his password reset and in the instructions it says that an initial password reset can take at least 30 minutes so the user says he&amp;#39;ll call back in 30 minutes to continue setup.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15 minutes later...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I receive another call from who else but New User.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Hello, thank you for contacting the [insert company name here] service desk, I&amp;#39;m Eon can I have your username? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: *&lt;em&gt;provides username&lt;/em&gt;* Yeah I just got off the phone 30 minutes ago and am ready to go through the setup some more. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Yes sir, it was me you spoke with and based on the time it has not yet been 30 minutes, I recommend calling back in another 15 minutes. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: Alright&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;The call gets disconnected and this would be another good time to provide some information. The reason I didn&amp;#39;t continue to help is because the &amp;quot;at least 30 minutes&amp;quot; isn&amp;#39;t an exaggeration, 30 minutes is the quickest that the password will synchronize for first time users in our system. Not sure why though, but that&amp;#39;s just how it is.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Back to the story again though.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15 more minutes later...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Of course the guy calls in again, and at this point I just recognize the number.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Hello, thank you for contacting the [insert company name here] service desk, is this [insert users name]? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;New User: Yes this is him. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Yes I&amp;#39;ve been the same agent you&amp;#39;ve spoken to every time you&amp;#39;ve called this morning. How can I help you this time?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;The user then proceeds to basically tell me his life story, culminating in a summary of his issue. A very incorrect summary mind you, but still a summary nonetheless. I work with him for the next &lt;strong&gt;45 MINUTES!!&lt;/strong&gt; On something that the users are expected to do by themselves mind you. Getting a number of questions that would be answered if the guy actually read the instructions that were given to him. I finally manage to talk him into working through it himself, and he agrees stating that he&amp;#39;ll call back if he has any other issues. I end the call and pray to any god that will listen that I don&amp;#39;t have to deal with him again. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Later that day he does callback, and is very promptly taken care of by a coworker.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I was hoping this would be the end of my interactions with him, at least until some point far down the line... Today has unfortunately rained on that parade.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m just going to give you the cliff notes of this call, as I don&amp;#39;t want to transpose it. He called back in because only the default password was letting him sign into his computer, the new password he created wasn&amp;#39;t working. His new password would work when in the computer however, this was caused by him not locking and unlocking his computer while on VPN. This was odd to me, since, you guessed it, a step in the setup for the computer! When I mentioned this he of course got defensive because, and I quote &amp;quot;I followed them steps on the paper&amp;quot;. Luckily the call didn&amp;#39;t last that long and I, hopefully, won&amp;#39;t have to deal with this guy for a nice loooooong while.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I hope you all enjoyed my little story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/EonThief&quot;&gt; /u/EonThief &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pek3xi/new_user_nightmare/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pek3xi/new_user_nightmare/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pek3xi</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pek3xi/new_user_nightmare/"><updated>2021-08-30T15:15:42+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-30T15:15:42+00:00</published><title>New User Nightmare</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Aikaparsa</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Aikaparsa</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I work for a small OEM company that builds pcs and sell them via different distributors. To find out anything about any configuration we made we prefer to work of the serialnumber as this is unique to every single device. We also have similar configurations which only differ by which mainboard is used or another CPU that is used and all those tiny differences that make a big difference at the end. Today I got a very interesting exchange with a customer that I helped figure out what he wanted but I did it wrong. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;His first email was as follow:&lt;br/&gt; Dear company, &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;2 years ago I bought a pc with windows, but I wish the windows disk was bigger.&lt;br/&gt; Now I want to use a bigger one.&lt;br/&gt; Can you tell me what RAM is installed (manufacturer and how many slots are available 4x4 or 2x8 RAM installed?) and if the RAM I want to install would fit.&lt;br/&gt; Sadly I have no documents regarding this pc and I have no product name and I don&amp;#39;t want to take the pc oout of the desk just to see if a serial number might be on the back or to open the case and see how many slots are available. You have to know this kind of information and be able to tell me if I can do that.&lt;br/&gt; (List of specs like CPU, GPU, amount of disk space on C: and D:, 64x Windows 10)&lt;br/&gt; I want to use (this) RAM and want to know if its compatible. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My response was as this:&lt;br/&gt; Dear customer, &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;sadly I can&amp;#39;t provide you correct information without a serialnumber.&lt;br/&gt; There is a freeware called &amp;quot;Speccy&amp;quot; that reads all the systemdata and gives you information like productnames of the components and such.&lt;br/&gt; With the productname you can easily search those on the manufacturers site and find all the needed information. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is a google translate of his respons:&lt;br/&gt; Thank you very much for your helpful tip with the Speccy, that worked wonderfully and now I know what I have. Of course this is a quick solution, but not really what you mean by &amp;quot;the customer is king&amp;quot; or customer-friendly service. ;-) Therefore I have to say that it would be customer-friendly not only to clip the old serial numbers on the back of the computer, but to store them somewhere under the driver files on the computer. Who is constantly crawling under the desk where he has to determine a tiny number with a flashlight, just because he wants some information from the manufacturer. This is really tedious, especially when you have a dozen cables hanging on the computer, all of which just barely reach the socket. Or do you really expect that we all have desks in the middle of the room? As you can see, that&amp;#39;s a typical male way of thinking. (Definition of men&amp;#39;s thinking: construction of coffee machines with ultra-modern equipment and in the end all the pots spill because they let their women make coffee for them) For advertising, companies like you make all sorts of changes so that it flashes everywhere, the customer is led to some partner site and the company logo appears permanently. A little more customer friendliness would be a good idea if you don&amp;#39;t provide any support without a serial number. And why do you actually need a serial number to determine the number and size of the ram banks? And let&amp;#39;s be honest, that is completely superfluous for this question, even for a possible reason that is not enough. The support of a manufacturer should actually know what he has sold, you will surely see that as well. You only need to collect the data sheets of the computers on offer and write the date of the offer on it, then you can determine within a few minutes which complete systems you sold 2 years ago. I don&amp;#39;t know, but sometimes companies really trip themselves up because they don&amp;#39;t come up with the simplest ideas. I just threw a product out of my company because they had such shitty support and overloaded the system with customer-unfriendly nerd functions. On the other hand, I also recommend computers to my company and they are constantly buying new computers for their more than 200 partner companies throughout the country. You certainly want to shine in your job, so you can bring it in as an &amp;quot;innovative suggestion&amp;quot;. Sometimes there is even a financial bonus for this. Well that was a comment. As I said, you helped me so thank you and have a nice weekend &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I am unsure what to do with is insightful tip, I forwarded it to my coworkers and my superior hopefully they can figure it out.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Aikaparsa&quot;&gt; /u/Aikaparsa &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pedvmr/thank_you_for_helping_me_but_here_is_a_400_word/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pedvmr/thank_you_for_helping_me_but_here_is_a_400_word/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pedvmr</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pedvmr/thank_you_for_helping_me_but_here_is_a_400_word/"><updated>2021-08-30T08:23:49+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-30T08:23:49+00:00</published><title>Thank you for helping me but here is a 400+ word message why you helped me wrong.</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/blameline</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/blameline</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was working tech support for a real estate company. I was seated in my office/server room when I got a knock at the door. It was the boss&amp;#39;s assistant. She said she was having a problem. Every time she clicked on a desktop icon, the item opened, and then immediately closed. Then, when she clicked on the Start Menu, the menu popped up, then closed. She was sure the problem was a virus, and I had to admit, I hadn&amp;#39;t seen that problem before. So, I followed her to her office and she showed me her PC. I immediately spotted the problem: &amp;quot;First thing we&amp;#39;ll need to do is remove the spiral notebook from resting on your keyboard, and most specifically, your escape key.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/blameline&quot;&gt; /u/blameline &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pe722o/well_i_havent_seen_this_problem_before/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pe722o/well_i_havent_seen_this_problem_before/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pe722o</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pe722o/well_i_havent_seen_this_problem_before/"><updated>2021-08-30T00:13:51+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-30T00:13:51+00:00</published><title>Well, I haven't seen this problem before</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Radarman2</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Radarman2</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, I used to work in Tech Support for a private business handling calls/emails from a UK government agency. I only lasted 3 weeks…somehow receiving emails demanding a new SatNav “for Health &amp;amp; Safety reasons” and “I don’t have to send you an email to authenticate because of who I am” had me looking elsewhere. Today’s story was a call that my buddy took (I was listening in to learn) and he was rapidly looking perplexed. The lady in question said she couldn’t log in to her laptop. No matter what she did the little stars didn’t appear. Now the laptops didn’t have a docking station for when at home, but did come with a monitor, port replicator and keyboard/mouse. In a moment of clarity I asked my buddy if I could unmute and takeover… Me “Hello, could you tell me if you’re typing using the wireless keyboard supplied?” Her “Yes, nothing’s happening” Me “Could you remove the keyboard dongle from the laptop, this will disconnect the wireless keyboard and then use the laptops own keyboard to enter your password” The well-known Windows bu-bum of USB device being removed followed by key presses followed by a heavier hand jabbing uncontrollably at the keyboard. Her “nothing, nothing at all!” Me “have you just tried logging into the laptop using the wireless keyboard you just disconnected?” Her, without a pause, “yes”…longer pause…”oh…it’s working now”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Radarman2&quot;&gt; /u/Radarman2 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdrw6s/i_cant_log_in/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdrw6s/i_cant_log_in/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pdrw6s</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdrw6s/i_cant_log_in/"><updated>2021-08-29T08:59:46+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-29T08:59:46+00:00</published><title>I can’t log in…</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/tyr4774</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/tyr4774</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was back maybe a decade ago, I had just got my start in IT after being out of college and working retail attempting to get out. I had been able to join a small 5 person firm that was in the middle of a merger with another 5 person firm. As such our firm &amp;quot;IT&amp;quot; was taking over the IT of the clients of the other company &amp;quot;Phone Setup&amp;quot;. We came in to one of &amp;quot;Phone Setups&amp;quot; big clients, large manufacturing company in the area that basically everyone in this small town had family working for, &amp;quot;Builder, Inc&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I was tasked to work with one of the senior guys in &amp;quot;IT&amp;quot; to roll out a new AV for all of the machines at &amp;quot;Builder, Inc&amp;quot;. Mostly this should&amp;#39;ve been done via GPO but their old AV (I forgot what it was) had a manual removal process so I was tasked with going to each machine during someone lunch break or downtime to run the uninstall steps, reboot, and reboot again so the AV would install. All in all this was going to take awhile. However not even a week in when we had maybe 25% of the company protected we get a call about how the new AV is causing massive slowdowns to &amp;quot;all&amp;quot; the machines they are installed on. Me, being new to IT deferred to the senior tech, but didn&amp;#39;t think it was ours as full scanning hadn&amp;#39;t been enabled. In fact the only &amp;quot;scanning&amp;quot; that was done for this test group was nightly from like 8p-1a.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Joe&amp;quot;, the lead on this roll out, asks me for a list of devices from each division of &amp;quot;Builder&amp;quot; so he can pull one from each to once again separate into another group. So I did that and asked Joe what he was thinking. Joe let me know that since these are old (even at that time) 32-bit machines with 2GB of RAM and XP installed on them (this was near the great XP EoL) that the machines were just slow to begin with and that the users were blaming it on the AV to try and not make their bosses look cheap/lazy for not updating their machines in over a decade. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I get Joe the list and he makes a new group with some different settings. We wait a week and have a meeting with the client including one of the Shift Managers, Hank, who had been yelling the loudest about how the new AV was making thing slow. I don&amp;#39;t recall it verbatim but part of the conversation went like this: &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joe: So Hank, how has your machine been running this past week?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hank: Fantastic! I told you that new Virus Software you put on was slowing us down. We need to go back to that old software as it doesn&amp;#39;t keep us from slowing down.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Joe:Are you sure about that? You&amp;#39;re absolutely sure that compared to last week everything has been running faster? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hank: Yup, its like night and day Joe&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t recall the rest of the meeting but after Hank left Joe let the higher ups know that the only change he did was remove the icon on the task bar showing the AV was &amp;quot;on&amp;quot; and that all other scanning settings were the same. He even brought up the policies he created and the only difference was the &amp;quot;Show Icon&amp;quot; button was unchecked. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We did eventually have to upgrade those machines ahead of the XP EoL deadline because of the AV but that was down the line and after an upgrade and is another story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/tyr4774&quot;&gt; /u/tyr4774 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdfxof/your_new_antivirus_broke_a_whole_division/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdfxof/your_new_antivirus_broke_a_whole_division/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pdfxof</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdfxof/your_new_antivirus_broke_a_whole_division/"><updated>2021-08-28T19:12:56+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-28T19:12:56+00:00</published><title>Your new AntiVirus broke a whole division!</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/TheAnniCake</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/TheAnniCake</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hey guys!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Currently I&amp;#39;m doing my apprenticeship in a local town hall in Germany to become a sysadmin. My final exams are coming up next year, so I&amp;#39;m pretty much aware of what I&amp;#39;m doing. Working for the government isn&amp;#39;t really challenging. Most of the time you help coworkers with simple stuff like &amp;#39;How to use your second monitor&amp;#39;, replacing broken hardware or updating the servers. Really simple work if you ask me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Right now we&amp;#39;ve got elections coming up and you can do a postal vote. We&amp;#39;ve set up a special office for this. This office got a pc, a printer and a barcode scanner so my coworkers don&amp;#39;t have to type every name by hand. The barcodes are on the polling cards people get per mail.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One of my coworkers called me that she had some issues with the printer. It just won&amp;#39;t work. She claimed that if the used that barcode scanner, the printer won&amp;#39;t work which didn&amp;#39;t make any sense. The only issue was that the printer wasn&amp;#39;t set as the standard printer. I set it as the standard and told her to try again. She refused because she didn&amp;#39;t want some important documents printed elsewhere which is understandable because it contains sensible data (it only tried to print it into OneNote which she also didn&amp;#39;t understand). My coworker just refused to see that I&amp;#39;ve fixed the issue and wanted one of the other IT guys to come because she apparently can&amp;#39;t trust me because I&amp;#39;m still an apprentice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That one colleague she tried to call wasn&amp;#39;t available so after half an hour of waiting and talking her into it, she finally tried it again. She was a bit shocked that it magically worked and we could move on. But she still was convinced that the barcode scanner was responsible for this issue.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/TheAnniCake&quot;&gt; /u/TheAnniCake &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdir25/somethings_wrong_with_the_printer/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdir25/somethings_wrong_with_the_printer/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pdir25</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pdir25/somethings_wrong_with_the_printer/"><updated>2021-08-28T21:53:46+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-28T21:53:46+00:00</published><title>'Something's wrong with the printer!'</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/night-otter</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/night-otter</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was temp worker at a government office. I was a clerk, filing, forms, mail, etc. But folks soon figured out I knew about computers and I responded much faster than the IT team. The IT team was in another building in another part of the city.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One day the admin assistant for the Senior Director flags me down. &amp;quot;My computer is very slow. Can you look at it.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wow this machine is old. Still running plain old DOS. Early 90s, not unheard of, but every other system in the building was running Windows. I start looking around and find the root directory is filled with *.tmp files. So I clear them all out and reboot. Zoom (relatively speaking) it boots.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;She fires up WordPerfect and everything is fine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks later, same thing. This time I stuck around to see her work. Starts WordPerfect, types up a document, prints it, and shuts off the computer. She grabs another set of notes, starts up the computer, types up the document, etc, etc.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I try to convince to do saves, to not shut off the computer every time. Nope, Nope, that&amp;#39;s how she was trained so long ago and she&amp;#39;s not going to change.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d already done time in the trenches of Tech Support so I knew arguing with a long term Senior Admin Assistant was not worth my time. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So I created a autoexec.bat file that deleted the tmp files on every start up. She never bugged me again&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/night-otter&quot;&gt; /u/night-otter &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pd41p9/because_thats_the_way_i_was_trained/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pd41p9/because_thats_the_way_i_was_trained/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pd41p9</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pd41p9/because_thats_the_way_i_was_trained/"><updated>2021-08-28T05:32:22+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-28T05:32:22+00:00</published><title>Because that's the way I was trained.</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/iammandalore</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/iammandalore</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are the stories of the New Guy. All of what you are about to read is true. I write you these tales of mirth and woe, of entertainment and anger with as much accuracy and as little embellishment as I can manage. Many conversations are written as best I can remember them from my notes and memories about the incidents they describe, but the heart of what you are about to read is as true as I can make it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Names have been changed to protect the innocent. And the guilty.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREFACE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;We need a new tech on the team. We have a team of three guys supporting almost 600 users. Tickets are up almost 60% over the last five years and we can&amp;#39;t keep up. On top of that we have to migrate almost 500 workstations from Windows 7 to Windows 10. How are we supposed to find the time to do that?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My director, Laurie, looked at me tiredly. We&amp;#39;d had this conversation many times, and the answer had always been &amp;#39;no&amp;#39;. I hoped this time would be different, but I knew not to hold to that hope too strongly. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I&amp;#39;ll bring it up with Steve, but he won&amp;#39;t want to spend the money on another person.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ah. Steve. The CEO. The penny-pincher. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Look, I&amp;#39;m not even necessarily asking for a full-time person. Even a part-time intern or whatever would be a huge boon to the department. I&amp;#39;m just telling you we don&amp;#39;t have the resources to keep up with day-to-day tasks much longer, nevermind a massive migration project.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I&amp;#39;ll see what I can do.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A few days later I got word from Laurie that it actually looked promising. I began excitedly writing job descriptions for two different positions. One for a full-time tier-1 helpdesk technician, and one for a part-time intern. This was exactly what we needed. A full-time helpdesk technician could work almost exclusively on Windows 10 upgrades and get us finished by January 2020 without us having to do much with it at all. A part-time intern could at least take most of the burden off the main team. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I sent the job descriptions over to Laurie the next day. A few hours later I got the call. We&amp;#39;re definitely getting our guy. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;That&amp;#39;s fantastic. Are we getting someone full-time or part-time?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Full-time.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Awesome. Did you take a look at the job descriptions I sent over? Do you think it needs any changes?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The briefest of pauses. &amp;quot;Well...&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oh no. No good can come of this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;He&amp;#39;s already picked out, actually,&amp;quot; she continued.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Whose kid is it?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Was it that obvious?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes. Whose kid?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sherry.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The director of HR? You&amp;#39;ve got to be kidding. Surely she knows better than this. &lt;em&gt;sigh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Alright. I&amp;#39;ll get with her.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;a few hours later&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hey, Sherry. I understand your son will be starting with us soon.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes. His name is Jordan. Now you&amp;#39;ll have to teach him, because he doesn&amp;#39;t have much experience. But he&amp;#39;s very smart and he loves technology.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;We&amp;#39;ll teach him whatever he needs to know.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;That&amp;#39;s great! He&amp;#39;ll start in a few days. And don&amp;#39;t worry. He&amp;#39;ll be treated just like any other employee.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DAY 1&lt;/strong&gt; - The Arrival&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;7:50&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Welcome. I&amp;#39;m Thomas, I&amp;#39;ll be your manager. John and Daniel usually arrive around 8:30; they&amp;#39;re the more senior sysadmins. So how much experience do you have?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s mostly just from playing around with computers at home and stuff to be honest. I took a couple classes in school but I don&amp;#39;t have a degree.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Well, as long as you&amp;#39;re willing to learn we&amp;#39;ll teach you everything you need to know. I will tell you that a lot of your time - especially at the beginning - is going to be spent upgrading and imaging computers. It&amp;#39;s not going to be particularly fun work. All of the computers here are still on Windows 7 and we need to be on Windows 10 by January 2020. Along with imaging them you&amp;#39;ll be upgrading a lot. Some of them are over 10 years old and we&amp;#39;ll be adding RAM and upgrading them to SSDs.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;10 years? I can&amp;#39;t believe you have modems that old.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And so begin - The New Guy Chronicles&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pemwdf/the_new_guy_chronicles_episode_2_the_betrayal&quot;&gt;Episode 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/iammandalore&quot;&gt; /u/iammandalore &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pcvl1s/the_new_guy_chronicles_episode_1/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pcvl1s/the_new_guy_chronicles_episode_1/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pcvl1s</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pcvl1s/the_new_guy_chronicles_episode_1/"><updated>2021-08-27T20:37:55+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-27T20:37:55+00:00</published><title>The New Guy Chronicles - Episode 1</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Guslet</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Guslet</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This happened recently, I work as a Systems/Network Engineer, but do a solid amount of Tier 2 &amp;quot;troubleshooting&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So I get a call from our hardware guy, who is a great guy, but not the best troubleshooter. He is replacing someone&amp;#39;s computer (He does a profile restore from the old computer, which copies down Desktop, Documents, etc, etc) and when he gave it to her, she complained it was incredibly slow on login and when they logged in it was taking a log time for things to load etc, she also mentioned she could not see the files on her desktop.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He calls me up for some guidance. So I remote into the computer and sure enough nothing is showing on the desktop. The computer is definitely crawling too, I look at task manager, nothing seems to be particularly high as far as usage.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Navigating into file explorer I go to the users desktop folder. They had over 2600 files on their desktop.....apparently Windows finally got fed up and decided it just cannot handle loading that many files at login. I promptly highlight all the files and put them into a new &amp;quot;Old Desktop&amp;quot; folder, then reboot the machine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Of course it logs in like a dream and the remaining 7 folders that I left show up on the desktop.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been in IT for 10 years and it never ceases to amaze me that someone would think having 2600+ items on their desktop wouldn&amp;#39;t be a problem....I don&amp;#39;t even understand how this person worked before on their old laptop with that many files.....&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Guslet&quot;&gt; /u/Guslet &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pcst3k/so_many_desktop_files/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pcst3k/so_many_desktop_files/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pcst3k</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pcst3k/so_many_desktop_files/"><updated>2021-08-27T18:13:14+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-27T18:13:14+00:00</published><title>So many desktop files.....</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/MAD_ROB</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/MAD_ROB</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another, very recent tale. Caution: german without proofreading skills.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You can guess what the tale is about just from the title, and see in the end if you guessed right.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The setting:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;one robotcell with an IPC* (Industrial PC, see below) which is connected to the customers company-lan (vlan)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;customer difficulty: easy&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;it difficulty: easy&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;players:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$me: me&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$itguy: the it guy of the customer&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$cust: the customer&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;story:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We installed a new robot cell with an IPC with Win10. My policy is that the $cust gets a patched system which is up to date, and can decide if he wants to run it off grid, or connect it to something and takes the responsibility for security and updates. This customer does the latter, and his external $itguy gets an local admin account and sets his things up (AV, Backup, ...)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After a few days the $cust calls me and tells me that every night at around 9pm the IPC is shutting down, bringing the production to a halt. I have no clue what happens, so I decide to visit the site at 9pm and have a look.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Did you already guessed it?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes... the backup runs at 9pm. And the standard-setting for this customer is &amp;quot;do the backup, and then shut the machine down&amp;quot;. Why? Because the it put the IPC in the office-group for the backup, and not the machine-group. And the office workers have to leave their pcs on, they make the backup and shut down.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A short mail to $itguy solved this rather quickly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;TL/DR: After the backup the PC gets shut down. Stopping the machine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Edit: spelling corrected after I woke up refreshed. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And a little bit of clarification here and there. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;IPC = Industrial PC&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Special Hardware for running 24/7 in rough enviroments like workshops.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/MAD_ROB&quot;&gt; /u/MAD_ROB &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pctwh5/backups_keep_the_machine_running/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pctwh5/backups_keep_the_machine_running/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pctwh5</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pctwh5/backups_keep_the_machine_running/"><updated>2021-08-27T19:10:10+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-27T19:10:10+00:00</published><title>Backups keep the machine running</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/DebbyRubottom53</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/DebbyRubottom53</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Caller: I&amp;#39;m looking in my outlook and a bunch of my emails are missing. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Ok, I&amp;#39;m looking at your Outlook data file and it&amp;#39;s really really large. As that file grows larger and larger the chances for corruption increase. Short term we can scan and repair it. For a long term fix I recommend archiving old email to reduce the size of that PST file. Remember...we talk about this about once a year and you say you hate archiving and you never want to do it because you lose emails? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caller: We&amp;#39;ve never talked about this before. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Yep, every time you have an Outlook problem. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caller: Well can you tell me how to archive my old email? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: Do you still have the notes I asked you to take last time? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caller: YOU HAVE NEVER TOLD ME ABOUT THIS!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: I have....repeatedly....for years. I&amp;#39;ll be happy to step you through the process but please take notes so you can refer to them in the future. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caller: Forget it! I&amp;#39;ll just figure it out on my own!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: I wouldn&amp;#39;t recommend that, there are some default settings you have to change otherwise Outlook will slow WAY down. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caller: I&amp;#39;ll figure it out! --Click--&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/DebbyRubottom53&quot;&gt; /u/DebbyRubottom53 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbyjis/i_love_it_when_they_threaten_to_figure_it_out_for/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbyjis/i_love_it_when_they_threaten_to_figure_it_out_for/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pbyjis</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbyjis/i_love_it_when_they_threaten_to_figure_it_out_for/"><updated>2021-08-26T12:31:18+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-26T12:31:18+00:00</published><title>I love it when they threaten to figure it out for themselves.</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/VictoryInChains</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/VictoryInChains</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I work as a field tech for $ISP, a little local company in the U.S.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$client has been having issues lately with their gateway router, which is almost ten years old.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$client, being a fairly high-functioning adult with more sense than God gave a goose, uses this thing called a search engine, actually figures out that their gateway router is probably old, and replaces it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$client gets a fairly basic home mesh system from the local box store, avoiding the kit from those vendors who want to just suck up ALL your data. $client gets this system home, plugged in, and powered up. Correctly!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$client&amp;#39;s Smart TV, less than a year old, from the people who make those cool phones, connects up to the new Wi-Fi network without a problem and starts throwing &amp;#39;cannot communicate with server&amp;#39; errors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$client calls mesh system support. Support blames TV manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$client calls TV support. Support blames mesh system manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$client calls mesh system manufacturer support, conferences in TV manufacturer support. Both mutually agree to blame the ISP.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$ISP phone support determines $client&amp;#39;s connection working great. Warns of service fee but $client has had enough and is totally willing to pay the fifty bucks to have someone actually look at their stuff.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Enter me, $FieldTech!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I quickly determine that the new router/mesh system is not, in fact, routing IP traffic. It is actually eating traffic. I log into the gateway, and then run the initial setup process. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new router begins routing traffic. The TV works!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;$client mutters about recovering the service fee from their router manufacturer. $FieldTech agrees.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s really not so much the client&amp;#39;s fault here, either. S/he downloaded the appropriate smartphone app, connected to the appropriate wifi network, and saw the pretty &amp;#39;congratulations, you&amp;#39;re online!&amp;#39; screen presented by said app, just missed &amp;#39;Tap here to finish setting up your network&amp;#39;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mostly I&amp;#39;m impressively aghast at the support for the mesh system. How did they miss needing to finish the INITIAL SETUP?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/VictoryInChains&quot;&gt; /u/VictoryInChains &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pc2viu/another_win_for_the_little_guy/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pc2viu/another_win_for_the_little_guy/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pc2viu</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pc2viu/another_win_for_the_little_guy/"><updated>2021-08-26T16:21:09+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-26T16:21:09+00:00</published><title>Another win for the little guy?</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/dave999dave</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/dave999dave</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m Dave and once again we going through a mass migration from one tool to another. About 15K will participate in this move.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll call the new tool TruthSayer, which is almost absurd as the real name it was branded.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And once again I have drafted extensive documentation, churned out quick reference guides, wrote reports, compiled FAQs, held demo sessions, held Q&amp;amp;As sessions, presented road shows, recorded presentations for replay, composed WBTs, done troubleshooting with the vendor, etc etc. I&amp;#39;m constantly incorporating feedback from all of this to make it all more appealing / accessible / concise etc.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;All of this and many many more is listed on our new tool&amp;#39;s sorted and organized landing page. A one stop shop if you have ANY questions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I was chatting with my coworker Stan today when I noticed the landing page had gotten a review. I didn&amp;#39;t even know the pages could get reviews. I leaned forward and saw it was a 1 star review. So it sucks I guess?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dave&lt;/strong&gt;: Huh. Our TruthSayer landing page got a review.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stan&lt;/strong&gt;: Oh, what was it?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dave&lt;/strong&gt;: No comments, but they did give it a star. A one star review.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stan&lt;/strong&gt;: So how many reviews so far?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dave&lt;/strong&gt;: Just that one, one review.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stan&lt;/strong&gt;: I see. Here, Dave I&amp;#39;ll help you out. Your page now has TWO one star reviews! Gotta go! &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;Click&amp;gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I checked and yes, seconds after our call there were now two one star reviews. Thanks Stan.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/dave999dave&quot;&gt; /u/dave999dave &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbsi7n/now_you_have_two_reviews_dave/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbsi7n/now_you_have_two_reviews_dave/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pbsi7n</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbsi7n/now_you_have_two_reviews_dave/"><updated>2021-08-26T04:49:15+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-26T04:49:15+00:00</published><title>Now you have TWO reviews Dave!</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/xforce2000</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/xforce2000</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I do consumer tech support. Recently I had a very long call about a customer’s elderly computer. Their display was showing two windows!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tried to remote in. No joy. Checked for documentation of what I understood to be the issue based on the customer’s responses to my questions. No luck.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After about 40 minutes I realized that the customer’s operating system had gone through an automatic update and wiped the customer’s customized display, including the desktop photo and programs they left open, and it was that which prompted the call. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;15 minutes later I was able to guide them back to the way the computer looked before the update….&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Our target time is less than 30 minutes per call. Hopefully I get some short snappers in the next couple of weeks!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/xforce2000&quot;&gt; /u/xforce2000 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbe2qz/duh_oh_that_is_what_you_meant/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbe2qz/duh_oh_that_is_what_you_meant/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pbe2qz</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pbe2qz/duh_oh_that_is_what_you_meant/"><updated>2021-08-25T15:53:32+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-25T15:53:32+00:00</published><title>D’uh… oh, *that* is what you meant!</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/polandreh</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/polandreh</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hey TFTS, first time posting, which is odd since I&amp;#39;ve worked all my professional life in application support and couldn&amp;#39;t think of a story to post even though I have thousands.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My first job in London was providing 1st and 2nd line of support to a reporting software my company built and sold to clients in the financial sector.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We had two types of clients: hosted or in-house install. While the first were easy to debug (log in to their environment, replicate and assess, all while having full access to the back end), the others were less so for obvious reasons, yet we kept a (virtually stale) copy of their initial environment to provide some semblance of support. This story, obviously, is about the latter type.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The software itself was like Tableau, in which you add objects to a sheet (graphics, tables, images,...) to create a template, and the workflow fills in the latest data as often as you want it (daily, weekly, monthly,...) and generates the final report in the format you want, the most common being Word or PDF.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Also, the software used a proprietary third party software to convert Word documents into PDF. Don&amp;#39;t recall which one it was, but we would buy the license ourselves and would give it to the client for their in-house install. We didn&amp;#39;t only recommend this software in our install documentation but insisted that they use it since our product only &amp;quot;supported&amp;quot; this vendor in particular (meaning it could probably work with others, but we only tested this particular one, so could only ensure it works as expected with it and it alone).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, the ticket in question was floating around for a while, bouncing from one Support member to another, and no one could figure it out. We were only 4 in the Support team, so it was bound to land on my plate eventually. Also, side note, I was the youngest (by far) in the team, and my impostor syndrome was high, so I was dreading my turn to have a go at this issue.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The problem was that the generated PDF reports were showing the objects completely misaligned compared to what they were supposed to look like. Moreover, this only happened when generating PDFs; Word docs came out as expected. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, this being an in-house installation, we could only try to replicate it on our end to no avail. A co-worker tried to get a copy of their database to get our environment in line with the client&amp;#39;s, but that was turned down because of &amp;quot;sensitive information&amp;quot; that they couldn&amp;#39;t share (what&amp;#39;s the point of non-disclosure contracts?). Another co-worker tried a screen sharing session but all it helped for was to see the report being generated incorrectly, since their IT team wouldn&amp;#39;t let us take a look at the back end and see if the software was installed properly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;By then, the client was getting impatient with how long it was taking for this issue to be resolved. So having this information telling me how tied my hands were, plus the pressure on being the last line of defense, I do the first thing I can come up with: I check in Acrobat Reader who is the PDF Producer of the file the client sent. Usually, you would expect to see the name of the third-party software as the creator, but lo and behold, the client was using some other tool for the PDF conversion (why? As I said, we provided the license for FOR FREE!!! So it wasn&amp;#39;t a matter of saving pennies). &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, I happily send my reply to the client stating &amp;quot;Unfortunately, you&amp;#39;re using a software we don&amp;#39;t support, please use [product name] as is specified in our documentation.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One would expect the issue to be closed: the client was caught red-handed using our software incorrectly, thus in breach of contract. However, as you read the title of this story, this was not the case. All I got in return was a condescending reply to my email CC&amp;#39;ing the account manager on our company and my boss stating &amp;quot;This is ridiculous, [Account Manager&amp;#39;s name]. This has taken long enough. Can&amp;#39;t someone fix the damn problem?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I wish I could say the story had a satisfying ending but unfortunately for me, my company was &amp;quot;too British&amp;quot; in their mentality and followed the creed of &amp;quot;the customer is always right&amp;quot;. I didn&amp;#39;t hear back on this issue, and luckily that client didn&amp;#39;t raise many tickets, so I didn&amp;#39;t have to deal with them again. My guess is that the AM had to convince them to use the third-party software we supplied, but I never asked her how that discussion went.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;All I got was a chuckle from the rest of the team saying &amp;quot;how didn&amp;#39;t I think about that before?&amp;quot; and a pat on the back from my manager which would come back and haunt me for the rest of my days at that company since I became known as the &amp;quot;last resort&amp;quot; guy, which meant I had to deal with all the troublesome tickets.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/polandreh&quot;&gt; /u/polandreh &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/papt60/client_cannot_accept_theyre_wrong/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/papt60/client_cannot_accept_theyre_wrong/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_papt60</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/papt60/client_cannot_accept_theyre_wrong/"><updated>2021-08-24T15:39:44+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-24T15:39:44+00:00</published><title>Client cannot accept they're wrong</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Odd_Seaweed_5985</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Odd_Seaweed_5985</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;New guy joins the support team and we share an office.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m the more experienced one, so he&amp;#39;s learning the ropes from me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On one of his very first days, he gets a request to upgrade Windows on a laptop for some big mucky-muck.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thinking that he&amp;#39;ll impress me with his initiative, he starts the process before I get to work.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When I arrive, my new, somewhat reactive office-mate immediately grabs me and starts in with &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m in big, big trouble, I&amp;#39;m going to get fired!&amp;quot; I can see that he&amp;#39;s really worried. I can&amp;#39;t imagine what he could have done at THIS place that could get him fired so quickly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Why, what happened?&amp;quot; I asked.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;I needed to upgrade a Windows laptop for [important guy in corner office] so I grabbed your install disk... and it... &lt;em&gt;whiped everything!&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;What disk did you grab?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He shows me a disk labeled &amp;quot;ASR&amp;quot;. Oops. That&amp;#39;s NOT a setup disk, it&amp;#39;s an Automated System Recovery disk, used for automatically, mass-installing, Windows onto many devices at the same time. You insert the disk, turn ON the system, and it immediately whipes the harddrive and installs Windows over the network.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I still kinda smile imagining what horrors must have been going through his head as he saw the harddrive suddenly start going crazy....instead of getting a normal Windows setup screen. And then it wouldn&amp;#39;t boot afterward? Oh the pain he must have been feeling!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I tell him what he had just done. He asks me why I would have such a dangerous thing in my possession, and actually gets kinda mad at me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He tells me that the laptop belongs to a &lt;em&gt;high-level&lt;/em&gt; exec, and he&amp;#39;s deathly afraid to tell him that all of his data is now gone. He&amp;#39;s sure to be fired on the spot.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I laugh and say &amp;quot;No, you won&amp;#39;t. Come with me, watch and learn, we&amp;#39;ll take care of it together. He should have backups or copies of anything important. If he&amp;#39;s in such a position in the company, then he&amp;#39;s fully aware of his responsibility to protect his and the companies data.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We go to the guys office and I tell him what had happened. He&amp;#39;s disappointed, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; disappointed. I apologize for the accident, and tell him that we&amp;#39;ve removed every ASR disk so that it couldn&amp;#39;t possibly happen again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He asks about data recovery. Sure, we can atttempt that, but no guarantees, and it&amp;#39;s expensive. I can tell that he&amp;#39;s getting more agitated.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As a subtle reminder of &lt;em&gt;his&lt;/em&gt; responsibilities, I casually mention &amp;quot;You know, for quite some time now, Support has offered a few different services that will automatically backup your data and even your complete profile. You just never know, &lt;em&gt;even when things are going perfectly&lt;/em&gt;, when a harddrive might fail, a laptop gets dropped or stolen...&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He stood there and I see a transformation come over his face. He gets it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yeah, I should have enrolled this into the [automatic backup process] a long time ago.&amp;quot; He even knew the name of the backup software we were using?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We eventually leave and never hear of it again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new guy eventually moved to Executive Support, so I guess he was just a glutton for punishment...&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Odd_Seaweed_5985&quot;&gt; /u/Odd_Seaweed_5985 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/parxa5/i_just_grabbed_your_asr_disk_and_its_all_gone/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/parxa5/i_just_grabbed_your_asr_disk_and_its_all_gone/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_parxa5</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/parxa5/i_just_grabbed_your_asr_disk_and_its_all_gone/"><updated>2021-08-24T17:26:22+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-24T17:26:22+00:00</published><title>I just grabbed your ASR disk and... it's ALL GONE!</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/newtekie1</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/newtekie1</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, I do freelance IT for small businesses. One of my customers decided to replace me. The &amp;quot;company&amp;quot; they replaced me with is really just the IT Director of the local community college. He is a people manager, and know next to nothing about actual IT. But he&amp;#39;s a friend of one of the employees and he&amp;#39;s cheap. So I tell my customer good luck and contact me if the every need me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;#39;t even a week and the first thing this guy tried to do he botched.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I get a call from him in a panic. He was tasked with replacing their ancient AVAYA phone system with a modern VOIP system. This is what he did:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He tested all the phones connected at his office, and they worked. The next day he takes them out to the customer&amp;#39;s office. He plugs a phone directly into the ISP gateway and the phone connects. So he calls the VIOP company and tells them all is good, the phones are connecting correctly, and they can start porting the phone numbers over from the POTs lines to the VOIP service.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While the porting is happening, he starts disconnecting the old phones at people&amp;#39;s desks and connecting the new VOIP phones. And when he is done he realizes none of the phones are connecting.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The VOIP company tells him to run a connection test tool on his laptop plugged in through one of the phones and sure enough the connection is being blocked.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But by this point the numbers are already ported to the VOIP service and the customer is without phones, and he has no clue why they aren&amp;#39;t working.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s when I get the call. He explains what he did and I asked him why he didn&amp;#39;t test the phones from behind the firewall. And I shit you not, his exact words were &amp;quot;What&amp;#39;s a firewall?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Seriously, he had no clue what a firewall was. He always just assumed you plugged everything into the ISP gateway and used that. I was floored. This is a guy that is doing business IT and he doesn&amp;#39;t know what a firewall is.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oh, and the kicker, his next project is to set up a site to site VPN connection between their current office and a new office they just rented. He told them he totally knows how to do that. They guy that doesn&amp;#39;t know what a firewall is claims he knows how to setup up site to site VPNs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So I logged in remotely and set up the firewall properly to work with the VOIP phones. I&amp;#39;m sure the owner of the business will question why I had to be brought in to fix the phones when he receives my detailed bill.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;TL;DR - Customer of mine when with a cheaper friend of an employee for their IT and fired me. The person they hired doesn&amp;#39;t even know what a firewall is.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/newtekie1&quot;&gt; /u/newtekie1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa3u12/the_phones_worked_when_i_tested_them_connected_to/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa3u12/the_phones_worked_when_i_tested_them_connected_to/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pa3u12</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa3u12/the_phones_worked_when_i_tested_them_connected_to/"><updated>2021-08-23T16:52:49+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-23T16:52:49+00:00</published><title>The phones worked when I tested them connected to the ISP gateway, why doesn't it work when I plug it in at people's desks? What's a firewall? - The IT Company That Replaced Me</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/ulimi2002</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/ulimi2002</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m an IT Director of a medium sized business, have been pushing cybersecurity training for the users for several years now. Some of the users are so paranoid about opening emails, they forward the emails to me for confirmation first. I usually tell them to trust their judgment (after I check to make sure it was safe).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But today a salesperson forwarded an email he thinks was a customer sending him pics of something but was not sure. It took about 10 seconds for me to realize he forwarded a text he received to his email and forgot he did it. The email came from &amp;lt;phone#&amp;gt;@mms.att.net and he didn&amp;#39;t notice the number was his own.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m glad he is careful, but maybe I scared them a bit too much about phishing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/ulimi2002&quot;&gt; /u/ulimi2002 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa8ail/too_much_training/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa8ail/too_much_training/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pa8ail</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa8ail/too_much_training/"><updated>2021-08-23T20:36:51+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-23T20:36:51+00:00</published><title>Too much training?</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/YDAQ</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/YDAQ</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;❌ Incredible Feats of Networking Heroics;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;🤔 Tech Troubleshooting Under the Direst of Circumstances;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;✔️ Unsolvable Problems Cracked by Sheer Genius and/or Pure Luck;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;✔️ Moral Support after Having Dealt with Difficult Clients;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;✔️ And of course, Stupid User Stories!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I left my job of many years recently and have sort of been floating from one random location to another. While I don&amp;#39;t plan to stick around at the current place I do get to put food on my table in the interim. Anyway, you know how you can tell a lot about a person by how they treat the help? Well, it turns out that I am both the help and an idiot magnet so I&amp;#39;m learning a lot about people today!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I had barely exited my vehicle when Mal Content, the local blowhard, descended down the steps towards me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mal:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Why didn&amp;#39;t you fix my computer?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Because I didn&amp;#39;t know there was anything wrong with it...?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mal:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;It won&amp;#39;t turn on and I need to do &lt;em&gt;important&lt;/em&gt; work, so I had to troubleshoot it myself. I know it&amp;#39;s not the [tower] because I pushed the power button and nothing happened.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Nothing at all?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mal:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Nothing. Just some lights and a bit of noise, and then &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt;. I can&amp;#39;t believe you didn&amp;#39;t fix this! You were supposed to fix this yesterday!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;sigh&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;All right, I&amp;#39;ll take a look.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;And so with Mal breathing down my neck, I pressed the power button on the tower.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mal:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;See?! Nothing! I told you the [tower] was broken!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;And then I pressed the power button on the monitor...&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mal:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;What?! What did you just do?&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me:&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;quot;Magic.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sometimes, just sometimes, you win.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/YDAQ&quot;&gt; /u/YDAQ &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa6trp/i_just_turned_it_on/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa6trp/i_just_turned_it_on/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_pa6trp</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/pa6trp/i_just_turned_it_on/"><updated>2021-08-23T19:21:03+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-23T19:21:03+00:00</published><title>I just... turned it on...</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/TheNobleMustelid</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/TheNobleMustelid</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;TL;DR at the end.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some years ago I needed a particular sort of sensor for my biology research. It was neither high-precision nor particularly complex, but it was strange. No one sold anything like it. So I designed and built the sensors I needed on a minimal budget, on a scratched-up table at home, using a soldering iron half my own age. And then, through a series of improbable events, this sensor got a lot of attention. It made the college I work at look good and to this day if you search for my real name what you’ll probably find is the college’s press releases about how my device will solve world hunger and cure AIDS while you sleep. As an indication that even the college did not believe this they rewarded me with a $15 gift certificate at the local coffee shop.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, the computer science (CS) department did notice that I had just done something that looked very much like “Internet of Things” and made me an offer: instead of building my next device on a table at home using a soldering iron from the Late Paleolithic I could use their very nice lab, with lots of equipment, and even raid their parts bins, as long as I also passed off some of my knowledge to their students. And so I ended up spending a lot of time in the CS lab. This story comes from that time. Some details of actual projects have been fuzzed because specific projects would de-anonymize me quite easily.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On the day this story begins I am in lab laying out a circuit. As I am doing so I am chatting with the students, a small group who I have come to know fairly well, who spend most of their free time in the lab tinkering with things. One student, who I will dub Hamilcar (who doesn’t like the Second Punic War?) calls me over for troubleshooting.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I get up from my chair, careful to bring my cup of coffee with me. When troubleshooting with students a cup of coffee is essential, because you can raise it to your face and take a sip from it to hide the fact that while your voice is saying, “That happens sometimes,” your face is saying, “I don’t think you’ve fully recovered from that brain injury.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hamilcar’s project involves a speaker. He’s quite early on in working on it and only has the speaker attached to an audio control board/amplifier which is, in turn, attached to an Arduino. (Arduinos are programmable microcontrollers.) Hamilcar points to his screen where a small program is open in an IDE. “This [points] should play a small tune through here [points]. But nothing is happening.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“When did it break?” I ask.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“It never worked,” he responds.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This seems strange. I question him a bit more. As I think we all know the right way to build this device would be: 1) wire up the speaker, run current through and make sure you hear something. 2) write a tiny piece of code that just makes some sort of noise, verify that you can get the code on the Arduino and get noise out of the speaker. 3) turn “make a noise” into “make these specific noises”. What Hamilcar has done is wire everything together, write a giant block of code, and then test it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“Have you checked the hardware?” I ask. Always start troubleshooting at step zero. I then have to explain that I mean “have you done anything to verify that the hardware works?”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“It’s wired correctly,” Hamilcar says. This is not what I asked.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“Have you ever gotten any sound out of that speaker?” I ask. “A blip when you plugged it in? A short code snippet that just makes it hum? Anything to test it?”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“No!” Hamilcar exclaims, clearly unreasonably annoyed by these questions. Other students look up from their projects and stare at him in surprise. “It’s plugged in correctly! I’m not an idiot!”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I bring my coffee cup up to my face and take a long sip. “But did you test it?”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“No!” Hamilcar yells. I understand, a bit, where his frustration is coming from. He does have some real skills from his own, independent study, and nothing he’s done yet has been able to showcase this. He feels like we don’t believe that he knows things. On the other hand, he’s being an ass.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I bring the coffee cup down and give Hamilcar The Look. If you ever find yourself teaching teenagers or young adults make sure to practice The Look. Done correctly, the victim should feel the chill of the coming winter creeping into their bones and hear the distant howl of the first wolves picking up their trail. “This is,” I say, gesturing expansively with my coffee mug while continuing to glare, “Computer SCIENCE. We TEST things. Check your hardware.” I then remind him that the day before I had wasted time debugging a bad solder joint.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hamilcar makes his saving throw against The Look. “I know how to solder!”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I point out that the years of his life are but a blink of my eye, and that while I had learned to solder as the great ice sheets retreated at the end of the Younger Dryas he had learned to solder two weeks earlier, from me. And that his solder joints still closely resembled metal potatoes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“You’re not helping!”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“No,” I finally agreed, “I’m not. And I won’t, until you check your hardware.” Then I walked back to my bench. And thus began the descent into madness.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Day One: Hamilcar has discovered that Arduinos are not very good at keeping time by themselves. He has a theory that this is, somehow, messing up the speaker. Perhaps the sound frequencies are being compressed into the ultrasonic, or something. He’s fiddling around with clock chips, which are really only needed when your time intervals are hours or days. Obviously, this just further complicates his untested circuit and doesn’t help.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Day Two: Hamilcar spends an hour undoing his clock chip changes from yesterday. He is now convinced that he is running the Arduino at the wrong internal clock speed. This can happen to the chip-brain of the Arduino but only if you buy that chip yourself and wire it up. Inside an Arduino that won’t happen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Day Three: Hamilcar is now propounding a new theory to the other students. Arduinos use a C-derived coding language. But what if this language does not handle global and local variables in the same way? Much like the Carthaginian invasion of Italy, this theory serves only to cause a lot of destruction and get people angry without actually making any progress towards winning the war.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Day Four: Hamilcar is bouncing his latest idea off another student. At this point Hamilcar’s broken circuit and his refusal to test the hardware have become a running joke. Before he gets past the first sentence of his new theory the other student asks, “Have you checked the hardware?” Hamilcar explodes in anger. The other students just shake their heads, and I eventually have to tell him to use his inside voice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Day Five: Hamilcar is hunched over his station, muttering something in an unknown language. Is this a dark ritual to the old gods of blood and fire, meant to strike me down for questioning his soldering skills? Has he completely snapped and is speaking in a new language that makes sense only to him? I listen more closely. No, he’s just swearing continuously under his breath.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Day Six is a Saturday. As a biologist I sometimes have to come in to work on a weekend to keep my living study subjects, well, living. I had also glued some pieces together on a device on Friday, so I swing by the CS lab to see if they set up correctly, and, if so, to glue the next set.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The lab is quiet, empty of students. As much as I like joking around with the students it’s relaxing to be alone and able to focus. I finish my own project and decide to check Hamilcar’s project. If I can debug it I’ll steer him correctly on Monday.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There’s no multimeter on Hamilcar’s station (of course) but once I grab one his power and ground check out. The Arduino is pinned-out correctly, and I’m getting power where I should there, too. The audio controller/amplifier is a bit of a mystery. I haven’t used this design before. I unlock the computer and find that Hamilcar already has the wiring diagram open. Power is solid. Ground is ground. LVL is….not attached to anything. What the hell is LVL, anyway? I know that the chip can do much more complicated things than what Hamilcar is doing with it, so maybe it’s not needed. But debugging means figuring out what things are. I find a webpage where someone is using LVL on this chip in their own circuit. I look at what they seem to be doing with it. It’s not amazingly helpful. I bend over to poke at the chip with the multimeter, just to see if I can tell if LVL is output or input. As my head gets close to the chip I hear a faint sound in the quiet of the room. I pick up the speaker and put it up to my ear. It’s playing a tune. Right. LVL. As in “sound level”. Thirty seconds later I’ve decoded the wiring diagram and have LVL attached to 5V power. The speaker is humming out a tune clear as day. I leave a text file open on the computer. “Checked your hardware. Amplifier on chip was not powered.”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Two months later we’re sitting in lab. A new student loudly complains to no one in particular that his starter exercise (get an LED to blink) isn’t working. “Did your LED power on solidly when you first plugged it in?” I ask.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;“No,” the new student says. “Does that matter?”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A wave of apocalyptic fury breaks over us, a roar of sound and anger. It’s Hamilcar. “CHECK YOUR DAMN HARDWARE!”&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Student has an issue with a program. I tell him to check the hardware. He doesn’t. It’s the hardware.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/TheNobleMustelid&quot;&gt; /u/TheNobleMustelid &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/p9qm1y/check_the_hardware/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/p9qm1y/check_the_hardware/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_p9qm1y</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/p9qm1y/check_the_hardware/"><updated>2021-08-23T02:35:39+00:00</updated><published>2021-08-23T02:35:39+00:00</published><title>Check the hardware</title></entry></feed>