<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><updated>2022-11-17T13:05:40+00:00</updated><icon>https://www.redditstatic.com/icon.png/</icon><id>/r/talesfromtechsupport.rss</id><link rel="self" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport.rss" type="application/atom+xml"><link rel="alternate" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport" type="text/html"><logo>https://b.thumbs.redditmedia.com/vjnTCecCm4tO6tmHqheYNXHORjwzbOrhEbLX7HduMdw.png</logo><subtitle>Welcome to Tales From Tech Support, the subreddit where we post stories about helping someone with a tech issue. Did you try turning it off and on again?</subtitle><title>Tales From Tech Support</title><entry><author><name>/u/MagicBigfoot</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/MagicBigfoot</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hey, we can have two stickies now!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, something like 90% of the mod removals are posts that obviously don&amp;#39;t belong here.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When we ask if they checked the rules first, almost everyone says, &amp;quot;O sorry, I didn&amp;#39;t read the sidebar.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And when asked why they didn&amp;#39;t read the sidebar, almost everyone says, &amp;quot;B-b-but I&amp;#39;m on mobile!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So this sticky is for &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt;, dear non-sidebar-reading mobile users.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;First off, here&amp;#39;s a link to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/about/sidebar&quot;&gt;TFTS Sidebar&lt;/a&gt; for your convenience and non-plausible-deniability.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;Second, here is a hot list of the rules of TFTS:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 0&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_.2205_.3A_your_post_must_be_a_written_story_about_tech_support&quot;&gt;YOUR POST MUST BE A STORY ABOUT TECH SUPPORT&lt;/a&gt; - Just like it says. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 1&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_1_.3A_anonymize_your_info&quot;&gt;ANONYMIZE YOUR INFO&lt;/a&gt; - Keep your personal and business names out of the story. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 2&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_2_.3A_keep_your_posts_.26_comments_sfw&quot;&gt;KEEP YOUR POST SFW&lt;/a&gt; - People do browse TFTS on the job and we need to respect that. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 3&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_3_.3A_no_posts_that_ask_a_question&quot;&gt;NO QUESTION POSTS&lt;/a&gt; - Post here AFTER you figure out what the problem was. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 4&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_4_.3A_no_image_links&quot;&gt;NO IMAGE LINKS&lt;/a&gt; - Tell your story with words please, not graphics or memes. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 5&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_5_.3A_no_standalone_links&quot;&gt;NO OTHER LINKS&lt;/a&gt; - Do not redirect us someplace else, even on Reddit. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 6&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_6_.3A_no_customer_complaint_posts&quot;&gt;NO COMPLAINT POSTS&lt;/a&gt; - We don&amp;#39;t want to hear about it. Really. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule 7&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_7_.3A_no_pranking_or_hacking_tales&quot;&gt;NO PRANKING, HACKING, ETC.&lt;/a&gt; - TFTS is about helping people, not messing with them. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule &amp;#8734;&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_rule_.221E_.3A_don.27t_be_a_jerk&quot;&gt;DON&amp;#39;T BE A JERK.&lt;/a&gt; - You know exactly what I&amp;#39;m talking &amp;#39;bout, Willis. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index&quot;&gt;TFTS Wiki&lt;/a&gt; has more details on all of these rules and other notable TFTS info as well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For instance, you can review our list of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_what_tales_have_jumped_the_shark.3F&quot;&gt;Officially Retired Topics&lt;/a&gt;, or check out all of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/wiki/index#wiki_the_compleat_best_of_tfts&quot;&gt;Best of TFTS Collections&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading &amp;amp; welcome to &lt;a href=&quot;/r/TalesFromTechSupport&quot;&gt;/r/TalesFromTechSupport&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;hr/&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post has been locked, comments will be auto-removed.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/message/compose?to=%2Fr%2Ftalesfromtechsupport&quot;&gt;message the mods&lt;/a&gt; if you have a question or a suggestion.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Remember you can hide this message once you have read it and never see it again!)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;edit: fixed links for some mobile users.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/MagicBigfoot&quot;&gt; /u/MagicBigfoot &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/3dqlny/tfts_posting_rules_mobile_users_please_read/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/3dqlny/tfts_posting_rules_mobile_users_please_read/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_3dqlny</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/3dqlny/tfts_posting_rules_mobile_users_please_read/"><updated>2015-07-18T14:29:59+00:00</updated><published>2015-07-18T14:29:59+00:00</published><title>TFTS POSTING RULES (MOBILE USERS PLEASE READ!)</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/__Mattt__</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/__Mattt__</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;First time posting. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br/&gt; I used to work in a NOC for an WISP, and we also fielded the user calls. I was a senior engineer which was basically a glorified L1 engineer that took charge in Managers absence. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STORY:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt; It was a Sunday I had started work nice an early and was the senior engineer on duty with 2 other junior engineers. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An outage occurred in quite a large segment of out network so we where all hands on deck fielding calls for a 200 - 300 user segment of the network, when I received a call from a user.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Thank you for Calling [Company Name] Your speaking to Matthew, How can I assist?&amp;quot; I say in my best telephone voice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;She replies &amp;quot;My Internet is off&amp;quot; in a frustrated tone.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At this moment I realize the customer is upset and most likely affecting by the outage we have, but due to process I need to create a ticket and link user to the parent case for email and SMS updates on the ongoing issue.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kindly ask the user &amp;quot;No problem Ma&amp;#39;am, I just need to locate your account. Please may I have the account holders name and an email address or account ID?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;She then screams &amp;quot;[Customers Physical address]!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now normally this is enough to locate an account but we are tasked to confirm 3 or more details on the account to make sure that we are speaking to the user in question and to ensure that we are somewhat upholding GDPR and not leaking information.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I kindly repeat to the user &amp;quot;Please may I have the account holders name or telephone number as well?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;She then proceeds to scream at me &amp;quot;YOU DO NOT NEED THIS INFORMATION I HAVE DEALT WITH THIS TECH SUPPORT MORE TIMES THAN I CAN COUNT BECAUSE MY INTERNET IS SO SH$#...!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At this moment I give the customer the benefit of the doubt and understand internet problems are frustrating and ask the user &amp;quot;Please ma&amp;#39;am, I require this information to confirm that I am speaking to the account holder&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;User goes quite for 10 seconds there is an awkward silence...&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;User: &amp;quot;You dont work for [Company Name], Do you?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Shocked by the question because who in their right mind would want to work in a call center during an outage &amp;quot;Excuse me Ma&amp;#39;am???&amp;quot; I reply confused.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Your a Thief! You have broken into the office and are stealing customers info...&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I cut the call mid sentence, I look at my Juniors who are both staring at me and say &amp;quot;I am not paid enough to deal with that...&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Customer proceeded to call over and over but I spent the next 2 hours dropping her call every time I saw it in the call queue.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Let my boss know to check the call recordings, I get a laughing emoji in response.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;6 Days later I find 16 customer service complaints logged against me that no-one in management or Customer service team told me about.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Listen to the Voicemails attached to tickets. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hello??? There is someone in your office stealing peoples information, I am worried about your staffs safety. He kept asking me for my information and when I asked him why he needed this information he told me it is because it is what I want and when I asked him if he truly works for [Company name] he said no he doesn&amp;#39;t and told me to F#$% Off.... Please I am worried about your staffs safety... and also my internet is off&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I must have listened to this voice recording a 100 times and was declared the Data Thief of the office. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Never dealt with a more delusional customer before, I asked the higher ups if they terminated her contract like they have in the past for abusing staff on the phone they neither confirmed or denied that they had but we have never heard from them since :) &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t let customers treat you like trash.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/__Mattt__&quot;&gt; /u/__Mattt__ &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yx7tmg/accused_of_breaking_into_my_own_office/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yx7tmg/accused_of_breaking_into_my_own_office/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yx7tmg</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yx7tmg/accused_of_breaking_into_my_own_office/"><updated>2022-11-16T22:07:11+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-16T22:07:11+00:00</published><title>Accused of breaking into my own office</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/theoboley</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/theoboley</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m just getting settled in for my day and my first tech support call of the day comes in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;Help Desk, this is (me)&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;User: &amp;quot;Hi...I locked my keys in my car&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Silence for about 10 seconds&lt;/em&gt; U: &amp;quot;hello?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;M: &amp;quot;Yes, I&amp;#39;m still here, is there an issue with a computer you&amp;#39;re having?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;U: &amp;quot;no... I locked my keys in the car, and can&amp;#39;t leave&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;M: &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m not sure what I can do, did you want me to get you the number for AAA?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;U: &amp;quot;Y&amp;#39;all used to come out with a slim Jim and unlock our cars for us&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;M: &amp;quot;Ma&amp;#39;am, I&amp;#39;ve been here for 5 years and this is the first time I&amp;#39;ve heard of this happening...&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;U: &amp;quot;Can you call maintenance? They used to do this all the time&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;M: &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m pretty sure they&amp;#39;d say the same thing, it&amp;#39;s a liability issue and if something happens to your car door the company is liable for the damages... Here&amp;#39;s their number. You can call them and talk to them.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;U: &lt;em&gt;hangs up phone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;About 30 minutes later I follow up with maintenance. They said exactly what I said. They couldn&amp;#39;t because of company liability. Apparently happened in the past, and a door got screwed up and were brought to small claims over it. Never again. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Wonderful way to start that day.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/theoboley&quot;&gt; /u/theoboley &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ywucdg/during_a_shift_change/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ywucdg/during_a_shift_change/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_ywucdg</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ywucdg/during_a_shift_change/"><updated>2022-11-16T14:07:12+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-16T14:07:12+00:00</published><title>During a shift change</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/dickcheney600</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/dickcheney600</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several days later, someone else had untangled the string on the claw and put it back in place. They also glued a washer over the broken end of the pulley. The string couldn&amp;#39;t slip off anymore, but may still catch on the remaining broken part from time to time. I suppose that will have to do until a replacement part was obtained. The boss knew what it needed so if he wanted me to order it myself, I figured he would say so.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You may remember that I mentioned a missing ground prong on the plug. I included that in the email to my boss about the claw machine. We didn&amp;#39;t originally get the machine like that, it broke off in an outlet while it was at our store. We didn&amp;#39;t have any replacement plugs OR cords that I knew of, but in this disorganized mess of a store, who could say? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A couple weeks later, on a day where the boss wasn&amp;#39;t there, a customer complained that the claw machine shocked him. I described what an electric shock from AC felt like and asked if it felt like that, or more like a static shock. He said it felt like AC was present. So I asked him to, without touching the machine, point to what shocked him. He pointed to the metal box where the joystick and coin slots were. I told him, thanks. He left the store without another word. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I grabbed my little voltage detector pen, and turned it on, testing it on a known-live outlet before I &amp;quot;trusted&amp;quot; it. I poked the metal box with it. The pen lit up and beeped. Ruh roh. I then poked the metal decorative trim that ran up the corners/edges, which surrounded the decorative &amp;quot;rope lights&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;strip lights&amp;quot;. This too was live. Yikes! Even the metal frame of the front door was live, with 110 VAC.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This needed to be unplugged, IMMEDIATELY, and not hooked back up until it was repaired. The trouble was moving the machine back so I could remove the plug without touching either 1: The metal trim up the corners, 2: the coin/controller box, or 3: The metal frame of the front door. I didn&amp;#39;t have any insulated gloves, and even if I did, I was wearing a short sleeved shirt and didn&amp;#39;t have a coat to cover my arms, due to the weather that day. I asked my coworker if he knew which breaker controlled that set of outlets where the claw machine was. He said he didn&amp;#39;t know. I told him that he should shut down the computer, because it might lose power. He asked why, and I explained the claw machine was shocking people, and I couldn&amp;#39;t reach the plug without touching the machine, so I needed to find the breaker, and that might mean the computer would lose power. He said he needed the computer to stay on. I literally facepalmed right in front of him, and said &amp;quot;I don&amp;#39;t think you understand, there is high voltage on the outside of the machine. The outside that people can touch. That means someone could get electrocuted, and we would get sued. That could put us out of business, which means we would all lose our jobs. No one&amp;#39;s lives are depending on that computer right now, nor is our business.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;With that, I went to the breaker room and took a few guesses. I went back out to the floor, and I had indeed shut off the outlet cluster that fed the claw machine. I pulled the machine away from the wall and unplugged it. I opened up the back cover and removed the fuse, putting a big DANGER note covering the fuse slot. This was inside the machine. Since the machine was on wheels, I went ahead and wheeled it to the back room, and then I turned the breakers back on. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I called the boss and left a message explaining why the claw machine had been moved to the back room. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I took the cord and tried using a continuity checker to zero in on the source of the problem. I measured between the hot prong and the metal parts on the outside, but the checker didn&amp;#39;t beep or light up. I figured if it did, I could disconnect parts of the machine one by one until I found where the short was. Unfortunately, the continuity checker isn&amp;#39;t seeing it, so it&amp;#39;s probably a case of slight leakage from something rather than a dead short. So I armed myself with the multimeter and voltage detector pen from before. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I went through a similar process that I&amp;#39;d originally planned, but with the ohms setting on my meter. I measure between the hot prong and the metal trim on the machine. It should either be open or at least in the mega-ohms, but it&amp;#39;s lower resistance than that. Not a dead short, though, so it probably isn&amp;#39;t an actual frayed wire touching the inside of one of the metal parts. So I disconnected one light fixture inside the machine, but the leakage was still there. I disconnected another light fixture, the leakage was still there. I disconnected the power supply... bingo! There was leakage between Hot and Ground on the power supply. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The ground strap is supposed to be connected to the inside of all user-accessible metal trim, so that if a hot wire touches it from inside, it shorts out and blows a fuse/breaker. However, with the third prong missing on the plug, the ground strap instead carried the fault current from the power supply to all the outside metal parts of the machine. I reconnected the lights, but left the power supply box disconnected. The power supply was 24V for the motors and 5V for the control board. Great, that shouldn&amp;#39;t be hard to find. I labeled the wires for the power supply outputs so we&amp;#39;d know where the wires were supposed to go on the new power supply when we got one. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We lacked any ticketing or record keeping system for repairs of machines that belonged to us, so I just wrote on a blank piece of paper that the machine needed a new 24V/5V power supply, and a new cord or plug (The missing ground prong was the reason the machine became live on the outside. With a ground prong, the fuse would have simply blown instead, or lower current leakage would just harmlessly go to ground) &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I worked on some other machines, did some cleaning and busy work until closing time and went home for the day. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The next day, I see the claw machine back out on the floor already. Given that both of my coworkers had a track record of disregard for electrical safety, I had little doubt it was still a shock risk. Indeed, I grabbed my voltage detector pen, poked the metal coin door with it, and found that it was live, again! They had hooked the same power supply back up again, and didn&amp;#39;t replace the plug! If they had done &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; the machine wouldn&amp;#39;t be live! But where did they get another fuse? I pulled out the original, and we didn&amp;#39;t have any in stock as far as I knew. Unless.... You guessed it, they bypassed the fuse to get the machine running again, effectively going for double Jeopardy: Now you can get shocked AND burn the store down! Of course, what else are claw machines for?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I called my boss and, since he of course didn&amp;#39;t pick up, I basically left a message saying that someone else had undone all my safety measures and put the machine back out on the floor, still unrepaired, still a shock hazard to customers who simply wanted to play the machine. This time, the machine was in a different position and I was able to safely reach the plug without pulling the breaker first. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I honestly can&amp;#39;t imagine how the idiot managed to plug it in without touching the metal parts, which would have immediately clued him in that neither I nor the customer were joking when we said it was shocking people. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now you&amp;#39;re all saying &amp;quot;cut the plug off&amp;quot; and yes, in hindsight I probably could have done that. However, I figured the boss might consider that destruction of the store&amp;#39;s property (even though that would be the first step to putting a new plug on the end of the cord) which is why I didn&amp;#39;t do that. That said, I had pretty much run out of any other options that didn&amp;#39;t involve physical violence. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After unplugging the machine, I disconnected the power supply from the inside, then plugged it back in so the lights would be on, therefore my idiot coworkers would be none the wiser until/unless they actually tried to play it, or looked at the little LED screen that was supposed to show the credits and time. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To be clear, the machine was now technically safe to touch for people. It just wouldn&amp;#39;t work with the power supply disconnected, but it wouldn&amp;#39;t shock people either.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Whoever pulled it back out was clearly fixated on having a claw machine out on the floor. Therefore, I decided to look and see if we had a power cord and power supply from another machine so we could have the claw machine working again. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I asked my coworkers if they knew of any machines that we could use for parts. They both said no. I asked if they knew of anything else that used a 24V supply. They had no idea. Well, thanks for nothing, I guess.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This was the only claw machine we had in the store, so using another one for parts (or using this one for parts to fix that one) wasn&amp;#39;t an option. I went to the back room and checked if we had any power supplies. Finding anything back there was always a chore due to the lack of organization. I found that most of them were 12 V power supplies. I didn&amp;#39;t think wiring them in series for 24V would actually work due to the capacitors in the power supply, and I&amp;#39;d hate to ruin a good power supply trying it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, I decided to take a closer look at some other machines to see if their power supplies will work. Nah, most of them are 12 volts. But, a long-deceased driving game (the motherboard quit) with a force feedback motor on the steering wheel had a 24V power supply that still worked! I put a note on the machine &amp;quot;Power supply removed for claw machine up front, PS make / model was x/y, specs were z&amp;quot; so if anyone objected, they could revert it to it&amp;#39;s original state, and if they found a replacement motherboard, they&amp;#39;d know what power supply to get. Now for the cord.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Every machine I could find back there had the ground prong missing. What the heck is it with the lack of ground prongs? Pretty much everything in the back either belonged to a customer, or appeared to be a &amp;quot;scrap&amp;quot; machine. But there was nothing I could &amp;quot;steal&amp;quot; an intact cord from, all the good ones had long since been taken to fix other machines, and none of them had been replaced. At this point I had already mentioned to the boss that we needed more cords or plugs, so I decided to not pester him about it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, I could at least half-fix the machine. With the wires already labeled, I unplugged the machine, removed the old power supply and connected the wires to the new one. I put the fuse back in, but did not connect the &amp;quot;hot&amp;quot; wire from the cord back to the new PSU, since we still needed to fix the missing ground issue. I figured if they saw the machine was &amp;quot;working&amp;quot; again, they wouldn&amp;#39;t see the need to fix the ground issue. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A few days later, I noticed someone playing the machine. At least they weren&amp;#39;t getting shocked, but out of curiosity, I looked at the cord when they were done playing. What do you know, a new plug was put on. It was even done properly, what more do you want? Other than a new pulley, where the original still had a washer glued on it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A few more days later, the inevitable happened and the washer came unglued, allowing the string to tangle up again. I asked around about what kind of glue was used, so that I could try a different kind of glue, but no one knows what was originally used. I wasn&amp;#39;t sure anything would work that well between metal and plastic. With the string tangled up, I was worried that if someone tried to play the machine, the up/down motor might burn out or the gears could strip. Therefore, I disconnected the power supply inside the machine once again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I had figured that sometime the next day, I could try super glueing the washer back on. The beginning of that day, I turned the machines on like always. I was the only one who turned them off after closing, my coworkers left them on. A few minutes later, I hear the dreaded sound of &amp;quot;capacitor popcorn&amp;quot; coming from the general direction of the claw machine. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sure enough, the claw machine was quickly filling with smoke. I unplugged it quickly and grabbed the fire extinguisher and flung the door open. There were no actual flames, so rather than actually spray, I waited to see if the smoke died down on it&amp;#39;s own. Thankfully, it did. It was coming from the motherboard and the power supply. Oh fsck.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I took a closer look and found that one of the connectors had been pulled out, but then put back in backwards. To be fair, they weren&amp;#39;t keyed which meant this was possible without the use of a hammer. However, the connectors didn&amp;#39;t need to be unplugged to begin with. I unscrewed the board and approached my coworker.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;Were you messing with the claw machine, by any chance?&amp;quot; Idiot: &amp;quot;Yeah, the machine wasn&amp;#39;t working again so I figured I could pull the connectors out and put them back in again and it would work&amp;quot; Me: &amp;quot;Well you put it in backwards&amp;quot; Idiot: &amp;quot;So? Just put it back the right way&amp;quot; Me: (Screaming internally, I put the board where it&amp;#39;s plainly visible to him, with all the burned traces, popped capacitors and chips with craters in them, all visible) &amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s destroyed. You reverse a connector or put it in the wrong hole, this is what happens. Did you not see all that smoke or hear those popping noises? If I hadn&amp;#39;t been there, it might have caused a fire.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Remember how there was no information about this machine available anywhere? Even with the manufacturer&amp;#39;s name in hand, I couldn&amp;#39;t even find a picture of it, let alone a manual. This meant that finding an entire circuit board, or even just a programmed microcontroller, would have been darn near impossible. Okay, I suppose it would be technically possible, but only to the extent that winning the lottery would also be &amp;quot;technically possible&amp;quot;. In other words, realistically, we were never going to find another motherboard for this machine. It&amp;#39;s fate was sealed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Claw machine gets a band-aid fix for the broken pulley. Later on, a deadly electrical short occurs and both my coworkers insist that it remain plugged in despite it being a death trap. I fixed the short by replacing the power supply. Someone replaced the plug, properly. But then, one of the idiots tried &amp;quot;fixing&amp;quot; the machine by reseating the connectors, but accidentally reversed it and burned out the motherboard.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/dickcheney600&quot;&gt; /u/dickcheney600 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yxbefp/makes_you_want_to_claw_your_way_to_a_new_job_part/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yxbefp/makes_you_want_to_claw_your_way_to_a_new_job_part/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yxbefp</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yxbefp/makes_you_want_to_claw_your_way_to_a_new_job_part/"><updated>2022-11-17T00:35:56+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-17T00:35:56+00:00</published><title>Makes you want to &quot;claw&quot; your way to a new job, Part 2</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/LongIslandTrooper</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/LongIslandTrooper</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I dont post alot of tales but after a conversation with a co-worker she suggested i MUST share this tale. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Picture IT. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Its 2010. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im a Network Admin at a financial institution. We were looking to move to VOIP from an OLD and i mean old PBX system. I had some VOIP experience so guess who they asked from IT to get this started. Easy guess , me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We went through a few vendors and a few demos and after a couple of months and a little coaxing we went with the Cisco solution. Fast forward we implement the solution and after a few late nights and long days all is well. I maintain the system on the network side and since i have previous experience with VOIP i learn as much as i can when comes to CUCM and UCCX (Keep UCCX in mind). Over years i take various training classes and overall be become pretty proficient in all things CUCM and UCCX. I also develop some pretty good contacts that i can lean on within Cisco for help with anything i may need some some assistance on. Keep in mind these contacts are outside of Cisco TAC.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fast forward a few years and a new VP of the Dept the Contact Center is in is assigned to head up the dept. He goes over some of the reporting and does not like the numbers. I just heard this via hearsay. My thinking is &amp;quot;I guess some changes may need to be made personell wise to achieve the numbers you want&amp;quot;. Mind you i just said this in my head, i never expressed this to anyone. It was just a thought. A couple of weeks go by and i get a call asking to attend a meeting later that day. No big deal i get to the conference room and its the VP of the Contact Center, and the Contact Center supervisors. We all exchange pleasantries and they get to meat of why they asked me here.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;VP - &amp;quot;We been looking at these reporting numbers and we don&amp;#39;t think that they are right&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me - &amp;quot; What do you think is off with the numbers&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;VP - &amp;quot;Call Center Supervisor #1, can you explain further?&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Call Center Supervisor #1 - &amp;quot;These numbers are all off. We think some of these people had to be taking more calls than this. Something must be wrong with the system &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me - &amp;quot;Let me know exactly what report you are running and i&amp;#39;ll look into it.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;They send me the name of the report and off i go into report land. The land of pulling numbers from a database and checking on its accuracy. After a couple of days of trouble shooting i&amp;#39;m really not seeing anything wrong. I note my findings via email and don&amp;#39;t hear anything back. I&amp;#39;m thinking the matter is closed but little do i know in an exective meeting its being told that the numbers are &amp;quot;way off&amp;quot; and LongIsland is wrong and does not have a clue. The system is wrong.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now i have no problem being wrong but in this case the data is the data. Just because you don&amp;#39;t like whats in the report doesn&amp;#39;t mean I or the report is wrong. Time to step this up a notch. I decided to get on the phone with a few of my contacts at Cisco. I sent them over the reports and we performed a quick webex and determined the reports were indeed legit and made sure i had their verification in Email. I scheduled a meeting with the Cisco Contacts, Contact Center VP, Supervisors and my VP to go over the findings and the meeting sort of went like this.&lt;br/&gt; After exchanging introductions. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cisco Contact - &amp;quot;So heard you are having some issues with numbers generated on this particular report.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Contact Center VP - &amp;quot;Yeah these number are way off, they cannot be right. We think there is issue with the system.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cisco Contact - LongIsland and i went over the system and the numbers thoroughly and i really dont see any issues. Usually in cases like this the customer wants the numbers to reflect what they feel they should reflect. The numbers pulled from the database are just that. They cannot be manipulated in any way. Usually when they don&amp;#39;t produce the results you want that is a personell issue not a data issue. We do have a few consultants that can help you acheive the numbers you are trying to attain. if you like i can reach out to them on your behalf.&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Silence &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me - I guess we will have to take this offline. Thanks for your help Cisco Contact. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And that was that. It was hard to keep that shit eating grin off my face and my VP knew it. I never heard about any issues with UCCX reports again. The phone menu is a diffrent matter, but that is for another time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/LongIslandTrooper&quot;&gt; /u/LongIslandTrooper &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yxd00u/dont_hate_the_data_hate_the_game/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yxd00u/dont_hate_the_data_hate_the_game/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yxd00u</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yxd00u/dont_hate_the_data_hate_the_game/"><updated>2022-11-17T01:47:09+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-17T01:47:09+00:00</published><title>&quot;Don't hate the data, hate the game&quot;</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/dickcheney600</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/dickcheney600</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this crappy gameroom store I used to work in, we had a claw machine. Ever since I had started there, the claw had been stuck: it would move forward, backward, left and right, but not up and down.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I took it upon myself to try and figure out the problem. First, I opened it up and unscrewed the cover over the &amp;quot;box&amp;quot; that held the mechanism that moved the claw up and down. One of the plastic pulleys was broken in such a way that the little string could slip off and get stuck. Indeed, the string was already tangled up every which way. Now, I hadn&amp;#39;t dealt with a claw machine before, so some kind of manual would help if I could find one. I&amp;#39;ll also need to figure out who built the thing to be able to order a part for it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now, the claw machine had a name on the &amp;quot;marquee&amp;quot; but it did not show a manufacturer&amp;#39;s name. I opened up the machine and look for any evidence of who made the thing. There is none: the machine is literally built with no-name parts. The motors, the board, the power supply, all lack any manufacturer&amp;#39;s name on them. On an unrelated note, I found a manual for a completely different machine, stuffed inside this claw machine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, the machine itself obviously wasn&amp;#39;t the best place to find the manufacturer&amp;#39;s info in this case. So I punted and just Googled (name of machine) claw machine. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, disappointingly, after going through page after page (while doing other things around the store in between) I found practically nothing pointing me in the direction of who made this thing, or even, for that matter, if the company still exists.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Later, someone found an old brochure online from a well-known arcade game manufacturer, advertising the machine. A company that was still in business! Great! So I called them up. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oops, premature celebration. It turns out that company also used to &lt;em&gt;sell&lt;/em&gt; other machines that they themselves did not make, and this was one of them. The company that actually made the machine itself had long since gone bankrupt. The support rep also didn&amp;#39;t know of any machines that shared any parts with this one. But on the other hand, I am now armed with the name of the original manufacturer, so I may not be able to order original parts, but I could probably find information about how this thing is supposed to work so that I can rethread the string properly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Armed with the name of the manufacturer, I turned to Google again. I Googled and Googled until my Googler was sore, and, for the lack of a phrase that rhymes, I found ZERO evidence that the manufacturer &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; existed or what they made.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I had tried (name with an A) and (other name with an O) in case I heard the guy wrong over the phone. I tried it as one word, and as two words. None of which yielded any additional results to even tell me which name was accurate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In short, I was back to square one.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The next time I came back to this machine, I decided to try finding parts another way. I used calipers to take measurements of the pulleys that the string wrapped around, so that I could order replacements whose measurements matched. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As I looked up claw machine parts, I was rather disconcerted to find that, out of everyone that makes or sells parts for claw machines in general, &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of them listed the specific machine(s) that the parts would fit and &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of them listed the dimensions! So my measurements weren&amp;#39;t worth a quarter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Later on, a light bulb came on over my head. Perhaps some industrial suppliers might sell pullies for other purposes that happen to match the size, or at least be close enough? After all, there&amp;#39;s nothing particularly extravagent or unusual about these pullies as far as I can tell. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I spent some time searching around industrial machine suppliers that took small-quantity orders. I decided to simply forward links to the product pages to my boss, so that he could research the actual suppliers and decide on which one was the best one to use. I also forwarded the measurements as well, in case he had another kind of machine with a similar enough part to fit, or for that matter, try to fabricate something. I also pointed out that the plug was missing the ground prong, so we would need to order more replacement plugs unless we had some somewhere that I didn&amp;#39;t know about.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for the second part of the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/dickcheney600&quot;&gt; /u/dickcheney600 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ywx4zm/makes_you_want_to_claw_your_way_to_a_new_job_part/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ywx4zm/makes_you_want_to_claw_your_way_to_a_new_job_part/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_ywx4zm</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ywx4zm/makes_you_want_to_claw_your_way_to_a_new_job_part/"><updated>2022-11-16T15:52:51+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-16T15:52:51+00:00</published><title>Makes you want to &quot;claw&quot; your way to a new job, Part 1</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/SonOfAQuiche</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/SonOfAQuiche</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;So this one is fairly short, but I was absolutely in awe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I work as second line support for a big multinational. Not going into further detail, because of reasons. I also have additional duties regarding tech support of meetings and other events involving MS Teams and a multitude of other tools. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago I received a long e-mail chain regarding an online meeting between sites in around a dozen different countries including mine. I read through the entire chain and it boiled down to: the meeting itself always works fine, but for some reason we always have issues with the Q&amp;amp;A. One site has issues accessing it. It was never mentioned which site.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I contacted the person, who sent it to me:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dear User,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Could you please elaborate on the issues this site is facing? We use this tool every day on site and it never appears to make problems.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Best Regards,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Quiche&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;User then replied:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dear Quiche,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The participants in question are situated in Iran and they have difficulty accessing the Q&amp;amp;A. It is probably due to the sanctions from the US against Iran. Do you know any way we can bypass them?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kind regards,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;User&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I sat there at my desk, comprehending what was asked of me. My eyelids opening and closing by themselves, probably spelling out The Hague in Morse Code or something. My internal monologue went something like &amp;quot;sure thang just let me hit up old Joey and deal with this Malarkey right away. Might solve the FUCKING MIDDLE EAST CRISIS, while were at it amirite?&amp;quot; &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I am not sure on what lists I just ended up on just being involved in an e-mail exchange with the words &amp;#39;bypass US-sanctions&amp;#39; in it. I will try to avoid visiting the US for a good while until I need my prostate checked by the TSA.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I replied to user:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dear User,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Please consider using [other common tool]. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Best regards,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Quiche&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/SonOfAQuiche&quot;&gt; /u/SonOfAQuiche &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yw4c9j/can_you_help_me_bypass_those_pesky_ussanctions/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yw4c9j/can_you_help_me_bypass_those_pesky_ussanctions/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yw4c9j</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yw4c9j/can_you_help_me_bypass_those_pesky_ussanctions/"><updated>2022-11-15T17:45:11+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-15T17:45:11+00:00</published><title>&quot;Can you help me bypass those pesky US-sanctions?&quot;</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/mattthepianoman</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/mattthepianoman</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got a call from one of our younger engineers today complaining that their shiny new 3D printer wasn&amp;#39;t talking to their workstation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;Okay, what&amp;#39;s the message you&amp;#39;re getting when you try to connect?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eng: &amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s saying that the C O M port&amp;quot; (pronouncing it See Oh Emm) &amp;quot;is not responding. What&amp;#39;s a C O M port? It&amp;#39;s plugged into the front USB&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;Oh, er, right&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;(scratching my head while trying to remember the last time I had to configure a serial port on Windows while also feeling old)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;do you know what baud rate the printer is expecting?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eng: &amp;quot;is that like the rate of extrusion?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;...I think it&amp;#39;d be easier if I come down there and take a look&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Took a walk down, set the serial port to 115200 baud 8N1 with no flow control and the printer responded. Lucky guess.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/mattthepianoman&quot;&gt; /u/mattthepianoman &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvdm8a/whats_a_com_port/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvdm8a/whats_a_com_port/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yvdm8a</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvdm8a/whats_a_com_port/"><updated>2022-11-14T21:44:22+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-14T21:44:22+00:00</published><title>&quot;What's a C-O-M port?&quot;</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/pyroguyFTW</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/pyroguyFTW</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;User: So how did we get here? What do I do next time to prevent this?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Analyst: Nothing to worry about! It was just a frozen session, it just happens sometimes. There&amp;#39;s nothing you can do to prevent it. Sometimes the server just freezes like that.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;User: But my space heater has been running all morning, and my computer is hot!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s that time, folks. For my hardware peeps, I&amp;#39;m sorry for you guys who service enclosed cubes with desktops on the floor and end users who are able to smuggle in space heaters. You know what&amp;#39;s coming.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/pyroguyFTW&quot;&gt; /u/pyroguyFTW &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvipj3/its_winter_my_peoples/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvipj3/its_winter_my_peoples/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yvipj3</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvipj3/its_winter_my_peoples/"><updated>2022-11-15T01:18:23+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-15T01:18:23+00:00</published><title>It's winter my peoples.</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/darkhelmet46</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/darkhelmet46</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note: This story is real. In accordance with the rules, the names of the people and businesses involved have been changed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This story goes back to the early 2000&amp;#39;s. I was working for an IT support company located in the city of New Bedford, Massachusetts. New Bedford has a rich fishing history and was once considered to be &amp;quot;the whaling capital of the world&amp;quot;. In fact, the story of &amp;quot;Moby Dick&amp;quot; takes place in this very city. However, at the time this story takes place, New Bedford would more accurately be described as &amp;quot;the Mos Eisley of Massachusetts&amp;quot; - you would never find a more wretched hive of sum and villainy. Especially on the waterfront.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The fishing industry being the main center of commerce for New Bedford, many of our clients were in this line of business. One client in particular, Stormy Seas Fisheries, is at the center of this story. Stormy Seas was a good client. They were easy to deal with, paid their bills, rarely complained, and were not too demanding. We enjoyed supporting them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One day I walked into the office and the owner of the IT company, his wife, and several employees, were standing around talking with concerned looks on their faces. There was a story in one of the local newspapers which reported Stormy Seas was the victim of a literal &amp;quot;hostile takeover&amp;quot; where a man named James Greco literally held a gun to the owner&amp;#39;s face and informed him he would be taking over. We came to learn that James was a major figure of organized crime in the area.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The discussion was about what to do about the situation. As I said, Stormy Seas was a great client and we&amp;#39;d hate to lose them. After some deliberation the decision was made to keep them on and just see how it goes. So we did, and things went along just as before. We&amp;#39;d show up onsite, the same people were there, no weird vibes, no red flags, no sign of this mysterious organized crime figure. Stormy Seas continued to pay their bills no questions asked and we happily continued supporting them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This went along for several months, and honestly most of us had forgotten all about the whole hostile takeover bit because as I said, no weirdness came out of it. Then one day we got a call from a woman we had never heard of but who claimed to work for Stormy Seas Fisheries and was reporting a problem with the internet connection at their house and asked if we could urgently send someone by. We weren&amp;#39;t really in the business of doing residential work, but since Stormy Seas was such a good client we figured we&amp;#39;d do them a favor and send someone. That someone ended up being me. Me, a young and nave 20-something with too much innocence and zeal for his own good. So I drove out to the address in a wealthy part of a neighboring town. As I pulled up to the house I drove past a Ford Explorer SUV with dark tinted windows and bristling with antennas sitting on the side of the road near the end of the driveway. I thought that was odd but I paid it no mind as I pulled into the driveway and arrived at what locals would have described as a &amp;quot;Portuguese Palace&amp;quot;. Those familiar with the area would know what I mean. An expansive front lawn lined by a wrought iron fence, a long gravel driveway leading to an ornate concrete staircase with concrete lion gargoyles on either side, terminating at a large house with a brick and stucco finish and a gigantic wooden door.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I strolled up to the door and rang the bell. It opened, and I was suddenly faced with what could best be described as a human grizzly bear who dwarfed my wiry 5&amp;#39;11&amp;quot; frame. A large, imposing man who looked like he hadn&amp;#39;t shaved or changed clothes in about a week. Taken aback, I looked up at the man, held out my hand and sheepishly said &amp;quot;Hi, I&amp;#39;m Dark Helmet, I&amp;#39;m here to fix the computer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The man smiled, gripped my hand with his giant meat paw and said &amp;quot;Hey, nice to meet you! Jimmy Greco!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I felt my entire body tense up. I tried to maintain my composure but I&amp;#39;m pretty certain my eyeballs were bulging out of my head as I remembered the newspaper story as an image of this man stalking into the office of Stormy Seas Fisheries and holding a gun to the owner&amp;#39;s head flashed before my eyes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I think I blacked out a bit because the next memory I have is of me in the living room sitting at the computer at a desk in the corner, pecking away, while Jimmy sat on the couch to my left. I glanced over at him and I noticed a bulge under one of his pant legs near the ankle. An ankle bracelet, I realized. Suddenly it all came together. Jimmy&amp;#39;s disheveled appearance. The unmarked SUV watching the house. The urgent need to repair the internet. This man was under house arrest! I would later learn the SUV belonged to the FBI.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So Jimmy was sitting there just jabbering my ear off with small talk. He seemed almost giddy to have someone new to talk to. By the way, you have to imagine his voice in the stereotypical baritone NY City gangster accent you hear in movies, because that&amp;#39;s exactly what he sounded like.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;So anyways, what&amp;#39;d you say your name was again kid?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I replied nervously, &amp;quot;Dark Helmet&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jimmy leaned back and pensively said, &amp;quot;Helmet Helmet I know a few Helmet&amp;#39;s&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: &amp;quot;Yeah, well I know my uncle Bill is friends with Chris.&amp;quot; (Chris was another guy who worked at Stormy Seas, and my uncle was notorious for having friends in low places.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jimmy cocked his head to the side in thought as he pondered. &amp;quot;Hmmm Helmet Billy Helmet Hey, didn&amp;#39;t he have a twin brother?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Not really sure where this was going I replied, &amp;quot;Yeah, Tom. That&amp;#39;s my dad.&amp;quot; (They are identical twins.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jimmy&amp;#39;s eyes narrowed as he leaned forward towards me, gesturing with his index finger at me as he spoke. Sort of jabbing at the air towards me with his finger.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yeah, Tom Helmet! TOM HELMET!&amp;quot; He said excitedly, his eyes gleaming. &amp;quot;You know, I was in Walpole once. He was one of my CO&amp;#39;s!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Walpole was a prison. CO stands for Corrections Officer. Prison guard in layman&amp;#39;s terms. Yes, my dad worked there.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I froze and just stared blankly at the screen in front of me as I felt the blood drain away from my face. &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m dead. I am never leaving this house alive. I&amp;#39;m going to be killed and dismembered and buried in this man&amp;#39;s back yard.&amp;quot; These thoughts raced through my head as I tried to judge my ability to spring from my chair and dash out the door before Jimmy had time to leap from the couch and tackle me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Then, the unexpected happened. Jimmy relaxed and leaned back as his face brightened and he said, &amp;quot;You know, he was a REALLY nice guy!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m pretty sure I visibly breathed a sigh of relief and relaxed as I felt the color return to my face. Jimmy went on and regaled me of stories of my father&amp;#39;s kindness while he was imprisoned in Walpole. Come to find out, my dad was the night kitchen officer. Some inmates who had certain dietary needs or medical conditions were allowed a carton of milk in their cell after hours. Jimmy at the time was a young 18 year old kid. My dad took pity on him and would bring him any extra milk he had, even though Jimmy technically wasn&amp;#39;t allowed to have it in his cell.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I still had work to do and Jimmy was still talkative so the banter continued.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;So, you got any brothers or sisters?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes, I have a younger sister.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh, and what does she do for work?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;She&amp;#39;s a massage therapist.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh, yeah? Massage Therapy, that&amp;#39;s nice! You know, last year for Christmas the guys from the office got me one of those you know &amp;quot;massage a month&amp;quot; type deals. Dumb [expletive] only showed up three times and stopped coming. I oughta send someone out to bust her knee caps. Hey, you should give me your sister&amp;#39;s number!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yeah uh I&amp;#39;ll uh give it to Chris and he can give it to you.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Thanks, kid!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Spoiler: I didn&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is where our story concludes. I have absolutely no recollection of what the actual problem was with the computer or internet connection. I do remember texting my dad on the way down the driveway something like &amp;quot;Hi dad, Jimmy Greco says hi and thanks for the milk!&amp;quot; and I waved to the FBI folks as I drove past. My license plate number and description of my vehicle is probably enshrined in an FBI file in Boston somewhere. That was the last time we ever saw or heard from Jimmy Greco. Shortly after these events he was tried and convicted, but he was released from prison in 2011.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/darkhelmet46&quot;&gt; /u/darkhelmet46 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yv70bb/that_time_i_thought_id_be_dismembered_by_a_mob/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yv70bb/that_time_i_thought_id_be_dismembered_by_a_mob/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yv70bb</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yv70bb/that_time_i_thought_id_be_dismembered_by_a_mob/"><updated>2022-11-14T17:51:25+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-14T17:51:25+00:00</published><title>That time I thought I'd be dismembered by a mob boss</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/dickcheney600</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/dickcheney600</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I worked at a company that made 110VAC and 220VAC motors, all of which had some degree of control intelligence built into them. Some of them only had a soft-start routine along with current protection (so if something stopped the motor from turning, it wouldn&amp;#39;t burn out) but others allowed an input from an external system to control them. The soft start ability would save energy in the long run for things that had to cycle on and off a lot.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The previous owners of the building also had the need to test certain things on 220VAC as well. How did they do this? No, of course they didn&amp;#39;t use a proper outlet into which only 220VAC plugs would fit. They wired a regular 110VAC outlet to be 220VAC instead. You can probably guess where this is going.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So as I understand it, they wanted to use the power strip as a convenient switch for their motor. The power strip they chose was also a surge protector, which by definition does something to prevent an excessive voltage from reaching devices plugged into it. There are power strips that are JUST power strips, and we had several of those, which didn&amp;#39;t give a hoot about the input voltage. Surge protectors, on the other hand, &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; react to an overvoltage, by definition.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I was working on something else when my coworker brought me the surge protector. He admitted that he hooked it up to 220 and it went &amp;quot;pop&amp;quot; and didn&amp;#39;t work anymore. I set it aside, and kept at my current project until I was done with it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Later on, I had nothing better to do, so I decide to take apart the surge protector, assuming there&amp;#39;s any way to do so non-destructively in the first place. And indeed, there was. It wasn&amp;#39;t designed intentionally to &lt;em&gt;prevent&lt;/em&gt; repairs, but it wasn&amp;#39;t designed with repairs in mind, either. I&amp;#39;ll leave it at that. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I was looking for a fuse, but before I even found it, I saw the problem. The traces that once carried the input power were &lt;em&gt;gone&lt;/em&gt; and the surface of the board itself has two big burn marks where the traces used to be. There actually &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; a thermal fuse next to the MOVs, as well as a circuit breaker which was part of the switch. Both of which did diddly squat. I&amp;#39;ll explain in a comment how (most) surge protectors work.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I showed my coworker the burned up board, and he thankfully didn&amp;#39;t try to get me to &amp;quot;fix&amp;quot; it. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;TL;DR: electrical codes exist for a reason. A 110V outlet wired for 220V is a recipe for disaster&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/dickcheney600&quot;&gt; /u/dickcheney600 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvguwt/in_case_of_stupid_wiring_break_device/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvguwt/in_case_of_stupid_wiring_break_device/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yvguwt</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yvguwt/in_case_of_stupid_wiring_break_device/"><updated>2022-11-14T23:56:04+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-14T23:56:04+00:00</published><title>In case of stupid wiring, break device</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Active-Vermicelli-31</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Active-Vermicelli-31</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I useed to work for an ISP in the NOC, monitoring its national and international networks. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I had been there for a few months when winter hits, and we notice a edge node going offline for a week, comming back up for a while and then going offline again. This happens multiple times that winter, and we just follow protocol and alert the nearest technician. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So one stormy winter night my curiosity got the better of me when reporting yet again that said node was down. I asked what is it with this node?&lt;br/&gt; I then got the surprising answer that this node was located on a small island of &amp;gt;100ppl, poorly placed on the docks, so that when the winter storms hit the waves would spray over it, and the seaspray would then cause a ground fault tripping the GFI. All that was needed was for the tech to travel the few hours by boat, and reset the GFI.....&lt;br/&gt; Moving that node just a bit up the road, away from the water would fix the issue. Should have been raised as an issue in planning the node!&lt;br/&gt; This is what happens when engineers and designers does not work on fixing things.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Active-Vermicelli-31&quot;&gt; /u/Active-Vermicelli-31 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yv56ym/node_down/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yv56ym/node_down/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yv56ym</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yv56ym/node_down/"><updated>2022-11-14T16:51:28+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-14T16:51:28+00:00</published><title>Node down!</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/WandiWasTaken</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/WandiWasTaken</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our User calls the internal Help Desk because of lacking permissions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Help Desk creates a ticket and sends it to an external help desk for the required permission.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Our Help Desk explains the Issue in the first Service Unit of the Incident Ticket.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;All fine until now. But.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The external guy in the second Service Unit comments &amp;quot;Closed&amp;quot; &amp;amp; sends it back to our ServiceDesk.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Our ServiceDesk asks &amp;quot;What do you mean &amp;#39;closed&amp;#39;, please elaborate.&amp;quot; in Service Unit 3 and sends it back to the external help desk.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In Service Unit 4 *the same guy from the second service unit* sends it to us, our third-level support, and asks what is meant by the comment &amp;quot;closed&amp;quot; from the second service unit.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I hope that guy is not actually that daft and is only recovering from the weekend.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/WandiWasTaken&quot;&gt; /u/WandiWasTaken &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yus2jv/monday_morning_shannigans/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yus2jv/monday_morning_shannigans/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yus2jv</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yus2jv/monday_morning_shannigans/"><updated>2022-11-14T07:33:39+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-14T07:33:39+00:00</published><title>monday morning shannigans</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Far-Ad1423</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Far-Ad1423</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is one of those times I asked myself &amp;quot;why do I have to deal with this sh*t! Why me always??&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A caller calls in &amp;quot;My mouse is not working. I&amp;#39;m trying to close a document and I point at the red x and hit enter but nothing is happening&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: *mutes the mic, shouts a few profanities until I feel better. &amp;quot;Ok I can help you with this&amp;quot;. I ask a couple of triage questions then ask caller to unplug their mouse. At this point in already know it&amp;#39;s user error but I have to follow triage or else QA will rain upon me like a hailstorm.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Let&amp;#39;s unplug the mouse then use your touchpad&amp;quot; Surprisingly, caller knows what a touchpad is, or do they..?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caller: I&amp;#39;ve done that but now I can&amp;#39;t use my mouse at all&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: that&amp;#39;s because we unplugged the mouse now we have to use the touchpad&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caller: same thing, I hit enter but it doesn&amp;#39;t close&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me:*educates the caller on the use of right and left click.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Caller: oh wow I didn&amp;#39;t know you could do that!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I go on to point out the similarities between a touchpad and a mouse, plug mouse back in and voila, it&amp;#39;s working again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I was left wondering how they finessed their way through the interview process and landed a job that requires daily use of a computer!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Far-Ad1423&quot;&gt; /u/Far-Ad1423 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yshqcf/how_did_you_even_get_hired_if_you_dont_know_how/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yshqcf/how_did_you_even_get_hired_if_you_dont_know_how/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yshqcf</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yshqcf/how_did_you_even_get_hired_if_you_dont_know_how/"><updated>2022-11-11T17:54:56+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-11T17:54:56+00:00</published><title>How did you even get hired if you don't know how to use a mouse?</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/mattthepianoman</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/mattthepianoman</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m a sysadmin/database admin/developer (jack of all trades, master of none) for a small company that recently took on a few developers to build and maintain company-specific applications.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We were getting a HUGE number of SSH login attempts to our main application server from bots originating mainly from Russia and the Far East. Obviously the root account is locked down tight, but the big bosses wanted us to do something, so I suggested login rate limiting and IP banning for repeat offenders. We had the usual meeting that could have been an email to decide on the specifics, and we settled on 5 failed attempts in 10 minutes resulting in a roughly 2 hour IP ban, which increased exponentially for each subsequent string of failed attempts within a certain time period. For obvious reasons we white listed various important IPs so that we couldn&amp;#39;t lock ourselves out.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I tested a couple of solutions before settling on one, and before pulling the trigger we had another meeting to make sure that everyone could log in and knew their passwords, and that everyone had their main WFH machines set up using key-based login. We also unofficially agreed that the first dumbass to lock themselves out would have to buy the person who had to unblock their IP a bottle of spirit of their choice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The new policy went live at 4pm yesterday. At 8:30pm I get a phone call from one of our senior developers asking what bottle I wanted. He had left his WFH machine at home and had used his personal laptop to try to SSH in, but without specifying a username so it defaulted to his local machine&amp;#39;s username. It only took 4 and a half hours before I had to perform my first unban.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Looks like I&amp;#39;ll be enjoying a bottle of rum this weekend. Cheers!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/mattthepianoman&quot;&gt; /u/mattthepianoman &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ys41pg/just_so_were_clear_you_do_all_know_your_passwords/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ys41pg/just_so_were_clear_you_do_all_know_your_passwords/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_ys41pg</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ys41pg/just_so_were_clear_you_do_all_know_your_passwords/"><updated>2022-11-11T07:24:33+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-11T07:24:33+00:00</published><title>Just so we're clear - you do all know your passwords, right?</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/L3veLUP</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/L3veLUP</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I work in a family run it support shop for private and business customers (around 500 users) and some of our support contracts involve health check-ups on PC&amp;#39;s remotely. I&amp;#39;ve only been here for a few months&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Usually these consist of running Windows updates, Office updates and generally basic hygiene of a PC. We took on a new client under one of these support contracts which means we usually try to remote on the 2nd week of the month. On the day I contacted the user to leave their machine&amp;#39;s on so we can remote on trigger the updates, save work and restart however come 4:10pm (they all leave the office at 4) the machines were not showing as online on our dashboard. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I give the client a call. &amp;quot;oh yeah we put our machines to sleep&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Cue head desk.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Edit: a word&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/L3veLUP&quot;&gt; /u/L3veLUP &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yrckgt/asleep_is_not_on/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yrckgt/asleep_is_not_on/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yrckgt</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yrckgt/asleep_is_not_on/"><updated>2022-11-10T11:50:06+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-10T11:50:06+00:00</published><title>Asleep is not on</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/DrHugh</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/DrHugh</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I lead a corporate IT team that supports a particular kind of platform; back in the day, these were first called PDM systems, for Product Data Management, as they worked like electronic libraries where people could only check-out files if they were checked in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Our ticketing system for user support has groups for the different teams. We have a &amp;quot;Corporate PDM&amp;quot; group for our team&amp;#39;s stuff. If any other organization at the company needs to assign a ticket to us, they just put it in the &amp;quot;Corporate PDM&amp;quot; group and we get notified of it. There is even a document in the ticketing system, so if you search for &amp;quot;PDM&amp;quot; then this document comes up and says, &amp;quot;Assign to the &amp;#39;Corporate PDM&amp;#39; group.&amp;quot; We can see on a ticket if someone searched for such a ticketing system document and indicated it was the solution.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Our corporation acquired another company a few years back. One thing that Old Company -- let&amp;#39;s call them OLDco -- had in-progress was an attempt to put a PDM system in place.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At first, it sounded like our PDM group would have to provide support to the users of this other PDM system, but our management wanted it kept separate from our &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; tickets. So we created a new group in the ticketing system, called &amp;quot;Corporate PDM - OLDco&amp;quot; to be distinctive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After having done that, and after the folks at that acquired company saw our PDM system, they decided to abandon their project. We never used the group, and we dropped members from it, so no one got notifications about it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Our mistake was in not requesting deletion of the &amp;quot;Corporate PDM - OLDco&amp;quot; group at that time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Every so often, the ticketing system people see this unused group and decide to harvest it. They ask me, and I say to go ahead. Then they come back and say they can&amp;#39;t, there&amp;#39;s a ticket in it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lo and behold, they are right. Such tickets are put in by folks in IT helpdesks in other countries. We all use the same ticketing system, but apparently they hear that someone was once part of OLDco, so they look for groups with OLDco in the name to assign the ticket. It is important to understand that there are no ticketing system help documents that tell anyone to use the &amp;quot;Corporate PDM - OLDco&amp;quot; group. Not one. So these other helpdesk people are not following proper procedure in assigning tickets.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, I take the tickets (which are weeks or months old at that point), reassign them to the proper group, ask the IT agent who assigned them to the wrong place why they did it, and to update whatever documentation they are using, because they shouldn&amp;#39;t do this again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But the next time a harvest cycle comes around, the same problem crops up with someone else who put a ticket in there. It&amp;#39;s like playing whack-a-mole with a game that&amp;#39;s been put in storage, but someone won&amp;#39;t unplug it while a mole is sticking up, and they won&amp;#39;t let the person who whacks the mole do the unplugging.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It feels like I&amp;#39;ve been doing this every quarter of the last two years. Today, I got ahold of someone who is involved in the harvest process, and he says they will expedite the harvest, hopefully it will happen tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m keeping my fingers crossed, but I am not holding my breath.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/DrHugh&quot;&gt; /u/DrHugh &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yri789/harvest_dont_harvest_harvest_dont_harvest/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yri789/harvest_dont_harvest_harvest_dont_harvest/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yri789</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yri789/harvest_dont_harvest_harvest_dont_harvest/"><updated>2022-11-10T15:22:42+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-10T15:22:42+00:00</published><title>Harvest. Don't harvest! Harvest. Don't harvest!</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/CroMignonMan</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/CroMignonMan</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A recent security camera post reminded me of an issue I ran into with my mother-in-law&amp;#39;s home business security cameras a few years ago:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Every time the power went out her system would not be accessible from the network when it came back up, you could only reach the cameras by connecting a monitor to the local device. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;She would call the installer and they would come out and fix it &amp;#39;under warranty&amp;#39;. When the warranty ran out she did not want to pay them so asked me to take a look.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thankfully she had all of the password information. When I got on the device&amp;#39;s interface I saw a few odd things, including that it was enabled as a DHCP server and had its MTU set to a negative number (!?). The one that really caught my eye was the IP address it had assigned. It was something like:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;805.400.1.50&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I have no idea where that came from, and presume some sort of corrupted firmware. I did check, however, and the fields allowed you to enter any three digits instead of limiting it to 0-255. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Changing that to the correct local IP address (which I was able to determine based on her router&amp;#39;s port forwarding settings), and adjusting the MTU and a few other things fixed it, but we had to do that each time the power blipped. I wrote her up a complete set of steps to follow which she has now given to her neighbor so he can come over when the power drops and get it back online.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;(I guess the IP address issue was somewhat helpful in that the machine coming up as a DHCP server AND actually being on the network could have caused even more mysterious problems!)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/CroMignonMan&quot;&gt; /u/CroMignonMan &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yqoi8a/this_one_goes_way_past_11/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yqoi8a/this_one_goes_way_past_11/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yqoi8a</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yqoi8a/this_one_goes_way_past_11/"><updated>2022-11-09T16:54:34+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-09T16:54:34+00:00</published><title>This one goes way past 11</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/iamdisasta</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/iamdisasta</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;So...this is a story you won&amp;#39;t believe to be true because its not only stupid or unbelievable, it&amp;#39;s insane ... but it happened...&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We care for about 4000 Users and do the tech support. Software, Hardware... everything that keeps your systems running.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So one day (COV19 and homeoffice has been newly implemented) a User calls and demands a technician at her home office, 400 km away. Because her external display won&amp;#39;t work.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;-Your external display - does it give you a backlight?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*NO! I demand a technician here! My Displays does not work!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;-ok, your monitors and your laptop are connected to the same technician power distributor?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*YES! But why...I DEMAND A TECHNICAN HERE!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;- that will be about  500,- if we see it isn&amp;#39;t our fault...and as I see it isn&amp;#39;t as I can&amp;#39;t even reach your laptop....&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*ok, what should I do?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;- try anoter power supply&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*yeah, doesn&amp;#39;t work as well, so just send me an technician....&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;-sigh .... which room are you in?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*at the livin room, why?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;-turn your light switch on&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*I don&amp;#39;t need my lights on! I need to work with that external monitor!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;-turn them on!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*yeah, got it-&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;so....you turned your light switch on?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;-yes-&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;did the lights go on?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*NO!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;-ok, walk into the kitchen&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*WHAT THE HELL I DO IN KITCHEN?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;- open your refrigerador. does the light goes on?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*NO!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m afraid your power is off...&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*oh....but why would my Laptop would even work if there is no power? Could you fucking riddle me this?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;-----Batterie, have a nice day.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As soon as she had power again her displays wohl have been turned on again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*edit for readability&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/iamdisasta&quot;&gt; /u/iamdisasta &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yq7u7j/powerless_but_complaintmess/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yq7u7j/powerless_but_complaintmess/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yq7u7j</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yq7u7j/powerless_but_complaintmess/"><updated>2022-11-09T03:54:27+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-09T03:54:27+00:00</published><title>Powerless but complaintmess</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Scorpious187</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Scorpious187</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yesterday (Monday) I came to the office, and for some reason, most of our phones were down. I did troubleshooting on them, called the company, they said it looks like the phones are dead. Ordered new phones.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Today I get to the office early, and nothing is working. No phones, no computers, nothing can connect to the internet. I&amp;#39;m like, what the hell is going on...&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Last Friday we had a bunch of storms roll through and knock out power for a few minutes, on and off. Yesterday I was thinking that maybe the power outage blew up the phones somehow, &amp;#39;cause some of them were still working. But then I plugged in a spare phone that was new in the box to test it... dead.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;angry IT Guy noises&lt;/em&gt;*&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Then today nothing would connect at all. I&amp;#39;m thinking &amp;quot;Did the storms blow out my network switch somehow?&amp;quot; Except there were three devices in the building that still had connectivity throughout all this, and they were all connected to the switch with all the other devices that were failing. And some of the devices that weren&amp;#39;t working earlier started working for a bit, and then stopped again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Now I&amp;#39;m even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; confused.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Then I logged onto the one computer that could still connect, and went back to my training: I ran ipconfig. Checked all the settings, everything looked right. I checked all the settings on another computer that couldn&amp;#39;t connect, and the Default Gateway was wrong. I&amp;#39;m like, &amp;quot;why do these two have different Default Gateways... how the hell did that happen...&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And then I realized what the IP address it was pointing to was:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The security camera DVR.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Tuesday of last week, the security camera company came in and put in a new DVR. For reasons I don&amp;#39;t understand, even though they knew the old camera DVR was on my main network and all the cameras they were setting up were analog cameras directly connected to the DVR... they set it up as a DHCP server. So when Friday rolled around and the storms knocked out our power, everything started getting its IP addresses from the DVR instead of my network&amp;#39;s DHCP server.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Went into the DVR settings to confirm... sure enough, they had its DHCP server turned on. Turned that off, rebooted my network switches, and everything went back to normal.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s Tuesday and I already feel like I&amp;#39;ve worked a full week.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Edit: Couple points...&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;First of all, the reason these aren&amp;#39;t on a separate VLAN is they&amp;#39;re old-school analog cameras that are wired to the DVR over coax, not IP cameras. When the original installation was put in, VLANs and digital IP cameras didn&amp;#39;t even exist. That&amp;#39;s what I&amp;#39;m workin&amp;#39; with here. Our company is small and we can&amp;#39;t afford all this new-fangled &amp;quot;technology&amp;quot; like cameras from this century and whatnot (trust me, I tried, the purchase got denied)... so cut me some slack here. :P&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Second: Yes I cancelled the phone order. :D&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Scorpious187&quot;&gt; /u/Scorpious187 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypskyb/just_your_average_network_failures_for_no/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypskyb/just_your_average_network_failures_for_no/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_ypskyb</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypskyb/just_your_average_network_failures_for_no/"><updated>2022-11-08T17:19:40+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-08T17:19:40+00:00</published><title>Just your average network failures for no apparent reason</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Loxtus</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Loxtus</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;When i entered the First Level Support in our company, I was a career changer and fairly new to tech stuff. (6 years ago)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, the following call happened on one of my first days there:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;User:&amp;quot;Hello, my keyboard doesn&amp;#39;t work&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me:&amp;quot;Ok, like, what does or does it not do?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;User:&amp;quot;So, when i press F it does H, when i press P it does 7 and other weird things&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So newby me had no actual idea what was going on and to cover up my insecurity i laughingly said:&amp;quot;Did you by ANY CHANCE pour coffee on your keyboard this morning?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Silence. Like, DEAD silence. After a while, the user whispered, with fear in her voice:&amp;quot;How did you know????&amp;quot;She was actually scared.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from this call, like never trust users.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And this is fellow techies, how i lost my tech-support-virginity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Loxtus&quot;&gt; /u/Loxtus &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypuucf/how_i_lost_my_techsupportvirginity/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypuucf/how_i_lost_my_techsupportvirginity/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_ypuucf</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypuucf/how_i_lost_my_techsupportvirginity/"><updated>2022-11-08T18:45:09+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-08T18:45:09+00:00</published><title>How i lost my tech-support-virginity</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/maitreg</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/maitreg</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;During my first few months of a new tech support job I took years ago, I had one particular user who&amp;#39;d been in the company more than 20 years, and for 6 consecutive Monday mornings she left me a voice-mail before I got to work about her mouse not working. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On the first 3, she fixed it herself before I got to the office so I never confirmed what the problem was. On the 4th one I got there and went straight to her office.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;So your mouse isn&amp;#39;t working again?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yeah! I don&amp;#39;t know why it keeps doing it. But every time I plug my laptop back in after taking it home the mouse won&amp;#39;t work. I usually just unplug it and back a few times and it starts working on its own.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Oh that&amp;#39;s weird!&amp;quot; I said to her even though I suspected she just wasn&amp;#39;t waiting for the USB driver to load on startup.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Yes! And it&amp;#39;s doing it again today!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So I took a look at the mouse, followed the cord around, and found the USB plugged snugly into the RJ45 port. (Little did I know they were the same width)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I explained nicely to her that the mouse needed to be plugged into the USB port on the other side. A week went by.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Monday morning, same user, same voice-mail, same problem, same solution.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And then it happened AGAIN. From what I could tell she had plugged her USB mouse into her ethernet port on 6 consecutive Monday mornings before she figured out what she was doing wrong.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/maitreg&quot;&gt; /u/maitreg &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypwrtu/my_mouse_doesnt_work/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypwrtu/my_mouse_doesnt_work/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_ypwrtu</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ypwrtu/my_mouse_doesnt_work/"><updated>2022-11-08T19:59:18+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-08T19:59:18+00:00</published><title>My mouse doesn't work</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/SubstantialTerm3843</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/SubstantialTerm3843</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A story from my next job after I moved on from MyBoss. Its another small business, my job isnt actually IT support but of course Im the one providing it. Its 2011 by now.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;NextBoss has a requirement for computers for a one time job in another city but with the plan to expand so the resources can be used for further odd jobs away from our main site. He wants portable and simple to set up, so about a dozen laptops.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;NextBoss: Problem is we need to meet the documented performance requirement that a 5400RPM 2.5 hard drive wont give us, but to go with SSDs takes us way over budget. They only come in laptops on the high end. We dont need that high a spec for CPU and RAM but you cant get entry or mid level laptops with SSDs&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Neurons fire with the brilliance of Creation itself. Across synapses a universe is born, erupts into being with the rage and violence of the First Thought, I AM. The laws of physics are written in the cosmic forge, order begins its rule and the order is Chaos. Everything and all is fire beyond fire.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The birth scream of reality itself soothes. It cools and hardens, forms mass. The dust settles. The dust attracts, dust to dust.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The First Life. The First Death. The first consumption of another life to sustain life, the first blood meal. The First Kill.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alamahen urges his tamed beasts to hurry. The sun has set but the sky is lit, war has come to the valley. Fire beyond the hills, and howling. Always war, endless war. He must keep moving.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Valaceran stands accused. His heresy exposed, his books burnt and instruments smashed at his feet. He is sentenced to the flame. The Ultimate Judgement awaits you in the afterlife!!. No, he smiles as the crowd harasses him with curses and stones. The executioner throws the torch No, it does not.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Karalenlin steps out into the void. Hers are the first eyes to look down upon her home from above, so fragile and bright in the aching darkness. If only they could see, she wails. Powerless, hopeless. Weightless. If only they could see.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sacaranan gives the order. JUMP! Spacetime kneels at the heel of the experimental vessel. Vast distances fold and touch. The technology works! To travel, NO! Not moved, but exchanged between points across the expanse in an instant! This will give their masters the decisive weapon against the enemy, victory is assured!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Menistahen gazes down in sombre anticipation. Quiet falls upon the audience chamber, crushing grinding breathless panicked silence. Finally, There can be no doubt?. No, Most Excellent Majesty. There is no error, it is confirmed. Sobbing, Every result from across the seven galaxies concludes the same. We live in an illusion, a simulation. Reality, the entire universe is a construct. Some sort of.. process. A kind of exercise. Everything we are, everything we do, is to achieve some sort of calculation? We do not exist in the concrete sense, we are the reflections and shadows of holograms. Without any substance whatsoever. The Eternal Emperor breaks from his being held bound dumbstruck. His first thought, his first words. His squealed begging despair. Then why do we fight? Why have we waged.. What was it all for??&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Talahansen takes a moment. The first moment, they realise, only for themself. The first breaths, the first heartbeats not given in service, for the cause. They deserve a moment, do they not? Just a tiny share of time only for them and them alone. Why not? It doesnt mean anything anyway. It isnt real, nothing is. Nothing IS. All that war that never was. The moment passes. They plead, to no one but for the sake of pleading. If none of it was real, if none of us were real, if we were all nothing but the ghosts of interpretations, echoes of whispered suggestion.. Please let us become something. Please let us take any kind of form. Please let us BE. If it takes the death of a universe to end the madness, end the chaos, let it materialise. Let it matter. Let us transcend into something. Even if its still not real. Even if its still not tangible or measurable. Please let me be something. Please let me become a force, an influence. They place their hand on the activation control of the device. Please let me be an expression. Or a choice. Or a determination. Even just an idea.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;#x200B;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Me: We could get the cheaper laptops, replace the hard drives with SSDs, grab a cheap RAID card off ebay and I build you that backup server youve been wanting? Lovely lovely identical model hard disks for a budget eight disk fault tolerant backup server. You get the laptops up to spec within budget plus some basic data security we desperately need. The extra drives will be your cold spares&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;NextBoss: Thats inspired, I like that&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/SubstantialTerm3843&quot;&gt; /u/SubstantialTerm3843 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yrhwii/i_do_a_thinky/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yrhwii/i_do_a_thinky/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yrhwii</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yrhwii/i_do_a_thinky/"><updated>2022-11-10T15:12:21+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-10T15:12:21+00:00</published><title>I do a thinky</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Architect_of_Sanity</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Architect_of_Sanity</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Im helping a client get licensing under control and from the initial evaluation, theyve spent hundreds of thousands of unnecessary dollars on licensing on specific software because they deployed around without considering the type and versions theyre installing. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;No worries fam, I dont charge you a dime as Im a presales resource here to help. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I need to gather a detailed list of your site locations, quantities of users, and current work loads and I offered to help do it. I just need help to show me where all your sites are and how to get to them. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oh no cant do that, now that was asking too much. Now Im getting random spreadsheets without half the information in them and god knows what locations they apply to. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My dude, I dont know your shorthand naming conventions because you havent shared any of this with me, I dont understand what the numbers are in this csv files your coworkers are sending me without any labels or context &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ive provided exactly what I needed and you cant even follow basic instructions or provide these requirements. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I came close to flipping my desk over this afternoon when the client had the balls to complain about the delays in our audit report and theyre pissed they just got their renewal bill from vendor X and it blows their budget out of the water unless we do our job. Insert mute button tirade. Unmute button offering assistance to gather the data requested so we can help them slash that bill&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im strongly leaning on the account manager to fire this customer thanks for listening. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Im fucking tired of working my ass off for thankless fuckups that land in these IT leadership roles in companies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Architect_of_Sanity&quot;&gt; /u/Architect_of_Sanity &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yp7oxo/why_arent_you_done_yet/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yp7oxo/why_arent_you_done_yet/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yp7oxo</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yp7oxo/why_arent_you_done_yet/"><updated>2022-11-08T01:46:23+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-08T01:46:23+00:00</published><title>Why arent you done yet?</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/Emderth</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/Emderth</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I work in TV post production so while its not a traditional tech job its very tech heavy and when theres an issue my position is usually the first port of call for clients.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A colleague of mine did an export a few days ago for a client who since flagged it as having a weird end frame. I didnt see the original export they were sent, but when I played back the sequence in the editing software nothing looked weird, so I went ahead and exported it again and sent it to the client.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The client got back to me shortly after saying there was still an issue with the end frame and sent me a screenshot of the text thats not on the last frame but the last thing seen before it fades to black.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;They say that the curved letters still arent smooth.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I checked it back against the sequence I was told to export, and what I assume the original sequence was. They all look the same and nothing looks different at all.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;All but two of the letters in the text they flagged consisted of straight lines, it was just the two curved ones they had an issue with, D and S.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This client was complaining about the roundness, or lack there of, of pixels.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thats just how round letters look when theyre made of squares mate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/Emderth&quot;&gt; /u/Emderth &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yoy1ld/the_roundness_of_pixels/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yoy1ld/the_roundness_of_pixels/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_yoy1ld</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/yoy1ld/the_roundness_of_pixels/"><updated>2022-11-07T19:45:39+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-07T19:45:39+00:00</published><title>The roundness of pixels</title></entry><entry><author><name>/u/dickcheney600</name><uri>https://www.reddit.com/user/dickcheney600</uri></author><category term="talesfromtechsupport" label="r/talesfromtechsupport"/><content type="html">&lt;!-- SC_OFF --&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;md&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I worked at a vending company that placed vending and arcade machines at locations like restaurants, bars and similar in exchange for either paying a fixed rent to the location owner or splitting the profits with the location owner. They also rented machines out for events and parties and such.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This place for the most part had actual competent techs working for it. Unfortunately, I wasn&amp;#39;t so great at helping to move large items, and they needed that more than they needed a full time tech due to their rentals and events, therefore I had a relatively short period of employment there.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One day, we got a call from a bar that our shooting game was initially starting up okay when they turned it on upon opening up the bar, but later on it would black out and show &amp;quot;no signal&amp;quot; on the screen. (yes, some arcade monitors do that). We knew by the title, that this was one of those games that had a computer tower inside acting as the &amp;quot;brain&amp;quot; of the game rather than a custom arcade motherboard. This also meant that the tower in some cases used a standard ATX power supply, which we had several of laying round as spares for these types of games. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;After finding a power supply and verifying it worked using our tester, I headed over to the bar. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It was soon enough after opening that the machine had not shut itself down yet, but I decided to do some exploratory &amp;quot;surgery&amp;quot; on it rather than just wait around for it to go wrong. I opened the back cover with the key, and thankfully, there is plenty of room around the tower to take it&amp;#39;s cover off while it&amp;#39;s still in place. I popped the cover off, and I saw that the CPU fan wasn&amp;#39;t turning anymore. Well, darn. I don&amp;#39;t think we have a spare of that. On the other hand, we caught it before the actual CPU failed: score one for whoever designed this motherboard. Clearly the computer was going into thermal shutdown. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I noted in the ticket that the CPU fan was broken, and I took pictures of both the fan itself and the model number on the computer tower case, so that we could figure out what fan to order, or find a broken tower of the same model to pull a fan from.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Even with thermal throttling and shutdown, it&amp;#39;s not wise to continue to run something that has improper cooling, because hitting the upper limit repeatedly is still a good way to cause failure sooner or later. The machine had a removable power cord, so I decided to take it with me - and let the bar manager know the reason I was taking it with me. He appeared to understand so I went on my way. I also made a call to the boss and explained the whole thing. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fast forward about 4 weeks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While I was out replacing the monitor on another machine in a different location, I got a call from my boss. He said that (same shooting game) is broken down at (address) and just showing &amp;quot;No Signal&amp;quot; on the screen. The address sounded familiar, but I didn&amp;#39;t make the connection in the moment. As I got closer to the location, the realization hit that it&amp;#39;s the same one I had found the fan broken in..... But how did they even get to the point of saying &amp;quot;No Signal&amp;quot;? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I entered the bar and just as I suspected, there was another power cord attached and plugged in. Sure enough, the screen is saying &amp;quot;No Signal&amp;quot;. I tried to reboot it, however, instead of the single short &amp;quot;beep&amp;quot; that this machine usually made on startup, I get an ominous series of long beeps. I forget what the pattern was offhand, but it wasn&amp;#39;t what you would want to hear when booting up a computer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I took the back cover off again and found that whoever put the new power cord on hadn&amp;#39;t even closed up the tower so it was still open. More importantly, the fan was still broken, so the CPU had been started and forced to run up to it&amp;#39;s limits multiple times. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Normally, I would try reseating the RAM and possibly the CPU and graphics card to see if that fixes the problem. My hope of that working here was quite thin, knowing what&amp;#39;s happened, but I might as well try something while I&amp;#39;m here. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I pulled out the RAM first amd put it back in. No change. Then I tried the graphics card. No change. The thing I saved for last, because it&amp;#39;s not a pleasant task due to the thermal paste, is the CPU. Well, whatever, I might as well get it over with. So, I unscrewed the heat sink, removed it, undid the lock on the CPU socket and removed the CPU, then put it back in and reattached the heat sink. Lights, Camera, Action! Power on and, just as I suspected, no change. I get the same error beeps. Drat. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I called my boss to see if he knew anything about the power cord finding it&amp;#39;s way back to the bar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It turns out that he had gotten a call that &amp;quot;the power cord is missing&amp;quot; and he had just sent one of the other employees out there with another power cord, and that guy had just plugged it in, and when it booted up in front of him he (understandably) assumed all was well. However, neither that employee OR my boss had bothered to look at the ticket. The restaurant manager didn&amp;#39;t mention anything either, and apparently assumed the problem was fixed or forgot what I had said, and didn&amp;#39;t unplug the machine. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I calmly reminded my boss to check the ticket from 4 weeks ago that had my name on it. After a moment of silence on his part, he surprisingly doesn&amp;#39;t find a way to blame me, for once. Score one for him, but that&amp;#39;s about all he got due to his generally poor attitude. Well, maybe two because he wouldn&amp;#39;t have stood for the kind of crap that went on at the other game room store I had worked for previously. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The guy who didn&amp;#39;t look at the ticket got an earful from the boss, but I don&amp;#39;t think that was entirely fair because the boss could have checked the ticket himself, or the call-taker if it wasn&amp;#39;t the boss. (I don&amp;#39;t know who picked up the &amp;quot;power cord is missing&amp;quot; call). I told that employee that I didn&amp;#39;t blame him.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;TL;DR: The crap hit the fan, but the fan wasn&amp;#39;t working anymore so the crap just stayed there.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- SC_ON --&gt; &amp;#32; submitted by &amp;#32; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/dickcheney600&quot;&gt; /u/dickcheney600 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ynrt36/a_miscommunication_that_really_heats_things_up/&quot;&gt;[link]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#32; &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ynrt36/a_miscommunication_that_really_heats_things_up/&quot;&gt;[comments]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</content><id>t3_ynrt36</id><link href="https://www.reddit.com/r/talesfromtechsupport/comments/ynrt36/a_miscommunication_that_really_heats_things_up/"><updated>2022-11-06T14:47:16+00:00</updated><published>2022-11-06T14:47:16+00:00</published><title>A miscommunication that really heats things up</title></entry></feed>