<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title><![CDATA[Y Combinator Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[Y Combinator Blog]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/</link><image><url>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/favicon.png</url><title>Y Combinator Blog</title><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/</link></image><generator>Ghost 4.48</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 12:17:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Welcome Diana, Dave, Edrizio, and Umur]]></title><description><![CDATA[Today, we’re excited to welcome Diana Hu as our newest Group Partner and Dave Lieb, Edrizio Delacruz, and Umur Cubukcu, as our newest Visiting Group Partners.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/welcome-diana-dave-edrizio-and-umur/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6361a7d8b221a60001ccd254</guid><category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Aaron Epstein]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 15:55:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/11/BlogTwitter-Image-Template.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/11/BlogTwitter-Image-Template.jpeg" alt="Welcome Diana, Dave, Edrizio, and Umur"><p>Every batch, we invite founders and executives to advise YC companies as Visiting Group Partners. These advisors bring valuable insights and recent operational experience to YC&#x2019;s early-stage companies. Throughout the batch, they take on a variety of responsibilities, including application reading, interviews, group and individual office hours, Demo Day prep, and more.</p><p>As YC grows, some of our Visiting Group Partners join us full time as Group Partners to continue supporting YC companies and build out new programs and initiatives to better support our community. </p><p>Today, we&#x2019;re excited to welcome Diana Hu as our newest Group Partner and Dave Lieb, Edrizio Delacruz, and Umur Cubukcu, as our newest Visiting Group Partners. And <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/welcome-s22-visiting-group-partners">welcome back</a> to Visiting Group Partners JJ Fliegelman, Liz Wessel, Pete Koomen, Puneet Kumar, Rich Aberman, and Tom Blomfield.</p><h3 id="group-partner">Group Partner</h3><p>After three batches as a Visiting Group Partner, Diana Hu is joining YC as a Group Partner.</p><p><strong>Diana Hu</strong><br>Diana was co-founder and CTO of <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/escher-reality">Escher Reality</a> (YC S17), an Augmented Reality Backend company that was acquired by Niantic (makers of Pok&#xE9;mon Go). At Niantic, she was the head of the AR platform. Previously, she led data science at OnCue TV that was sold to Verizon. Originally from Chile, Diana graduated from Carnegie Mellon University with a BS and MS in Electrical and Computer Engineering with a focus in computer vision and machine learning.</p><h3 id="visiting-group-partners">Visiting Group Partners<br></h3><p><strong>Dave Lieb</strong><br>Dave was co-founder and CEO of <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/bump">Bump</a> (S09), the mobile app used by more than 150M people to share photos and contact info by bumping phones together. After pivoting to photo sharing, Bump was acquired by Google in 2013, and its unreleased Photoroll app formed the basis for Google Photos, which Dave co-founded and led from inception to more than 1B users. Before Bump, Dave was a researcher in the Stanford AI Lab and a software engineer at Texas Instruments. He holds EE/CS degrees from Princeton and Stanford and finished &#xBD; an MBA at Chicago Booth before dropping out to start Bump. Dave lives with his family in San Francisco and enjoys skiing, cycling, and reading tweets.</p><p><strong>Edrizio Delacruz</strong><br>Edrizio was the co-founder and CEO of <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/arcus">Arcus</a> (S13), a Latin America payments platform. The company grew to serve over 200 clients and process billions of dollars annually. In 2021, the company was sold to Mastercard. Edrizio holds an MBA from The Wharton School. He was born in the Dominican Republic, grew up in Harlem, and now resides in Miami. He loves comedy, hiking, writing, and his one-year-old baby girl.</p><p><strong>Umur Cubukcu</strong><br>Umur was the co-founder and CEO of <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/citus-data">Citus Data</a> (S11), the creators of Citus, the distributed PostgreSQL database, and the first company in the world to donate equity to open source foundations. With millions of downloads and powering database infrastructure across Fortune 500 and SaaS companies, Citus Data was acquired by Microsoft in 2019; and Umur has since led the PostgreSQL product team at Azure. Umur received his MS from Stanford University, and lives with his wife and son in San Francisco, visiting Turkey every summer.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[How to maintain engineering velocity as you scale]]></title><description><![CDATA[Faire’s engineering team grew from five to over 100 engineers in three years. Throughout this growth, we were able to sustain our pace of engineering execution by adhering to four guiding principles.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/how-to-maintain-engineering-velocity-as-you-scale/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6357f9044557ad0001018040</guid><category><![CDATA[Essay]]></category><category><![CDATA[YC Continuity]]></category><category><![CDATA[Technical]]></category><category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category><category><![CDATA[Leadership]]></category><category><![CDATA[Company Building]]></category><category><![CDATA[Growth]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Marcelo Cortes]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/BlogTwitter-Image-Template-2.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/BlogTwitter-Image-Template-2.jpeg" alt="How to maintain engineering velocity as you scale"><p>Engineering is typically the function that grows fastest at a scaling startup. It requires a lot of attention to make sure the pace of execution does not slow and cultural issues do not emerge as you scale.</p><p>We&#x2019;ve learned a lot about pace of execution in the past five years at Faire. When we launched in 2017, we were a team of five engineers. From the beginning, we built a simple but solid foundation that allowed us to maintain both velocity and quality. When we found product-market fit later that year and started bringing on lots of new customers, instead of spending engineering resources on re-architecturing our platform to scale, we were able to double down on product engineering to accelerate the growth. In this post, we discuss the guiding principles that allowed us to maintain our engineering velocity as we scaled.</p><h2 id="four-guiding-principles-to-maintaining-velocity">Four guiding principles to maintaining velocity</h2><p>Faire&#x2019;s engineering team grew from five to over 100 engineers in three years. Throughout this growth, we were able to sustain our pace of engineering execution by adhering to four important elements:</p><ol><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/how-to-maintain-engineering-velocity-as-you-scale/#1-hire-the-best-engineers">Hiring the best engineers</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/how-to-maintain-engineering-velocity-as-you-scale/#2-build-a-solid-long-term-foundation-from-day-one">Building solid long-term foundations from day one</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/how-to-maintain-engineering-velocity-as-you-scale/#3-track-engineering-metrics-to-drive-decision-making">Tracking metrics to guide decision-making</a></li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/how-to-maintain-engineering-velocity-as-you-scale/#4-keep-teams-small-and-independent">Keeping teams small and independent</a></li></ol><h2 id="1-hire-the-best-engineers">1. Hire the best engineers</h2><p>You want to hire the best early team that you can, as they&#x2019;re going to be the people helping you scale and maintain velocity. And good people follow good people, helping you grow your team down the road.</p><p>This sounds obvious, but it&#x2019;s tempting to get people in seats fast because you have a truckload of priorities and you&#x2019;re often the only one doing engineering recruiting in those early years. What makes this even harder is you often have to play the long game to get the best engineers signed on. Your job is to build a case for why your company is <em>the</em> opportunity for them. </p><p>We had a few amazing engineers in mind we wanted to hire early on. I spent over a year doing coffee meetings with some of them. I used these meetings to get advice, but more importantly I was always giving them updates on our progress, vision, fundraising, and product releases. That created FOMO which eventually got them so excited about what was happening at Faire that they signed up for the ride.</p><p>While recruiting, I looked for key competencies that I thought were vital for our engineering team to be successful as we scaled. These were:</p><h3 id="a-experts-at-our-core-technology">a. Experts at our core technology</h3><p>In early stages, you need to move extremely fast and you cannot afford to make mistakes. We wanted the best engineers who had previously built the components we needed so they knew where mistakes could happen, what to avoid, what to focus on, and more. For example, we built a complex payments infrastructure in a couple of weeks. That included integrating with multiple payment processors in order to charge debit/credit cards, process partial refunds, async retries, voiding canceled transactions, and linking bank accounts for ACH payouts. We had built similar infrastructure for the Cash App at Square and that experience allowed us to move extremely quickly while avoiding pitfalls.</p><h3 id="b-focused-on-delivering-value-to-customers">b. Focused on delivering value to customers</h3><p>Faire&#x2019;s mission is to empower entrepreneurs to chase their dreams. When hiring engineers, we looked for people who were amazing technically but also understood our business, were customer focused, were passionate about entrepreneurship&#x2014;and understood how they needed to work. That is, they understood how to use technology to add value to customers and product, quickly and with quality. To test for this, I would ask questions like: &#x201C;Give me examples of how you or your team impacted the<em> </em>business.&#x201D; Their answers would show how well they understood their current company&#x2019;s business and how engineering can impact customers and change a company&#x2019;s top-line numbers.</p><p>I also learned a lot when I let them ask questions about Faire. I love when engineering candidates ask questions about how our business works, how we make money, what our market size is, etc. If they don&apos;t ask these kinds of questions, I ask them things like: &#x201C;Do you understand how Faire works?&#x201D; &#x201C;Why is Faire good for retailers?&#x201D; &#x201C;How would you sell Faire to a brand?&#x201D; After asking questions like these a few times, you&#x2019;ll see patterns and be able to quickly identify engineers who are business-minded and customer-focused.</p><p>Another benefit of hiring customer-focused engineers is that it&#x2019;s much easier to shut down projects, start new ones, and move people around, because everyone is focused on delivering value for the customer and not wedded to the products they helped build. During COVID, our customers saw enormous change, with in-person trade shows getting canceled and lockdowns impacting in-person foot traffic. We had to adapt quickly, which required us to stop certain initiatives and move our product and engineering teams to launch new ones, such as our own version of <a href="https://blog.faire.com/thestorefront/introducing-faire-summer-market-our-first-online-trade-show-event/">online trade shows</a>.</p><h3 id="c-grit">c. Grit</h3><p>When we first started, we couldn&#x2019;t afford to build the most beautiful piece of engineering work. We had to be fast and agile. This is critical when you are pre-product-market fit. Our CEO Max and a few early employees would go to trade shows to present our product to customers, understand their needs, and learn what resonated with them. Max would call us with new ideas several times a day. It was paramount that our engineers were <a href="https://angeladuckworth.com/grit-book/">gritty</a> and able to quickly make changes to the product. Over the three or four days of a trade show, our team deployed changes nonstop to the platform. We experimented with offerings like:</p><ul><li>Free shipping on first orders</li><li>Buy now, pay later</li><li>Buy from a brand and get $100 off when you re-order from the same brand</li><li>Free returns</li></ul><p>By trying different value propositions in a short time, our engineering team helped us figure out what was most valuable to our customers. That was how we found strong product-market fit within six months of starting the company.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/CrRDf25EV8if-oP6rfEnSYeA_ttfKsayeQoM61gMOYFODZvpYsId0z2Y5RQ8z5xH4zt8UQaPBOwe1xus8oaqKQW1zxqNxz_ss9LHTpWyCc6tWsyJUm6_g6lVUtb6PkHluwNcqIU9MN3silgCLqtNHO2S8RkPcQCHBYiVPhK9Fteoiq_w9dZJqaxTqA" class="kg-image" alt="How to maintain engineering velocity as you scale" loading="lazy"></figure><p><em>Our trade show storefront back when we were called Indigo Fair.</em></p><h2 id="2-build-a-solid-long-term-foundation-from-day-one">2. Build a solid long-term foundation from day one</h2><p>The number one impediment to engineering velocity at scale is a lack of solid, consistent foundation. A simple but solid foundation will allow your team to keep building on top of it instead of having to throw away or re-architecture your base when hypergrowth starts.</p><p>To create a solid long-term foundation, you first need to get clear on what practices you believe are important for your engineering team to scale. For example, I remember speaking with senior engineers at other startups who were surprised we were writing tests and doing code reviews and that we had a code style guide from the very early days. But we couldn&#x2019;t have operated well without these processes. When we started to grow fast and add lots of engineers, we were able to keep over 95% of the team focused on building features and adding value to our customers, increasing our growth. </p><p>Once you know what long-term foundations you want to build, you need to write it down. We were intentional about this from day one and documented it in our <a href="https://craft.faire.com/handbook-89f166841ec9">engineering handbook</a>. Today, every engineer is onboarded using this handbook.</p><p>The four foundational elements we decided on were:</p><h3 id="a-being-data-driven">a. Being data-driven</h3><p>The most important thing is to build your data muscle early. We started doing this at 10 customers. At the time, the data wasn&#x2019;t particularly useful; the more important thing was to start to collect it. At some point, you&#x2019;ll need data to drive product decision-making. The longer you wait, the harder it is to embed into your team.</p><p>Here&#x2019;s what I recommend you start doing as early as possible:</p><ul><li>Set up data pipelines that feed into a data warehouse.</li><li>Start collecting data on how people are using your product. As you add features and iterate, record how those changes are impacting user interactions. All of this should go into a data warehouse that is updated within minutes and made available to your team. As your product gets increasingly complex, it will become more and more important to use data to validate your intuition.</li><li>We use Redshift to store data. As user events are happening, our relational database (MySQL) replicates them in Redshift. Within minutes, the data is available for queries and reports.</li><li>Train your team to use experimentation frameworks.</li><li>Make it part of the product development process. The goal is to transform your intuition into a statistically testable statement. A good place to start is to establish principles and high-level steps for your team to follow when they run experiments. We&#x2019;ve set principles around when to run experiments vs. when not to, that running rigorous experiments should be the default (and when it isn&#x2019;t), and when to stop an experiment earlier than expected. We also have teams log experiments in a Notion dashboard.</li><li>The initial focus should be on what impact you think a feature will have and how to measure that change. As you&#x2019;re scoping a feature, ask questions like: How are we going to validate that this feature is achieving intended goals? What events/data do we need to collect to support that? What reports are we going to build? Over time, these core principles will expand.</li><li>The entire team should be thinking about this, not just the engineers or data team. We reinforced the importance of data fluency by pushing employees to learn SQL, so that they could run their own queries and experience the data firsthand.</li><li>It&#x2019;ll take you multiple reps to get this right. We still miss steps and fail to collect the right data. The sooner you get your team doing this, the easier it will be to teach it to new people and become better at it as an organization.</li></ul><h3 id="b-our-choice-of-programming-language-and-database">b. Our choice of programming language and database</h3><p>When choosing a language and database, pick something you know best that is also scalable long-term.<strong> </strong>If you choose a language you don&#x2019;t know well because it seems easier or faster to get started, you won&#x2019;t foresee pitfalls and you&#x2019;ll have to learn as you go. This is expensive and time-consuming. We started with Java as our backend programming language and MySQL as our relational database. In the early days, we were building two to three features per week and it took us a couple of weeks to build the framework we needed around MySQL. This was a big tradeoff that paid dividends later on.</p><h3 id="c-writing-tests-from-day-one">c. Writing tests from day one</h3><p>Many startups think they can move faster by not writing tests; it&#x2019;s the opposite. Tests help you avoid bugs and prevent legacy code at scale. They aren&#x2019;t just validating the code you are writing now. They should be used to enforce, validate, and document requirements. Good tests protect your code from future changes as your codebase grows and features are added or changed. They also catch problems early and help avoid production bugs, saving you time and money. Code without tests becomes legacy very fast. Within months after untested code is written, no one will remember the exact requirements, edge cases, constraints, etc. If you don&#x2019;t have tests to enforce these things, new engineers will be afraid of changing the code in case they break something or change an expected behavior.<br><br>There are two reasons why tests break when a developer is making code changes:</p><ul><li>Requirements change. In this case, we expect tests to break and they should be updated to validate and enforce the new requirements.</li><li>Behavior changes unexpectedly. For example, a bug was introduced and the test alerted us early in the development process.</li></ul><p>Every language has tools to measure and keep track of test coverage. I highly recommend introducing them early to track how much of your code is protected by tests. You don&#x2019;t need to have 100% code coverage, but you should make sure that critical paths, important logic, edge cases, etc. are well tested. <a href="https://leanylabs.com/blog/good-unit-tests/">Here are tips for writing good tests</a>.</p><h3 id="d-doing-code-reviews">d. Doing code reviews</h3><p>We started doing code reviews when we hired our first engineer. Having another engineer review your code changes helps ensure quality, prevents mistakes, and shares good patterns. In other words, it&#x2019;s a great learning tool for new and experienced engineers. Through code reviews, you are teaching your engineers patterns: what to avoid, why to do something, the features of languages you should and shouldn&#x2019;t use. </p><p>Along with this, you should have a coding style guide. Coding guides help enforce consistency and quality on your engineering team. It doesn&#x2019;t have to be complex. We use a tool that formats our code so our style guide is automatically enforced before a change can be merged. This leads to higher code quality, especially when teams are collaborating and other people are reviewing code.</p><p>We switched from Java to Kotlin in 2019 and we have a comprehensive style guide that includes recommendations and rules for programming in Kotlin. For anything not explicitly specified in our guide, we ask that engineers follow <a href="https://kotlinlang.org/docs/coding-conventions.html">JetBrains&#x2019; coding conventions</a>.</p><p>These are the code review best practices we share internally:</p><ul><li>#bekind when doing a code review. Use positive phrasing where possible (&quot;there might be a better way&quot; instead of &quot;this is terrible&quot;; &quot;how about we name this X?&quot; instead of &quot;naming this Y is bad&quot;). It&apos;s easy to unintentionally come across as critical, especially if you have a remote team.</li><li>Don&apos;t block changes from being merged if the issues are minor (e.g., a request for variable name change, indentation fixes). Instead, make the ask verbally. Only block merging if the request contains potentially dangerous changes that could cause issues or if there is an easier/safer way to accomplish the same.</li><li>When doing a code review, ensure that the code adheres to your style guide. When giving feedback, refer to the relevant sections in the style guide.</li><li>If the code review is large, consider checking out the branch locally and inspecting the changes in IntelliJ (Git tab on the bottom). It&#x2019;s easier to have all of the navigation tools at hand.</li></ul><h2 id="3-track-engineering-metrics-to-drive-decision-making">3. Track engineering metrics to drive decision-making</h2><p>Tracking metrics is imperative to maintaining engineering velocity. Without clear metrics, Faire would be in the dark about how our team is performing and where we should focus our efforts. We would have to rely on intuition and assumptions to guide what we should be prioritizing. </p><p>Examples of metrics we started tracking early (at around 20 engineers) included:</p><ul><li><strong>Uptime.</strong> One of the first metrics we tracked was <a href="https://docs.datadoghq.com/integrations/uptime/">uptime</a>. We started measuring this because we were receiving anecdotal reports of site stability issues. Once we started tracking it, we confirmed the anecdotal evidence and dedicated a few engineers to resolve the issue.</li><li><strong>CI wait time.</strong> Another metric that was really important was CI wait time (i.e., time for the build system to build/test pull requests). We were receiving anecdotal reports of long CI wait times for developers, confirmed it with data, and fixed the issue.</li></ul><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/KiE8tjsqkFvtJFmyY_6-IinXuT1A6C4x6JBUSX9qb9nDHB9lurJZAlHocGDEi3Sx_HSHNuBxozMBljGOsNokrQIJ9Hk6ZolI39yQtKPz0yuAbue0G2weaKWXqD65_Gbal_LYuEC5TpPoGIdCGd0jflhy1yRQzuG-pxV1IePbh8LuEtvqehC1gHs5lw" class="kg-image" alt="How to maintain engineering velocity as you scale" loading="lazy"></figure><p><em>This is a dashboard we created in the early days of Faire to track important engineering metrics. It was updated manually by collecting data from different sources. Today, we have more comprehensive dashboards that are fully automated.</em></p><p>Once our engineering team grew to 100+, our top-level metrics became more difficult to take action against. When metrics trended beyond concerning thresholds, we didn&#x2019;t have a clear way to address them. Each team was busy with their own product roadmap, and it didn&#x2019;t seem worthwhile to spin up new teams to address temporary needs. Additionally, many of the problems were large in scale and would have required a dedicated group of engineers. </p><p>We found that the best solution was to build <a href="https://www.datadoghq.com/blog/the-power-of-tagged-metrics/">dimensions</a> so that we could view metrics by team. Once we had metrics cut by team, we could set top-down expectations and priorities. We were happy to see that individual teams did a great job of taking ownership of and improving their metrics and, consequently, the company&#x2019;s top-level metrics.</p><h4 id="an-example-transaction-run-duration">An example: transaction run duration</h4><p>Coming out of our virtual trade show, <a href="https://blog.faire.com/thestudio/faire-summer-market-2021-our-global-trade-show-event-is-coming-in-july/">Faire Summer Market</a>, we knew we needed significant investment in our database utilization. During the event, site usage pushed our database capacity to its limits and we realized we wouldn&#x2019;t be able to handle similar events in the future.</p><p>In response, we created a metric of how long transactions were open every time our application interacted with the database. Each transaction was attributed to a specific team. We then had a visualization of the hottest areas of our application along with the teams responsible for those areas. We asked each team to set a goal during our planning process to reduce their database usage by 20% over a three-month period. The aggregate results were staggering. Six months later, before our next event&#x2014;<a href="https://blog.faire.com/thestorefront/announcing-faires-2022-winter-virtual-trade-show-events/">Faire Winter Market</a>&#x2014;incoming traffic was 1.6x higher, but we were nowhere close to maxing out our database capacity. Now, each team is responsible for monitoring their database utilization and ensuring it doesn&#x2019;t trend in the wrong direction.</p><h3 id="managing-metrics-with-kpi-scorecards">Managing metrics with KPI scorecards</h3><p>We&#x2019;re moving towards a model where each team maintains a set of key performance indicators (KPIs) that get published as a scorecard reflecting how successful the team is at maintaining its product areas and the parts of the tech stack it owns.</p><p>We&#x2019;re starting with a top-level scorecard for the whole engineering team that tracks our highest-level KPIs (e.g., <a href="https://docs.datadoghq.com/tracing/guide/configure_an_apdex_for_your_traces_with_datadog_apm/">Apdex</a>, database utilization, CI wait time, severe bug escapes, flaky tests). Each team maintains a scorecard with its assigned top-level KPIs as well as domain-specific KPIs. As teams grow and split into sub-teams, the scorecards follow the same path recursively. Engineering leaders managing multiple teams use these scorecards to gauge the relative success of their teams and to better understand where they should be focusing their own time.</p><p>Scorecard generation should be as automated and as simple as possible so that it becomes a regular practice. If your process requires a lot of manual effort, you&#x2019;re likely going to have trouble committing to it on a regular cadence. Many of our metrics start in DataDog; we use their API to extract relevant metrics and push them into Redshift and then visualize them in Mode reports.</p><p>As we&#x2019;ve rolled this process out, we&#x2019;ve identified criteria for what makes a great engineering KPI:</p><ul><li><strong>Can be measured and has a believable source of truth.</strong> If capturing and viewing KPIs is not an easy and repeatable task, it&#x2019;s bound to stop happening. Invest in the infrastructure to reliably capture KPIs in a format that can be easily queried.</li><li><strong>Clearly ladders up to a top-level business metric.</strong> If there isn&#x2019;t a clear connection to a top-level business metric, you&#x2019;ll have a hard time convincing stakeholders to take action based on the data. For example, we&#x2019;ve started tracking pager volume for our critical services: High pager volume contributes to tired and distracted engineers which leads to less code output, which leads to fewer features delivered, which ultimately means less customer value.</li><li><strong>Is independent of other KPIs.</strong> When viewing and sharing KPIs, give appropriate relative weight to each one depending on your priorities. If you&#x2019;re showing two highly correlated KPIs (e.g., cycle time and PR throughput), then you&#x2019;re not leaving room for something that&#x2019;s less correlated (e.g., uptime). You might want to capture some correlated KPIs so that you can quickly diagnose a worrying trend, but you should present non-duplicative KPIs when crafting the overall scorecard that you share with stakeholders.</li><li><strong>Is normalized in a meaningful way.</strong> Looking at absolute numbers can be misleading in a high-growth environment, which makes it hard to compare performance across teams. For example, we initially tracked growth of overall infrastructure cost. The numbers more than doubled every year, which was concerning. When we later normalized this KPI by the amount of revenue a product was producing, we observed the KPI was flat over time. Now we have a clear KPI of &#x201C;amount spent on infrastructure to generate $1 in revenue.&#x201D; This resulted in us being comfortable with our rate of spend, whereas previously we were considering staffing a team to address growing infrastructure costs.</li></ul><p>We plan to keep investing in this area as we grow. KPIs allow us to work and build with confidence, knowing that we&#x2019;re focusing on the right problems to continue serving our customers.</p><h2 id="4-keep-teams-small-and-independent">4. Keep teams small and independent</h2><p>When we were a company of 25 employees, we had a single engineering team. Eventually, we split into two teams in order to prioritize multiple areas simultaneously and ship faster. When you split into multiple teams, things can break because people lose context. To navigate this, we developed a pod structure to ensure that every team was able to operate independently but with all the context and resources they needed. </p><p>When you first create a pod structure, here are some rules of thumb:</p><ul><li><strong>Pods should operate like small startups.</strong> Give them a mission, goals, and the resources they need. It&#x2019;s up to them to figure out the strategy to achieve those goals. Pods at Faire typically do an in-person offsite to brainstorm ideas and come up with a prioritized roadmap and expected business results, which they then present for feedback and approval.</li><li><strong><strong><strong>Each pod should have no more than 8 to 10 employees. </strong></strong></strong>For us, pods generally include 5 to 7 engineers (including an engineering manager), a product manager, a designer, and a data scientist.</li><li><strong>Each pod should have a clear leader. </strong>We have an engineering manager and a product manager co-lead each pod. We designed it this way to give engineering a voice and more ownership in the planning process.</li><li><strong>Expect people to be members of multiple pods. </strong>While this isn&#x2019;t ideal, there isn&#x2019;t any other way to do it early on. Resources are constrained, and you need a combination of seasoned employees and new hires on each pod (otherwise they&#x2019;ll lack context). Pick one or two people who have lots of context to seed the pod, then add new members. When we first did this, pods shared backend engineers, designers, and data analysts, and had their own product manager and frontend engineer.</li><li><strong>If you only have one product, assign a pod to each well-defined part of the product.</strong> If there&#x2019;s not an obvious way to split up your product surface area, try to break it out into large features and assign a pod to each.</li><li><strong><strong><strong>Keep reporting lines and performance management within functional teams. </strong></strong></strong>This makes it easier to maintain:</li></ul><p>		(1) Standardized tooling/processes across the engineering team and balanced 		leadership between functions</p><p>		(2) Standardized career frameworks and performance calibration. We give our 		managers guidance and tools to make sure this is happening. For example, I 		have a spreadsheet for every manager that I expect them to update on a 	 		monthly basis with a scorecard and brief summary of their direct reports&#x2019; 		 		performance.</p><h3 id="how-we-stay-on-top-of-resource-allocation-census-and-horsepower">How we stay on top of resource allocation: Census and Horsepower</h3><p>Our engineering priorities change often. We need to be able to move engineers around and create, merge, split, or sunset pods. In order to keep track of who is on which team&#x2014;taking into account where that person is located, their skill set, tenure at the company, and more&#x2014;we built a tool called Census.</p><p>Census is a real-time visualization of our team&#x2019;s structure. It automatically updates with data from our ATS and HR system. The visual aspect is crucial and makes it easier for leadership to make decisions around resource allocation and pod changes as priorities shift. Alongside Census, we also built an algorithm to evaluate the &#x201C;horsepower&#x201D; of a pod. If horsepower is showing up as yellow or red, that pod either needs more senior engineers, has a disproportionate number of new employees, or both.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card kg-card-hascaption"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/pJk7SUqsmeQLU_dYU3BrN5wMnzyHwVySmydpuiNbHgDddt_FzwwQzCQ_pQH75FX-InduoRGg5hSVhcfXZxRC3FztBZ3aF_2JnwIFMBOhjSey2cgRQEqs38oORhgZgrtwrmgO7CM-WSU_34oeyp15hdzHOrH_FAXTlFlJOt-A87J4Brce_ri3MER8RA" class="kg-image" alt="How to maintain engineering velocity as you scale" loading="lazy"><figcaption>.</figcaption></figure><p><em>Census.</em></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/N7btbx4GDkomhZp8wj0CMlTiGywqDffV6qCakK6aZEILScjRiIqjhwjV1q2AlT6bmrzU9vqo_pa1ggXn8j_C0CWsO4BEQdHoq5EcPfOhZwhe8tg1oMmmmDeYQXNrjF99WOdM5AKVTT5GAisZM_idtecOsjdXH_qQ2ezvEVRLltbkMfmk1j3qouwt7g" class="kg-image" alt="How to maintain engineering velocity as you scale" loading="lazy"></figure><p><em>Pods are colored either green, yellow, or red depending on their horsepower.</em><br><br>One of the most common questions that founders have is how to balance speed with everything else: product quality, architecture debt, team culture. Too often, startups stall out and sacrifice their early momentum in order to correct technical debt. In building Faire, we set out to both establish a unified foundation <em>and</em> continue shipping fast. These four guiding principles are how we did it, and I hope they help others do the same.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[YC Founder Firesides: Mutiny on AI and the next era of company growth]]></title><description><![CDATA[YC’s Anu Hariharan sat down with Mutiny co-founder and CEO Jaleh Rezaei to talk about their recent acquisition of Intellipse, an AI marketing platform, as well as how AI will impact the next era of growth.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/yc-founder-firesides-mutiny-on-ai-and-the-next-era-of-company-growth/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6356a9c957e9f90001984b62</guid><category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category><category><![CDATA[Interview]]></category><category><![CDATA[YC Continuity]]></category><category><![CDATA[Founder Stories]]></category><category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category><category><![CDATA[Growth]]></category><category><![CDATA[Leadership]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Y Combinator]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 16:25:31 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/BlogTwitter-Image-Template-1.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/BlogTwitter-Image-Template-1.jpeg" alt="YC Founder Firesides: Mutiny on AI and the next era of company growth"><p><a href="https://www.mutinyhq.com/">Mutiny</a> (<a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/mutiny">YC S18</a>) uses AI and data to convert website visitors into customers. Today, the fastest growing B2B companies such as Notion and Snowflake use Mutiny to identify ideal customers, determine sections of websites that will increase conversion, and produce copy that converts visitors into customers. </p><p>YC&#x2019;s <a href="https://twitter.com/anuhariharan/status/1557784730543632384">Anu Hariharan</a> sat down with Mutiny co-founder and CEO <a href="https://twitter.com/jalehr">Jaleh Rezaei</a> to talk about their <a href="https://twitter.com/jalehr/status/1582352047659024385">recent acquisition</a> of Intellipse, an AI marketing platform, as well as how AI will impact the next era of growth. Throughout, Jaleh shares advice about acquisitions as a growth strategy and evolving your product with AI. </p><p>You can listen here or on <a href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/7dy1qB7XQfOryE4kj4spGS">Spotify</a>, <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/160-yc-founder-firesides-mutiny-on-ai-and-the-next/id1236907421?i=1000583708925">Apple Podcasts</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/i/spaces/1yNxaNzAPPnKj">Twitter</a>.</p><div class="kg-card kg-audio-card"><img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/media/2022/10/anu---jaleh-edit_thumb.jpeg?v=1666624417996" alt="YC Founder Firesides: Mutiny on AI and the next era of company growth" class="kg-audio-thumbnail"><div class="kg-audio-thumbnail placeholder kg-audio-hide"><svg width="24" height="24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" d="M7.5 15.33a.75.75 0 1 0 0 1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0-1.5Zm-2.25.75a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 4.5 0 2.25 2.25 0 0 1-4.5 0ZM15 13.83a.75.75 0 1 0 0 1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0-1.5Zm-2.25.75a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 4.5 0 2.25 2.25 0 0 1-4.5 0Z"/><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" d="M14.486 6.81A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 17.25 9v5.579a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0v-5.58a.75.75 0 0 0-.932-.727.755.755 0 0 1-.059.013l-4.465.744a.75.75 0 0 0-.544.72v6.33a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0v-6.33a2.25 2.25 0 0 1 1.763-2.194l4.473-.746Z"/><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" d="M3 1.5a.75.75 0 0 0-.75.75v19.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75.75h18a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75V5.133a.75.75 0 0 0-.225-.535l-.002-.002-3-2.883A.75.75 0 0 0 18 1.5H3ZM1.409.659A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3 0h15a2.25 2.25 0 0 1 1.568.637l.003.002 3 2.883a2.25 2.25 0 0 1 .679 1.61V21.75A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 21 24H3a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25-2.25V2.25c0-.597.237-1.169.659-1.591Z"/></svg></div><div class="kg-audio-player-container"><audio src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/media/2022/10/anu---jaleh-edit.mp3" preload="metadata"></audio><div class="kg-audio-title">YC Founder Firesides: Mutiny on AI and the next era of company growth</div><div class="kg-audio-player"><button class="kg-audio-play-icon"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewbox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M23.14 10.608 2.253.164A1.559 1.559 0 0 0 0 1.557v20.887a1.558 1.558 0 0 0 2.253 1.392L23.14 13.393a1.557 1.557 0 0 0 0-2.785Z"/></svg></button><button class="kg-audio-pause-icon kg-audio-hide"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewbox="0 0 24 24"><rect x="3" y="1" width="7" height="22" rx="1.5" ry="1.5"/><rect x="14" y="1" width="7" height="22" rx="1.5" ry="1.5"/></svg></button><span class="kg-audio-current-time">0:00</span><div class="kg-audio-time">/<span class="kg-audio-duration">57:56</span></div><input type="range" class="kg-audio-seek-slider" max="100" value="0"><button class="kg-audio-playback-rate">1&#xD7;</button><button class="kg-audio-unmute-icon"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewbox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M15.189 2.021a9.728 9.728 0 0 0-7.924 4.85.249.249 0 0 1-.221.133H5.25a3 3 0 0 0-3 3v2a3 3 0 0 0 3 3h1.794a.249.249 0 0 1 .221.133 9.73 9.73 0 0 0 7.924 4.85h.06a1 1 0 0 0 1-1V3.02a1 1 0 0 0-1.06-.998Z"/></svg></button><button class="kg-audio-mute-icon kg-audio-hide"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewbox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M16.177 4.3a.248.248 0 0 0 .073-.176v-1.1a1 1 0 0 0-1.061-1 9.728 9.728 0 0 0-7.924 4.85.249.249 0 0 1-.221.133H5.25a3 3 0 0 0-3 3v2a3 3 0 0 0 3 3h.114a.251.251 0 0 0 .177-.073ZM23.707 1.706A1 1 0 0 0 22.293.292l-22 22a1 1 0 0 0 0 1.414l.009.009a1 1 0 0 0 1.405-.009l6.63-6.631A.251.251 0 0 1 8.515 17a.245.245 0 0 1 .177.075 10.081 10.081 0 0 0 6.5 2.92 1 1 0 0 0 1.061-1V9.266a.247.247 0 0 1 .073-.176Z"/></svg></button><input type="range" class="kg-audio-volume-slider" max="100" value="100"></div></div></div><p><strong>1:35</strong> - What is the founding story of Mutiny? </p><ul><li>There are two levers of growth: demand and conversion. Often companies improve their conversion rate by hiring a dedicated growth team &#x2013; but it is difficult to build a system from scratch and hire the engineers to do so. Jaleh and her co-founder decided to create a no code platform and serve as the world&#x2019;s growth team. </li></ul><p><strong>4:25</strong> - Jaleh elaborates on the challenges growth teams face in conversion optimization. </p><ul><li>Teams first source and use data to understand the part of the funnel to prioritize. Then they estimate revenue improvements and brainstorm tactics to improve conversion. (The time invested compared to impact is taken into consideration.) Finally, the engineers build a measurement system to capture the impact of those changes. The entire process takes months. With Mutiny, this process takes minutes even for people who aren&#x2019;t technical and has a massive impact on teams&#x2019; ability to launch new experiences and optimize conversion. </li></ul><p><strong>9:00</strong> - When should a startup use Mutiny? </p><ul><li>There are use cases for pre-product market fit companies (as long as you know the customers you want to go after) and post-product market fit.</li><li>Example 1: <a href="https://www.mutinyhq.com/playbooks/personalize-paid-landing-pages-to-reduce-cost-per-lead">Notion drives 60% more leads through paid marketing</a></li><li>Example 2: <a href="https://www.mutinyhq.com/blog/the-second-lever-replays#conversion-secret-how-snowflake-runs-abm-at-scale">Snowflake builds an ABM and enterprise marketing program</a></li></ul><p><strong>12:50</strong> - You recently shared that with data and AI, Mutiny transforms conversion from a niche A/B testing tool to a platform that every go-to-market team can use to drive efficient growth at scale. What does that mean, and how have you leveraged the advances in AI over the last four years? </p><ul><li>When you can give the entire go-to-market team x-ray vision into every visitor and how they are converting &#x2013; and then pair that insight with the ability to change the website for different segments &#x2013; every team will make the website a core part of their strategy to drive more revenue. Mutiny uses AI to give teams this insight and answer questions like: What segments should I prioritize? What parts of the website should I change? What copy will resonate? Where should I focus? </li></ul><p><strong>17:00</strong> - At Mutiny when looking at data, when do you know the right questions to ask and when do you say these are not questions we need to optimize now?</p><ul><li>In the early days, one of the most valuable things we did was follow our customers&#x2019; growth teams. We would attend team meetings, watch them use our product, and ask questions. It became clear what we should build for our customers. </li></ul><p><strong>20:30</strong> - Since you started Mutiny, what are some of the advances in AI that you&#x2019;ve leveraged? </p><ul><li>We did things that didn&apos;t scale in the early days to solve customers&#x2019; problems. As our customers grew, our data set grew and we used AI models and inputs to improve our recommendation engines and service a broader customer base. Today, we can build models that tell a user where on the website they should make changes and write personalized copy leveraging GPT-3. </li></ul><p><strong>29:10</strong> - Did you have moments when you felt Mutiny could be doing more with the advances being made in AI? </p><ul><li>We saw an opportunity to marry our proprietary data set with GPT-3 to produce highly personalized copy. </li></ul><p><strong>32:15</strong> - GPT-3 was an inflection point for Munity. What is the next inflection point? </p><ul><li>There are a lot of opportunities with DALL-E, as visuals are important in marketing.</li></ul><p><strong>36:30</strong> - Do you have cautionary advice on how to think about using technologies like GPT-3 and DALL-E for founders dabbling in AI? </p><ul><li>Think through the ultimate long-term vision of the product and the long-term defensibility of the business. And launch fast, as technology develops quickly. </li></ul><p><strong>38:40</strong> - What advice do you have for founders in terms of leveraging OpenAI, GPT-3, etc. while focusing on the long-term vision? </p><ul><li>Your vision and long-term view is separate from your day-to-day execution. Your long-term vision (i.e. the opportunity and what you&#x2019;re trying to create over the course of a decade) provides clarity around where you&#x2019;re trying to go and brings other people along with you, like your investors and employees. Day-to-day, you&#x2019;re focused and executing quickly &#x2013; and not always thinking about the ten year vision when you&#x2019;re building V1.</li></ul><p><strong>43:45</strong> - You decided to grow your team by acquiring Intellipse. And now, Mutiny has one of the larger engineering teams with production experience in modern marketing AI technologies. Why did you decide to pursue an acquisition? </p><ul><li>Founders have to look for inflection points where something happens in the market leading to the &#x201C;old way&#x201D; no longer being as good. And as a result, a much larger portion of the market is open to a new and better way. We&#x2019;re in a recession, and this is an inflection point for Mutiny. Companies need to convert every dollar to a customer, and Mutiny has built a product that makes marketing dollars more efficient. We can accelerate our road map with the acquisition of Intellipse</li></ul><p><strong>46:40</strong> - How did you know you wanted to work with the Intellipse team so much that you had to go through an acquisition?</p><ul><li>We were interested in the Intellipse team and the skills the team had developed. Their CTO and senior engineers had a unique experience with marketing AI and newer technologies, like GPT-3.</li><li>The personality and values of the founder spreads in an organization and becomes the company culture. After getting to know the founder and the free am, it was evident the two companies had a similar culture and shared values &#x2013; and we&#x2019;d be able to bring this team in and enhance our culture.</li></ul><p><strong>50:15</strong> - How long did it take to assess the culture? </p><ul><li>We spent the same amount of time with each individual as if we were hiring them onto the team through our typical recruiting process.</li></ul><p><strong>51:30</strong> - Do you expect to acquire more companies in the future? And how should founders and CEOs determine whether this strategy is right for their company? </p><ul><li>Be clear about your goals and why an acquisition is the right way to achieve those goals. When a company is working toward a similar goal &#x2013; building something we would have done ourselves &#x2013; it is a successful acquisition. With Intellipse, the team shared similar goals and company culture, and could accelerate our timing.</li><li>We want to hire founders onto our product team who are user focused and move quickly. Founders can focus their entrepreneurial energy on building a product and growing that business area within Mutiny. </li></ul><p><strong>54:55</strong> - What are your thoughts about how AI will impact the next ten years? </p><ul><li>There has been enough productization of backend AI technologies that as a founder you can tap into AI to accelerate the product you want to build and the value you give to customers. From a user and growth perspective, AI enables us to automate many of the tasks no one wants to do. And for those who aren&#x2019;t technical &#x2013; but understand what they are trying to do &#x2013; they can now be self sufficient.</li></ul>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Learnings of a CEO: Matt Schulman, Pave, on Hiring]]></title><description><![CDATA[Pave Founder and CEO Matt Schulman has created one of the most comprehensive and thorough recruiting processes, which has made him one of the most successful recruiters in the YC community.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/learnings-of-a-ceo-matt-schulman-pave/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6348578e2184dc0001eebf80</guid><category><![CDATA[YC Continuity]]></category><category><![CDATA[Advice]]></category><category><![CDATA[Founder Stories]]></category><category><![CDATA[Leadership]]></category><category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category><category><![CDATA[Growth]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Lindsay Amos]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 16:00:11 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/BlogTwitter-Image-Template--8-.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/BlogTwitter-Image-Template--8-.jpg" alt="Learnings of a CEO: Matt Schulman, Pave, on Hiring"><p>Welcome to the third edition of Learnings of a CEO. You can read previous editions <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog?query=learnings%20of%20a%20CEO">here</a>.</p><p><a href="https://www.pave.com/">Pave</a> helps companies plan, communicate, and benchmark employee compensation. Today, the company has 160 employees, more than 3,500 customers, and is valued at $1.6B. Founder and CEO <a href="https://twitter.com/matthewschulman?lang=en">Matt Schulman</a> has created one of the most comprehensive and thorough recruiting processes, which has made him one of the most successful recruiters in the YC community. We sat down with Matt to hear his insight on <a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/pave-2">building a team</a> in the early stages of his company and today as a CEO of a growth-stage company. </p><p><strong>Many of the first Pave employees were hired as a contractor before converting to a full-time employee. Would you recommend this strategy to founders? </strong></p><p>I strongly recommend the contract-to-hire setup in the early days of a startup, as it led me to have a 100% close rate with the candidates we wanted to convert to full-time. This strategy worked for two reasons: </p><p>1) By the end of the contract, the contractors had poured weeks of energy into the work &#x2013; learning the code base and investing their time &#x2013; and getting to know potential coworkers. This escalated their sense of commitment.</p><p>2) I was flexible on working hours &#x2013; open to them working nights or weekends. This made it easier for the candidates who were busy with full-time employment to say yes to working with Pave and earn extra income on the side. </p><p>To convince people who were employed to work for Pave as a contractor on top of their current job, I framed the process as a mutual evaluation. This is an opportunity to evaluate the company and come to a mutual decision at the end of 2, 4, or 6 weeks together &#x2013; no pressure. We paid them a fair market rate, and as mentioned, we were flexible on working hours. One contractor worked their day job until 5:00pm and then on Pave from 6:00pm-2:00am, for example. They were excited to be able to build something from the ground up and work closely with me at the earliest stage of the company &#x2013; which is another strategy I used to encourage people to work with us. </p><p>Before Pave, I was an engineer at Facebook and regularly worked on side projects. These projects were my fun, guilty pleasures because when I built something from the ground up, I felt an emotional attachment to the work. Usually engineers at large companies feel part of a machine, but when they build something full-stack from the ground up, there&#x2019;s a magical allure to that work. I gave those contractors ownership over the work and often jammed out with them &#x2013; working side by side at all hours. (One note: I did not have the contractors touch customer PII.) Within weeks, we&#x2019;d both know whether Pave would be a good fit, and if so, we were already committed to each other.</p><p><strong>What were you looking for in early employees? </strong></p><p>When starting to build out the team, I was given a tip that the first 10 hires would set the tone for the next 100. Because of this, I personally recruited 100% of the early Pave employees. I sourced people, took phone screens, went to dinner, coffee, and on walks with candidates, and spoke with them for hours on Zoom and Facetime. It was an all-encompassing process. But I found that early advice to be accurate: The first 10 employees are the most important aspect in the company&#x2019;s life cycle &#x2013; other than finding product-market fit &#x2013; and recruiting has to be the founder&#x2019;s priority.</p><p>When recruiting for the first ten employees, I wasn&#x2019;t looking for experts in specific areas but generalists with rapid career growth, passion for our mission, and a hunger to work. Those early employees readily tackled whatever fire we were facing that day from engineering work and sales to back office and HR. I also had a deep level of trust with those first ten hires, as they were all in my network. </p><p>Today, I still look for mission alignment and hunger but there are times I need to hire a specialist. I identify the tightest set of criteria for the role and only talk to people who fit that criteria. This is very different from the early days when I was solely looking for generalists who could fill multiple roles.</p><p><strong>How did you convince those early employees to join Pave? </strong></p><p>I always found ways to continue our conversation even when I could sense the candidate wanted to turn down the offer. I would do this by scheduling future conversations &#x2013; saying that I needed to share something new with them &#x2013; and then I would get to work writing a Google Doc that showed how I planned to invest in their career. We still use this strategy at Pave today, but it has evolved and is now affectionately called the collaborative Google Doc.</p><p>The collaborative Google Doc is shared with the candidate and used throughout the entire interview process. The document outlines expectations for the role and frames the interview process in stages, communicating which stage the candidate is in at any given time to ensure we are working within their ideal timeline. We encourage the candidate to comment and add their thoughts to the document, including feedback for me and their thoughts on the interview process.</p><p>As we get further into the interview process, I get more specific about what I&#x2019;m looking for in a candidate. And when we get even deeper, I write multiple pages on what I&#x2019;ve learned about their career aspirations through our conversations and backchanneling, and how I&#x2019;m going to support them. </p><p>When it comes to backchanneling for potential executive hires, I try to talk with at least 10 people and ask, &#x201C;If I have the privilege to be this person&apos;s manager, I want to set them up for the utmost success. What are your specific recommendations about the best ways to set this person up for success and unleash their full potential?&#x201D; This 360 review is shared with the candidate right before I deliver the compensation package. I outline what I learned about their strengths and weaknesses, and specific ways that I&#x2019;ll push them and support them.</p><p>When I communicate compensation, I lay out all the facts, including cash amount, equity (shares and dollar amount), and the benefits package. In addition, we also share:</p><ul><li>The salary band for the role (and implicitly their position in it).</li><li>The level that the employee will be in the organization, along with more information on our leveling framework and what each level means.</li><li>The methodology for determining the compensation, like the market data we use (75th percentile for similar stage companies).</li><li>Broader information on compensation philosophy, including how someone moves through the band, gets promoted, etc.</li><li>Additional info on equity: current preferred price, current post money valuation, details on vesting, PTE window, 409A price, and more &#x2013; essentially everything they need to determine the actual value of the grant.</li></ul><p>We&#x2019;re ultra transparent about compensation because compensation should not be a guessing game; people deserve to understand every aspect of their compensation package and how it was derived. I then offer to meet live to answer any questions or discuss feedback &#x2013; or ask them to leave their comments in the Google Doc. Most candidates will ask questions in the document, as it can be more approachable.</p><p><strong>For every open role at Pave, a Slack channel is created to drive urgency and ensure no detail goes missed. Tell me about this process. </strong></p><p>As a seed-stage company, I was creating Slack channels for every role. Today, Slack channels are created for roles that I&#x2019;m involved with &#x2013; like hiring a head of finance or VP of engineering. The process still looks the same, however. </p><p>I create a Slack channel for that role and add relevant stakeholders. Every morning I ask for an update. What&#x2019;s the movement? Have we sourced any more candidates? Have we talked with candidates X, Y, and Z? I do this to keep the process moving forward every day. I also post updates &#x2013; sharing with the team when I spoke with a reference, for example. When we extend an offer, I use this Slack channel to encourage stakeholders to reach out to the candidate through text messages or Loom videos. </p><p>Loom videos are an interesting medium. If you&#x2019;re a candidate and receive six Loom videos from different people at the company, it may feel bizarre and a bit overwhelming. But the videos show we are excited about the candidate and also gives insight into our energetic culture. </p><p><strong>You also review email copy and do drip campaigns for candidate outreach. Tell me about this. </strong></p><p>We have a pre-written email sequence that is sent from me or the hiring manager depending on the context, and then we use <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/gem">Gem</a> to automate this. The response rates for these campaigns are much higher than if the emails were coming from a recruiter. Before the emails are sent out, I&#x2019;ll spend 30 minutes personalizing 30 emails (one to two sentences at the onset of the email) that will be sent to target profiles. And then it&#x2019;s important you do a drip. If you only send one email, most of the time the candidate won&#x2019;t respond. I find sending a third email with a short message like, &#x201C;Hey, any thoughts?&#x201D; leads to the most responses. </p><p><strong>How do you think about where your job ends and your team begins when it comes to recruiting?</strong></p><p>Today, if I&#x2019;m not the hiring manager, I delegate and come in only at the end of the process for a sell call. The process looks vastly different if I&#x2019;m the hiring manager. I spend a lot of time reviewing resumes and identifying the top 25 profiles in the space. Every outreach to them is very personalized, and I have time to do this because I focus on quality over quantity of candidates. Quality over quantity was a big lesson for me, actually. At first, I would look at all inbound resumes and thousands of applicants. But I have come to realize that I have more success when I map out the market and find the top 25 candidates in the space. Then I&apos;ll find a way to get one of them in the door.</p><p><strong>Describe the ideal candidate for senior-level positions when Pave was a smaller company. </strong></p><p>As a company of 35 people, we didn&#x2019;t need managers who delegated &#x2013; which has merit at a later-stage company. We needed people who would personally take on the hard work. Often, first-time founders hire someone senior for optics reasons. Instead, you should look for someone earlier in their career who has grown at a crazy high slope &#x2013; often referred to in the tech industry as a high-slope candidate versus a Y-intercept candidate. There is a time and place for both types of hires, but as a 35-person startup, almost always go for the slope, not the high Y-intercept. And in some cases, you may meet exceptional candidates with both high slope and high Y-intercept. This is the dream case!</p><p>Another mistake first-time founders can make is rushing hires by trying to squeeze them in before a term sheet. Don&#x2019;t try to meet some arbitrary deadline or cliff date. If it takes six months or a year to hire an executive, that&#x2019;s ok &#x2013; wait for the right person.*<br><br><em>*This answer has been updated to clarify the founder&#x2019;s intention behind the statement.</em></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[YC ClimateTech Co-Founder Meetup]]></title><description><![CDATA[We’re excited to announce the first YC ClimateTech Co-Founder Meetup. If you’re interested in starting a ClimateTech startup and want to meet other potential co-founders in the space, register to attend by October 25th.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/yc-climatetech-co-founder-meetup/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63484a5f2184dc0001eebf38</guid><category><![CDATA[Startup School]]></category><category><![CDATA[YC Events]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Catheryn Li]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/climatetech2.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/climatetech2.jpeg" alt="YC ClimateTech Co-Founder Meetup"><p>We&#x2019;re excited to announce the first <a href="http://startupschool.org/climatetech-cofounder-meetup">YC ClimateTech Co-Founder Meetup</a>! It will take place at <strong>11am PT on Saturday, October 29, 2022</strong>. This event is for anyone interested in meeting a potential co-founder in the ClimateTech space.</p><!--kg-card-begin: html--><center>
<a class="ycdc-retro-btn ycdc-retro-btn-gold mt-[-10px] ml-[13px]" href="http://startupschool.org/climatetech-cofounder-meetup" style="text-decoration: none;" title="YC ClimateTech Co-Founder Meetup" target="_blank">Register to Attend</a>
</center><!--kg-card-end: html--><p>The 2-hour virtual program will feature a 30-minute conversation by YC Group Partner Gustaf Alstromer and YC ClimateTech founders on how to find a good startup idea, and how to make progress in ClimateTech. This will be followed by a speed-dating session on the <a href="http://ycombinator.com/cofounder-matching">YC co-founder matching platform</a>, in which founders are matched for 5-minute 1:1 conversations.</p><p><strong>Speakers</strong></p><p><strong>Gustaf Alstromer</strong>, YC Group Partner<br><strong>Paul Gross</strong>, Co-Founder &amp; CEO of <a href="https://remoracarbon.com/">Remora</a> (W21)<br><strong>Jose Ignacio</strong>, Co-Founder of <a href="https://www.waterplan.com/">Waterplan</a> (S21)<br><strong>Caroline McKeon &amp; Daria Balatsky,</strong> Co-Founders of <a href="https://www.alga.bio/">Alga Biosciences</a> (W22)</p><p>If you&#x2019;re interested in starting a ClimateTech startup and want to meet other potential co-founders in the space, we hope you join us!</p><p><strong>Registration is limited and closes on Tuesday, October 25th. </strong><a href="http://startupschool.org/climatetech-cofounder-meetup"><strong>Sign up to attend here</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Exclusive access to software deals for employees at YC companies]]></title><description><![CDATA[We are thrilled to announce that employees at YC companies can now leverage one of the major benefits previously only available to YC founders – YC Deals. Through YC Deals, employees have access to more than 100 discounts and exclusive offers on industry leading tools.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/announcing-yc-deals/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">633c56ed248d7f00015cff8c</guid><category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category><category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Oliver Ortlieb]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 16:00:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/ycombinator_YCDeals_02--1-.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/ycombinator_YCDeals_02--1-.png" alt="Exclusive access to software deals for employees at YC companies"><p>We are thrilled to announce that employees at YC companies can now leverage one of the major benefits previously only available to YC founders &#x2013; <a href="https://deals.ycombinator.com/">YC Deals</a>. Through YC Deals, employees have access to more than 100 discounts and exclusive offers on industry leading tools. There are already $500,000 worth of free credits and discounts available, and new deals are constantly being added.</p><p>We built YC Deals for our companies with a growing team. The founders still want to take advantage of the wide variety of discounts and free credits that YC companies receive, but their employees don&#x2019;t have access to Bookface (our internal platform for YC founders), where these exclusive deals are listed. Now any employee of a YC company can redeem these deals and help their company save money. </p><p>Building something new? There are dozens of dev tools like PostHog, Fivetran, and OneSignal. &#xA0;First HR or ops hire? Get Deel and Stable up and running at a discount. In charge of security? Check out Vanta. &#xA0;Also find deals on startup staples, like Gusto, GitHub, Algolia, and Amplitude. Help build and grow your company using world-class tools on a startup budget. </p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/Untitled-design.png" class="kg-image" alt="Exclusive access to software deals for employees at YC companies" loading="lazy" width="1600" height="919" srcset="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/size/w600/2022/10/Untitled-design.png 600w, https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/size/w1000/2022/10/Untitled-design.png 1000w, https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/10/Untitled-design.png 1600w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Employees at YC companies can access YC Deals by completing a simple email verification flow using their company email address <a href="https://deals.ycombinator.com/">here</a>.</p><p>If you&#x2019;d like to offer a deal to the YC community and their employees, you can submit one <a href="https://bookface.ycombinator.com/deals/new">here</a>. <br><br>Any additional questions about YC Deals? Visit our FAQs <a href="https://deals.ycombinator.com/faq">here</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[First Five Launches with Whatnot]]></title><description><![CDATA[Like every startup, the founders of Whatnot began with only an idea. YC’s Anu Hariharan sat down with the co-founder and CEO of Whatnot Grant LaFontaine to discuss their first five launches, and how they helped shape the company into a billion dollar marketplace today.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/first-five-launches-with-whatnot/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6335e2416c330f000113fac3</guid><category><![CDATA[Video]]></category><category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category><category><![CDATA[Company Building]]></category><category><![CDATA[Founder Stories]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Y Combinator]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 20:43:30 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-29-at-1.06.17-PM.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/Screen-Shot-2022-09-29-at-1.06.17-PM.png" alt="First Five Launches with Whatnot"><p>Today <a href="https://www.whatnot.com/">Whatnot</a> (<a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/whatnot">W20</a>) is a lively platform where collectors can buy, sell, go live, and geek out with other like-minded people across a wide variety of product categories. But, like every startup, the founders of Whatnot began with only an idea. YC&#x2019;s <a href="https://twitter.com/anuhariharan">Anu Hariharan</a> sat down with the co-founder and CEO of Whatnot <a href="https://twitter.com/grantlafontaine?lang=en">Grant LaFontaine</a> to discuss their first five launches.</p><p>The takeaways are below, and the interview can be watched on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OKD0IAcwMig">Youtube</a>.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OKD0IAcwMig?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen title="How Whatnot Growth Hacked To A Billion Dollar Marketplace"></iframe></figure><p><strong>(<a href="https://youtu.be/OKD0IAcwMig?t=40">00:40</a>) Launch #1 Takeaway</strong></p><p>Build the buyer side of the marketplace &#x2013; even if you have to hack your way there.</p><p>To build a great marketplace experience, both sides of the Whatnot marketplace had to be built out. Buyers would come, but only if sellers listed inventory. In the early days, the founders would list products on Whatnot that they didn&#x2019;t have (i.e. fake listing), and when the item would sell, they&#x2019;d purchase it on eBay.</p><p><strong>(<a href="https://youtu.be/OKD0IAcwMig?t=266">04:26</a>) Launch #2 Takeaway</strong></p><p>Increase your returning visitor rate through creative marketing campaigns.</p><p>Whatnot launched with only a website and found it was not engaging enough for consumers to visit frequently. To solve this, they developed an app and a growth channel to push traffic to the app, called <a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/?v=2488270838055833">Whatnot Drop</a>. Whatnot Drop was a raffle for Funko Grail, and consumers could load up on raffle tickets by sharing referral code and content assets that would draw people back to Whatnot.</p><p><strong>(<a href="https://youtu.be/OKD0IAcwMig?t=377">06:17</a>) Launch #3 Takeaway</strong></p><p>Work with trusted influencers in the community.</p><p>Whatnot worked with a Funko Pop influencer who was trusted by the Funko Pop fanbase. The influencer created a Youtube video talking about their experience on Whatnot, which helped the audience trust Whatnot as a reputable marketplace for collectibles.</p><p><strong>(<a href="https://youtu.be/OKD0IAcwMig?t=439">07:19</a>) Launch #4 Takeaway</strong></p><p>Build the seller side of the marketplace by encouraging high sell-through rates.</p><p>Whatnot delivered more sales to sellers by building a cross listing tool. Every seller on Whatnot could easily have their inventory cross listed to their eBay account &#x2013; delivering more sales for sellers. </p><p><strong>(<a href="https://youtu.be/OKD0IAcwMig?t=626">10:26</a>) Launch #5 Takeaway</strong></p><p>Experiment with new content formats to drive traffic.</p><p>Whatnot built and launched a live shop feature &#x2013; a first in the collections industry. The seller tool was built into the product, so it was simple for sellers to go live on Whatnot and talk about their products to the community.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Women Engineers in Startups: Tess's Story]]></title><description><![CDATA[This October, we are hosting our second annual Women Engineers in Startups program. One participant in our first cohort, Tess Huelskamp, accepted a role at Middesk (YC W19). She shared her experience and advice for thinking about joining a startup.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/women-engineers-in-startups-tess/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6335a9276c330f000113fa77</guid><category><![CDATA[YC Events]]></category><category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category><category><![CDATA[Women Founders]]></category><category><![CDATA[Work at a Startup]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Y Combinator]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2022 15:49:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/IMG_0053.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/IMG_0053.jpeg" alt="Women Engineers in Startups: Tess&apos;s Story"><p>Last year we launched the first *<a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2022">Women Engineers in Startups</a> series, and our goal was to encourage more women to consider working at high-growth startups.</p><p>Why?</p><p>At YC, most of us have worked at or started startups, and they&#x2019;ve changed our lives for the better. We&#x2019;ve seen, firsthand, the impact they can have on one&#x2019;s life and career. The amount you learn is immense, and a lot of early startup employees go on to start their own companies. </p><p>We believe the opportunity should be explored by every hard working, ambitious person.</p><p>Yet, when we spoke to our founders, we learned that very few women engineers apply for jobs at YC companies. We wondered whether there were misconceptions about startups that we could help clear up, or whether there were resources we could build to connect more women to startup opportunities. </p><p>So, we brought together a cohort of women engineers and introduced them to YC founders, engineering managers, recruiters and women who had joined YC startups as early engineers. They came together for three weeks, learned about what startups are looking for, what the work/life balance was like at various companies, and what they should think about and ask when considering companies and roles. </p><p>At the end of the first session, we were delighted to see a few women from that first cohort accept roles at YC companies. </p><p>One participant in that first cohort, Tess Huelskamp, accepted a role at <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/middesk">Middesk</a> (YC W19), a fast-growing company that helps b2b financial services companies verify business customers. She shared her experience and advice for thinking about joining a startup here: </p><blockquote><em>Prior to working at my startup Middesk, I worked for a few years on Dropbox&apos;s Sharing team on a lot of backend changes to make it easier to share files and folders within Dropbox. </em><br><br><em>After a few years at Dropbox, I had learned a lot about how to build and ship code, but my learning was slowing. I always knew that I wanted to work at a startup before I moved home to the Midwest, and I figured this was the time to do it.</em><br><br><em>Before participating in the YC Women Eng in Startup series I didn&apos;t know a lot about the startup lifecycle. I didn&apos;t know what &quot;pre-&quot; vs. &quot;post-seed&quot; meant and I didn&apos;t know what type of work startups do as they move from trying to find product-market fit to scaling up their company. It helped me better identify the stage and type of company I wanted to work at.</em><br><br><em>When I started my job search, I knew I wanted to work at a post-Series A company that had a great culture, healthy work-life balance, and an interesting product. I found Middesk through the </em><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/"><em>Work at a Startup</em></a><em> job board and took an informational call to learn more. As I was interviewing, I got a great vibe from the team at Middesk and respected all of the people I talked to.</em><br><br><em>I&apos;ve been happily surprised with the breadth of work I&apos;ve been able to do at an earlier stage company.</em><br><br><em>Established companies already have a lot of key features built, so the impact you can have is limited to improving an already existing feature. At an earlier stage company, I&apos;ve been able to have a huge impact on my company by scaling, improving core business flows and also building multiple features from the ground up.</em><br><br><em>Earlier in my career, I was scared to move to a startup because I didn&apos;t think that I knew enough about engineering to be able to contribute to a startup. If I were to do my career over again, I would&apos;ve left a larger company as soon as I felt my growth stalling out, because I could&apos;ve easily handled working at a startup once I had learned how to ship projects at a larger company.</em></blockquote><p><strong>We&#x2019;re hosting the second Women Engineers in Startups series this fall. Learn more about it </strong><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/women-engineers-in-startups"><strong>here</strong></a><strong>.</strong><br><br><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2022/?utm_source=ycblog"><strong>Apply to participate by October 7</strong></a><strong>. </strong></p><!--kg-card-begin: html--><center>
<a class="ycdc-retro-btn ycdc-retro-btn-gold mt-[-10px] ml-[13px]" href="https://www.ycombinator.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2022/?utm_source=ycblog" style="text-decoration: none;" title="Women Engineers in Startups" target="_blank">Apply Now</a>
</center><!--kg-card-end: html--><p>* <em>We use an inclusive definition of &#x201C;women&#x201D; and welcome trans women as well as genderqueer and non-binary people who identify as women or femme in any way to attend this event.</em></p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2022/?utm_source=ycblog"><img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/6.jpg" class="kg-image" alt="Women Engineers in Startups: Tess&apos;s Story" loading="lazy" width="1200" height="630" srcset="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/size/w600/2022/09/6.jpg 600w, https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/size/w1000/2022/09/6.jpg 1000w, https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/6.jpg 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></a></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[YC’s 1st Health and Bio Summit]]></title><description><![CDATA[We’re excited to announce the first YC Health and Bio Summit that will take place in San Francisco on October 21, 2022. 
The half day conference will feature bio and healthcare founders and investors who will tell their stories and share advice for entrepreneurs who are just getting started. ]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/ycs-1st-health-and-bio-summit/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6320f7135142100001443588</guid><category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category><category><![CDATA[YC Events]]></category><category><![CDATA[Biotech]]></category><category><![CDATA[Healthcare]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Surbhi Sarna]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 15:55:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/biosummit.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/biosummit.jpeg" alt="YC&#x2019;s 1st Health and Bio Summit"><p>We&#x2019;re excited to announce the first <a href="https://ychealthandbiosummit2022.splashthat.com/">YC Health and Bio Summit</a> that will take place in San Francisco on October 21, 2022. </p><p>The half day conference will feature bio and healthcare founders and investors who will tell their stories and share advice for entrepreneurs who are just getting started. </p><p><strong>Speakers include:</strong><br>Vineeta Agarwala, General Partner, <a href="https://a16z.com/">a16z</a><br>Ivana Djuretic, Co-founder and CSO, <a href="https://asherbio.com/">Asher Bio</a><br>Rachel Rea, Sr. Director, <a href="https://www.medtronic.com/us-en/index.html">Medtronic</a><br>Cami Samuels, Partner, <a href="https://www.venrock.com/">Venrock</a><br>Tanay Tandon, Co-founder and CEO of <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/athelas">Athelas</a><br>Sid Viswanathan, Co-founder and CEO, <a href="https://truepill.com/">TruePill</a><br>and more to be announced<br><br>When people think of Y Combinator, what often comes to mind first are the software companies that got their start with YC &#x2013; companies like Airbnb, DoorDash and Stripe. But within the last 5 years, YC has funded over 500 healthcare and bio startups, 9 of which are now billion dollar companies. We&#x2019;ve quietly become the largest seed stage funder of bio startups in the world. We&apos;re looking forward to sharing what we&#x2019;ve learned from funding hundreds of founders and working alongside them as their companies have grown. <br><br>If you&#x2019;re in the early stages of starting a bio startup or are considering starting one, we hope you join us. <a href="https://ychealthandbiosummit2022.splashthat.com/">Sign up to attend here</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Meet the YC Summer 2022 Batch]]></title><description><![CDATA[For the Summer 2022 batch, we received 19,000 applications from founders around the world and funded 240. Today, these founders will present their companies to an invite-only audience of investors at our 35th Demo Day. Here’s what we saw in the S22 batch.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/meet-the-yc-summer-2022-batch/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63176fa2a32f070001d502cf</guid><category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category><category><![CDATA[Batch Stats]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Seibel]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 15:00:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/ycombinator_announcement_1200x603-1.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/ycombinator_announcement_1200x603-1.png" alt="Meet the YC Summer 2022 Batch"><p>For the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/yc-s20-remote-batch/">first time</a> since the Winter 2020 batch, the Summer 2022 batch was in person. The batch kicked off with an in-person retreat followed by weekly meetups in San Francisco and around the world. And soon after Demo Day, we&#x2019;re hosting an end-of-batch celebration with the entire <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies">YC community</a>. </p><p>The program was still remote friendly with office hours and batch talks online, but we encouraged all teams who could to move to the Bay Area to participate. About 30% of the batch moved to the Bay Area during the 3-month program, and about 23% were already in the Bay Area when they applied to YC. &#xA0;</p><p>For the Summer 2022 batch, we received 19,000 applications from founders around the world and funded <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22">240</a>. Today, these founders will present their companies to an invite-only audience of investors at our 35th <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/demoday/faq/">Demo Day</a>. Here&#x2019;s what we saw in the S22 batch:</p><ul><li>50% of the batch applied more than once</li><li>43% of the batch were accepted with only an idea</li><li>36% of the batch raised money before YC</li><li>71% of the batch had zero revenue before YC</li><li>7% had more than $50k of monthly revenue when accepted</li></ul><p>S22 companies are building in <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22">more than 100 verticals</a>. There isn&#x2019;t an industry being touched by software that we don&#x2019;t fund. During the batch, we divide the companies into 33 small groups that are organized by vertical. The groups meet for bi-weekly office hours led by 18 group partners and visiting group partners. During these group office hours, founders help each other and get the benefit of an intimate setting within the larger batch. At a high level:</p><ul><li>39% in B2B/Enterprise SaaS</li><li>21% in Fintech</li><li>13% in DevTools</li><li>9% in Consumer</li><li>9% in Healthcare</li><li>3% in Proptech</li><li>3% in Aerospace</li><li>2% in Climate, Energy, or Sustainability</li><li>1% in Education </li></ul><p>The companies come from 34 countries around the world that combined have over 3 billion inhabitants. About 42% are outside of the U.S. &#x2013; and a sign of the times, 35% of the companies are remote and 37% are remote friendly. The top countries represented include: </p><ul><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=United%20States%20of%20America">United States</a>: 140 startups</li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=India">India</a>: 19 startups</li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=United%20Kingdom">United Kingdom</a>: 11 startups</li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=Israel">Israel</a>: 8 startups</li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=Canada">Canada</a>: 6 startups</li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=Germany">Germany</a>: 6 startups</li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=Mexico">Mexico</a>: 6 startups</li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=France">France</a>: 6 startups</li><li><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=S22&amp;regions=Nigeria">Nigeria</a>: 5 startups</li></ul><p>New this batch, we added &#x201C;multiracial&#x201D; as an option when collecting demographic information. While this change makes it harder for us to measure our progress compared to prior batches, this addition was long overdue. Here is the demographic breakdown for the S22 batch:</p><ul><li>13% Asian</li><li>3% Black</li><li>6% Hispanic or Latino</li><li>5% Middle Eastern or North African</li><li>8% Multiracial</li><li>15% South Asian</li><li>29% White</li></ul><p>Additionally, 15% of the companies have a woman founder and 9% of the founders are women.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-image-card"><img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/22-YC-Retreat-Day-1-Welcome_39.jpeg" class="kg-image" alt="Meet the YC Summer 2022 Batch" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1331" srcset="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/size/w600/2022/09/22-YC-Retreat-Day-1-Welcome_39.jpeg 600w, https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/size/w1000/2022/09/22-YC-Retreat-Day-1-Welcome_39.jpeg 1000w, https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/size/w1600/2022/09/22-YC-Retreat-Day-1-Welcome_39.jpeg 1600w, https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/size/w2400/2022/09/22-YC-Retreat-Day-1-Welcome_39.jpeg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[YC Jobs Series: Women Engineers in Startups]]></title><description><![CDATA[This fall, we are hosting our second annual Women Engineers in Startups program. The program brings together a cohort of women engineers who are interested in finding roles at fast growing startups.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/women-engineers-in-startups/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">63121593a32f070001d5027b</guid><category><![CDATA[YC Events]]></category><category><![CDATA[Women Founders]]></category><category><![CDATA[Jobs]]></category><category><![CDATA[Female Founders]]></category><category><![CDATA[Event]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Paige Omura]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 15:37:26 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/BlogTwitter-Image-Template.jpeg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/09/BlogTwitter-Image-Template.jpeg" alt="YC Jobs Series: Women Engineers in Startups"><p>This fall, we are hosting our second annual <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2022">Women Engineers in Startups</a> program. The program brings together a cohort of women engineers who are interested in finding roles at fast growing startups.</p><p>YC will host a 3-week-long series where participants meet once a week for two-hour sessions. During these sessions, you will hear from women founders, women who joined YC startups as early engineers and engineering managers, and startup recruiters. You&#x2019;ll build a community of peers and learn about building a career at a tech startup. The program will culminate in interviews at YC startups who are excited to hire their next engineers.</p><p>Topics discussed will include:</p><ul><li>Why join a startup and what are the pros and cons</li><li>How to determine where you should work and what should you look for in a startup and founding team</li><li>How to prepare for the interview process &#x2013; including live feedback on your interview skills from technical recruiters</li></ul><p>Each week, we will also host intimate breakout sessions with founders, engineers and hiring managers to dig deeper into startups and navigating your career. Our speakers come from a variety of YC startups &#x2013; from early stage to growth stage &#x2013; including:</p><ul><li><a href="https://twitter.com/jalehr">Jaleh Rezaei</a>, Co-founder &amp; CEO of <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/mutiny">Mutiny</a></li><li><a href="https://twitter.com/ReshmaKhilnani">Reshma Khilnani</a>, Co-founder &amp; CEO of <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/medplum">Medplum</a>, prior co-founder &amp; CTO of MedXT and YC Visiting Group Partner</li><li><a href="https://twitter.com/sdianahu">Diana Hu</a>, Co-founder &amp; CTO of <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/escher-reality">Escher Reality</a> and YC Visiting Group Partner</li></ul><p>If you are a software engineer who is considering or already looking for your next role, this series is for you. We want to help you transition to a startup.</p><p>To apply for the program, visit <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2022">YC&#x2019;s Work at a Startup</a>, create a profile, and <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2022">apply to the program</a> by September 13th. (Note that profiles are visible to YC founders and hiring managers at YC startups. If you&#x2019;re not ready to share your profile, please specify so on the application.)</p><!--kg-card-begin: html--><center>
<a class="ycdc-retro-btn ycdc-retro-btn-gold mt-[-10px] ml-[13px]" href="https://www.ycombinator.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2022/?utm_source=ycblog" style="text-decoration: none;" title="Women Engineers in Startups" target="_blank">Apply Now</a>
</center><!--kg-card-end: html--><p><em>At YC, we use an inclusive definition of &#x201C;women&#x201D; and welcome trans women as well as genderqueer and non-binary people who identify as women or femme in any way.</em></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Welcome Home, Garry Tan]]></title><description><![CDATA[Today we're excited to announce that Garry Tan will be YC's next president and CEO. He is a visionary and builder — having founded the earliest blogging platform and advised hundreds of startups over the last decade.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/welcome-home-garry-tan/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6308ee710539de0001b3c12d</guid><category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Geoff Ralston]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 13:04:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/08/BlogTwitter-Image-Template--8-.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/08/BlogTwitter-Image-Template--8-.jpg" alt="Welcome Home, Garry Tan"><p>Dear YC Community,</p><p>Today we announced that I am stepping down from my role as YC&#x2019;s President and CEO at the end of this year. I am leaving YC, but I&#x2019;m not actually the retiring type and am looking forward to some to-be-discovered adventures. Although the time is right for me to leave and I&#x2019;m sad to move on from YC, I am excited to announce that Garry Tan will be YC&#x2019;s next President and CEO.</p><p>We have an amazing organization and it deserves a fantastic leader, so let me explain why I am so confident that YC will thrive under Garry&#x2019;s leadership. All of us at YC know Garry well. He was a YC founder in the summer of 2008 and is both a terrific hacker and a brilliant designer. Garry is also one of the most trustworthy, kind, and likable people I know. </p><p>After earning a degree in computer engineering from Stanford, Garry was an engineer at Palantir and then created one of the earliest and best-designed blogging platforms, <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/posterous">Posterous</a>. After selling Posterous to Twitter, Garry joined YC as a partner - almost exactly when I also joined PG, Jessica, and co. For the next five years we worked together advising startups. Garry also found the time to build some of the core internal software (including Bookface!) still used at YC. In 2015, Garry left YC to focus on Initialized Capital, the venture fund he co-founded. Over the years at Initialized, Garry showed his investing expertise and <a href="https://news.crunchbase.com/business/initialized-capital-garry-tan-seed-unicorn-investor-under-the-hood/">continued supporting</a> YC companies. He built a superb team there which will continue investing in great companies while Garry comes back home to YC.</p><p>Throughout his career, Garry has impressed everyone around him with his intelligence, his affability, and his desire to get things done or, as he might say, &#x201C;let&#x2019;s get building!&#x201D; And while showing that he is a leader who understands the details of building and running a business, he also demonstrates his extraordinary communications skills, with hundreds of thousands of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/GarryTan">YouTube</a> followers who watch his many videos on startups, jobs, and life. </p><p>My goal has been to cement YC as an institution that will endure for decades &#x2013; not only through <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/building-for-the-future/">organizational changes</a> but by leading a team that has scaled the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/scaling-yc">community</a> we bring together, the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/about">products</a> and <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/ycs-500-000-standard-deal">capital</a> we provide to startups, and the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/yc-w21-remote-batch">software</a> we build. Garry, the visionary hacker, designer, and builder who has described how YC is &#x201C;engraved on his heart&#x201D; believes in this future and is precisely the right person to take over as YC&#x2019;s chief executive.</p><p>The last decade and more have been transformative for me. There are so many amazing startups I have had the privilege of working with and watching make products people want. And I&#x2019;ve learned so much from the brilliant people at YC. There are perhaps millions of people who can honestly say PG taught them everything important that they know about startups. I&#x2019;m one of them. Thank you PG, Jessica, Robert, and Trevor for creating the platform built to help founders figure out how to make something people want. </p><p>Garry, you&#x2019;re up! I can&#x2019;t wait to watch you lead YC as we continue to fund amazing startups and help founders build the epic companies of the decades to come.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Y Combinator Top Companies - August 2022]]></title><description><![CDATA[Today we’re excited to release an update to the YC Top Companies list. There are now 15 public YC companies, 316 private YC companies that are valued at over $150M, and over 80 are valued at over $1B.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/y-combinator-top-companies-aug-2022/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">630443393abd0500014104a3</guid><category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category><category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category><category><![CDATA[YC Continuity]]></category><category><![CDATA[Founder Stories]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Y Combinator]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 15:55:00 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/08/BlogTwitter-Image-Template.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/08/BlogTwitter-Image-Template.png" alt="Y Combinator Top Companies - August 2022"><p>Today we&#x2019;re excited to release an update to the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies">YC Top Companies</a> list. </p><p>The list includes private and acquired companies valued at $150M or more as of July 31, 2022, and is sorted by valuation (YC&#x2019;s public companies are featured <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies/public">here</a>). </p><p>We&#x2019;ve also published an update to the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies/breakthrough">YC Breakthrough Companies</a> list which highlights fast-growing companies that have received significant additional investment from YC. You can read more about some of the Breakthrough Companies <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies/featured">here</a>, and congrats to <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies/breadfast">Breadfast</a>, the newest Breakthrough addition.</p><p>Here are some stats about the August 2022 YC Top Companies list:</p><ul><li>There are now 15 <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies/public">public</a> YC companies, 316 private YC companies that are valued at over $150M, and over 80 are valued at over $1B.</li><li>63 companies have been added to the list since our last update in February 2022.</li><li>76% of the companies consider themselves remote or remote friendly. 59% have an HQ located in the Bay Area.</li><li>YC W16 has the largest percentage of companies from their batch on the YC Top Companies list. See the YC W16 companies <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies?batch=W16&amp;top_company=true">here</a>.</li></ul><p>Here&#x2019;s a sector breakdown of our Top Companies:</p><!--kg-card-begin: markdown--><p>B2B Software and Services: 43.3%<br>
Healthcare: 11.5%<br>
Education: 2.7%<br>
Consumer: 13.3%<br>
Financial Technology: 18.8%<br>
Real Estate and Construction: 3.0%<br>
Industrials: 7.0%<br>
Government: .3%</p>
<!--kg-card-end: markdown--><p>Congrats to all of the YC founders who are building these amazing companies! <br><br>Meet some of the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies/featured">featured companies</a> on the list and learn more about the founders, their missions, and the predictions they have for the future. To see a full list of YC companies, visit the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies">YC Startup Directory</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[First Five Hires with PostHog]]></title><description><![CDATA[PostHog (YC W20) is a suite of open source product analytic tools that companies can host themselves. YC’s Anu Hariharan sat down with the co-founder and CEO of PostHog James Hawkins to discuss hiring their first five employees.]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/first-five-hires-with-posthog/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">62fbab82b9e394000104de02</guid><category><![CDATA[Video]]></category><category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category><category><![CDATA[Founder Stories]]></category><category><![CDATA[Company Building]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Y Combinator]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 14:41:30 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/08/S05E02_Thumbnail.png" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/08/S05E02_Thumbnail.png" alt="First Five Hires with PostHog"><p><a href="https://posthog.com/">PostHog</a> (<a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/posthog">YC W20</a>) is a suite of open source product analytic tools that companies can host themselves. YC&#x2019;s <a href="https://twitter.com/anuhariharan">Anu Hariharan</a> sat down with the co-founder and CEO of PostHog <a href="https://twitter.com/james406">James Hawkins</a> to discuss hiring their first five employees: </p><ol><li>A full-stack engineer</li><li>Software engineer</li><li>Data engineer</li><li>Graphic designer</li><li>Software engineer</li></ol><p>James discusses each hire and dives into the unique ways they found their earliest employees, the importance of writing a company handbook, and lessons learned along the way. Today, PostHog has a <a href="http://posthog.com/careers">team of 30</a>. <br><br>You can watch the interview <a href="https://youtu.be/gF1NGUsjxLU">on Youtube</a>.</p><figure class="kg-card kg-embed-card"><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gF1NGUsjxLU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen title="Most Transparent Startup Ever? Here&#x2019;s Its First Five Hires"></iframe></figure>]]></content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[YC Founder Firesides: Gusto on building for new verticals]]></title><description><![CDATA[Today, more than 200,000 businesses use Gusto for payroll, employee benefits, talent management, and more. And with the recent addition of Gusto Embedded, developers now use Gusto’s APIs and pre-build UI  flows to embed payroll, tax filing, and payments infrastructure into products. ]]></description><link>https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/yc-founder-firesides-gusto-on-building-for-new-verticals/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">62fa7b87ab52db0001d3b656</guid><category><![CDATA[YC Events]]></category><category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category><category><![CDATA[Interview]]></category><category><![CDATA[YC Continuity]]></category><category><![CDATA[Founder Stories]]></category><category><![CDATA[Podcast]]></category><category><![CDATA[Growth]]></category><category><![CDATA[Leadership]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Y Combinator]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 15 Aug 2022 18:32:19 GMT</pubDate><media:content url="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/08/BlogTwitter-Image-Template--5-.jpg" medium="image"/><content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/images/2022/08/BlogTwitter-Image-Template--5-.jpg" alt="YC Founder Firesides: Gusto on building for new verticals"><p><a href="https://gusto.com/">Gusto</a> (<a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies/gusto">YC W12</a>) provides growing businesses with everything to take care of their team. Today, more than 200,000 businesses use Gusto for payroll, employee benefits, talent management, and more. And with the recent addition of <a href="https://embedded.gusto.com/">Gusto Embedded</a>, developers now use Gusto&#x2019;s APIs and pre-build UI &#xA0;flows to embed payroll, tax filing, and payments infrastructure into products. </p><p>Last week, Gusto <a href="https://gusto.com/company-news/gusto-embedded-one-year-in-fueling-smb-tech-success-at-scale-with-critical-compliance-">announced</a> they have dozens of new partners across verticals like laundromats, health &amp; beauty, and construction building with Gusto Embedded. The company also announced they are making it easier for software providers to keep their payroll customers in compliance.</p><p>YC&#x2019;s <a href="https://twitter.com/anuhariharan/status/1557784730543632384">Anu Hariharan</a> sat down with Gusto co-founder and CPO <a href="https://twitter.com/tomerlondon">Tomer London</a> to talk about building for new customer segments and the future of embedded finance &#x2014; sharing advice for startup founders and CEOs along the way. </p><div class="kg-card kg-audio-card"><img src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/media/2022/08/Founder-Fireside---Tomer-London--Gusto-_thumb.jpg?v=1660587475243" alt="YC Founder Firesides: Gusto on building for new verticals" class="kg-audio-thumbnail"><div class="kg-audio-thumbnail placeholder kg-audio-hide"><svg width="24" height="24" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" d="M7.5 15.33a.75.75 0 1 0 0 1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0-1.5Zm-2.25.75a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 4.5 0 2.25 2.25 0 0 1-4.5 0ZM15 13.83a.75.75 0 1 0 0 1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0-1.5Zm-2.25.75a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 4.5 0 2.25 2.25 0 0 1-4.5 0Z"/><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" d="M14.486 6.81A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 17.25 9v5.579a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0v-5.58a.75.75 0 0 0-.932-.727.755.755 0 0 1-.059.013l-4.465.744a.75.75 0 0 0-.544.72v6.33a.75.75 0 0 1-1.5 0v-6.33a2.25 2.25 0 0 1 1.763-2.194l4.473-.746Z"/><path fill-rule="evenodd" clip-rule="evenodd" d="M3 1.5a.75.75 0 0 0-.75.75v19.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75.75h18a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75V5.133a.75.75 0 0 0-.225-.535l-.002-.002-3-2.883A.75.75 0 0 0 18 1.5H3ZM1.409.659A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3 0h15a2.25 2.25 0 0 1 1.568.637l.003.002 3 2.883a2.25 2.25 0 0 1 .679 1.61V21.75A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 21 24H3a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25-2.25V2.25c0-.597.237-1.169.659-1.591Z"/></svg></div><div class="kg-audio-player-container"><audio src="https://www.ycombinator.com/blog/content/media/2022/08/Founder-Fireside---Tomer-London--Gusto-.mp3" preload="metadata"></audio><div class="kg-audio-title">Founder Firesides: Gusto&apos;s Tomer London on building for new verticals</div><div class="kg-audio-player"><button class="kg-audio-play-icon"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewbox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M23.14 10.608 2.253.164A1.559 1.559 0 0 0 0 1.557v20.887a1.558 1.558 0 0 0 2.253 1.392L23.14 13.393a1.557 1.557 0 0 0 0-2.785Z"/></svg></button><button class="kg-audio-pause-icon kg-audio-hide"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewbox="0 0 24 24"><rect x="3" y="1" width="7" height="22" rx="1.5" ry="1.5"/><rect x="14" y="1" width="7" height="22" rx="1.5" ry="1.5"/></svg></button><span class="kg-audio-current-time">0:00</span><div class="kg-audio-time">/<span class="kg-audio-duration">118:07</span></div><input type="range" class="kg-audio-seek-slider" max="100" value="0"><button class="kg-audio-playback-rate">1&#xD7;</button><button class="kg-audio-unmute-icon"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewbox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M15.189 2.021a9.728 9.728 0 0 0-7.924 4.85.249.249 0 0 1-.221.133H5.25a3 3 0 0 0-3 3v2a3 3 0 0 0 3 3h1.794a.249.249 0 0 1 .221.133 9.73 9.73 0 0 0 7.924 4.85h.06a1 1 0 0 0 1-1V3.02a1 1 0 0 0-1.06-.998Z"/></svg></button><button class="kg-audio-mute-icon kg-audio-hide"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewbox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M16.177 4.3a.248.248 0 0 0 .073-.176v-1.1a1 1 0 0 0-1.061-1 9.728 9.728 0 0 0-7.924 4.85.249.249 0 0 1-.221.133H5.25a3 3 0 0 0-3 3v2a3 3 0 0 0 3 3h.114a.251.251 0 0 0 .177-.073ZM23.707 1.706A1 1 0 0 0 22.293.292l-22 22a1 1 0 0 0 0 1.414l.009.009a1 1 0 0 0 1.405-.009l6.63-6.631A.251.251 0 0 1 8.515 17a.245.245 0 0 1 .177.075 10.081 10.081 0 0 0 6.5 2.92 1 1 0 0 0 1.061-1V9.266a.247.247 0 0 1 .073-.176Z"/></svg></button><input type="range" class="kg-audio-volume-slider" max="100" value="100"></div></div></div><p>You can also listen on <a href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/0FTnE08QzuCg6I21S4PB8e?si=ShDfsjwnRWKYH0LjwzI-rg">Spotify</a>, <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/159-yc-founder-firesides-gusto-on-building-for-new/id1236907421?i=1000576161014">Apple Podcasts</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/i/spaces/1dRKZldrvOzJB?s=20">Twitter</a>.</p><p><strong>1:28</strong> - Tomer describes Gusto Embedded and the complexities behind compliance.</p><ul><li>Gusto Embedded takes ten years of Gusto&#x2019;s experience building payroll software and compliance and makes it available to any software company wanting to ship their own payroll product to the market. </li></ul><p><strong>5:00 </strong>- Why did you decide to pursue startups as the company&#x2019;s first target audience? How did you think about customer segments in that first year? </p><p><em>Over the last ten years, Gusto has scaled to build for multiple customer segments &#x2013; starting with startups, then SMBs, accountants, and now with Gusto Embedded Payroll, developers who are embedding payroll directly into their software. </em></p><ul><li>When you have a grand vision, where do you start as a founder? Choose a customer segment. Make sure you choose a segment where 1) they have an important customer problem, 2) the product you are building solves that problem, and 3) you can reach your customer. </li></ul><p><strong>9:30 </strong>- Who were your competitors in the early days? </p><ul><li>The old, traditional payroll solutions, which were complex. With Gusto, <em>anyone</em> can run payroll at <em>any time</em>. Gusto also focuses on employees, a critical part of the system, by building a great payroll experience for them. </li></ul><p><strong>11:30 </strong>- Why did you decide to build for SMBs after startups? </p><ul><li>Look at your current customer base and learn from customers adjacent to the market you want to expand into. When you do expand into another vertical, make sure you maintain that early customer love. &#xA0;</li></ul><p><strong>14:45</strong> - How did you maintain the customer love of the existing customer segment? </p><ul><li>Think about your long-term vision and don&#x2019;t put yourself in a corner when you want to move to the next segment. </li></ul><p><strong>17:00</strong> - Most startups find it hard to tackle the SMB market. Why do you think this is the case? </p><ul><li>Traditionally SMBs are hard to reach and use incomplete or manual solutions. Since 2000 an entire generation of business owners had to learn to trust online financial services. Today, SMBs are online and looking for solutions.</li></ul><p><strong>22:25 </strong>- What is different about serving SMBs as a customer versus startups? </p><ul><li>Startups come and go, and the real economics come from the big winners. Focusing on startups is a good place to start your journey, but think about how to scale with them.</li><li>There are more small businesses than startups, and they are around for a long time &#x2013; but most don&#x2019;t grow to thousands of employees. You need to build a business model that works with that dynamic. </li></ul><p><strong>27:00 - </strong>Why did you pursue developers and how did you decide to service them? </p><ul><li>For many verticals, it is much better to have an all-in-one platform to run your small businesses. But payroll is really hard to build yourself. Gusto Embedded helps partners deliver a more integrated solution for customers without investing the several years and tens of millions of dollars.</li></ul><p><strong>29:00 </strong>- Gusto went from directly acquiring small businesses as customers to creating an embedded solution &#x2013; essentially &#xA0;&#x201C;giving up&#x201D; the relationship with the customer. How did you think about that? </p><ul><li>Evaluate the future of the industry and don&#x2019;t ignore reality. Be the one to create that future. In this case, many payroll customers want all-in-one solutions. We can either try to meet those needs directly, or empower hundreds of partners to customize unique solutions.</li></ul><p><strong>33:00 - </strong>How should founders think about who to partner with? When should founders build directly for the industry and when should they go the embedded route? </p><ul><li>Think about the unique insight you have in the business you&#x2019;re creating and make sure you own your destiny around that insight.</li><li>For your customer, what does a successful product look like, and could you partner with a company to fulfill those needs.</li><li>Your product must be high-quality. You have to put enough resources behind whatever you own. For everything else, you must ensure you bring in the right partner. It&#x2019;s all about the end-to-end experience. </li></ul><p><strong>39:30</strong> - Gusto now makes it easier for software providers to bake compliance into embedded payroll. Tomer, I think developers looking at a payroll API would assume that compliance is baked in. But there are often steps companies have to take beyond just calling APIs. Tell us if that assumption holds.</p><ul><li>Regulation can change every quarter and every year. This is built into the product. We protect the customer and make it easy for developers to ship something quickly that is compliant for the long term.</li><li>One third of the companies in the U.S. get fined for mistakes on payroll. </li></ul><p><strong>43:00 - </strong>Compliance is the hardest part of payroll to build and ultimately has to be right. It took ten years of experience in compliance to launch this into Gusto Embedded Payroll. What advice do you have for founders who are building complicated, yet essential, components for an industry?</p><ul><li>Determine the parts of your product that are highly regulated and which areas are not. Build a culture that ensures quality-first in those highly-regulated areas, as well as a culture where people can iterate quickly in other areas. You can&#x2019;t build a monolithic culture.</li><li>Embrace cross functional work. </li></ul><p><strong>46:00 </strong>- In the early days of Gusto, what guidance did you provide to your engineers about building payroll? What areas could break and which areas could not break? </p><p><strong>48:40</strong> - Looking back, would you have done anything different? </p><ul><li>Start charging what you feel is the value you provide; fix downwards versus upwards. If you&#x2019;re truly adding value, customers won&#x2019;t hesitate moving forward at that price.</li><li>Have the humility to learn from the customer and how the market changes around you. </li></ul><p><strong>51:45 </strong>- How should founders be thinking about embedded finance and how does this market evolve over the next 5-10 years? </p><ul><li>When you build a new software system for your customer, the more connected the system is for your customer, the better it is. Embedded products enable you to do that quickly and in high quality.</li><li>Bring more solutions into your product that are driven by what your customer needs. Understand your customer&#x2019;s day-to-day, and figure out how to build something that solves their entire flow instead of one segment.</li><li>If you are not making money on your product, you don&#x2019;t know if there&apos;s a product market fit. If you can charge and retain a customer, then there is product market fit. </li></ul><p><strong>56:30</strong> - Outside of payroll, what are you seeing product wise offered by APIs? </p><ul><li>This space is brand new and there&#x2019;s a ton of opportunity to create a product that helps customers go through the end-to-end journey successfully and solves multiple pain points &#x2013; instead of the customer needing ten years of background to create a high-quality solution.</li></ul>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>