<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#">

<channel>
	<title>Ius &amp; Iustitium</title>
	<atom:link href="https://iusetiustitium.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
	<link>https://iusetiustitium.com</link>
	<description/>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 19:21:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://i0.wp.com/iusetiustitium.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/cropped-yMF3qI-o_400x400-1.png?fit=32%2C32&amp;ssl=1</url>
	<title>Ius &amp; Iustitium</title>
	<link>https://iusetiustitium.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">179055766</site>	<item>
		<title>The Common Good As A Legal Concept</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/the-common-good-as-a-legal-concept/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=the-common-good-as-a-legal-concept</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adrian Vermeule]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 14:15:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1880</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What follows are unedited remarks, without footnotes, delivered at the Abigail Adams Institute’s colloquium on the common good, held at Harvard University on Thursday, November 10. Thanks to the organizers and to fellow speakers Fr. Jeff Langan, Mary Hirschfeld, and Darel Paul. I’ll talk today about the common good as a legal concept. And I&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/the-common-good-as-a-legal-concept/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">The Common Good As A Legal Concept</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>What follows are unedited remarks, without footnotes, delivered at the Abigail Adams Institute’s colloquium on the common good, held at Harvard University on Thursday, November 10. Thanks to the organizers and to fellow speakers Fr. Jeff Langan, Mary Hirschfeld, and Darel Paul.</em></p>
<hr />
<p>I’ll talk today about the common good as a <em>legal</em> concept. And I hope you can hear in my voice that legal is in italics. That is, I’m going to sketch with criminal celerity the more distinctively legal side of the classical tradition and say a few words in praise of the civilian jurists as opposed to the philosophical and theological side of the tradition.</p>
<p>Let me begin with a simple point that the book emphasizes, but which some of the commentators have overlooked, although others have not. “The common good” in the legal sense is not to be seen, at least not solely, as an external concept, that the analyst uses to justify or evaluate the legal system. Rather, it is a concept used by actors <em>within</em> the system. And it is an absolutely ubiquitous concept. Indeed, it is often literally embodied in the language of enacted provisions and judicial doctrines. Lawyers have constantly to construe provisions or work with doctrines that refer in terms to “the common good,” “the public interest,” “the general welfare,” or similar terms. (I follow the comparativist Elisabeth Zoller’s analysis of the concept of <em>res publica</em> in treating these versions of the common good as relatives and cognates of one another).</p>
<p>In order to illustrate how lawyers have to work with the common good as a concept within the legal system, I’m going to begin by introducing some provisions, and even cite some cases, to provide a few scattershot examples from around the law and its history, at all levels of legal systems (and these examples could be multiplied almost indefinitely). So buckle up everyone, it’s going to be a wild ride.<span id="more-1880"></span></p>
<p>At the level of constitutional provisions, the Massachusetts Constitution of 1780 is the world&#8217;s oldest functioning written constitution and was often cited as a model for the federal Constitution. And the Massachusetts Constitution specifies both that “all shall be governed by certain laws for the common good,” and that “[g]overnment is instituted for the common good, for the protection, safety, prosperity, and happiness of the people, and not for the profit, honor, or private interest of any one man, family, or class of men.”</p>
<p>Following suit, the United States’ federal Constitution of 1789 both specifies in its preamble that one of the master aims of the Constitution is to “promote the general Welfare,” and grants Congress the power “To lay and collect Taxes, Duties, Imposts and Excises, to pay the Debts and provide for the common Defence and general Welfare of the United States.” The interpretation of these provisions has been and still is contested. Although the Supreme Court interpreted the second narrowly in 1936, during its ill-fated resistance to the New Deal, the originalist credentials of that interpretation are, ironically enough, highly debatable. For those interested, I would recommend recent scholarship on the general welfare clause(s) by David Schwartz at the University of Wisconsin.</p>
<p>The general welfare language in the U.S. Constitution influenced provisions around the world. It has well-known connections to the famous Polish constitution of 3 May 1791, often called the first written constitution in Europe, which specifies that it is made, among other aims, “for the general welfare.” These and related provisions also had a profound influence on 19th-century constitution-making in Latin America and on pan-American framework treaties and instruments to which the United States is a signatory (whether or not the Senate has ratified them). Thus the preamble of the Constitution of Argentina specifies that one of the purposes of the federal or national government is to “promote the general welfare,” and, in a Schwarzian interpretation, the Argentine Supreme Court once held that the General Welfare clause of the Argentine Constitution confers on the the federal government a general source of authority for national legislation. So too, the American Convention on Human Rights specifies that “The rights of each person are limited by the rights of others, by the safety of all, and by the just demands of the common good.”</p>
<p>At the level of statutes, in the United States, the Federal Communications Act of 1934 gave the Federal Communications Commission sweeping regulatory powers to act in “the public interest,” using that phrase no less than 102 times. Similar organic statutes are everywhere in American public law; taken together, as I argue elsewhere, they amount to no less than an American version of the classical <em>lex regia</em>, transferring broad authority to the executive and the administrative agencies to make rules with the force of law.</p>
<p>At the level of judge-made legal doctrines, consider, as one example chosen nearly at random, the four-part test for the granting of a preliminary injunction by a federal court, of which the last part is whether granting an injunction is in “the public interest.” As that and the other examples show, the public interest is often invoked *within* adjudication or legal interpretation.</p>
<p>As the book tries to show, these provisions, doctrines and principles draw upon even more ancient sources, going right back to the origins of European law, sources such as the <em>Etymologies</em> of Isidore of Seville in the 7th century, which says that laws properly so-called are formulated “for no private benefit, but for the common well being (<em>communis utilitas</em>) of the citizens.” It is probably a fruitless exercise to try to locate the ultimate source of such ideas, like a deranged explorer searching for the origin of the Nile. But one location that must be mentioned here, a profoundly influential source, is Papinian’s injunction, later recorded in the opening book of the <em>Digest of Justinian</em>, that the ground for the validity of the <em>ius honorarium</em>, the legal principles and doctrines developed by magistrates called praetors, is that it serves the public interest, the <em>utilitatem publicam</em>. As Papinian puts it (in Alan Watson’s translation), “praetorian law is that which in the public interest the praetors have introduced in aid or supplementation or correction of the <em>jus civile</em>.” And this basic approach becomes a standard too for civilian lawyers, not just in the Republic but throughout the Principate, the Dominate, and the medieval <em>ius commune </em>and into the Ango-American law<em>.</em></p>
<p>The examples are quotidian and on the ground level of the law. Suppose ship cargo has to be jettisoned in a storm to save the ship—where should the loss fall? The <em>Digest</em> tells us that “[t]he Rhodian law [of the sea] provides that if cargo has been jettisoned in order to lighten a ship, the sacrifice for the common good must be made good by common contribution.” Is a sentence of punishment suspended pending appeal? Generally yes, except as to “persons whom it is in the public interest to punish immediately on condemnation, such as notorious brigands or stirrers of sedition or leaders of gangs.” So too, the praetor will, in the public interest, give fourfold damages against those who engage in looting after a fire or natural disaster. And so forth. The jurists spend a decent chunk of their time making the common good concrete, workable, and sensible.</p>
<p>As the book argues, the best current analogue for this work of the praetors, the imperial bureaucracy, and the imperial and medieval jurists in aiding, supplementing or correcting the baseline civil law in the public interest is the work of the administrative state. Like the praetors, magistrates without the formal power to enact statutes who nonetheless spoke with the force of law through interpretation and supplementation of statutes, so too our agencies interpret, enforce, and supplement the law under broad delegations from Congress. Like the <em>ius honorarium</em> of the praetors, the rules made by the administrative state are the “living voice” of our law.</p>
<p>What is the larger significance of these provisions, legal doctrines, cases and juristic arguments? You will notice some names that haven’t appeared in my talk so far: Aristotle, Aquinas, Heinrich Rommen, Charles De Koninck, John Finnis, and so forth. It is not that I do not respect these figures; on the contrary, I have the deepest respect and admiration for them, especially for the Angelic Doctor. But I do mean to highlight that the common good as a legal concept has ancient roots on what we might call the civilian juristic side of the tradition, and that the common good as a legal concept is part of a tradition of thought, legal theory and practical application that is partially independent of the philosophical and theological tradition of the common good. Indeed, a somewhat neglected topic is the influence running from the legal side of the tradition to its philosophical side. Appropriately, the Angelic Doctor, who knew everything, straddles both traditions. His citations in the relevant sections of the <em>Summa</em>, such as the so-called <em>Treatise on Law</em> and the sections on right, justice and judgment, are as often to civilian jurists as to philosophers or theologians or even canon lawyers.</p>
<p>To explain this partial independence of the distinctively legal common good, let me make more explicit my methodological premises, and even express a very amicable methodological complaint, delivered in quiet tones.</p>
<p>So, to begin with some broad premises: law (or more precisely jurisprudence, understanding that term in the civilian sense rather than the Anglo-American academic sense) is best seen as a department of political morality, a <a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/jurisprudence-as-a-subaltern-science/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">subaltern science</a>. In particular, it is the department that attempts to embody in practical reasoning the virtue of what Aquinas called general or legal justice, the rendering of each his due, a virtue intrinsically ordered to the common good of the community. But, and conversely, this means law is also a special department of political morality; it is not to be assimilated or dissolved into political morality as such, let alone morality <em>simpliciter</em>. Law has to treat justice in special ways because practical reason applied to governance through law ordered to the common good is a prudential activity, one that faces distinctive problems.</p>
<p>For example, is it always desirable to change a rule of positive law that can be seen to be harmful or that has become obsolete? Not necessarily; one has to consider the disruption and confusion inherent in any change of legal rules, even if the change is an improvement taken in itself, and one also has to consider the reliance interests of those who have structured their affairs in light of the old rule. Law is full of dilemmas and tradeoffs like this. There is no general algorithm for resolving them, which is why governance through law requires the virtue of regnative prudence, and why law is an art or a craft of judgment, rather than a technique like doing a math problem (or like the mere technique of interpretation that modern textualist judges claim to possess). Thus, as the jurist Celsus put it, as given by Ulpian in the <em>Digest of Justinian</em>, law is the “<em>ars boni et aequi</em>,” the <em>art</em> of the good and equitable.</p>
<p>Now to my mild methodological complaint. In the white-hot debates over the classical legal tradition and the natural law tradition in the past three years, but also more broadly, there has been a distinct tendency in my view to emphasize what might be called the philosophical and theological side of the classical tradition. One often sees something like the following sequence: the theorist discusses Aristotle, gives Augustine a brief nod, discusses Aquinas extensively, and then immediately and somewhat bewilderingly skips forward to post World War II theorists and delves deeply into controversies over DeKoninck, over Finnis’ evolving views of the common good, and so forth. Ironically enough, this is somewhat parallel to the bad habit of liberal theorists of starting with the Greeks — offering an interpretation of Polybius that somehow makes him sound remarkably like Madison — then skipping straight to Machiavelli and then on to Locke and the American founders, with Rawls looming in the distance. What is left out here is the millennia-long legal tradition of the common good as an operative, working legal system, one that tried to bring the abstractions down to earth and implement them in concrete, beneficial ways.</p>
<p>Put another way, construing legal provisions or working with legal doctrines of the sort I illustrated is not like doing straight philosophy or theology. That is, the provisions are not directly open to philosophical debates over the common good in the way that certain styles of architecture are directly open to the outside air. Rather they are partially independent of underlying philosophical concepts, insofar as law is a distinctive department of political morality, the art or craft of practical reasoning about legal justice that takes into account distinctive considerations arising from the institutional embodiment of the legal system. I stress only partially, because <a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/enriching-legal-theory/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the classical view</a> is that background principles of legal justice (<em>ius</em>) inhere in and permeate positive provisions of law (<em>lex</em>) and help constitute even the semantic meaning of <em>lex</em>, and are <em>a fortiori</em> used to interpret <em>lex</em> when the latter is general, vague, ambiguous, or overbroad relative to the lawmaker’s aims. But the <em>ius</em> that inheres in <em>lex</em> and is used to interpret <em>lex</em> is not just “morality” as such. It is a system of principles that are themselves relevant to and embody legal justice, such as, to pick some random examples, the principle that no man should be judge in his own cause, or the principle that no man should profit from his own wrong.</p>
<p>Given that such provisions and doctrines have to be interpreted and applied for legal purposes that are partly independent of high-level philosophical and theological debates, two conclusions follow. First, the working lawyer or judge cannot simply recline back into some sort of general skepticism about the common good or its determinacy, intoning “who decides?” For legal purposes, the jurists decide. Morever, in contrast to the academic legal theorist (or the part-time theorist who also happens to wear a judicial robe), the working lawyer or judge cannot wave a refined hand in the air and say “I’m not sure what that means — let the seminar go on.” A provision or doctrine that says, in terms, “the common good” or “public interest” or “general welfare,” has to be given some interpretation or other by the working lawyer and especially by the judge. Now, one way the lawyer or judge can lighten his own burdens is to interpret the provision as commanding deference within a reasonable range to an executive body, and this is an ordinary way our law works. But that too is a substantive interpretation. It is not philosophical skepticism.</p>
<p>Second, for concrete legal purposes one usually does not have to choose between high-level, contested sub-conceptions of the common good. Philosophers and theologians debate so-called distinctive, aggregative, and instrumental conceptions of the common good, among others. The book adopts the classical or distinctive conception of the common good, because I think it is the conception that unites Aristotle, Augustine and Aquinas, and for the sake of concreteness, and because I think it is true. But very little in the operative interpretations of our constitutional order offered in the book, and very little in the quotidian work of law generally, turns on contested philosophical refinements of the common good at the outer boundaries of debate. As George Duke observed, the differences among high-level conceptions of the common good often make little difference in the work of practical reason. Those conceptions can travel a long way together, and this is a problem both for the jurisprude (in the Anglo-American sense) who is eager to plunge into conceptual refinements and also for the skeptic about the common good or natural law. Instead the quotidian activity of practical reasoning about the legal common good serves concrete ends, on which different speculative conceptions of the common good usually converge in practice. It condemns the abuse of official power for private purposes like nepotism or peculation; it underwrites equitable and public-regarding interpretations of semantic meaning; and it helps to prevent a kind of pointless and fetishistic legal formalism that benefits few and harms all.</p>
<p>In short — and here I am attempting to summarize a major theme of the book — I would urge that lawyers and legal commentators pay rather less attention to debatable philosophical refinements of the common good and rather more attention to the civilian-lawyer side of the<em> ius commune</em>, in which <em>bonum commune</em> or common good does not refer in the first instance to some debatable philosophical conception or other. By no means do I want to deny the philosophers their fun, but to the extent lawyers are capable of having fun, it’s of a somewhat different kind.</p>
<p>-Adrian Vermeule</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1880</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Lex and Ius in Football</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/lex-and-ius-in-football/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=lex-and-ius-in-football</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jacob Neu]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 16:39:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1856</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What do you do in an official sporting event when something patently unfair happens? As it is football season in the US, I thought we could use a famous play as a light-hearted and enlightening example about lex, ius, the common good, and statutory interpretation. Now, I should be clear at the outset that judges&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/lex-and-ius-in-football/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Lex and Ius in Football</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>What do you do in an official sporting event when something patently unfair happens? As it is football season in the US, I thought we could use a famous play as a light-hearted and enlightening example about <em>lex</em>, <em>ius</em>, the common good, and statutory interpretation. Now, I should be clear at the outset that judges and referees are not exactly the same. Referees are tasked with determining violations of the rules, and those rules are set based on the good of the game, not necessarily the good of the players involved. The referee also typically has little discretion about the implementation of those rules. Nevertheless, as the following story shows, on some occasions even referees look beyond the mere rules of the game.</p>



<p>Our story concerns the 1954 Cotton Bowl played between the mighty University of Alabama Crimson Tide and my <em>alma mater</em>, the lowly Rice University Owls. The Rice Owl football program has not had much historical success. At one time the Owls went 45 years—1961 to 2006—without earning a berth to a postseason bowl games. In 1962, when President John F. Kennedy announced that the US manned space program would send a man to the Moon, he gave the speech at Rice Stadium in Houston, Texas. As part of that speech, Kennedy asked rhetorically, &#8220;But why, some say, the Moon? Why choose this as our goal? And they may well ask why climb the highest mountain? Why, 35 years ago, fly the Atlantic? <em>Why does Rice play Texas?</em> We choose to go to the Moon. We choose to go to the Moon in this decade and do the other things, not because they are easy, but because they are hard.” So, yes, Rice has a bit of a reputation for historical football futility.</p>



<p>That was not the case in 1953, however, when Rice went 9-2 and won the Southwest Conference championship. On New Year’s Day in 1954, Rice played in the Cotton Bowl in Dallas, Texas against the champions of the Southeastern Conference, the Alabama Crimson Tide. Rice running back Dicky Moegle* turned in the game of his life, rushing for 265 yards and 3 touchdowns on <em>11 carries.</em> (That’s an average of 24.1 yards per carry. For our international readers to understand how much this is, the current season’s leading individual rusher&#8217;s average is 7.5 yards per carry.)</p>



<span id="more-1856"></span>



<p>The most famous run came in the second quarter, when Rice had the ball on its own 5 yard line. Moegle took the handoff, broke around the right side, and dashed up the sideline in front of the Alabama bench. Moegle had a mostly clear path to the end zone, although one or two Alabama players probably could have caught him. But at about the Alabama 45-yard line, Alabama’s Tommy Lewis, who was sitting on the bench, came off the sideline and made a surprise blind tackle on Moegle, leaving him sprawled out at about the 40 yard line. Lewis sheepishly snuck back onto the sideline and sat on the bench with his head in his hands. In interviews after the game, he was profusely apologetic to Moegle, saying later that he “was just too full of Alabama” to let Moegle run roughshod over the overmatched Crimson Tide defense.</p>



<p>So back to our question—what happens when something patently unfair occurs? In this case, there is a proper penalty—a penal law, you might say—to assess against Lewis. It would be illegal participation, a 5-yard penalty that would have left Rice with the ball at about the 40 yard line. But that penalty would certainly not fit the inequity of what occurred. A man clearly not involved in the game at the time came off the bench and tackled Moegle. When the drafters of the football rulebook considered “illegal participation” a 5-yard penalty, surely this was not what they had in mind.</p>



<p>The referees conferred and decided that, for the good of the game and fair play, Moegle would be awarded the touchdown rather than just assessing the illegal participation penalty. This is despite the fact that at least one other Alabama player could probably have tackled Moegle or pushed him out of bounds before reaching the end zone. And so Moegle was given credit for a 95-yard touchdown rush, which counted towards his official statistics for the game. As one newspaper put it afterward, it was the first time “where a runner received credit for a touchdown while flat on his back 38 yards from the goal line.”</p>



<p>If we think of the head referee as a judge making a legal decision for applying a statutory rule, what mode of legal analysis most persuasively supports the referee? It is not “textualism”–either the referee awarded a plainly improper remedy for the penalty of illegal participation, or the referee acted on the basis of no written rule at all. Is it “originalism,” in the sense that one must look to the meaning of the rule drafters? Perhaps one could say that what Lewis did was not actually illegal participation as the rule drafters intended–but then, the rulebook would be silent on the matter, and there would be no rule covering Lewis’ illegal tackle. This leads to the same place as wooden textualism. Perhaps one could argue that the <em>intent</em> or <em>purpose </em>of the expressed rules of the rulebook was to promote the general rule of fair play, but even under such an intentionalistic or purposivistic analysis, we have little guidance on how Lewis’ tackle should be punished. For example, no other penalty in the rule book allows the referee to award a touchdown when the player was tackled 38 yards from the goal line. Finally, one could make a guess at what the rule drafters would have done in such a situation, but unless one relies upon a commonly held background morality about the sense of fair play in football, there is no way to make that determination or to determine the right penalty. Therefore textualism, originalism, intentionalism, purposivism, and dynamic interpretation all fail to provide a convincing account for the referee’s decision to award Moegle the touchdown.</p>



<p>But the classical natural law concepts of <em>lex</em>, <em>ius</em>, and the common good come to the rescue. In essence, what we have here is a play where the official rules, the <em>lex</em> of American football, did not account for a unique and unforeseen action on the field that violated the background sense of fair play, integrity, and the common good of the game, the <em>ius</em>. There was a rule that did literally fit the definition of the play, but that no one watching the game would have agreed would be a proper penalty for Lewis’ actions. Therefore, the referee took it upon himself to step outside the rulebook and award what was in his mind the most just result—Moegle would be given credit for the touchdown run. Moreover, this decision acts as a deterrent against similar such actions. If a player knew that coming off the bench to tackle a player on a clear scoring play would result in only a 5-yard penalty, there would be no reason not to do that. The referees in this instance acted like a judge turning to the natural law to fill in the gaps where the positive law would have generated an unjust result. That background law relied upon the common moral understanding of those involved in the game to recognize what was clearly unfair in view of the good of the game.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Today, as a result of the famous “Bench Tackle,” the official college football rule book now states that in the event of a “palpably unfair act,” the referee may award a penalty he believes is most fitting to address the injustice. The <em>lex</em> now expressly implements the <em>ius</em>, but even in 1954, the referee enforced the sense of the <em>ius</em> where the <em>lex</em> failed to provide a reasonably just result.</p>



<p>Behind Moegle’s sensational game, Rice beat Alabama 28-6. Until 2017, Moegle’s 95-yard touchdown-that-wasn’t was the longest play from scrimmage in Rice history—a fitting result for a school known as much for its students&#8217; quirky sense of humor as for athletic success. Meanwhile, as Rice subsequently went through decades of futility, Alabama became a powerhouse, claiming 13 national titles since 1954. But as I like to remind my friends who cheer on the Tide, Rice is 3-0 all-time against Alabama–the only team to play Alabama multiple times without a loss. Sometimes the last shall be first, even in the crazy business of college football.</p>



<p>Ultimately, while it is not correct that judges are like referees, merely calling balls and strikes, sometimes referees must act like judges: implementing the rules the best they can, but turning to background principles when those rules would operate an injustice against the game. Perhaps Chief Justice Roberts spoke truer than he knew.</p>



<p>*<em>Moegle is pronounced with a long &#8220;a,&#8221; like &#8220;Maegle,&#8221; the spelling to which he later changed his name. As the newspaper reports and playing records use &#8220;Moegle,&#8221; I have kept that spelling here.</em></p>



<p><em>You can see Tommy Lewis&#8217; Bench Tackle below.</em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="jetpack-video-wrapper"><iframe title="1954 Cotton Bowl: Dicky Maegle - Tommy Lewis Tackle Play" width="739" height="554" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eSteCSinjTs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1856</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bleeding Montana</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/bleeding-montana/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=bleeding-montana</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pat Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 18:37:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Constitutional Law]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1863</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In August, Kansas voters rejected a constitutional amendment specifying that the Kansas Constitution did not protect a right to abortion or require the state government to fund abortion. In response, I wrote a piece here pointing out that this was precisely the result that the conservative legal movement sought via the Supreme Court’s decision in&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/bleeding-montana/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Bleeding Montana</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In August, Kansas voters rejected a constitutional amendment specifying that the Kansas Constitution did not protect a right to abortion or require the state government to fund abortion. In response, <a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/the-price-of-victory-in-kansas/">I wrote a </a><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/the-price-of-victory-in-kansas/" target="_blank">piece</a><a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/the-price-of-victory-in-kansas/"> here</a> pointing out that this was precisely the result that the conservative legal movement sought via the Supreme Court’s decision in <em>Dobbs</em>. The only principled position, we have been told, is neutrality. The voters can approve or disapprove abortion as they like, but what matters is that the voters decide. The Constitution does not tell them what they must or must not do, and judges must not interfere with this posture of principled neutrality. </p>



<p>Such a position does not have deep roots in the classical legal tradition, which certainly does not hold that the law can be neutral on essential questions of morality, letting the voters decide such basic questions as who is alive. And one can find arguments against the idea in the American tradition, including in Abraham Lincoln’s arguments against Stephen Douglas’s principled neutrality on the question of slavery. I said so. <em>New York Times</em> columnist Ross Douthat took issue, <a href="https://twitter.com/douthatnyt/status/1554966481590489088?s=61" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">saying</a> that I “complain[ed] the Court did Something when it could have just done Everything itself.” The Institute for Human Ecology at the Catholic University of America even took a short break from posting pictures of the saint the day to amplify Douthat’s criticism. (Don&#8217;t worry: the Institute got back to posting pictures of the saint of the day.) </p>



<p>However trenchant the criticism may have seemed to Douthat and his friends at the Institute in August, it is by no means clear that it is so trenchant today. Five states had measures on the ballot relating to abortion. In California, Michigan, and Vermont, the question was whether to amend the state constitution to create an explicit right to reproductive freedom, which is of course a euphemism for abortion. In Kentucky, the question was about an amendment specifying that nothing in the state constitution protected a right to abortion. And in Montana there was a proposal to establish that children born alive were persons and entitled to legal protection. In each state, the pro-life position was rejected.&nbsp;In every state where life was put to the vote, the voters chose the other option. As Douthat says, the Court did Something instead of Everything—and what a Something! </p>



<span id="more-1863"></span>



<p>The rejection of the Montana ballot question, Referendum 131, has gotten significant attention, probably because its rejection is shocking. The most relevant provision of the Montana law, if it had been adopted, stated first that, “[a] born-alive infant, including an infant born in the course of an abortion, must be treated as a legal person under the laws of the state, with the same rights to medically appropriate and reasonable care and treatment.” Next it provided that “[a] health care provider who is present at the time a born-alive infant is born shall take all medically appropriate and reasonable actions to preserve the life and health of the infant.”&nbsp;Neither provision addresses abortion <em>per se</em>, but the question of infants born alive during abortion procedures has come up before. President George W. Bush signed the Born-Alive Infants Protection Act into law in 2002, for example.</p>



<p>About fifty-two percent of Montana voters voted against the provision. Already, at <em>National Review</em>, Wesley Smith <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.nationalreview.com/corner/why-montana-voters-rejected-the-born-alive-infant-protection-act/" target="_blank">has argued</a> that Referendum 131 failed because it was badly drafted and failed to make clear that there were potential exceptions to the requirement to provide treatment. Based on this bad drafting, he argues, abortion supporters were able to twist the proposal’s text and argue that the law would ban legitimate palliative care for gravely ill infants. On the other hand, House Bill 167, which is the legislation underlying Referendum 131, was drafted by Matt Regier, a Montana legislator since 2016, who has drafted numerous bills during his legislative career (a fact Smith ignores). That is to say, the author of the law was not a well meaning but inexperienced pro-life advocate but a member of the Montana legislature with plenty of experience drafting laws. </p>



<p>Certainly, it is possible that the Montana drafters’ failure to produce nuanced legislation simply turned off moderate voters. This view would be consistent with the attitude expressed more broadly by Ed Whelan, of <em>National Review</em> and the Ethics and Public Policy Center, who <a href="https://twitter.com/EdWhelanEPPC/status/1590376544111063045">noted on Twitter</a> that “the <em>Roe</em> regime made it easy for [the] pro-life movement to be absolutist and not to think seriously about the sort of legislative compromises (e.g., rape exception) necessary in real-world politics.” But there are, of course, limits to such realism. In another <a href="https://twitter.com/EdWhelanEPPC/status/1590368547821465600" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tweet</a>, Whelan argued “[i]f [the] Court had failed to overturn <em>Roe</em> in <em>Dobbs</em>, lots of social conservative voters would have been badly demoralized, given up on Republican party.” One can think of worse things that would have happened, of course, but the electoral fortunes of the Republican Party are not nothing. </p>



<p>But such realism—whatever its limits may be—ultimately misses the point. Voters rejected the proposition that an infant born alive “must be treated as a legal person under the laws of the state, with the same rights to medically appropriate and reasonable care and treatment.” We have gone from letting the people decide—as Justice Brett Kavanaugh framed it in his important concurrence in <em>Dobbs</em>—whether a fetus is a human life to letting the people decide whether an infant born alive is a human life. One may argue that the failure of Referendum 131 was not foreseen by <em>Dobbs</em> and the failure of the bill should not be credited to <em>Dobbs</em>. (This is, I suppose, what Ross Douthat would argue.)&nbsp;</p>



<p>Recall, however, what Justice Kavanaugh said: “The issue before this Court is what the Constitution says about abortion. The Constitution does not take sides on the issue of abortion. The text of the Constitution does not refer to or encompass abortion.” One can simply swap “the moment a ‘fetus’ becomes an ‘infant’” for “abortion,” and the statements would be no less true. Silence, on Justice Kavanaugh’s account, is neutrality: “On the question of abortion, the Constitution is therefore neither pro-life nor pro-choice. The Constitution is neutral and leaves the issue for the people and their elected representatives to resolve through the democratic process . . . .” Silence means neutrality; neutrality means the voters get to decide the question however they see fit. </p>



<p>Of course, on the classical conception of law, this is absurd. Law is something pertaining to reason, as a rule and measure of human actions (ST I-II q.90 a.1 co.). As such, the law must be ordered to the common good (ST I-II q.90 a.2 co.). Aquinas tells us what this means: “Est autem ultimus finis humanae vitae felicitas vel beatitudo, ut supra habitum est. Unde oportet quod lex maxime respiciat ordinem qui est in beatitudinem. Rursus, cum omnis pars ordinetur ad totum sicut imperfectum ad perfectum; unus autem homo est pars communitatis perfectae, necesse est quod lex proprie respiciat ordinem ad felicitatem communem”—“Now the first principle in practical matters, which are the object of the practical reason, is the last end: and the last end of human life is bliss or happiness, as stated above. Consequently the law must needs regard principally the relationship to happiness. Moreover, since every part is ordained to the whole, as imperfect to perfect; and since one man is a part of the perfect community, the law must needs regard properly the relationship to universal happiness.” (<em>Id.</em>)</p>



<p>If one takes the silence in the federal constitution as a sort of reservation of rights, which seems to be the thrust of Justice Kavanaugh’s argument, this does not mean that there is absolute neutrality, leaving the people to do as they please. The people still have the obligation to seek the objective common good. As Charles de Koninck put it in <a href="https://thejosias.com/2020/05/04/the-correspondence-between-charles-de-koninck-and-charles-n-r-mccoy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a 1946 letter to Charles McCoy</a>, “it is not the will of the people that makes the good it pursues a real good, not even a common good per accidens; it may be only a bonum apparens.” To put it another way, the will of the people regarding a putative good is not the decisive question. The common good is the common good notwithstanding the will of the people. And the essence of political life is to seek the common good. </p>



<p>And we see similar principles at work elsewhere. In a case when the lawgiver has not foreseen the effects of the law under particular circumstances, one may act beside the letter of the law precisely because the lawgiver generally orders his laws to the common good (ST I-II q.96 a.6 co.). Responding to an objection, Aquinas observes “nullius hominis sapientia tanta est ut possit omnes singulares casus excogitare, et ideo non potest sufficienter per verba sua exprimere ea quae conveniunt ad finem intentum”—“No man is so wise as to be able to take account of every single case; wherefore he is not able sufficiently to express in words all those things that are suitable for the end he has in view” (ST I-II q.96 a.6 ad 3). In such cases, the general intention of the lawgiver is what matters, and the general intention is always the common good (else the law would not be a true law). </p>



<p>The idea, expressed in <em>Dobbs</em>, that constitutional silence leaves the field altogether open for the people to do whatever pleases them is, therefore, alien to the classical view of law. The common good, which is to say the happiness of the body politic (or, to put it another way, the concord of order), is still the end of law regardless of whether a given written instrument says so or not. The will of the people cannot transform an apparent good into even an accidental common good, least of all when the will of the people is opposed directly to the common good. As De Koninck tells us, when the people do not seek even an accidental common good, they are perverse and lose their political nature. (De Koninck also reminds us, “to say that man is by nature a political animal does not mean that they necessarily have the proximate disposition to be citizens; man is by nature many things that he does not actually acquire or become.”) </p>



<p>Indeed, we have seen that Justice Kavanaugh’s idea that silence equals neutrality is squarely contrary to the classical idea that “nullius hominis sapientia tanta est ut possit omnes singulares casus excogitare, et ideo non potest sufficienter per verba sua exprimere ea quae conveniunt ad finem intentum” (ST I-II q.96 a.6 ad 3). In cases when the lawgiver has not taken account of a given case, the general intention toward the common good supplies the lacuna. The silence of the lawgiver does not create a zone free of the common good, where each person (or group of people or subordinate political entity) can do as he or she pleases. Yet once one rejects the classical concept and adopts the view that silence equals neutrality, the result in Montana follows the result in <em>Dobbs</em> as night follows day.&nbsp;</p>



<p>A lack of nuance, as Wesley Smith argues, or a failure to make the hard real-world compromises that lawmaking requires, as Ed Whelan implies, is not the problem with the rejection of the Montana referendum. It is fundamentally the idea that, because the Constitution is silent on a particular question, the electorate should be free to decide when a “fetus” becomes an “infant,” and therefore a bearer of subjective rights, including the right to medical treatment. Yet this freedom is precisely what <em>Dobbs</em> establishes, at least, according to Justice Kavanaugh, who provided the essential fifth vote for the majority opinion. To be sure, there is plenty of room for nuance and compromise in the law. But not here. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1863</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Enriching Legal Theory</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/enriching-legal-theory/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=enriching-legal-theory</link>
					<comments>https://iusetiustitium.com/enriching-legal-theory/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Adrian Vermeule]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2022 14:49:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Constitutional Law]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1848</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What follows are my notes from a semi-extemporaneous response I delivered at the conference on Common Good Constitutionalism organized by the Harvard Journal of Law and Public Policy and the Harvard Federalist Society on October 29, after receiving some but not all of the papers in advance and listening to the discussion. The other participants’&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/enriching-legal-theory/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Enriching Legal Theory</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>What follows are my notes from a semi-extemporaneous response I delivered at the <a href="https://www.harvard-jlpp.com/symposia/cgc-symposium/">conference on Common Good Constitutionalism</a> organized by the <em>Harvard Journal of Law and Public Policy</em> and the Harvard Federalist Society on October 29, after receiving some but not all of the papers in advance and listening to the discussion. The other participants’ papers and presentations were largely working drafts of final&nbsp;products that will appear in the <em>Journal</em>. The oral delivery differed from these notes in minor ways. A full version of the talk with footnotes will appear in the <em>Journal</em> in due course.</p>



<p><em>The editors wish to thank Mario Fiandeiro, editor-in-chief of the </em>Harvard Journal of Law and Public Policy<em>, and the </em>Journal<em> editorial board for their gracious permission to publish this in advance of the </em>Journal<em>’s publication.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity is-style-wide"/>



<p>Thanks to everyone for coming. I think it’s been a fascinating event and suggests that these debates have only begun and will continue for a long time. Yet these debates also have an ancient history. The discussions we have had today are iterations, with appropriate variation, of discussions that happened in and during the last revival of classical legal theory, in the US and Europe in the 1950s and 1960s in the shadow of Nuremberg, when legal positivism for a time seemed patently inadequate. And those in turn were variants of many earlier iterations, going all the way back to debates over legal interpretation between the schools of Proculeian and Sabinian lawyers in Rome. Indeed, as will become clear shortly, the eternal recurrence of this sort of debate is itself, in my view, one of the great facts of history that we have to recover to make sense of our discussion today.</p>



<span id="more-1848"></span>



<p>It’s hard to do a response of this kind, in part because the discussion is still fresh, in part because one must inevitably be selective. I won’t be able to respond to all of the speakers or all of the points made by even the speakers I do have something to say to. Moreover, I will in some cases refrain from comment on the papers until I see them (and thanks to those who sent versions or partial versions of the papers in advance). So let me just try to organize a few thoughts around the theme of <em>enriching legal theory</em> that I hope will be of general interest. By legal theory, I will very much mean to include legal practice as a central interest of legal theory, as I will explain.</p>



<p>In some ways, the situational premise for the book is a sense that legal theory, especially American legal theory, has become or had become rather desperately impoverished. One felt, or at least I felt, that most of the products of the law reviews were either immediate advocacy arguments in the service of some immediate cause or another, or else examples of theory that had settled into a kind of steady-state equilibrium of alternation or even duopoly between a couple of predictable positions and research programs — in the American case, chiefly progressive legal realism and originalism. Each of these churned up a great deal of activity, but were in my view making fewer and fewer contributions, although there were, especially in the case of originalism, a bewildering proliferation of variants and epicycles on known ideas and positions, not all of which were consistent with one another — law’s analogue to what philosophers of science call a degenerating research program.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, judicial practice had or has increasingly diverged from the theories of the academy, as Judge Matey’s illuminating paper points out. As Michael Smith put it recently, unfortunately not in the paper he presented here, “academic discussions of originalism and original public meaning are severely disconnected from judicial and political realities.” In many respects, the practicing judges and lawyers have been ahead of the theorists, in that &#8211; at least in the actual work of judging &#8211; they are more alert to the fundamental condition of legal work that the positive law cannot even be understood or interpreted apart from practical reasoning in light of normatively inflected background principles &#8211; a point to which I will return.</p>



<p>Against this backdrop, the constructive effort behind the recovery or revival of classical legal theory (without speaking for other participants in the revival) is to in some way re-enrich legal theory &#8211; an effort to make it broader, more continuous with our history before the advent of 20th century positivism and with the legal approaches of other nations, in a sense more inclusive.</p>



<p>Now, such an effort does not at all entail originality in any straightforward sense. It is a bad assumption of Romanticism that scholarship should or must strive for originality. Sometimes the way scholarship can make a contribution, in a paradoxical combination of new and old, is a recollection or re-appropriation of enduring principles that have for contingent reasons been temporarily forgotten or abandoned. But it is a feature of the classical law that the possibility of and resources for such recovery is itself built into the theory, because the theory itself distinguishes what is universal from what is particular. Michael Foran’s paper nicely illustrates this distinction, by drawing upon the principles of equal dignity of all human beings as such, deeply rooted in the natural law and identified by&nbsp; classical lawyers as inconsistent with the positive civil law of their own day &#8211; a point I would recommend to Darrell Miller’s attention.</p>



<p>Here Foran works in a venerable tradition. To choose only one example from a myriad, the great 14th century jurist Baldus de Ubaldis adapted the principles of the <em>Corpus Juris Civilis</em> to the circumstances of the independent city-state republics of northern Italy. In so doing he did not attempt to directly transpose all the particular rules of the positive civil law of republican or imperial Rome, an absurd program. But he translated and developed the general principles of the corpus for his very different circumstances, resulting in an approach that seamlessly combines what is enduring with what is local and contingent. The watchword here&nbsp; should be<em> non nova, sed nove</em>&nbsp; — “not a new thing, but in a new way.” The book, therefore, is in part and in one sense proudly unoriginal, and I’m afraid my disagreements with Lee Strang’s paper began at the first sentence, when he said “common good constitutionalism offers a new theory of constitutional interpretation.”</p>



<p>Here let me briefly answer a few of Linda McClain’s questions, although given my constraints and the number of papers we have heard today, I do worry that once again I won’t be able to satisfy her that I have done them justice. First, the criteria for valid adaptation or translation of enduring principles are actually set out in a chapter of the book. They are drawn from the account of development of doctrine offered by the 19th century Oxford don and theologian, St. John Henry Newman, which I take to be firmly in the mainstream of the classical tradition. We can disagree how to apply such criteria, but that is because the classical legal tradition itself provides a framework within which different prudential determinations can occur, and within which reasonable disagreements can be had with respect to those determinations, as Ryan Meade and others observed. Second, given the limits of my own expertise, I will have to leave further debates within the classical framework on the subjects Linda is interested in to scholars who know what they’re talking about and are already working in this area, such as Erika Bachiochi in her widely discussed recent book, and Julia Mahoney in a recent article. I do protest mildly that it is unreasonable for scholars in every given area to demand that I personally figure out what I think about the areas or cases of greatest interest to them; rather the book is meant as an invitation for others to work these things out in a broad range of areas, many well beyond my ken. Third, also actually in the book is a section on democracy, which argues — as one of Larry Solum’s slides showed — that democracy, rightly understood as and when oriented to the common good, is one perfectly valid way to structure a polity on the classical view. So I’m slightly comforted by the reflection that the book already answers at least some of Linda’s questions.</p>



<p>A nice example of the positive approach I am urging is on display in the paper by Conor Casey, which illustrates in a concrete and illuminating way the diversity of determinations, subject to reasonable prudential disagreement, that can occur within the framework of classical principles. This unique combination — stability of principle and flexibility of application — is what creates the famous capacity for the classical tradition to undergo repeated revivals over two millennia, in widely varying circumstances.</p>



<p>In this light, the latest recovery of the classical approach hopes to enrich legal theory on at least four dimensions: <em>temporal</em>, <em>comparative</em>, <em>professional</em>, and <em>methodological</em>. Let me explain.</p>



<p>Temporally, a legal theory that is richer is one that offers not only justification and fit with present law, synchronically, but also diachronic fit and justification — fit and justification that takes into account the past of our law and legal theory, putting in in its best light, and accounting to the extent possible for the evolution of our&nbsp; current law, legal institutions and legal practice from our own past. It is a chain novel that doesn’t start abruptly with the <em>Erie</em> case, or with Hart, or with Bork.</p>



<p>Conversely, it is a grievous form of temporal parochialism to talk about law as though everyone before Hart or Bork simply failed to understand the true nature of law or of legal interpretation. A slightly subtler form of intertemporal parochialism is to colonize the past, creating invented traditions that project modern positivism, originalism or progressivism onto the legal conceptions held by the Americans of the founding era or the 19th century — a mistake against which legal historians have rightly warned.</p>



<p>Here let me mention a scintillating paper by Emad Atiq, a legal philosopher from Cornell, who has no particular stake in the interpretive debates and is interested for philosophical reasons in the historical credentials of legal positivism, or rather the lack of such credentials. Relying on professional legal historians, Atiq walks through the classical legal tradition from its origins right through the Anglo-American common law, the founding era and the 19th century, and discusses a set of illustrative cases to show that American judges offered “[an] exceptionally clear treatment of unsourced principles of fairness as <em>bona fide</em> law.” Overall, in his view, “[classical American] jurists did not explain the legality of moral principle by adverting to social facts, judicial choice, or more fundamental laws; on the contrary, they seemed to treat ‘moral laws’ as self-evident, unchangeable, and applicable <em>ex proprio vigore </em>[of their own force].” In other words, these judges did <em>not</em> invoke these background principles only because they were already included elsewhere in social fact, but because they were law in their own right. For Atiq, the jurisprudential significance of all this is that it puts a challenge to current legal positivists, who can save “positivism’s truth” only by admitting that positivism of the post-World War II variety is historically “parochial,” and thereby requires developing very different justifications for positivism than currently exist.</p>



<p>And, I would add — especially in light of Judge Matey’s excellent and important discussion of Blackstone’s classical premises and its great influence on the Founders — the problem of historical or temporal parochialism is most severe for originalists, who stand in the paradoxical and difficult position of claiming to adhere to the original understanding while propounding a conception of law itself that is antithetical to the classical understanding of law the founders and their successors themselves held.</p>



<p>Comparatively, a richer legal theory is one that takes into account what we might call the <em>ius gentium</em> or law of nations at a higher-order level, the level of views about law and legal practice. An enriched theory takes into account what is thought about law not only in the United States, but in Europe, Latin America, and the rest of the world. Here a parochial legal theory is one that offers claims about the inherent nature of law, or of legal interpretation, or of legal communication, or of constitutionalism that do not capture or even flatly contradict conceptions of law and its practice that appear in the great variety of the world’s legal systems, approximately none of which practice originalism in anything like the American sense, if at all, and many of which do not understand themselves in the terms of 20th century Anglo-American positivism.</p>



<p>Professionally, a richer legal theory is one that both takes into account the internal perspective of practicing lawyers and judges, putting their self-conceptions in their best light, and that also fits with the development of our institutions outside the courts and the legal profession altogether. This is central to the book’s concerns. As to the activity of judges, it seems to me undeniable that when push comes to shove, most visibly in hard cases but not only in hard cases, judges — very much including judges who profess originalism — routinely read texts in light of general background principles of legal rationality and legal justice. These judges often show no real anxiety about grounding such principles in positive sources of law, yet take those principles to be an internal part of law’s fabric and integral to the activity of interpreting the law, not something imported into law and used to guide an exercise of legislative discretion writ small.</p>



<p>Methodologically, a richer legal theory is one that has a richer legal ontology and that puts the various sources of law into a well-ordered relationship to one another. The very thin positivist ontology on display in someone like Hart, who can see only rules, zones of “discretion,” and positive conventions, is profoundly impoverished and cannot account for the experience of legal practice, in which lawyers and judges do not take themselves to be doing something other than law when they draw upon background principles in order to understand the semantic meaning of texts, to disambiguate, specify, or supplement them, or otherwise to derive legal meaning from semantic meaning.</p>



<p>This view of course supposes that semantic meaning is fixed in a thin sense. To use an example that came up earlier, I do very much hope that the “Republican Form of Government” clause does <em>not</em> mean that Mitch McConnell is to be our sole governor. But this thin sense of fixation turns out to be absolutely common ground across originalist and non-originalist legal systems. European judges who think originalism is absurd may and do assent to it just as well. Hence this thin sense does not at all entail any of the further premises of modern American originalism, as Conor and I have argued at length elsewhere and I need not rehash here. (I note for Josh Hammer that if I didn’t wade into these issues in my old Atlantic piece but left them for the book and later papers, it is because it was a piece in the Atlantic. Try getting the phrase “semantic meaning” past the editors there.)</p>



<p>This brings us to what I take to be a serious conceptual mistake, an instance of circular reasoning, that I fear I have heard at a few points today and elsewhere, for example in the talk by Lee Strang, in work by Joel Alicea, and possibly in a recent review by Jeff Pojanowski and Kevin Walsh — although the review is almost as long as the book and I have only had a chance to skim it to date.</p>



<p>It begs all the key questions posed by the classical view to simply assume that the task of identifying <em>legal</em> meaning, an exercise of practical reasoning, can be reduced to the task of identifying <em>semantic</em> meaning. Put otherwise, it begs all the key questions to assume that even the semantic meaning of positive <em>lex</em>, however fixed, can be understood independently of background principles of <em>ius</em>. The classical view, as the book attempts to argue, is that those principles always already inform and permeate and inhere in <em>lex</em>, as it were, because <em>lex</em> is itself a determination or concretization of <em>ius, </em>inherits the nature and boundaries of practical reason inherent in<em> ius, </em>and is therefore interpreted to harmonize with <em>ius</em>. On the classical view, <em>ius</em> is promulgated just as much as <em>lex</em>, and itself serves, in part, coordinating functions. Conversely I think Lee Strang and others purporting to work within the natural law tradition have quietly and no doubt inadvertently dropped a key element of the the classical definition of <em>lex. </em>On<em> </em>that definition, even positive law is not only an ordination that serves the common good, but is also, always and essentially, an ordination <em>of reason</em>, not merely positive fiat. An ordination of reason is not merely an ordination that is made because there are good second-order reasons (like coordination) to make an ordination, resulting in a reason-independent or reason-excluding ordination of fiat, full stop. Instead an ordination of reason itself inextricably incorporates reason into its terms; reason inheres even in <em>lex</em>. As Dick Helmholz puts it in his wonderful book on <em>Natural Law in Court</em>, “[decisions of the <em>ius commune</em>] illustrate what might be called <em>the ‘internalist’ role played by the law of nature.</em> <em>It was used to discover the meaning of existing laws</em> [and] to help supply the answer to a legal question where the import of positive law was uncertain ….” (my emphasis).</p>



<p>This key feature of the classical view is very much, I think, the same point that Professor Rodriguez-Blanco made earlier today, in powerful terms, about the inextricability of the normative in interpretation of the law. Now, the classical view may or may not be correct, but it cannot be stipulated away by brute force. To tacitly assume that <em>lex</em> can be understood entirely independently of <em>ius</em> assumes the very conclusion that the positivist or originalist wants to prove. The claim of the classical lawyer is that reading <em>lex</em> in the light of <em>ius</em> is the right and indeed unavoidable way the work of law as law reads texts.</p>



<p>It is thus a misstep, however appealing it may appear, to argue (as “natural law originalists” do) that the common good enters in only at the level of justifying the enactment of positive law by the civil authorities. To repeat, this drops an essential element of the classical conception: law is not merely an ordination for the common good (resting on second-order reasons like coordination), but is itself constituted as an ordination of reason. As Finnis puts it (actually I am here quoting Conor both quoting and summarizing Finnis), “constitutional interpretation can never reasonably strive to be exclusively historical and seek to confine itself to ascertaining socio-historic facts. That is, from a normative perspective officials should not deliberately try to entirely exclude considerations of political morality during interpretation. It is defined into the nature of the posited law of a particular community that it derives from higher law that it determines and specifies…. [Legal] interpretation is an act that ‘can and should’ be ‘guided by moral principles and rules’ that are a matter of ‘objective reasonableness….’”</p>



<p>I have two examples of this. The first is the rules of chess, which Steve Sachs offered as an example (indeed the only example he mentioned) of a domain in which interpretation proceeds solely on the basis of social fact. I’m tempted to just say that law is not like chess, because it is not. Law, unlike chess, is not a closed system. But it turns out in any event that interpretation of the rules of chess does not at all operate the way Steve&nbsp; described; quite the opposite. Periodically a debate breaks out in the chess community over whether tacit, unspoken agreement on draws between grandmasters (as by repetition of moves), in tournaments where express verbal draw offers are banned (at least before a certain move), counts as&nbsp; circumvention of the rules or even a kind of cheating. Although of course there are fixed rules of chess, whose terms are settled by an authoritative body, participants on all sides of this debate offer interpretive arguments about the <em>point</em> of the rules, arguments sounding in fit and justification — arguments that try to reach reflective equilibrium among the point and purpose of all the written and unwritten rules of chess jointly and severally, and also among competing conceptions of sporting honor. With chess gone, we have no example on the table of an activity in which interpretation is not inevitably normative.</p>



<p>Let me now give a serious legal example, from a modern judge, of this view that even semantic meaning is always already to be understood and interpreted in light of background principles of <em>ius</em>. The case is called <em>Webster v. Doe</em>, and the judge is none other than Justice Scalia. The text at issue in <em>Webster</em> authorized the Director of the CIA, “in his discretion,” to terminate any CIA employee “whenever he shall deem such termination necessary or advisable in the interests of the United States.” The question was whether a termination was or was not reviewable by the courts on various grounds. The majority said that the text created a pure zone of discretion such that there was “no law to apply,” and the text authorized termination for any reason whatsoever — although the majority then immediately undermined its own holding by also saying that Congress had not meant to preclude review on constitutional grounds, as opposed to statutory grounds. Justice Scalia took an entirely different and entirely classical view. He observed that, quote, “there is no governmental decision that is not subject to a fair number of legal constraints precise enough to be susceptible of judicial application &#8211; <em>beginning with the fundamental constraint that the decision must be taken in order to further a public purpose rather than a purely private interest</em>.” This is to understand both the legal and indeed semantic meaning of the text at issue as <em>already</em> embodying a set of fundamental background principles, here the bedrock classical conception that law rightly understood must be rationally oriented to the public interest or common good. That conception is, on the classical view, a principle of the <em>ius naturale</em> itself. As Cicero put it in a treatise on public offices, “<em>sed communis utilitatis derelictio contra naturam est: est enim injusta</em>” (to disregard the common good is against nature; it is injustice itself). Note here, crucially, that Scalia goes well beyond Lee Strang’s idea of using the common good merely as a justification for positive lawmaking by civil authorities. Instead, like the classical lawyers, he invokes it <em>within</em> adjudication itself, as a ground or precondition of lawmaking that is always constitutive of and inherent within even the semantic meaning of legal texts.</p>



<p>I hope this example also clears up what I take to be another issue that appears in Lee’ Strang’s paper and in the Pojanowski and Walsh review, the question of different philosophical conceptions of the common good. As a first-order matter, the book adopts, straight from the tradition that runs consistently from Aristotle to Augustine to Aquinas, the Thomistic or distinctive conception of the common good, most clearly and concretely illustrated in my view when Aquinas says that “the individual good is impossible without the common good of the family, state, or kingdom. Hence Valerius Maximus says of the ancient Romans that ‘they would rather be poor in a rich empire than rich in a poor empire.’” Lee seems to opts for a different conception of the common good, the instrumental conception, one which is idiosyncratic among natural lawyers, and which John Finnis more or less abandoned after (and perhaps because) his work was critiqued by Fortin, as discussed in another recent paper by Erika Bachiochi.</p>



<p>That said, here is the more important point: as George Duke once rightly observed, and as Conor and I have written jointly and severally, for concrete legal purposes&nbsp; the lawyer or judge usually need not choose between high-level philosophical conceptions of the common good. (<em>Pace</em> a suggestion by Lee Strang, I fail entirely to see any inconsistency between that point and the first-order view I happen to hold). In particular, for the humdrum purposes of the classical lawyer, who works with the rough instruments of the law, refinements at the contested outer edges of the philosophical debates are&nbsp; usually irrelevant. Law is a department of political morality, but as it were a special department with its own distinctive problems and commitments. Principles of <em>ius</em> are thus not co-extensive with ‘morality’ <em>tout court</em>; they are, as the tradition puts it, principles of legal justice, and law is not seminar-room reasoning about morality, but rather the distinctive craft or “art” of the good and the equitable (<em>ars boni et aequi</em>).&nbsp;</p>



<p>The cases thus involve the sort of questions of practical legal reason Justice Scalia adverted to in <em>Webster v. Doe</em>, such as whether the CIA director really should be able to fire an employee in order to, say, give the job to his nephew. Thus I would urge that we lawyers pay rather less attention to debatable philosophical refinements of the common good and rather more attention to the civil-lawyer side of the <em>ius commune</em>, in which <em>bonum commune</em> or common good does not refer to some contested philosophical conception. Instead it serves very concrete ends. It condemns the abuse of official power for private purposes like nepotism or peculation; it underwrites equitable and public-regarding interpretations of semantic meaning; and it helps to prevent a kind of pointless and fetishistic legal formalism that benefits few and harms all.</p>



<p>In general, there are here two risks to avoid, two monsters between whom we have to steer. Law has two functions that are inextricably intertwined, settlement or coordination of social disputes and rational governance for the common good, and (hence) two aspects, fiat and reason. The twin errors arise when one or another side of these antinomies is made the master of the other — either near-exclusive concern for the settlement and coordinating function of law on the part of originalists and positivists, or excessive attention to pure speculative and normative reason on the part of the philosophers and jurisprudes. The classical lawyer, working <em>as</em> a lawyer, aims to hold these in a kind of productive balance, using both fit and justification. The book is thus very much a lawyer’s book, working <em>within</em> law in a way that is interpretive rather than purely positive or purely normative. It is a misapprehension of genre to read it as a philosophical exercise. Following another excellent paper by Emad Atiq, my suggestion for doctrinally trained law professors as such is that we rarely have much to contribute to technical debates in legal philosophy, but happily we rarely have any need to do so.</p>



<p>Here I should briefly re-emphasize a point I and others have made before, in order to clear up a misconception that I’ve heard at a few points today. On the classical view, judicial assessment of the common good is by no means an open-ended and unstructured imposition of judicial views of the common good in the name of higher constitutional law. To think this way is to adopt a framework oriented fundamentally to constitutional judicial review as a check or trump that invalidates political action — a&nbsp; quite recent framework that, as Helmholz has repeatedly pointed out, is marginal at best in the classical tradition. I was thinking about this as I listened to Stephanie Barclay’s interesting and admirably lawyerly paper. Originalists especially need, I think, to internalize the demonstrations by Helmholz, Jud Campbell, and others that constitutional review was by and large a sideshow in the Founding era. As Campbell puts it, “natural rights at the Founding scarcely resembled our modern notion of rights as determinate legal constraints on governmental authority.”</p>



<p>Rather, on the classical approach, judicial assessment of the common good is sharply limited and structured in at least three ways. First, it is primarily a subconstitutional interpretive tool, which reads and interprets legislative texts within the horizon of <em>ius, </em>including an orientation to the common good as a key element of <em>ius</em>. On this approach, putative acts of lawmaking that violate natural law or natural rights are seen as defective or perverse pseudo-lawmaking. But it is an entirely separate question whether a court, for example, has the authority to ignore, set aside or “strike down” the law, as both Aquinas and the classical lawyers make very clear, and it is usually a marginal question. Second, as the mainstream of classical American caselaw shows, classical judicial assessment of the common good is presumptively deferential within reasonable boundaries, not only or not primarily because of concerns about limited judicial capacities, but more fundamentally because the inherent office of the lawmaker is to provide reasonable specification or determination of background principles of <em>ius</em>. Third, as the book tries to make clear, the ordinary framework of judicial review in classical American law is at bottom analogous to what we would see today as an administrative-law conception of review, one that asks whether the action of the civil authorities is based on plausible reasons oriented to the public interest.</p>



<p>Here I thought Stephanie Barclay makes a slight misstep by assuming that asking government “to explain why it is not regulating in even-handed ways” and to offer a proper public-regarding motive is not a part of the classical administrative law model of review. On the contrary: as to the former, Aquinas argues that equal sharing of burdens is constitutive of the common good. As to the latter, the&nbsp; classical decisions, the classically-oriented Scalia opinion in <em>Webster v. Doe, </em>and indeed a quite recent decision of the Court in the census case illustrate that although general principles of law afford a presumption of regularity to official action, administrative law review for invalid purpose or pretext is possible, where no public-regarding motive is plausible in light of the scope and design of the action.</p>



<p>A final methodological point is that it is important not to run together two distinct issues that I fear are often conflated. Enrichment of our legal ontology need not produce more indeterminacy and disagreement at the level of interpretation; indeed it will in some range of cases produce less. As Helmholz argues throughout his work, and as Conor Casey illustrated from recent Irish law, a standard way classical lawyers draw upon <em>ius</em> is to invoke settled and traditional background principles in order to <em>reduce</em> indeterminacy that would otherwise obtain in the positive law. Whenever I hear stock points about the indeterminacy of <em>ius</em> or about disagreement about the content of <em>ius</em>, I think immediately of both the extraordinary proliferation of mutually opposed originalisms at the academic level and of the chronic disagreements that afflict originalist and positivist judges almost daily. And then I wonder why so many academic defenses of originalism implicitly assume that positive texts are fully determinate (practicing judges and lawyers are less susceptible to this), while also assuming that <em>ius</em> is chronically indeterminate. And I also wonder why the points about indeterminacy and disagreement are rarely run through consistently and comparatively across legal theories.</p>



<p>The fact is that disagreement, like fallibility, is just a universal condition of life for cognitively bounded and constrained human beings. It is just a condition of the fallen state of man. It applies to all legal theories if it applies to any; it cuts in all directions; or, to change the metaphor, it cuts too much ice and thereby ends up cutting none. When someone raised the old trope that “natural law theories are subject to bad-faith hijacking,” I thought “plug any theory into that blank. No legal theory, as such, can guarantee the conditions for its own enforcement.” To do so is not the province of legal theory.</p>



<p>This theme of disagreement is a good place to end.&nbsp; If history is any guide, these debates will continue ad infinitum, one side having the upper hand for a time, and then the other. None of that is inconsistent with believing that there is a right answer, as Dworkin used to stress. But it is perhaps at least a good reason to take a broader, more cosmopolitan attitude to those disagreements and to appreciate or even savor the rich variety both of law’s history and of law’s manifold forms around the world today.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://iusetiustitium.com/enriching-legal-theory/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1848</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Classical Political Forms, the Mixed Regime, and the State of Emergency—Roman, Byzantine, Muscovite?</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/classical-political-forms-the-mixed-regime-and-the-state-of-emergency-roman-byzantine-muscovite/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=classical-political-forms-the-mixed-regime-and-the-state-of-emergency-roman-byzantine-muscovite</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 16:48:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Roman Law]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1836</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ius &#38; Iustitium welcomes submissions from academics, practicing lawyers, and students interested in the classical legal tradition. The following essay was submitted by Julian G. Waller, Professorial Lecturer in Political Science at George Washington University, a Visiting Scholar at the Institute for European, Russian and Eurasian Studies, and a Non-Resident Fellow at Elliott School of&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/classical-political-forms-the-mixed-regime-and-the-state-of-emergency-roman-byzantine-muscovite/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Classical Political Forms, the Mixed Regime, and the State of Emergency—Roman, Byzantine, Muscovite?</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Ius &amp; Iustitium welcomes submissions from academics, practicing lawyers, and students interested in the classical legal tradition.</em> <em>The following essay was submitted by Julian G. Waller, Professorial Lecturer in Political Science at George Washington University, a Visiting Scholar at the Institute for European, Russian and Eurasian Studies, and a Non-Resident Fellow at Elliott School of International Affairs’ Illiberalism Studies Program. All views are his own and do not represent his employers or affiliated organizations.&nbsp;</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity is-style-wide"/>



<p>Interest in the&nbsp;<a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/reviving-the-classical-legal-tradition-in-an-age-of-legal-barbarism/">classical legal tradition</a>&nbsp;and the classical philosophies on political regime and&nbsp;<a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/catholic-constitutionalism-a-primer/">political order</a>&nbsp;from which it emerged have grown significantly, as this very publication outlet&nbsp;<a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/rights-and-the-common-good/">can</a>&nbsp;<a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/on-the-tyranny-of-rights/">attest</a>. This revival is particularly interesting because until recently the categories and frames of reference central to the classical tradition have been largely outside the mainstream of scholarly work across an array of academic genres, from legal theory to political science and beyond.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Given this, I wanted to invite the readers of&nbsp;<em>I&amp;I</em>’s attention to a recent attempt at melding older understandings of political regime with modern scholarship – thus far still a rare occasion. This summary is an encouragement for those interested in classical political concepts and their relevance to the classical legal tradition to engage with both the promise and pitfalls of this approach to the scholarly study of political order and political regime. Most scholarship today does not consciously rely on classical frameworks for these topics. It is therefore important to understand the difficulty of translating old and new ways of typifying regime, and to take interest whenever such a mixing, or an attempt at application, is undertaken.&nbsp;</p>



<span id="more-1836"></span>



<p><strong>Old and New in the Study of Comparative Authoritarianism&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>My own field of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/british-journal-of-political-science/article/abs/institutional-turn-in-comparative-authoritarianism/DF3E2FF1E79A8D41E3E60F1D45A1B5C5">comparative authoritarianism</a>&nbsp;studies – that is, the political science (sub-)subfield tasked with explaining the nature of, functioning, output, and patterned variations in non-democratic rule across societies – owes a great debt to classical thinking on the structural contours of political regime. Yet it also studiously ignores the primary categorizations of that legacy. These older frameworks, well developed in classical thought, largely coalesce around the interaction between a&nbsp;<a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/aristotle-politics/#GeneTheoConsCiti">simple tripartite division</a>&nbsp;of&nbsp;<em>de facto</em>&nbsp;rulership structure (single-few-many) with the motivating orientation of that given regime (for the common good/‘just’ vs. for personal benefit/‘unjust’). Thus, we have inherited terms, and their mirror-images, such as monarchy (tyranny), aristocracy (oligarchy), and polity (democracy).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Other derivations from the classical tradition include the core split between monarchy and republic, abstract understandings of the&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>&nbsp;or ‘commonwealth,’ and the interlocking institutional puzzle-pieces of the ‘mixed regime.’ Some of these terms have partially retained their old meaning, although often applied in distinct ways, while others have been entirely divorced from their original conceptualizations or simply discarded.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Indeed, when describing variations in political regime today we often prefer to think in terms of&nbsp;<a href="https://v-dem.net/media/publications/dr_2022.pdf">spectra of relative political pluralism</a>&nbsp;with a binary cut-point (liberal democracy/electoral democracy vs. electoral authoritarianism/closed authoritarianism) framed around electoral institutions. Or, alternatively, we rely on a subset of classification types constructed around distinct&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/perspectives-on-politics/article/abs/autocratic-breakdown-and-regime-transitions-a-new-data-set/EBDB9E5E64CF899AD50B9ACC630B593F">organizational patterns</a>&nbsp;(monarchy, military junta, party-state, personalist dictatorship, electoral authoritarianism, and ‘hybrid’ regimes).&nbsp;</p>



<p>In neither preferred framework do we explicitly use normative criteria (for example, ‘just’ or ‘unjust’) to determine category inclusion. Implicit normative associations are, of course, certainly present – but they are distinct from any given classifying exercise itself. This disjuncture in categorization approaches between modern and classical regime studies has major ramifications for how we delineate the empirical world into meaningful conceptual boxes, given that the desire for ideal-typical classification is just as strong today as it was two and a half millennia ago.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This leaves us in a strange place, where contemporary scholars are highly indebted to classical legacies of categorizing political order, yet we generally do not follow (or sometimes even remember) those older schemas. Any project to rehabilitate the classical tradition must grapple with the fact that we have dropped both the terms and the normative way of thinking that undergirded that intellectual heritage.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The problem therefore cuts both ways: while it is important for contemporary social scientists to think seriously about what may be gained by engaging once more with the classical tradition of regime study, it is also clear that those formed in the classical tradition can similarly gain from reflection on the results of&nbsp;<a href="https://politicalorders.substack.com/p/regime-types-and-their-limitations">modern frameworks</a>&nbsp;and our (sometimes)&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/perspectives-on-politics/article/autocratic-breakdown-and-regime-transitions-a-new-data-set/EBDB9E5E64CF899AD50B9ACC630B593F">empirically-derived</a>&nbsp;conceptualizations. As an example of correction on the social scientific side, in an ongoing book project with coauthors, we suggest that the comparative authoritarianism literature has likely made an error in some of its&nbsp;<a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4033720">hidden assumptions</a>&nbsp;baked into generic terms like ‘autocracy,’ which we sometimes use to describe all non-democratic regimes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These frames tend to take as a baseline assumption that all types of non-democracy share internal dynamics best expressed by the classical form of ‘tyranny’ (singular rulership motivated solely for the ruler’s own gain and survival). This has led us to assume the existence of a leader-directed, intentional politics of ‘autocracy’ that is often at odds with the institutional, ideological, and unintentional realities of real authoritarian politics across a vast set of country-cases over the last century or more. So let us turn to a recent use of classical concepts in modern scholarship, and how this can both be a success, and yet also lead to potential confusions that must be dealt with head-on.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>An Example in Bringing Classical Political Forms into Modern Scholarship</strong></p>



<p>Revitalizing promoters of the classical tradition face strong headwinds given that the vast majority of research output on politics largely elides that same tradition. It is therefore relevant to be aware of instances where the classical tradition’s theories are applied in contemporary social sciences and the political humanities. This brings us to a recent issue of&nbsp;<em>Slavic Review,</em>&nbsp;one of the&nbsp;<a href="http://www.slavicreview.illinois.edu/">premier academic journals</a>&nbsp;focusing the post-Soviet Eurasian region published by the interdisciplinary regional association&nbsp;<a href="https://www.aseees.org/">ASEEES</a>.</p>



<p>A curious article – and set of responses – was published in the Fall 2021 issue that dealt with the classical concept of the ‘mixed regime’ and its relation to the Schmittian/Agambenic ‘<a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/meditations-on-the-emergency/">state of exception</a>,’ in reference to the political history of Rome, Byzantium, and medieval Muscovy. The article in question, “<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/slavic-review/article/abs/authority-and-power-in-russia/2949CB5EFECD85C08AE8D2EBF8DBD0CA">Authority and Power in Russia</a>” by the Russian scholar Oleg Kharkhordin, was followed by responses from the classicist Anthony Kaldellis (“<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/slavic-review/article/abs/response-to-authority-and-power-in-russia/95899DF3C3251CFFF044AC7138A92E60">Response to ‘Authority and Power in Russia’</a>”), the historian Nancy Shields Kollman (“<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/slavic-review/article/abs/muscovite-republic/57B9784F515957556B06A20161C5A1F3">A Muscovite Republic?</a>”), and the political theorist Miguel Vatter (“<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/slavic-review/article/abs/third-rome-and-russian-republicanism-a-comment-on-oleg-kharkhordin-power-and-authority-in-russia/8A85A9CCD9D28A1350AF8A88988E48F5">The Third Rome and Russian Republicanism: A Comment on Oleg Kharkhordin ‘Power and Authority in Russia’</a>”). The article follows on Kharkhordin’s 2018 book,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674976726"><em>Republicanism in Russia</em></a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Kharkhordin’s article is summarized in its journal abstract as such:&nbsp;</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>Can classical political theories of mixed constitution from Polybius to Cicero help us shed new light on Russian politics? In order to so, this article first considers political structures of such non-parliamentary republics as medieval Novgorod and Venice, while choosing Constantinople as a basis for their comparison. Second, using Anthony Kaldellis&#8217;s recent book that has reinterpreted Byzantium in terms of the classical theory of&nbsp;</em>res publica<em>, it analyzes the question of&nbsp;</em>auctoritas<em>&nbsp;in ancient republican Rome and then imperial Constantinople. Third, the author employs Giorgio Agamben&#8217;s book on the state of exception, in order to see how mechanisms of power and authority that the Roman emperors had employed might help us interpret anew the phenomenon of tsardom, given that Ivan the Terrible was the first in Russia to be crowned as tsar, that is, Ceasar&nbsp;</em>[sic]<em>. This might have a lasting significance even for present day politics.</em></p></blockquote>



<p>The overview Kharkhordin’s argument – or several wandering arguments, as it turns out – below is a means to engender interest in what otherwise would be held within the paywalled confines of academic humanities and social scientific journals. The reader of&nbsp;<em>I&amp;I</em>&nbsp;may take it as is, but of course the best use of scholarship is to build on that which is useful and contest that which is off-target. Those engaged in the project of revitalizing the classics will find much to recommend and reject in this particular exercise in applied conceptualization and classification. As it is one of the few recent examples of an application of classical political theory beyond core European cases, it acts as a useful test-case in how such theories may – or may not – travel well.</p>



<p><strong>Brief Summary of “Authority and Power in Russia”&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Kharkhordin’s article is framed as a discussion of the deep legacies of Russian politics today (and how they sit in enduring relation to the modern Putin regime), but he is far more interested in a few key thematic questions of political history and regime classification. He relies entirely on classical concepts, rather than modern theories of authoritarianism or political regime.&nbsp;</p>



<p>First, Kharkhordin asks to which medieval Russian polity the ‘Third Rome’ epithet properly should be given. In assessing this, he makes the claim that both the historical Roman and Byzantine polities were examples of classical ‘mixed regimes.’ The northern state of Novgorod the Great fits this model far closer than the Rus successor states or Muscovy. In bringing the classical concept of the mixed regime into contact with non-Western political history, he makes special reference to the role of popular acclamation – the ‘democratic’ element of the mixed regime – as being of especially underappreciated conceptual relevance.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Second, Kharkhordin attempts to delineate medieval Muscovy’s relation to the mixed regime concept, having recourse to the concept of the ‘state of exception’ (or ‘state of emergency’), which he takes from Giorgio Agamben (and by implication Carl Schmitt). With this, he claims that the Muscovite autocracy, and its Russian successor, was itself a strange beast – a perversely institutionalized regime of emergency that nevertheless held in some ways to a mixed regime substrate. The article is a provocative set of conceptual interventions, all of which rely heavily on interpreting and applying classical political concepts beyond their original places of development in the Mediterranean basin. I draw out his claims in more detail below – where the interested reader will find a variety of classical concepts being used in quite distinct ways.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Mixed Regimes, Popular Acclamations, States of Emergency, and Redefining Autocracy</strong></p>



<p>At its core, Kharkhordin’s rather meandering narrative makes the argument that Russian politics in its <em>longue durée</em> should be understood as a fusion of an “excessive zeal of the powers that be and their insufficient formalism,” which is, in his view, strongly related to the legacy of “classical (non-parliamentary) republics” and their partial implantation in Russian political history (Kharkhordin, p. 470).</p>



<p>Kharkhordin starts by making a comparison of the famous mixed regime of medieval Venice with the more poorly-understood regime of Novgorod the Great – a northern Russian polity that was eclipsed and ultimately destroyed by Muscovy in the 16<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;century. He suggests that Novgorod was evolving towards something like the Venetian mixed regime ideal (embodied as the threefold Doge-Senate-Great Council division of political authority) in a process of “progressive oligarchization” of its popular elements, but without a concomitant crystallization of a guiding aristocracy (Kharkhordin pp. 471-472). Why does this matter? To Kharkhordin, the mixed regime is not only a vision of ‘republicanism’ as it partially existed in medieval Russia but is nothing less than a legacy of the Byzantine Empire.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In making this claim, he relies on a recategorization of Byzantium as a&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>&nbsp;(a classical “republic”) found in the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674365407">revisionist account</a>&nbsp;of Anthony Kaldellis. This account of a “<em>res publica&nbsp;</em>in its monarchical form” included “elements of popular sovereignty… [such that the] Byzantine people could reclaim its sovereignty for a moment if a given emperor was losing popularity or in those instances when one emperor was being replaced by another” (Kharkhordin p. 473).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Kharkhordin contends that this possibility for popular input via revolt and objection undergirded a political order in which popular acclamation was critical to the “maintenance of power” through a “continual referendum” that in calm times defaulted to giving power to a republican&nbsp;<em>qua</em>&nbsp;imperial executive. He further argues that it “explains to a large extent the common non-dynastic succession of the rulers as well as the Byzantine horrors of deposing a former emperor…in order to finally elicit acceptable public acclamation on the part of the people in the hippodrome or some other public venue.” (Kharkhordin p. 474).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Armed with this reframing of Byzantium as a&nbsp;<em>res publica&nbsp;</em>in monarchical garb, Kharkhordin turns to Muscovy proper, his primary interest. He controversially discounts the usual categorization of the Muscovite regime as an “unbridled autocracy” and argues instead that it was still “sometimes dependent on democratic contributions, coupled frequently with a very slight aristocratic element” (Kharkhordin p. 475). He suggests that the reign of Ivan IV Grozny (Ivan the Terrible, Grand Prince of Muscovy 1533-1547; Tsar of All Russias 1547-1587) is an example of republican Caesarism established through a permanent ‘state of exception,’ operating on a political system that otherwise largely inherited the structural underpinnings of the Byzantine mixed regime. Here he brings in work by Giorgio Agamben, who has revived the Schmittian account of the&nbsp;<em>stato di eccezione</em>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Using the crisis-ridden politics of late republican Rome as the primary case for how the mixed regime and the state of exception interact, Kharkhordin argues that during this period of political troubles Rome remained a mixed regime despite its troubles in this era. Yet he also states that, “[in] this republic of mixed government, however, there was a special condition that was designated under the name of&nbsp;<em>iustitium</em>, under which all laws came to a standstill and courts stopped their normal functioning,” and that “the reason for the introduction of&nbsp;<em>iustitium</em>&nbsp;was a condition called&nbsp;<em>tumulti</em>, internal or external disorders that threatened to topple&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>&nbsp;altogether.” (Kharkhordin p. 477).&nbsp;</p>



<p>In this retelling, “[t]he state of exception, or&nbsp;<em>iustitium</em>, was ushered into Rome during the pre-imperial days by authority of the Senate, not by decision of the consuls or the people. Therefore, after a transfer of&nbsp;<em>auctoritas</em>&nbsp;from the Senate to the emperor, he became the living embodiment of the right to declare the state of exception in order to save&nbsp;<em>patria</em>&nbsp;from collapse.” (Kharkhordin pp. 477-478).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Kharkhordin runs through a terminological discussion of the differences between <em>auctoritas</em>, <em>potestas</em>, and <em>imperium</em> – traditional conceptual differentiations found in the classical Roman political ecosystem – as well as how this translated itself into the Christianized late empire and even the conceptual innovation of the <a href="https://thejosias.com/2016/03/03/integralism-and-gelasian-dyarchy/">Gelasian Dyarchy</a> in early post-Roman Christendom. One imagines that this unusual understanding of the concept of iustitium alone will be of interest to readers here at I&amp;I. All of this is in service to an argument whose goal is to apply the concept of a state of exception in a mixed regime to polities well beyond the Western historical remit. </p>



<p>Kharkhordin then returns to Ivan Grozny’s reign of terror, and makes the claim that the Tsar and his infamous&nbsp;<em>oprichnina</em> (a personal regiment of warriors which bloodily enforced Ivan’s rule and whose membership, origin, and power remains still disputed today) displaced the mixed regime of the monarchical Muscovite ruler and the aristocratic Boyar Duma, which had developed organically over the course of the first half of the 16<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;century. “[Yet] [t]his process of deliberation and counselling still functioned save for the&nbsp;<em>oprich</em>΄ lands, where Ivan Groznyi had established his court at Aleksandrovskaia Sloboda to be run like a monastery. During the night the tsar prayed, during the day he tortured and punished, and during his joint meals with the courtiers of the exceptional realm he read the Holy Writ.” (Kharkhordin p. 480).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Kharkhordin points to Ivan’s own assessment of the failed Byzantine&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>, in a written testament where he “striv[ed] to prove that the emperors there relied far too much on their counsellors, and their struggles and intrigues had ruined the great Roman empire.” In this way, Ivan argued that “while the&nbsp;<em>ipaty</em>&nbsp;(consuls), the&nbsp;<em>sinklity</em>&nbsp;(senators), and the&nbsp;<em>eparkhi</em>&nbsp;(local dignitaries) were engaged in warfare for power and privilege, the territory of the Byzantine empire was shrinking, and Greek tsardom, as Ivan calls it, was crumbling.” (Kharkhordin p. 480). He points to the Tsar’s rejection of a distinct ecclesiastical authority and his emphasis on a unitary, millenarian caesaropapism as central to characterizing this state of exception.</p>



<p>Here, he points to a different conceptual division of rulership derived from Deacon Agapetus under the Emperor Justinian and its revision by the jurist Ioannes Lydus:&nbsp;<em>ennomos basileia</em>&nbsp;(“when the basileus rules according to laws”), tyranny (“when he ignores them or rules according to caprice”), and&nbsp;<em>autocratia&nbsp;</em>or&nbsp;<em>samoderzhavie</em>&nbsp;(“that is…supreme military command…and authority”). This third account is “<em>autarcheia kai authentia</em>&nbsp;[or]&nbsp;<em>imperium auctoritasque</em>” which sits conceptually alongside a ‘state of exception’ understanding of the Caesarian&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>. (Kharkhordin p. 483).&nbsp;</p>



<p>In this way, Kharkhordin implies that Ivan’s Muscovy was a sort of institutionalized (post-) commissary dictatorship&nbsp;<em>per</em><a href="https://www.worldcat.org/title/dictatorship-from-the-origin-of-the-modern-concept-of-sovereignty-to-proletarian-class-struggle/oclc/865144021"> Schmitt</a>, in which the autocratic emergency regime sat above an inherited, but unused, mixed-regime structural base. He concludes that the case is indeed simple, that “[i]t is illuminating to interpret [Ivan] Groznyi’s behavior with the help of the Byzantine notion of a Caesar-<em>autokrator</em>&nbsp;who combines power and authority in the same hands.” (Kharkhordin p.484).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Throughout the article, one is struck by the conceptual reliance on Roman, Byzantine, and medieval Russian sources in this account of certain premodern authoritarian political orders. Many of those who mine the classical tradition on political regime will find new sources and new ways of understanding very old terms of rulership and their justification – as well as controversial definitions and their uneven application.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Some of Kharkhordin’s contributions are more innovative. For example, the serious appraisal of symbolic acclamation (let alone real,&nbsp;<em>de facto</em>&nbsp;politically relevant forms of acclamation and objection) as an important element to political rule is something that has been lost in many accounts of authoritarianism, but fits quite well with concepts of Caesarism, Bonapartism, and other accounts that look to popular legitimacy as crucial to rule, for example.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Treating this at the end of the essay, Kharkhordin even suggests that acclamation is the political substance which “laud[s] a ruler, whose authority [then] allows him or her to introduce a state of exception at his or her discretion” (Kharkhordin p. 487). Finessing this to somehow be a primary source of political legitimacy for Russia’s varied forms of authoritarianism through the centuries is a more difficult argument to make, of course, and it ultimately raises more questions about the state of emergency concept itself than anything else.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>The Difficulty with Using Classical Concepts Authoritatively&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>So, does any of this actually work? In perfect frankness, the article is easily criticized on a number of dimensions, both conceptual and empirical, and I have made no effort to smooth over what amounts to a very confused narrative. The clunky summary above indeed fits the tone of the article. The primary claim that Muscovy can be plausibly identified as a kind of republican ‘mixed regime’ is weak at best, while the wide-ranging discussion of rather dissimilar imperial polities of Mediterranean civilization leaves the argument prone to ungrounded gestures rather than clear case-analysis. This comes out in the responses included in the journal issue, as one might expect.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Anthony Kaldellis, for one, does not buy the claim that his own revisionist account of the Byzantine polity really travels to the dark decades of Ivan IV. He points to the high conceptual bar in his own work to describe such a state as a ‘republican monarchy,’ requiring:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>&nbsp;“(a) a robust conception of the public interest and public property to which the monarch is subordinated in normative texts issued both by the monarchy itself and its elites; (b) a conception of a legally- or ethnically-defined populace whose material wellbeing forms the sole legitimating factor for the operation of government, even if that populace lacks formal institutions by which to take direct political action itself; (c) historical instances of popular intervention in the sphere of politics that were accepted by elites as legitimate, indeed often as constitutive of their own power and positions; and (d) documented continuity between that polity and the ancient Roman&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>, coupled with awareness of that continuity.” (Kaldellis p. 489).&nbsp;</p></blockquote>



<p>Even excising part (d) as a definitional overspecification, it does not work for Muscovy, and likely does not even work for Novgorod. Kaldellis as a reviewer is more interested in the state of exception discussion in relation to Ivan’s&nbsp;<em>oprichnina</em>, although reviewing the limited evidence, he does not find real substance behind the assertion that the polity rests on a philosophical claim to accountability to a public sphere&nbsp;<em>per se</em>. That is, unlike in his Byzantine account, “there is no conception of a polity defined by a specific populace to which the monarch is beholden and whose moral presence alone can legitimate (or delegitimate) his acts” (Kaldellis p.490). From Kaldellis’s perspective, this dooms the attempt at regime classification that runs through Kharkhordin’s article.&nbsp;</p>



<p>From a different perspective, Nancy Shields Kollman situates Kharkhordin’s argument in a historiographic frame, noting that “decades (since the 1930s) if not three centuries (since the Enlightenment) of ‘Byzantine Studies’ have distorted the historical record by ignoring&nbsp;<em>politeia</em>&nbsp;in favor of&nbsp;<em>avtokratia</em>,” and that this fails to allow for a fuller understanding of the key paradox of the Roman&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>: that “the ruler was posited as above the law even though he was supposed to rule according to the law” (Kollman p. 493). This useful endeavor, in her view, does not work in the cases assessed here, however. In application to Novgorod, Kollman finds the article deficient in empirical sourcing and underappreciative of the oligarchic nature of that polity, and for Muscovy the case is even more stretched.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In alignment with Kaldellis, she is most intrigued by the focus on the state of exception, rather than the ‘republican’ regime-classification claims made for these polities. Even given arguments made by some recent historians of Muscovite and Russian political culture that stress a focus on consensus rather than just unbridled autocracy, its characterization as a&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>&nbsp;goes too far in her view. Still, Kollman falls in this revisionist camp (i.e. those that emphasize consensus mechanisms in Russian history) to some degree, and concludes her review stating that, “Muscovite political culture was more than religiously based, the power of the ruler was&nbsp;<em>de facto</em>&nbsp;limited by dense networks of theory, custom, and political pragmatism, ‘autocracy’ was not absolute, and multiple social forces played a role in keeping the realm legitimate.” (Kollman p. 497). Whether Kharkhordin’s effort of translating classical political regime theory into medieval Russia yielded real fruit that fits this description, however, she is less certain.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Finally, Miguel Vatter returns to the opening claims in Kharkhordin’s article, comparing Novgorod the Great and Venice as mixed regimes, as well as the reassessment of Byzantium along non-caesaropapist lines as a&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>&nbsp;properly speaking (that is, in his words, “always characterized by a republican organization, and not by a fusion of imperial power with Christian religion, that is, by a politico-theological structure of power” (Vatter p. 498)). Enjoyably, Vatter disputes Kaldellis’ own conceptualization of a “republican monarchy” as “a contradiction in terms,” leaving the Kharkhordin argument undermined at the terminological level by Vatter’s very different account of Aristotle and Plato’s understanding of&nbsp;<em>politeia&nbsp;</em>(‘polity’) and its connection to&nbsp;<em>res publica</em>. Thus, the troubles of terminology balloon quite quickly, even just within the confines of the classical sources.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In doing so, Vatter contests Kharkhordin’s claim of any sort of connection between medieval Russian polities and modern Russia with its “dictatorship of laws”: “[i]n reality, [Putin’s] use of the term ‘dictatorship’ was more likely invoking the Schmittian idea of the dictator (or autocrat) as holder of constituent power whereby his will is&nbsp;<em>ipso facto</em>&nbsp;law. Dictatorship is a rule by decrees; constitutionalism is a rule of law. They are mutually exclusive.” (Vatter p. 500). In this sense, Vatter nods to more modern conceptualizations of authoritarianism, constitutionalism, and political order – underlining the relevance of bringing both classical and contemporary accounts of regime into clearer dialogue.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Vatter is overall unconvinced by most of the claims in the essay, bringing in a different account of Agamben’s vision of the state of exception as well as the role of acclamation (“the acclamation is a politico-theological device of imperial sovereignty, and not a republican institution”) as well as the uncertain genealogical account of&nbsp;<em>iustitium</em>&nbsp;used by Kharkhordin (Vatter p. 502). Indeed, Vatter sees much in Kharkhordin’s case descriptions that do not fit with the theoretical frameworks on offer, including Kaldellis’ work, the ‘republican monarchy,’ and even the role of popular “tumults” as constituting a regime practice in and of itself. He finds these all to be of dubious relevance to the actual record of political history in Muscovy (or Byzantium, in the case of his dispute with Kaldellis).&nbsp;</p>



<p>Vatter concludes by reformulating the article, stating that, “[i]n the end, if I understand Kharkhordin correctly, he believes that republicanism is characterized by a mixed form of government, and that this is best delivered by a Venetian model, because the Roman one (in the case of all three imperial Romes) ultimately tends to collapse into a Weberian&nbsp;<em>Führer-Prinzip</em>&nbsp;(to employ an anachronistic formula) in which the emperor assumes absolute power and all legal authority on the basis of the acclamation of ‘his’ people (or troops)” (Vatter p. 503). The problem of case categorization and application remains far from overcome, in Vatter’s reading, while also posing serious questions about the concept of the state of emergency, its potential for political institutionalization, and its relation to the structural assumptions of the mixed regime classification.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Useful Takeaways from a Curious Exercise</strong></p>



<p>Where does this leave us? It should leave us pleased with the vast vistas which can be opened when one takes classical concepts seriously and brings them into application beyond their origin. It should also forcefully remind us of the potential difficulties and complications in doing so, which cannot be assumed or wished away. There are tremendous open fields to explore, dispute, and engage with classical political concepts in contemporary scholarship, but these opportunities have to be balanced with the reality that such terms and interpretations are far more uncertain and disputed than we might sometimes like to think.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The belief that there is a singularly authoritative conceptual tradition from which to draw easily and uncomplicatedly cannot be sustained, at least not when faced with empirical application. Yet for those interested in either the classical political forms or the ‘state of exception’ concept found in 20<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;century heterodox political thought, there is much to be mined and much more to be careful with.&nbsp;</p>



<p>My own view is that those newly working in the classical tradition sometimes rely on an overly truncated set of literature dealing with these sorts of questions. Sticking only to the Aristotelian-Polybian models of political order leads one to miss a great deal of complexity in how we understand regime, and premodern sources are sometimes shockingly imprecise.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Look only to the&nbsp;<em>specula principum</em>&nbsp;(‘<a href="https://postliberalorder.substack.com/p/mirror-of-princes">mirrors for princes’</a>) genre of political advice literature, which has classical antecedents but was particularly popular in the Medieval and Early Modern periods. This genre, produced by both Catholic and Protestant thinkers, struggled with ideal-typical questions of political regime, authority, and order in dialogue with the actually-existing challenges of rule for practicioners. Indeed, just glance at works by&nbsp;<a href="https://isidore.co/aquinas/DeRegno.htm">Saint Thomas Aquinas</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/cusanus/">Nicholas of Cusa</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/bodin/">Jean Bodin</a>, and&nbsp;<a href="https://oll.libertyfund.org/title/althusius-politica">Johannes Althusius</a>, among many others, for disputes about what the ‘mixed regime’ alone really entails.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Translating these core accounts out-of-area – to Byzantium, to Muscovy, and elsewhere – further illustrates the difficulties of conceptualization at both the ideal-typical and empirical level. And this challenge is hardly new. Yet if we want to engage seriously in the comparative study of political regimes, that is exactly what one must do.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In the end, Kharkhordin’s ultimately quite flawed article remains a valuable resource and instructive example of all these difficulties – as well as the opportunities provided when able to work through such issues seriously. Connecting classical frameworks to contemporary accounts of political order (authoritarian or otherwise) will likely bear considerable fruit in time. The project to bring the classical tradition into dialogue with the modern age, mining it for insights and using it as a touchstone point from which to reassess and strengthen scholarship, is a worthy one, but we must be cognizant of both its possibilities and its problems.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>A Note for Interested Readers&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>For those with university library access (or membership with ASEEES), the articles briefly and insufficiently summarized here should be&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/slavic-review/issue/E2569DFC6D671B5D5F5EDDA5847FBE73">available</a>&nbsp;in PDF format for free. For those without, you are welcome to&nbsp;<a href="https://julianwaller.weebly.com/contact-information.html">message me</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Selected Bibliography</strong>:&nbsp;</p>



<p>Kharkhordin, Oleg. “Authority and Power in Russia.”&nbsp;<em>Slavic Review</em>&nbsp;80, no. 3 (2021): 469–88. doi:10.1017/slr.2021.144.</p>



<p>Kaldellis, Anthony. “Response to ‘Authority and Power in Russia.’”&nbsp;<em>Slavic Review</em>&nbsp;80, no. 3 (2021): 489–91. doi:10.1017/slr.2021.150.</p>



<p>Kollmann, Nancy Shields. “A Muscovite Republic?”&nbsp;<em>Slavic Review</em>&nbsp;80, no. 3 (2021): 492–97. doi:10.1017/slr.2021.152.</p>



<p>Vatter, Miguel. “The Third Rome and Russian Republicanism: A Comment on Oleg Kharkhordin ‘Power and Authority in Russia.’”&nbsp;<em>Slavic Review</em>&nbsp;80, no. 3 (2021): 498–503. doi:10.1017/slr.2021.151&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1836</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How the Supreme Court Misses the Point on Fair Use</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/how-the-supreme-court-misses-the-point-on-fair-use/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=how-the-supreme-court-misses-the-point-on-fair-use</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jacob Neu]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2022 16:17:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1819</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Three icons of American pop culture–Andy Warhol, Prince, and the Supreme Court of the United States–converged this week when the Court heard oral arguments in Andy Warhol Foundation for the Visual Arts, Inc. v. Goldsmith. The case concerns whether a Warhol print based on a portrait of Prince by photographer Lynn Goldsmith constituted fair use&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/how-the-supreme-court-misses-the-point-on-fair-use/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">How the Supreme Court Misses the Point on Fair Use</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Three icons of American pop culture–Andy Warhol, Prince, and the Supreme Court of the United States<span id='easy-footnote-1-1819' class='easy-footnote-margin-adjust'></span><span class='easy-footnote'><a href='https://iusetiustitium.com/how-the-supreme-court-misses-the-point-on-fair-use/#easy-footnote-bottom-1-1819' title='&amp;nbsp;I leave it to the reader to determine whether I’m being ironic, and if so, which of the three should be dropped from the list of pop icons. And before you suggest SCOTUS is the odd one out, consider the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C1GCEB_enUS873US873&amp;amp;sxsrf=ALiCzsZujEZfSwZPVANuzwp4FgVliX6LnA:1665661515342&amp;amp;source=univ&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;q=ruth+bader+ginsburg+pop+art&amp;amp;fir=kui5w2R4O7117M%252CQrVbh--FtMxDeM%252C_%253BiBAYqfvVOSZTSM%252C-zXFy1naXXw7WM%252C_%253BnwTs9H1Cd2543M%252CZiQcK7x6tQJydM%252C_%253Bnu_sGz0fa4klYM%252C61K1W-JEEaqs5M%252C_%253B9okschSDoZdu7M%252CydHjDQ2Tw_7lsM%252C_%253BPDg7S3nCBbF6AM%252CQSkS1jpBuS_RkM%252C_%253BHDzp0-8EycfSLM%252CA2LxidBQyl3p5M%252C_%253BzpH9tsFawFczKM%252CgR0E2gOI1zZQeM%252C_%253BGR4kydEJloZ7WM%252COxIhkzyVlI6zmM%252C_%253Be0sTn8IN8PhbIM%252Cio696EFf_2CIWM%252C_%253Bu6EA1C5Hvukq2M%252CHOc2f6PaxqxO7M%252C_%253BxEIhfD_DX6WEWM%252CKetS4NMBCEqhQM%252C_%253B6UquVaeyCC7pgM%252CAKzgZsLohGGnQM%252C_%253BxFeepgOiiJzQzM%252Cjn6KyoYDPWO-1M%252C_%253BQ5_R-2h3bBeXBM%252C1qIsRhu04W0BPM%252C_%253BdmMgPuNVsAkEAM%252CO-ecaimmb9ng8M%252C_%253B_Y1I7o8bOQwCdM%252Cb5n7aiJW059kOM%252C_%253BxXLwsVqG4sWMgM%252CN3VoQ15M-TT5TM%252C_&amp;amp;usg=AI4_-kT00iI8Oi_J7GQl2GPHt6_BJnmWWg&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwi867_XkN36AhUnrmoFHS-gArgQjJkEegQICRAC&amp;amp;biw=1920&amp;amp;bih=880&amp;amp;dpr=1&quot;&gt;pop culture treatment of the late Ruth Bader Ginsburg&lt;/a&gt;.'><sup>1</sup></a></span>–converged this week when the Court heard oral arguments in <em>Andy Warhol Foundation for the Visual Arts, Inc. v. Goldsmith</em>. The case concerns whether a Warhol print based on a portrait of Prince by photographer Lynn Goldsmith constituted fair use or was instead an infringement of Goldsmith’s copyright. Warhol’s “Orange Prince” was one of a series of 16 works based on the same photograph, none with a license from Goldsmith. Goldsmith has asserted that this infringed her reproduction and derivative work rights in the original photograph. The images in question may be viewed at <a href="https://www.scotusblog.com/2022/10/the-court-of-art-criticism-is-in-session/">SCOTUSBlog’s summary of the oral argument</a>.</p>



<span id="more-1819"></span>



<p>I have discussed <a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/copyright-authors-right-and-the-common-good-part-i/">copyright </a>and fair use before for <em>Ius et Iustitium</em>, and in particular t<a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/copyright-authors-right-and-the-common-good-fair-use-part-ii/">he manner in which the analysis of fair use has strayed far from the purpose and text of Section 107 of the Copyright Act</a>. The parties’ briefs in this case and the oral argument on Wednesday have only highlighted the need for a full reconsideration of the scope of rights in a copyrighted work and the scope of fair use. As I previously discussed, the origins of fair use as a judicially created limitation on copyright protection in <em>Folsom v. Marsh</em> and the eventual codification of the doctrine in the Copyright Act of 1976 relied on illustrative “fair uses” directed to the public benefit and reception of a work. Such reliance fell from favor in <em>Harper &amp; Row v. Nation Enterprises</em>, which ignored the public nature of the use and focused instead on the transformativeness of the use (the nature of the use being one of the four factors required for consideration in the fair use statute). Since <em>Campbell v. Acuff-Rose Music, Inc.</em>, the transformative nature of the use has become the most preeminent element of the fair use standard.</p>



<p>The problem is that the Copyright Act grants to authors the exclusive right to “prepare derivative works based on the original work.” 17 U.S.C. 106(2). A “derivative work” is “a work based upon one or more preexisting works, such as a translation, musical arrangement, dramatization, fictionalization, motion picture version, sound recording, art reproduction, abridgment, condensation, or any other form in which a work may be recast, transformed, or adapted.” 17 U.S.C. 100. That last clause is extremely broad–any recasting, transformation, or adaptation is deemed a “derivative work” under the author’s exclusive control.</p>



<p>So a transformation of the original work is a derivative work, but a transformative use may nevertheless be deemed a fair use. The Copyright Act giveth transformative works unto authors, and the Copyright Act taketh away. The oral argument at times focused on exactly this point, as the justices and counsel struggled to determine to what extent an accused infringer must transform the original work to be deemed fair use. This is an impossible question, but it arises not just from the Supreme Court&#8217;s amorphous expansion of fair use but also from the statutory text. It is fair to say that litigants’ counsel and the Supreme Court have been pushed to expand the scope of fair use, a process which I have described in the posts linked above, by the problematic definition of “derivative work” and the scope of the derivative work right.</p>



<p>The current case, <em>Andy Warhol Foundation v. Goldsmith</em>, is a good example of this problem. Under the definition of “derivative work,” there is no question that Warhol’s “Orange Prince” is merely a “transformation” of Goldsmith’s original photograph. This is not an instance of an artist innocently alighting on the same image of Prince as the photographer; Warhol was given a copy of the Goldsmith photograph in order to prepare his works. So AWF is left to argue not that Warhol did not infringe Goldsmith’s copyright, but rather that he should not be punished for that infringement. (Warhol likely would have appreciated part of that argument, which amounted to, &#8220;It&#8217;s not infringement if a famous person does it.&#8221;)</p>



<p>Yet if this case were determined under the 1909 Copyright Act, the last major revision to copyright law before 1976, the case for infringement would be razor-thin. Rather than the all-encompassing derivative work right, the <a href="https://www.copyright.gov/history/1909act.pdf">1909 Copyright Act</a> listed very specific rights beyond reproduction and distribution that applied only to individual types of works. It granted the author the right to translate literary works; to dramatize nondramatic works; to convert dramas into novels or other nondramatic works; and to arrange or adapt musical works. The owner of a dramatic or visual work of art could control the exhibition of the work and its bare reproduction, but exclusive control over transformation of the work into something else was not a right granted by the 1909 Act. The best that Goldsmith would be able to argue under that law would be that Warhol’s portraits of Prince violated the reproduction right, but intuitively that seems like a stretch. Warhol relied on the Goldsmith photograph, but he took it in entirely new directions. In any case, the argument put forth at the Supreme Court turns on the expansive derivative work right in the 1976 Act, not reproduction.</p>



<p>The expansion of fair use in the last 30 years, especially since <em>Campbell v. Acuff-Rose Music, Inc.</em>, can thus be seen as a direct response to the overly expansive rights granted to authors by the 1976 Copyright Act’s derivative work right. The Supreme Court has recognized that dissemination and reception of copyrighted works by the public and their participation in the informational, cultural, and artistic interaction between authors and works is an important public good that should not be foreclosed by broadly granted copyrights. The courts have therefore latched onto the fair use defense to preserve that exchange. If we want to cabin the fair use defense to its rightful place in protecting certain public-benefitting uses, then the proper resolution lies not in judicial guesswork about the transformative nature of art in communication with other art, but rather the statutory language itself.</p>



<p>Congress originated this problem almost 50 years ago, and Congress should fix it by replacing the broad derivative work right with a list of specific exclusive actions concerning particular types of works, as the 1909 Act did. Until then, the Supreme Court will keep trying to scale the mountain of balancing derivative work rights and fair use. But as<a href="https://www.gq.com/story/prince-stories"> Prince once told Jim Walsh</a>, “I’ve been to the mountaintop. There’s nothing there.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1819</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fourteenth Amendment Personhood Deferred Again</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/fourteenth-amendment-personhood-deferred-again/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=fourteenth-amendment-personhood-deferred-again</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pat Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 15:27:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Supreme Court of the United States]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1815</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Yesterday, the Supreme Court denied certiorari in Doe et al. v. McKee (No. 22-201), an appeal from the Rhode Island Supreme Court presenting squarely the question of whether unborn persons are entitled to Fourteenth Amendment protection. The petitioners, including pro-life organizations, had challenged a 2019 Rhode Island law that permitted abortion prior to viability and, importantly, repealed&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/fourteenth-amendment-personhood-deferred-again/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Fourteenth Amendment Personhood Deferred Again</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Yesterday, the Supreme Court denied certiorari in <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/search.aspx?filename=/docket/docketfiles/html/public/22-201.html"><em>Doe et al. v. McKee </em>(No. 22-201)</a>, an appeal from the Rhode Island Supreme Court presenting squarely the question of whether unborn persons are entitled to Fourteenth Amendment protection. The petitioners, including pro-life organizations, had challenged a 2019 Rhode Island law that permitted abortion prior to viability and, importantly, repealed an earlier law that established that “human life commences at the instant of conception and that said human life at the instant of conception is a person within the language and meaning of the fourteenth amendment of the constitution of the United States . . . .” The Supreme Court&#8217;s denial of certiorari has been reported as a setback for the personhood argument. No doubt it is.</p>



<span id="more-1815"></span>



<p>One can read <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/DocketPDF/22/22-201/236882/20220901130349933_Petition%20Brief.pdf">the certiorari petition</a> if one wants to get the full story, but Rhode Island courts ultimately affirmed the trial court’s ruling upholding the 2019 law because they held that the unborn plaintiffs (Baby Mary Doe and Baby Roe) lacked standing because they were not <em>persons</em> under the Fourteenth Amendment. The petitioners urged the Supreme Court to grant certiorari primarily to address the Fourteenth Amendment personhood argument, advanced notably by John Finnis and Josh Craddock (and others besides). In other words, the Rhode Island case presented directly the question deferred in <em>Dobbs</em>, namely whether there are any positive protections for the unborn under the Constitution. </p>



<p>The petitioners followed Finnis and Craddock’s lead, framing their discussion in originalist terms, discussing the historical meaning of the word “person” (as opposed to narrower terms, like “citizen”) in Anglo-American jurisprudence, including in the thought of John Bingham, the primary drafter of the Fourteenth Amendment. For my part, the petitioners make a compelling argument that &#8220;any person&#8221; as it would have been understood in the 1860s was broad enough to encompass any human being. The petition also does a masterful job marshaling the various decisions of courts from the Supreme Court on down to state courts finding that unborn children are persons with rights of various kinds. In other words, the original public meaning of &#8220;any person&#8221; should be read in conjunction with the tradition of various court decisions holding that unborn children are human beings with rights. </p>



<p>However compelling the argument may be in originalist terms, the Rhode Island attorney general declined on September 6 to file any response to the petition for certiorari and yesterday the Supreme Court denied the petition summarily. Court watchers naturally will caution reading too much into any summary denial of certiorari, but the Fourteenth Amendment personhood argument was present even during the oral argument in <em>Dobbs</em>. While Justice Alito’s opinion for the Court leaves the matter open, Justice Kavanaugh’s concurrence (and questions he asked during oral argument) indicates his strong disagreement with the argument. </p>



<p>The originalist argument of the petition did not seem to sway enough justices to grant certiorari—or even to direct the Rhode Island attorney general to file a response. Under such circumstances, one does wonder what the advantage of not articulating a broader argument, rooted in two thousand years of jurisprudence (as opposed to fifty or so) would be. The parties and their counsel, for all I know, could be committed to originalist argument, and that’s as may be. However, for litigants and lawyers open to classical argument, there may well be few reasons not to make a full-throated classical argument. </p>



<p>At any rate, Justice Kavanaugh was the crucial fifth vote for the <em>Dobbs</em> opinion. If one disregarded the sober advice of Court watchers, one might assume, therefore, that Justice Kavanaugh’s distaste for the Fourteenth Amendment argument is an important factor here. Justice Kavanaugh argued in his separate opinion that &#8220;[o]n the question of abortion, the Constitution is . . . neither pro-life nor pro-choice. The Constitution is neutral and leaves the issue for the people and their elected representatives to resolve through the democratic process in the States or Congress—like the numerous other difficult questions of American social and economic policy that the Constitution does not address.&#8221; Recognizing that &#8220;any person&#8221; in the Fourteenth Amendment includes unborn children would make Justice Kavanaugh&#8217;s preferred outcome—letting the states decide for themselves what to do about abortion—extremely difficult. </p>



<p>Additionally, Justice Amy Coney Barrett was quoted in the context of <a href="https://davidlat.substack.com/p/in-memoriam-judge-laurence-h-silberman">a memorial piece about Judge Laurence Silberman</a> by David Lat as saying (for some reason) “I am not a fan of common-good constitutionalism.” While the debate over common-good constitutionalism is separate in many respects from the debate over personhood under the Fourteenth Amendment, I suspect that the two are linked (somehow) in the minds of many observers. One could really throw caution to the wind and make some deductions about what Justice Barrett thinks about the Fourteenth Amendment argument. One could also really cut loose and ask whether declining to consider the sound originalist argument of the Rhode Island petitioners is not judges imposing their subjective policy preferences on the Constitution. </p>



<p>Such speculation will have to remain speculation for now.  However, I am far from sure that the question of personhood can be deferred forever, not least since some states are passing laws like the one Rhode Island repealed. While the Constitution may be silent on the question of abortion (I am far from sure it is), “any person” is contained in the text of Section 1 and it seems highly implausible that Congress meant to leave to the several states the definition of “person.” Indeed, allowing states to affect by legislation the definition of &#8220;person&#8221; for the purposes of the Fourteenth Amendment seems liable to undercut significantly the entire thrust of the Civil War Amendments. </p>



<p>Pat Smith</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1815</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Environmental Law and the Classical Legal Tradition</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/environmental-law-and-the-classical-legal-tradition/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=environmental-law-and-the-classical-legal-tradition</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 17:26:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1806</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Ius &#38; Iustitium welcomes submissions from academics, practicing lawyers, and students interested in the classical legal tradition.&#160;The following essay was submitted by Brian Quigley, Research and Reference Librarian at NSU Shepard Broad College of Law at Nova Southeastern University in Davie, Florida. This post is adapted from a longer article available here. The classical legal&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/environmental-law-and-the-classical-legal-tradition/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Environmental Law and the Classical Legal Tradition</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Ius &amp; Iustitium welcomes submissions from academics, practicing lawyers, and students interested in the classical legal tradition.</em>&nbsp;<em>The following essay was submitted by Brian Quigley, Research and Reference Librarian at NSU Shepard Broad College of Law at Nova Southeastern University in Davie, Florida. This post is adapted from a longer article available <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3955307" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p>The classical legal tradition is ever-new. Its history is one of repeated displacement and revival. Stuart Banner identifies several persuasive reasons for the decline in the use of natural law reasoning that began in the late nineteenth century. These include a greater reliance on written constitutions, that law and religion were increasingly viewed as separate domains, a dramatic increase in the volume of legal publishing, and a feeling that the natural law lacked useful content.<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-1" href="#post-1806-endnote-1">[1]</a></sup> In the face of these headwinds it is easy to imagine the classical legal tradition becoming a matter solely of historical, rather than practical, interest. Instead, the tradition has been subject to repeated revivals, first in the 1910s and early 1920s, and again—in more sustained fashion—in the 30s, 40s, and 50s as a response to the rise of totalitarianism and the horrors of the Second World War. While our legal culture has changed dramatically in the intervening decades, interest in the classical legal tradition has never fully receded and may be in the early stages of widespread resurgence.</p>



<span id="more-1806"></span>



<p>This perennial quality finds poetic expression in one of the classic texts of the post-war natural law revival, Heinrich Rommen’s <em>The Natural Law</em>. Rommen sees a few reasons for the endurance of the natural law tradition. Even when seemingly vanquished from serious academic consideration it has lived on in “the common sense of ordinary men and women.” In everyday disputes fairness and integrity are prioritized over adherence to set rules and legal formalities. This impulse is only intensified when applied to issues of broad societal concern. Rommen notes that “When he becomes interested in issues of economic, social, or political reform, the avowed positivist frequently turns, in practice and as it were unconsciously, to the idea of natural law and to standards of unchanging justice.”<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-2" href="#post-1806-endnote-2">[2]</a></sup> The natural desire for justice, however confused or suppressed, cannot be subdued for long. He continues with the following elegant lines: “The idea of the natural law may thus be compared to the seed which, buried under snow, sprouts forth as soon as the frigid and sterile winter of positivism yields to the unfailing spring of metaphysics. For the idea of natural law is immortal.”<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-3" href="#post-1806-endnote-3">[3]</a></sup></p>



<p>When confronted with immortal principles legal theorists are presented with a challenging, albeit fulfilling, task&#8211;that of translation. The insights of the classical legal tradition are to be applied to contemporary problems. Indeed, one of the main criticisms of the post-war revival was that it remained too centered upon history and theory. A 1957 article noted that “Even in the Neo-Scholastic tradition, where a concerted effort at translation and integration is going on, too many works presuppose basic courses in scholastic metaphysics and a fingertip knowledge of an involved terminology.”<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-4" href="#post-1806-endnote-4">[4]</a></sup> Writing in 1959, Johannes Messner agreed that discussion had been overly focused on the description and justification of principles. The next step would be the “application of the natural law principles to the changing world in the political, social, economic [and] cultural field.”<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-5" href="#post-1806-endnote-5">[5]</a></sup></p>



<p>The post-war years did see a flurry of articles considering American law through a natural law lens. While many concerned high-minded constitutional law issues, others dealt with more mundane topics. A 1949 report by an ABA committee on tax and the natural law held that taxes must be “imposed for a just purpose” and “connected with the common good and proportioned to the current necessity, as is required by legal or social justice.”<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-6" href="#post-1806-endnote-6">[6]</a></sup> Property scholars wrote approvingly of contemporary regulations on economic activity. A review of <em>Kaiser-Frazer v. Otis </em>saw that ruling as adhering to “the fundamental natural law principle of the unenforceability of contracts in derogation and injury of the rights of the innocent and unprotected public investor.”<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-7" href="#post-1806-endnote-7">[7]</a></sup></p>



<p>The reasons for the fading of the revival are multifaceted, historically contingent, and deserving of further investigation. Banner posits that as fascism receded the natural law tradition was no longer seen as a necessary antidote. Breen &amp; Strang credit the failure to create lasting institutions.<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-8" href="#post-1806-endnote-8">[8]</a></sup> An underappreciated factor may be the difficulties inherent in the process of translation. One must understand classical legal principles well enough to apply them to contemporary problems. These applications must chart a middle path between two errors. The first is to too closely imitate interpretations and solutions from the past that fail to fit the current moment. The second is to read modern theory into the classical tradition.<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-9" href="#post-1806-endnote-9">[9]</a></sup> All of this must be done while writing for a general legal audience unfamiliar with this sort of scholarship. A common criticism of the post-war revival was that its key figures spent too much time writing for a specialized and sympathetic audience.</p>



<p>While the movement from theory to practice presents challenges, it also can serve to clarify our thinking and present openings for reform. This is particularly true in the environmental context. The legal order of a given community inevitably shapes how that community regards the natural world. Many common law doctrines have an ecological component. These include the public trust doctrine, nuisance, and – as most fully expressed in the Nordic counties – the right to roam. These precepts reflect an understanding that the sovereign has a right to regulate resources for the benefit of the public, that environmental harms have a nasty habit of traveling, and that access to wilderness areas is a good due to all. Over the last century we have come to a much greater understanding of the complexity and interconnectedness of the natural world and of man’s capacity to commit lasting ecological damage. In response the 1970s saw the creation of the Environmental Protection Agency and the passage of, among others, the Clean Air, Clean Water, and Endangered Species Acts.</p>



<p>A stable and healthy environment is a paradigmatic example of a common good. Pollution, climate change, and the destruction of natural areas affect us all. Indeed, the purposes provisions of environmental statutes reflect their broad importance. Among those of the Clean Air Act is to “protect and enhance the quality of the Nation’s air resources so as to promote the public health and welfare and the productive capacity of its population.”<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-10" href="#post-1806-endnote-10">[10]</a></sup> The classical tradition would rightly regard environmental stewardship as a just goal. Jurists would be broadly deferential to legislative and administrative efforts at environmental protection and management. This outlook would have ramifications in areas including statutory interpretation, property, federalism, and standing.</p>



<p>To choose one timely example, West Virginia v. EPA would have been decided differently. The Clean Air Act authorizes the EPA to regulate power plant emissions. Complex procedural history aside, the Court was called on to decide “whether restructuring the Nation’s overall mix of electricity generation, to transition from 38% coal to 27% coal by 2030, can be the “best system of emission reduction”” as defined by the relevant CAA Section.<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-11" href="#post-1806-endnote-11">[11]</a></sup> Under the classical legal framework, lawmakers are tasked with promoting the good of the community. Congress delegates regulatory power to agencies because agencies have the scientific and administrative expertise to accomplish complex goals. Reducing emissions though a gradual 9% decrease in the use of coal for electricity generation is a model example of the EPA functioning as intended. Classically minded jurists would be deferential to agency determinations. Barring concerns of basic justice not implicated here, edits to the EPA’s plan would be left to the executive and legislative branches, not the courts.</p>



<p>Instead, the Court ruled against the EPA under the major questions doctrine. Under the MQD, “administrative agencies must be able to point to ‘clear congressional authorization’ when they claim the power to make decisions of vast ‘economic and political significance.’”<sup><a id="post-1806-endnote-ref-12" href="#post-1806-endnote-12">[12]</a></sup> Problems with this doctrine are many and obvious. The MQD is incredibly vague. Administrative agencies are tasked with trying to predict whether courts will find that a given regulation tackles problems of too great a political significance or economic impact. They are given almost no guidance in doing so. Indeed, it is hard to imagine how a legislature could draft delegations of power resistant to MQD challenge. This vagueness seems to be by design, as it allows courts to interfere with the functioning of administrative agencies at will.</p>



<p>Environmental law remains a young field. Its future will be shaped both by scientific and jurisprudential developments. Much good can be accomplished through thoughtful application of the principles of the classical legal tradition. Environmentalists and classical revivalists can both benefit. Indeed, environmental consciousness and the natural law tradition share similarities on a deeper level. In both instances we are confronted with realities much larger than ourselves. A right relationship with the natural world is one that recognizes its inherent value. This value exists apart from its utility to man and is connected to broader questions of meaning and right. Contemplating these themes can lead to insights of both theoretical and practical importance. A legal culture dedicated to the common good would play an important role in accomplishing a society in harmony with nature.</p>



<ol><li id="post-1806-endnote-1">Stuart Banner, The Decline of Natural Law: How American Lawyers Once Used Natural Law and Why They Stopped (2021). <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-1">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-2">Heinrich A. Rommen, The Natural Law: A Study in Legal and Social History and Philosophy 117 (1947). <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-2">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-3"><em>Id.</em> at 118. <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-3">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-4"><em>Natural Law for Today’s Lawyer</em>, 9 Stan. L. Rev. 455, 459 n.5 (1957). <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-4">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-5">Johannes Messner, <em>The Postwar Natural Law Revival and Its Outcome</em>, 4 Nat. L.F. 101, 105 (1959). <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-5">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-6">Joseph F. McCloy, et al., <em>The Moral Issue</em>, 27 Taxes 9, 10 (1949). <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-6">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-7">David C. Bayne, <em>Kaiser-Frazer v. Otis: A Legal and Moral Analysis</em>, 2 DePaul L. Rev. 131, 192-193 (1953). <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-7">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-8"><em>See </em>John M. Breen and Lee J. Strang, <em>The Forgotten Jurisprudential Debate: Catholic Legal Thoughts Response to Legal Realism</em>, 98 Marq. L. Rev. 1203, 1253-1256 (2015). <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-8">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-9">Adrian Vermeule, <em>The Theory and Practice of Common Good Constitutionalism</em>, Ius &amp; Iustitium (Aug. 8, 2022), https://iusetiustitium.com/the-theory-and-practice-of-common-good-constitutionalism/ <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-9">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-10">42 U.S.C. §7401(b)(1) <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-10">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-11">West Virginia v. EPA, 597 U.S. __ (2022) <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-11">↑</a></li><li id="post-1806-endnote-12"><em>Id.</em> <a href="#post-1806-endnote-ref-12">↑</a></li></ol>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1806</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>“Closure Rules” Are Ius for Originalists</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/closure-rules-are-ius-for-originalists/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=closure-rules-are-ius-for-originalists</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 16:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Constitutional Law]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1800</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Conor Casey is a Lecturer in Law, University of Liverpool School of Law &#38; Social Justice. Adrian Vermeule is the Ralph Tyler Jr. Professor of Constitutional Law, Harvard Law School.  A standard set of claims, common to both classical lawyers and Dworkinians, is that the interpretation of positive legal rules inevitably rests on express or&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/closure-rules-are-ius-for-originalists/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">&#8220;Closure Rules&#8221; Are Ius for Originalists</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Conor Casey is a Lecturer in Law, University of Liverpool School of Law &amp; Social Justice. Adrian Vermeule is the Ralph Tyler Jr. Professor of Constitutional Law, Harvard Law School. </em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity is-style-wide"/>



<p>A standard set of claims, common to both classical lawyers and Dworkinians, is that the interpretation of positive legal rules inevitably rests on express or implied arguments from political morality (in particular, for the classical lawyer, the subset of political morality bearing on legal justice), and that positive rules are inevitably under-determinate, due to the inherent limits of language and of lawmakers’&nbsp;foresight. Originalists have evolved an attempt at a solution:&nbsp;“closure rules.”</p>



<p>At the question and answer session following a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jfSUgrjH_XM">recent panel discussion</a>, organized by the&nbsp;<em>American Enterprise Institute,&nbsp;</em>on “Natural Law and Original Meaning,” an audience member asked the panelists (Sherif Girgis, Kevin Walsh, and Lee Strang) if judges should be able to apply “maxims of natural law as canons of construction” to find the meaning of posited constitutional text, where texts remain under-determinate after attempts to ascertain its original meaning from socio-historical sources.&nbsp;Strang’s headline response was that there was no conventional originalist position to address the question (a notable response in itself). But Strang proceeded to note that originalists have worked hard to identify additional conceptual resources to create so-called&nbsp;“closure rules” in cases where constitutional text remains under-determinate,&nbsp;<em>after</em>&nbsp;the search for things like original semantic and conventional public meaning has been exhausted. Strang cited the possibility of seeking out originally understood legal rules of interpretation to try and generate thicker, more robust, original meanings and ameliorate the under-determinacy problem. Where this kind of enterprise still yielded under-determinacy, Strang suggested that originalists had argued powerfully that constitutional actors should proceed in a Thayerian fashion: the legislative branch should be permitted to&nbsp;“construct” meaning and judges should defer to their construction unless they have acted in clear error of other constitutional commitments.</p>



<p>As we have previously noted, however, such “closure rules” just replicate the problem they are intended to address. Closure rules are themselves subject to the same problems as the first-order rules for which they attempt to provide a tourniquet of determinacy. The very fact that Professor Strang mentioned multiple possibilities for&nbsp;“closure rules” underscores the point: the choice between possible closure rules itself depends upon normative arguments. It is not just written in the nature of things, inherent in the nature of language or communication or inherent in the nature of interpretation, that the interpreter should simply “put the statute down” (as Frank Easterbrook once&nbsp;<a href="https://chicagounbound.uchicago.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?referer=&amp;httpsredir=1&amp;article=2154&amp;context=journal_articles">suggested</a>), should rely on party presentation of socio-historical facts rather than attempt their own search (as some originalists suggest), defer to legislators or agencies (the approach Strang finds powerful), or adopt some other approach. To adopt one or other approach itself requires a choice, necessarily based on arguments about which approach serves the public interest or common good — whether or not the interpreter makes those arguments explicit.</p>



<p>Likewise with the idea that originalists can just use the closure rules&nbsp;“used by the founding generation itself,” such as the above-mentioned use of conventional legal rules of interpretation present at the different times constitutional provisions were ratified. Apart from other grievous problems (notably, that the founding generation thought about law in an entirely different way, within a classical framework and based upon a classical legal ontology), such rules themselves come in multiple competing versions, are themselves inevitably partially indeterminate and require further, controversial specification, and themselves require interpretation, resting on normative arguments. Just as first-order rules can be read at multiple levels of generality, cashed out in different ways, and otherwise extrapolated in different directions, so too with the closure rules. Rules of historical evidence, for example, “rest on express or implied normative assumptions and arguments about the costs of decisionmaking and the costs of error, about the collateral and systemic effects of admitting or not admitting certain categories of evidence, and a myriad other topics” (as one of us recently&nbsp;<a href="https://iusetiustitium.com/the-bourbons-of-jurisprudence/">noted</a>). As H. Jefferson Powell&nbsp;<a href="https://scholarship.law.duke.edu/faculty_scholarship/444/">put it</a>, “Rather than avoiding the responsibility of choice, history requires of the originalist a whole new range of contestable…decisions.”</p>



<p>As another example, take Strang’s preferred example of&nbsp;“deference.” As administrative lawyers arguing over the best specification of&nbsp;<em>Chevron</em>&nbsp;deference can attest, merely saying&nbsp;“defer to reasonable interpretations of ambiguous text” is only the beginning of a very long story, involving threshold&nbsp;“step zero“ questions (when exactly does deference apply? Are there categories of decisions to which it doesn’t apply at all?),&nbsp;“step one” questions (how ambiguous is ambiguous?), and&nbsp;“step two” questions (how reasonable is reasonable?). At every such step, normative arguments have been and must be called into play. Consider the idea in the leading decision on the step zero problem,&nbsp;<em>United States v. Mead</em>, that a certain complex approach to step zero best serves&nbsp;“fairness and deliberation.” Consider also an argument for the&nbsp;“major questions” clear statement rule, recently advanced by Justice Neil Gorsuch, that it helps to prevent&nbsp;“government by the people” from being supplanted by&nbsp;“government by bureaucracy.” Gorsuch’s argument here can only be described as Dworkinian in method, although needless to say not Dworkinian in substance.</p>



<p>Sometimes,&nbsp;“closure rules” are said to lie within the&nbsp;“construction zone,” where&nbsp;“construction” is taken to be a different activity than&nbsp;“interpretation.” As we have also said before, this is in essence an arbitrary semantic categorization, one that presupposes a conception of&nbsp;“interpretation” that the classical lawyer contests. Actual interpreters do not approach or experience their task as though it involves a switch between an&nbsp;“interpretation” phase and a&nbsp;“construction” phase where “the law runs out.” It is all one process, a process that occurs&nbsp;<em>within</em>&nbsp;law and&nbsp;<em>within</em>&nbsp;legal interpretation, involving — from the classical perspective — the harmonization of two types of law: the harmonization of positive texts (<em>lex</em>) with background principles of legal justice (<em>ius</em>), not as a way of overriding&nbsp;<em>lex</em>, but as a way of understanding and interpreting&nbsp;<em>lex</em>&nbsp;in light of the larger commitments of the legal order.</p>



<p>As&nbsp;<a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/natural-law-theories/">John Finnis puts it</a>, basic principles of natural law<em>&nbsp;</em>are not extra-legal considerations or policy arguments brought to bear by lawyers and judge where the law runs out, but themselves function as a “direct source of law (or justification for judicial decision) and, in a certain sense, as already law.” Basic precepts of the natural law, says Finnis, are best regarded as “judicially applicable moral rules and principles” and “<em>ipso iure&nbsp;</em>(i.e., precisely as morally and judicially applicable) rules&nbsp;<em>of law</em>” belonging to the “<em>ius gentium&nbsp;</em>portion of our law.”</p>



<p>The best account of&nbsp;“closure rules,” then, is that they are just another set of arguments about the content of&nbsp;<em>ius</em>, as opposed to&nbsp;<em>lex</em>. Closure rules are just&nbsp;<em>ius</em>&nbsp;for originalists. Here as elsewhere, whatever their abstract theories, interpreters inevitably practice the classical legal approach, even without knowing it.</p>



<p>In the end, Strang’s response nicely highlights a serious fault line between the interpretive approach of the classical legal tradition, on the one hand, and the hybrid approach of so-called natural law originalism on the other. In the resolution of hard cases, both types of jurists will inevitably appeal to considerations of&nbsp;<em>ius&nbsp;</em>– whether they call it that or not.<em>&nbsp;</em>The former approach builds into the structure of the theory regard for the basic precepts of natural law and legal justice as the interpretive lodestar. But the latter appears (from what we have observed) reluctant to invoke them or, at most, will only have recourse to them when they are incorporated by posited law sources, all out of concern for undermining law’s stability, or co-ordination function, or other institutional goods — goods that, in our view, have&nbsp;<em>already</em>&nbsp;been left by the wayside in the class of cases that require recourse to “closure rules.” While both theories may share some fundamentals, this is a wide divergence indeed.</p>



<p>Conor Casey &amp; Adrian Vermeule</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1800</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some Reflections for Law Students</title>
		<link>https://iusetiustitium.com/some-reflections-for-law-students/#utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=some-reflections-for-law-students</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Pat Smith]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2022 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Great Jurists]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://iusetiustitium.com/?p=1783</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[You’ve decided to go to law school. You have probably acted against the advice of family, friends, acquaintances, strangers, teachers, clergy, and, above all, lawyers. But as my late mother said to me often: some people have to learn things the hard way. I will not dwell on the decision to go to law school.&#8230; <a class="more-link" href="https://iusetiustitium.com/some-reflections-for-law-students/">Continue reading <span class="screen-reader-text">Some Reflections for Law Students</span> <span class="meta-nav" aria-hidden="true">&#8594;</span></a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>You’ve decided to go to law school. You have probably acted against the advice of family, friends, acquaintances, strangers, teachers, clergy, and, above all, lawyers. But as my late mother said to me often: some people have to learn things the hard way. I will not dwell on the decision to go to law school. But if you are reading <em>Ius &amp; Iustitium</em>, you either are doing oppo research for your Conservatism Inc. job or you have an interest in the classical legal tradition. As many students are beginning law school this month, I thought I would offer some reflections for your edification.</p>



<span id="more-1783"></span>



<p>First, grades matter most. Some of the ways they matter, like employment, you already understand. You need good grades for clerkships and jobs. But that is not the only way. For example, you will not have time to explore the classical legal tradition if you’re playing catch up from being the anchor man (or woman) in Property your second semester. And you will not have the same opportunity to research and write on questions that interest you—perhaps even questions related to the common good or the tradition—if you are not on a journal. Enough said about that.</p>



<p>Second, you will have to find your own opportunities to learn about the classical tradition. It is unlikely that you will be greeted with smiles and solicitude if you walk into law school and proudly inform someone—anyone—that you want to learn everything there is about the common good and the classical legal tradition. The reception will be even frostier if you say how inspired you are by Adrian Vermeule’s&nbsp;<em>Common Good Constitutionalism</em>&nbsp;or Pat Smith’s epoch-making&nbsp;<em>Ius &amp; Iustitium</em>&nbsp;posts. Even at supposedly conservative schools, there are precious few friends and plenty of people who will try to steer you away from the common good and the tradition. (More on that in a moment.)&nbsp;</p>



<p>It is, of course, not impossible for you to find opportunities to learn about the tradition. Does the school offer a class on Roman law? If there is not a class in the law school, is there a co-listed class with another department? What other classes on legal history are available? For the most part, your 1L curriculum will be regimented. However, this means that you will have a year (in what little free time you do have) to do some research and find courses that will enable you to study the classical tradition in greater detail. And there are other options for independent research that may be available to you. Traditionally, this has been in the context of law journals.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Third (and perhaps crucially), you are under no obligation to tell your professors and fellow students what you are thinking at all times. You are under no obligation, for example, to tweet, and, indeed, you probably should not tweet, least of all about the common good, Adrian Vermeule, <em>Ius &amp; Iustitium</em>, Pat Smith, or the classical legal tradition. As I said, there are plenty of law professors, even at supposedly conservative schools, who are openly and deeply hostile to the project of <em>Ius &amp; Iustitium</em>. It is, of course, entirely possible that these opponents of the classical legal tradition are able to set aside their deeply held objections, some very sharp, to help students who hold such views. It would be extremely magnanimous of them to do so. Yet this is one question that can be answered only in retrospect—if ever. <em>Why be the first to find out?</em></p>



<p>Likewise, unless things have changed very much since I was in law school, law students are hugely competitive. There are a finite number of As, a finite number of journal positions, a finite number of clerkships, and a finite number of jobs. This much finitude would be enough to send people much less tightly wound than the average law student into fight-or-flight mode. I would not assume that all your fellow students will be favorably disposed toward you. Given the work of Aaron Sibarium at the <em>Washington Free Beacon</em>, revealing the extreme leftist ideology at some top law schools, it is pretty clear that some students will be very unfavorably disposed toward you. Neither would I assume that even conservative students are above whisper campaigns and some light detraction. It would be foolish to think that such behavior is known only among leftists and that right-liberals are above all that.  </p>



<p>What I propose is a kind of inner emigration. It is true that there is momentum building behind a politics of the common good and a jurisprudence of the common good. But it is equally true that the forces of liberalism remain entirely opposed to the common good, except to the extent that they can claim that it is actually served by the same old liberalism they have always been committed to. You may think that, among conservatives, you have found friends and sympathetic interlocutors. However, one need not look very far to see that, even among conservatives, there is staunch, well-funded resistance to a jurisprudence of the common good. The safest move under such conditions is to explore the common good and the classical legal tradition in an interior way. </p>



<p>But it is only an inner emigration. And it should not stop you from exploring questions <em>related</em> to a jurisprudence of the common good. There are interesting questions relating to antitrust, communications law, and executive power (to mention only three, predominately federal, topics and to say nothing of the plethora of state-law topics) that are intimately related to the common good and the classical legal tradition. A journal note or comment can explore these questions without flaunting deeper commitments for hostile scrutiny. </p>



<p>Furthermore, feel free to join various student organizations, even student organizations coded as “conservative.” If you want to be competitive for certain jobs, especially clerkships with some judges and government jobs under Republican administrations, you will need to join at least one of these organizations. Make friends, network with judges and lawyers, learn about opportunities. But remember: you are under no obligation to tell everyone what you think. These topics may come up, to be sure, but resist the temptation to be more than a noncommittal, if interested, observer. </p>



<p>One of the most important concepts of recent years has been Adrian Vermeule’s “<a href="https://americanaffairsjournal.org/2018/02/integration-from-within/">integration from within</a>.” Yet in order to become an important figure in the regime capable of turning it toward right order, one must first obtain the credentials necessary to become an important figure in the regime. Maybe liberal credentialism is going the way of liberalism itself. For example, some talent spotters for a proposed Second Trump Administration have talked about hiring young men and women who are first and foremost ideologically sound. But this seems to mean for the most part thinking that the agenda of Conservatism Inc. is quote-unquote based. And, more to the point, the odds are vanishingly slim that such an approach will ever mean that top graduates of top law schools will have a hard time finding a job. </p>



<p>Law school is only three years. There will be plenty of time to debate and discuss these questions, ideally after you have gotten great grades, written on a journal, clerked for a judge, and found a job. There is no reason, really, to jeopardize your chances of clerking for a judge and finding a job, especially if you expect to do so in supposedly conservative circles, to show off in class or to win some arguments at a networking event. What I propose, therefore, is simply focusing on obtaining necessary credentials in such a way that will avoid drawing the attention of gatekeepers. </p>



<p>Free advice is worth what you pay for it and some people really do have to learn things the hard way. But take my advice: keep your head down and your nose to the grindstone. </p>



<p>Pat Smith</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1783</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
