<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" xmlns:taxo="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/taxonomy/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>ACM Queue - Networks</title>
    <link>http://queue.acm.org/listing.cfm?item_topic=Networks&amp;qc_type=topics_list&amp;filter=Networks&amp;page_title=Networks&amp;order=desc</link>
    <description/>
    <item>
      <title>Distributed Latency Profiling through Critical Path Tracing: CPT can provide actionable and precise latency analysis.</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3526967</link>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 16:23:20 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Brian Eaton, Jeff Stewart, Jon Tedesco, N. Cihan Tas</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3526967</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Everything VPN is New Again: The 24-year-old security model has found a second wind.</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3439745</link>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 18:16:04 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>David Crawshaw</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3439745</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GAN Dissection and Datacenter RPCs: Visualizing and understanding generative adversarial networks; datacenter RPCs can be general and fast.</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3329783</link>
      <description>Image generation using GANs (generative adversarial networks) has made astonishing progress over the past few years. While staring in wonder at some of the incredible images, it's natural to ask how such feats are possible. &quot;GAN Dissection: Visualizing and Understanding Generative Adversarial Networks&quot; gives us a look under the hood to see what kinds of things are being learned by GAN units, and how manipulating those units can affect the generated images. February saw the 16th edition of the Usenix Symposium on Networked Systems Design and Implementation. Kalia et al. blew me away with their work on fast RPCs (remote procedure calls) in the datacenter. Through a carefully considered design, they show that RPC performance with commodity CPUs and standard lossy Ethernet can be competitive with specialized systems based on FPGAs (field-programmable gate arrays), programmable switches, and RDMA (remote direct memory access). It's a fabulous reminder to ensure we're making the most of what we already have before leaping to more expensive solutions.</description>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 May 2019 09:33:28 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Adrian Colyer</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3329783</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward a Network of Connected Things: A look into the future of IoT deployments and their usability</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3186470</link>
      <description>While the scale of data presents new avenues for improvement, the key challenges for the everyday adoption of IoT systems revolve around managing this data. First, we need to consider where the data is being processed and stored and what the privacy and systems implications of these policies are. Second, we need to develop systems that generate actionable insights from this diverse, hard-to-interpret data for non-tech users. Solving these challenges will allow IoT systems to deliver maximum value to end users.</description>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 15:09:09 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Deepak Vasisht</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3186470</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bitcoin&amp;#8217;s Underlying Incentives: The unseen economic forces that govern the Bitcoin protocol</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3168362</link>
      <description>Incentives are crucial for the Bitcoin protocol's security and effectively drive its daily operation. Miners go to extreme lengths to maximize their revenue and often find creative ways to do so that are sometimes at odds with the protocol. Cryptocurrency protocols should be placed on stronger foundations of incentives. There are many areas left to improve, ranging from the very basics of mining rewards and how they interact with the consensus mechanism, through the rewards in mining pools, and all the way to the transaction fee market itself.</description>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2017 12:06:30 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Yonatan Sompolinsky, Aviv Zohar</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3168362</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Private Online Communication; Highlights in Systems Verification: The importance of private communication will continue to grow. We need techniques to build larger verified systems from verified components.</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3149411</link>
      <description>First, Albert Kwon provides an overview of recent systems for secure and private communication. While messaging protocols such as Signal provide privacy guarantees, Albert's selected research papers illustrate what is possible at the cutting edge: more transparent endpoint authentication, better protection of communication metadata, and anonymous broadcasting. These papers marry state-of-the-art cryptography with practical, privacy-preserving protocols, providing a glimpse of what we might expect from tomorrow's secure messaging systems.

Second, James Wilcox takes us on a tour of recent advances in verified systems design. It's now possible to build end-to-end verified compilers, operating systems, and distributed systems that are &lt;i&gt;provably&lt;/i&gt; correct with respect to well-defined specifications, providing high assurance of well-defined, well-behaved code. Because these system components interact with low-level hardware like the instruction set architecture and external networks, each paper introduces new techniques to balance the tension between formal correctness and practical applicability. As programming language techniques advance and more of the modern computing stack continues to crystallize, expect these advances to make their way into production systems.</description>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 16:07:21 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Albert Kwon, James Wilcox</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3149411</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Applications Are Interactive: The network era requires new models, with interactions instead of algorithms.</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3145628</link>
      <description>The miniaturization of devices and the prolific interconnectedness of these devices over high-speed wireless networks is completely changing how commerce is conducted. These changes (a.k.a. digital) will profoundly change how enterprises operate. Software is at the heart of this digital world, but the software toolsets and languages were conceived for the host-based era. The issues that already plague software practice (such as high defects, poor software productivity, information vulnerability, poor software project success rates, etc.) will be more profound with such an approach. It is time for software to be made simpler, secure, and reliable.</description>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 15:27:01 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Antony Alappatt</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3145628</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cache Me If You Can: Building a decentralized web-delivery model</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3136953</link>
      <description>The world is more connected than it ever has been before, and with our pocket supercomputers and IoT (Internet of Things) future, the next generation of the web might just be delivered in a peer-to-peer model. It's a giant problem space, but the necessary tools and technology are here today. We just need to define the problem a little better.</description>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 16:07:29 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Jacob Loveless</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3136953</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold, Hard Cache: On the implementation and maintenance of caches</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3134436</link>
      <description>Dear KV,
Our latest project at work requires a large number of slightly different software stacks to deploy within our cloud infrastructure. With modern hardware, I can test this deployment on a laptop. The problem I keep running up against is that our deployment system seems to secretly cache some of my files and settings and not clear them, even when I repeatedly issue the command to do so. I've resorted to repeatedly using the find command so that I can blow away the offending files. What I've found is that the system caches data in many places so I've started a list. All of which brings me to my question: Who writes this stuff?!</description>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2017 14:14:44 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>George Neville-Neil</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3134436</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time, but Faster: A computing adventure about time through the looking glass</title>
      <link>http://queue.acm.org/detail.cfm?id=3036398</link>
      <description>The first premise was summed up perfectly by the late Douglas Adams in The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy: &quot;Time is an illusion. Lunchtime doubly so.&quot; The concept of time, when colliding with decoupled networks of computers that run at billions of operations per second, is... well, the truth of the matter is that you simply never really know what time it is. That is why Leslie Lamport's seminal paper on Lamport timestamps was so important to the industry, but this article is actually about wall-clock time, or a reasonably useful estimation of it.</description>
      <category>Networks</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 14:24:29 GMT</pubDate>
      <author>Theo Schlossnagle</author>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">3036398</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

