<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">

<channel>
	<title>Just Thomism</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thomism.wordpress.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
	<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com</link>
	<description>OMNES ENIM VIVUNT EI</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 01:36:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain="thomism.wordpress.com" port="80" path="/?rsscloud=notify" registerProcedure="" protocol="http-post"/>
<image>
		<url>https://s0.wp.com/i/buttonw-com.png</url>
		<title>Just Thomism</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="https://thomism.wordpress.com/osd.xml" title="Just Thomism"/>
	<atom:link rel="hub" href="https://thomism.wordpress.com/?pushpress=hub"/>
	<item>
		<title>Death as return to principle</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/11/13/death-as-return-to-principle/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 01:28:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26177</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If our accounts of death are limited to the Christian account of death as encounter with the God and the physicalist account of death as non-existence, both take death as a return to the principle of the self &#8211; either a soul arising from a divine act of creation and returning to it or from [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If our accounts of death are limited to the Christian account of death as encounter with the God and the physicalist account of death as non-existence, both take death as a return to the principle of the self &#8211; either a soul arising from a divine act of creation and returning to it or from a constellation of causes that were as indifferent to the self&#8217;s arising as they&#8217;ll be to its scattering in death. One way or another, we meet our maker.</p>
<p>Perhaps this was unavoidable due to death inescapably requiring an account of what the person is. What, after all, does does fundamentally bring to an end? My only interest here is how it seems axiomatic that it involves some sort of return to the principle of one&#8217;s being, and, given that this is encountered precisely in death, requires that the person himself is not that source.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Substance dualism</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/11/13/substance-dualism/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2022 15:38:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26171</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Taken literally, substance dualism is a man riding a horse or hunting with dogs; or perhaps an action rising to the level of naturally occurring symbiosis or parasitism. Lo, two substances interacting and giving rise to a common activity! This could never be more than a metaphor for the union of soul and body. The [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Taken literally, substance dualism is a man riding a horse or hunting with dogs; or perhaps an action rising to the level of naturally occurring symbiosis or parasitism. Lo, two substances interacting and giving rise to a common activity!</p>
<p>This could never be more than a metaphor for the union of soul and body. The when a man uses a dog to hunt he is using a physical thing, of course, and souls in some sense use bodies to do things, but living things make use of the physical by being one substance with it. This is clearest in the opposition between living things and machines: living things convert energy sources into parts of themselves, and so have the equivalent of an engineer within themselves; machines not only are engineered from without but have interfaces and on-off switches manifesting their order to a controlling substance. While both the living thing and the machine are physical, the machine has extrinsic substances engineering and using it while the living thing has these as intrinsically constitutive of its one substance, e.g. the living dog, plant, insect, etc. Since the living thing is equally as physical as the machine, moreover, we have to distinguish physicality as a complete substance and only potentially alive from the higher-order living substance that actualizes what is only potential at a lower order.</p>
<p>One can, of course, consider only what living things and machines have in common &#8211; and one could probably tell the whole story of biology in the last 70 years as the story of those who were interested in looking at it in that way. If all you want to know about is how, for example, living things use energy sources to accomplish tasks you don&#8217;t need to care about how they are essentially different from machines, and there are enough interesting things to discover here to sustain a very broad and long-lasting research program. When one tries to talk about &#8220;soul&#8221; or &#8220;life&#8221; from the standpoint of this research program, however, it will either be a completely superfluous term (since one is assuming life <em>just is </em>a function common with machines) or an alien substance dualistically interacting with a complete substance as opposed to actualizing potencies-for-substance in a lower order.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title/>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/11/08/26164/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 21:15:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26164</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[God, pure actuality, transcends the distinction between the absolute (for which real distinction is a limitation) and the relative (for which real distinction is a perfection.) We can understand God as subsistent being, and we can understand being as divided into absolute and relative, but we cannot understand God or being as the simultaneous existence [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>God, pure actuality, transcends the distinction between the absolute (for which real distinction is a limitation) and the relative (for which real distinction is a perfection.)</p>
<p>We can understand God as subsistent being, and we can understand being as divided into absolute and relative, but we cannot understand God or being as the simultaneous existence of the absolute and relative, since this is a contradiction and contradictions can neither be understood nor be. This is just as true of abstract wholes as of transcendent wholes, e.g. &#8220;animal&#8221; is an abstraction from cats, dogs, fish, etc. or even as an abstraction from cats and non-cats, but we can&#8217;t understand &#8220;animal&#8221; as though it were the subsistent unity of cat and non-cat at the same time and same respect, since this is contradictory.</p>
<p>If God simply showed us the transcendent unity of absolute and relative, we would see how relatives exist so as not to exclude absolutes and vice versa. At the moment we only see that this is true so far as both are actualities, but we can&#8217;t conceive both actualities formally in being.</p>
<p>Perfections possessed as contradictory in creatures are possessed without contradiction in God. In using creatures to understand God, we unavoidably run encounter times when there will be a contradiction in our thought that must be judged not to exist in God, but all this means is that if we try to understand an unlimited perfection as a series of limited ones we fail to understand it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Liberal punishment: the contradiction</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/11/06/liberal-punishment-the-contradiction/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2022 15:04:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26157</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The classically liberal view of punishment is that it&#8217;s main goal is to bring about a better tomorrow. Because of this, it wants punishments to reform criminals and/or it wants the punishment to be sufficiently terrible to deter future crime. Even after one gives up on this idea of deterrence, we still want to deter [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[


<p>The classically liberal view of punishment is that it&#8217;s main goal is to bring about a better tomorrow. Because of this, it wants punishments to reform criminals and/or it wants the punishment to be sufficiently terrible to deter future crime. Even after one gives up on this idea of deterrence, we still want to deter future crime by the punishment keeping us safe from predatory monsters. This appeal to punishment as a tool for public safety is particularly pronounced during election cycles. </p>



<p>Though the goals that that both wings of the liberal theory strive to attain are admirable, <em>as accounts of punishment</em> both are unjust.      Justice is simply meting out pain or loss for violations of justice and so seeks to give the offender something bad, while reform seeks to give someone something good. The desire for deterrence seeks to give a criminal a pain or loss not proportionate to what he has done, but to all the things he could do. We punish the person not by an objective evaluation of the badness of what he did, but we rather think about defending ourselves from all the crimes he could do if we let him run around in society. </p>



<p>The clearest example of the inherent contradictions in these views of punishment is the &#8220;war on drugs&#8221; or the various &#8220;get tough on crime&#8221; suggestions that we periodically get stirred up into supporting. Obviously, in calling it a &#8220;war on drugs&#8221; we are looking forward to a better tomorrow where no one uses drugs, and the whole point of &#8220;getting tough on crime&#8221; is to bring about better tomorrows by finally showing those nasty criminals who&#8217;s in charge. But of course, we want to bring about this better tomorrow <em>through punishments</em>. We&#8217;ll make the punishment for drug importation life in prison, for example. This is, of course, simply revolutionary terror &#8211; let&#8217;s show those powerful barrons and recalcitrant peasants we mean business! The supermax prison, high profile trial, and jokes about prison rape are all just the guillotine in the public square, with all the bawdiness and bloodlust of the mob. Nevertheless, the whole point of all this is to stop people from importing or taking drugs and build a better tomorrow, so what do we do when we&#8217;ve done as much terror as we&#8217;re willing to inflict, and the desired utopia hasn&#8217;t yet arrived? Well, then we complain that &#8220;the laws aren&#8217;t working&#8221; or that the war on drugs has failed. The instrument we chose to bring about a better tomorrow <em>by its nature </em>brings about disproportionate and hence unjust punishments, and at some point the guilt of all this catches up to us. So what is the answer? Legalize! The war on drugs isn&#8217;t working! The prison system isn&#8217;t working! Given our theory of punishment, all we are left able to do is give criminals good things. We will provide them opportunities for instruction, repentance, correction, etc or perhaps we&#8217;ll just let them go in a spirit of repentance for the revolutionary terror we inflicted on them. In lived experience, the justice system ends up as a grotesque melange of both horns of this dilemma, with the mob in front of the guillotine demanding both blood and repentance, insisting we simultaneously cut off the condemned&#8217;s head and crown him king. </p>



<p>The better theory of punishment is to forget about the future and seek to give pain in response to injustice, with a recognition that our inability to change hearts needs to be taken into account when the society decides whether some crime merits a permanent banishment (now called &#8220;life in prison&#8221;) or even an execution. </p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trinity and simplicity (4)</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/11/03/trinity-and-simplicity-4/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 23:52:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26151</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[God, pure act, transcends all limitation of perfection. The real distinction of absolute attributes is a limitation. So no real distinction of these is allowed in God. The distinction of wisdom from mercy from omnipotence arises from the limitation of our intellect. The real distinction of relative attributes from each other is not a limitation. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>God, pure act, transcends all limitation of perfection.</p>
<p>The real distinction of absolute attributes is a limitation. So no real distinction of these is allowed in God. The distinction of wisdom from mercy from omnipotence arises from the limitation of our intellect.</p>
<p>The real distinction of relative attributes from each other is not a limitation.</p>
<p>The distinction of absolute from relative attributes is a limitation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trinitarianism and simplicity (3)</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/10/31/trinitarianism-and-simplicity-3/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 19:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26146</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[1.) Real being first divides into the absolute (defined in itself) and the relative (defined with another.) 2.) God as pure act transcends all divisions in being so far as these involve imperfection. 3.) Real division is a perfection of relative being. 4.) Human intellects unite distinct things in a single concept only at the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>1.) Real being first divides into the absolute (defined in itself) and the relative (defined with another.)</p>
<p>2.) God as pure act transcends all divisions in being so far as these involve imperfection.</p>
<p>3.) Real division is a perfection of relative being.</p>
<p>4.) Human intellects unite distinct things in a single concept only at the expense of a clear and explicit conception of their distinction. If we consider the generic unity of badger and possum in &#8220;mammal&#8221; we lose the distinction of species, if we consider the specific unity of two individuals we lose the division of the individuals.</p>
<p>5.) A human intellect understands a transcendent being with a concept that unites the lower-order things it transcends. Nevertheless, a genus or species  have only a logical unity whereas a transcendent being has real unity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trinitarianism and simplicity (2)</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/10/30/trinity-and-simplicity-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 14:36:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26136</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Take the standard trinitarian aporias:&#160; Or, with&#160;part&#160;meaning&#160;what added to something distinct from it to make a whole&#160; The first has parallels for other divine attributes* The second conflates different ways something can be added to another. Your complete idea of an apple adds your knowledge of its color to your knowledge of its taste, but [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Take the standard trinitarian aporias:&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li>God is triune</li>



<li>The Father is not triune</li>



<li>The Father is God.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>Or, with&nbsp;<em>part&nbsp;</em>meaning&nbsp;<em>what added to something distinct from it to make a whole&nbsp;</em></p>



<ul>
<li>Divine simplicity states God has no parts</li>



<li>The Father is a part of the trinity</li>



<li>The Father is God</li>
</ul>



<p>The first has parallels for other divine attributes*</p>



<ul>
<li>God is the divine omnipotence</li>



<li>The divine mercy is not the divine omnipotence.</li>



<li>The divine mercy is not God.</li>
</ul>



<p>The second conflates different ways something can be added to another. Your complete idea of an apple adds your knowledge of its color to your knowledge of its taste, but this is a multiplicity generated by the limitation of different modes of knowing and not a real division arising <em>ex parte </em>the object.</p>



<p><em>Objection: </em>But the division of the trinitarian persons is by real relations, and so requires real division before the act of a limited intellect.</p>



<p><em>Response: </em>All the premises of the objection are true, but God in himself transcends the real division of relative terms as much as he transcends all non-relative or absolute terms like wisdom, omnipotence, mercy, etc.</p>



<p><em>Objection: </em>You are affirming contradictories of the same subject! This is no different from affirming the impossibility of that subject!</p>



<p><em>Response: </em>No. Transcendence simply is the unity in a higher order subject of what is diverse in lower-order subjects. Note also that the first principle of our thought is the principle of contradiction because we understand being only in its opposition to non-being, nevertheless, we can use that same principle to see how a subject that it supremely transcendent can only be known by us as subtending the opposition between the relative and the non-relative or absolute.</p>



<p>*&#8221;attribute&#8221; is a transliteration of the Latin. The sense is anything attributed to God, i.e. anything true about his substance.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Trinitarianism and simplicity</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/10/29/trinitarianism-and-simplicity/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 15:11:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26123</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[(a) The Son is not the Father, (b) so the reality that is the one is not the reality that is the other. Trinitarianism denies the inference, saying that the distinction in (a) can&#8217;t be taken as ruling out (b.) John of St. Thomas: the thing with contradictory names or terms adjoined to it is not [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>(a) The Son is not the Father, (b) so the reality that is the one is not the reality that is the other.</p>
<p>Trinitarianism denies the inference, saying that the distinction in (a) can&#8217;t be taken as ruling out (b.)</p>
<p>John of St. Thomas: <em>the thing with contradictory names or terms adjoined to it is not said to have a distinction in the subject about which it is said, unless that subject be limited&#8230; but not if the subject be transcendent (</em>eminens<em>) and equivalent to many limited realities</em> (aequivalens pluribus limitatis.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Conditional necessity of acts, with grace and without</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/10/28/conditional-necessity-of-acts-with-grace-and-without/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 16:02:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26118</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[(1) Every time God permits sin, the man will sin (2) Every time God does not permit sin but rather gives grace, man will not sin. Thomas believes both conditionals are necessarily true, but that their necessity is only in the composed sense and not in the divided sense. The analysis is the same as [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>(1) Every time God permits sin, the man will sin</p>
<p>(2) Every time God does not permit sin but rather gives grace, man will not sin.</p></blockquote>
<p>Thomas believes both conditionals are <em>necessarily </em>true, but that their necessity is only in the composed sense and not in the divided sense. The analysis is the same as <em>if you are sitting, you cannot be standing</em>, namely, <em>given </em>you are sitting it is impossible for you to be simultaneously standing; but the truth of the conditional is not a proof for your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astasis">astasis</a>, just as the truth of (1) or (2) is not a proof for your sins not being done freely.</p>
<p>The necessity of the composed sense in (1) is not the same as (2.) In (1) the antecedent is a sheer<em> sine qua non</em> for the consequent, while in the second the antecedent is an efficient cause. By a <em>sheer</em> sine qua non, moreover, we mean it does not enter into the proper account of why the consequent arose, like when one says <em>if an angel did your homework, it would not be missing. </em>The conditional is true, but it plays no role in the proper account of why the homework is missing, because the sufficient cause of the missing homework is something apart from the angels, just as a sufficient cause of sin is the fallibility of the creature.</p>
<p>The efficient causality of (2) is of a primary cause and not a secondary one, and so cannot be understood as a rival to the autonomy of its effect but as presupposed to it. This is simply how we find things: if there is created free act, by definition there is an creating efficient cause prior to the created free act. If a free act had no efficient causal antecedents, any free act would be a divine act, and any claim to free choice would be a claim to divinity.</p>
<p>Again, assume you had always understood the relation between God and freedom like this: &#8220;God makes persons exist, then persons make their acts exist.&#8221;  This is fine, but you don&#8217;t mean either that persons produce actions <em>ex nihilo </em>or that God does not. So <em>exists </em>is being said in analogous ways, first in the manner of a primary cause and next in the manner of a secondary one. Both act freely, and the freedom is an indetermination of alternatives, but the primary cause&#8217;s alternatives between being and non being simpliciter are not the same as the secondary cause&#8217;s alternatives between being and non being secundum quid. More to the point, &#8220;to act in the manner appropriate to a primary cause&#8221; is to act precisely as establishing a secondary cause in its being as autonomous.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gerrigou on permission of sin vs. withholding of efficacious Grace</title>
		<link>https://thomism.wordpress.com/2022/10/26/gerrigou-on-permission-of-sin-vs-withholding-of-efficacious-grace/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[James Chastek]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 21:16:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://thomism.wordpress.com/?p=26113</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Gerrigou distinguishes four moments in the commission of sin: 1.) God allows a moral defect in a creature. 2.) The creature sins, or sets up some impediment to grace. 3.) God withholds efficacious grace. 4.) The creature sins. The sequela of 1 and 3 are the same, but (3) is a punishment while (1) is [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Gerrigou distinguishes four moments in the commission of sin:</p>
<blockquote><p>1.) God allows a moral defect in a creature.</p>
<p>2.) The creature sins, or sets up some impediment to grace.</p>
<p>3.) God withholds efficacious grace.</p>
<p>4.) The creature sins.</p></blockquote>
<p>The sequela of 1 and 3 are the same, but (3) is a punishment while (1) is not a punishment, and even seems necessary for moral creatures to exist at all.</p>
<p>(2) Is understood as thwarting the development of sufficient grace, or harming the proximate potential to receive efficacious grace.</p>
<p>O&#8217;Neill explains that (1) is not a <em>cause </em>of (2) but only a condition:</p>
<blockquote><p>[I]f I do not give my beerless (and thus pitiable) neighbor the last beer in my refrigerator, this does not mean I have caused his beerlessness, although it is true that my not giving him my last beer is an indispensable condition of his not having beer. If I had given it to him he would not be in his sorry state of beerlessness.</p></blockquote>
<p>Notice the causal hiatus between (1) and (2.) While NON permission of moral defect makes sin impossible, it does not follow that non-permission plays any role in the <em>explanation</em> of sin. If an angel did Johnny&#8217;s homework, it&#8217;s impossible that it be missing, but this doesn&#8217;t give Johnny any right to invoke the angels (still less to blame them) in his explanation for why he didn&#8217;t turn it in.</p>
<p>One element in all this is that we have to see humans as in some way as sufficient causes, and even first causes of sin. If sin had a god, it would be us. This is hyperbole, of course, since sin at least has exterior conditions while divine causality does not, and sin does not formally have causes, since causes confer being. Nevertheless, we have a radical sufficiency in the order of moral evil that we simply don&#8217;t have in the order of moral goodness, which latter involves a real dependency on the first cause. The complete causal story of the good we do needs to take into account our participation in supreme goodness, but the complete causal story of the evil we do need not invoke participation in anything outside ourselves. Nevertheless, we still need to cry out to God to not permit us to fall into sin.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
		
		<media:content url="https://1.gravatar.com/avatar/760ad5e157c918341b9f6d695cd131f1?s=96&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&amp;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">a thomist</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
