<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#">

<channel>
	<title>Y Combinator</title>
	<atom:link href="http://blog.ycombinator.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
	<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com</link>
	<description/>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Aug 2021 21:46:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Gusto: The People Platform for SMBs</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/gusto-the-people-platform-for-smbs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anu Hariharan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Aug 2021 17:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Essay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Historically, there has been an undeniable gap in business services in the US. There are nearly six million small and medium businesses (SMBs) in the country, employing 43&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Historically, there has been an undeniable gap in business services in the US. There are nearly six million small and medium businesses (SMBs) in the country, employing 43 million people.<sup id="footnoteid1"><a href="#footnote1">1</a></sup> But unlike their larger counterparts, SMBs have been ignored by service providers, who have deemed the cost of reaching and serving them too high to warrant the effort. As a result, SMBs have been forced to cobble together off-the-shelf products, spreadsheets, and manual work to run their operations.</p>
<p>This gap is most visible in the payroll and benefits sectors. Even though companies like ADP and Paychex have existed for more than 50 years, about 30% of SMBs still manage payroll without the help of a third-party service.<sup id="footnoteid2"><a href="#footnote2">2</a></sup></p>
<p>There are three reasons why existing providers haven’t cracked small business payroll and benefits. First, SMBs are fragmented and hard to reach. Relative to the value they bring in, the cost of reaching and serving them has traditionally been too high to warrant the effort unless you can sell multiple products to them. Second, there is significant signup friction for benefits and payroll products. Lastly, benefits products can be costly for SMBs to offer to employees, which results in many just forgoing benefits altogether. The lack of access to simple payroll and benefits tools has had a significant impact on the operational efficiency of SMBs and the well-being of their employees. But where there is a gap, there is an opportunity.</p>
<p>Gusto launched in 2012 to tackle this opportunity, and more. Josh Reeves, Tomer London, and Eddie Kim saw an opportunity to build a people-centered software platform for SMBs that would do three things: (1) bring peace of mind to the employer and employee around complex actions like payroll, benefits, setting up software, and more; (2) help build better places to work by focusing more on the employer-employee partnership; and (3) create personal prosperity for employees by helping supercharge the paycheck and providing access to better benefits. Gusto initially focused on building payroll because it was the most acute pain point, and it was a natural system of record for employee data and transactions. Payroll was the foundation for Gusto to achieve its vision of being a comprehensive “people platform.” Far beyond just paying employees and maintaining compliance, <strong>Gusto’s goal is to help employers build great places to work and run successful teams.</strong> And for employees, <strong>Gusto’s goal is to help put the individual in the driver’s seat of their financial health and their career.</strong> The name “Gusto” embodies the company’s mission to create a world where work empowers a better life—where work can be done “with Gusto.”</p>
<p>The emergence of SaaS business models has further set the stage for companies like Gusto to transform SMB operations. With cloud-based software and automation, customers are cheaper to serve and simpler to onboard. In the long run, software platforms have the potential to be much larger than traditional incumbents. For customers, this will likely mean a significant bend in the cost curve for products and services. For SMBs specifically, this will lead to a meaningful boost financially and emotionally, and perhaps even higher degrees of company output. In this post, we will walk through Gusto’s journey from digital payroll provider to integrated people platform.</p>
<h1>Act 1: Payroll: The Perfect Starting Point</h1>
<p>When Gusto founders Josh, Tomer, and Eddie came together in 2011, they saw an unmet need in small business payroll. Despite the major players in the payroll space, 46% of SMBs in the US were spending more than three hours per month managing payroll logistics.<sup id="footnoteid3"><a href="#footnote3">3</a></sup> On top of that, 40% were paying a penalty each year for incorrect payroll filings.<sup id="footnoteid4"><a href="#footnote4">4</a></sup></p>
<p>This was both an emotional and logistical pain point for SMB owners, with many becoming visibly upset as they talked to Josh, Tomer, and Eddie about it. Upon digging deeper, the founders realized that incumbent providers were overly complex, and more manual than necessary. For example, to become a customer of ADP or Paychex, SMBs had to go through a lengthy process of filling out paper forms and talking with sales reps. Once using the product, they had to rely on the provider’s human specialists to input information and manage the payroll process rather than doing it independently. For SMBs that had neither the hours nor resources to initiate these processes, this approach was untenable. In addition, the employee experience was an afterthought. Incumbent providers treated payroll as a transactional activity, often forcing people to log in using ID numbers and providing limited functionality once they did log in. This made for an impersonal experience for employers and employees alike, and created even more manual work and overhead for employers.</p>
<p>Gusto saw an opportunity to upend the way payroll was done. First, by making payroll about people, not simply a transaction. And second, by bringing the strengths of modern software to this problem, using cloud, paperless, and mobile, to create a dramatically easier-to-use product. If the enrollment process were digitized and companies could access all aspects of payroll on their own time, barriers to getting set up and using the product would be removed. So Gusto began building a cloud-based engine that would allow SMBs to manage payroll with the click of a few buttons, and also make the employee an equally important user of the product instead of an afterthought.</p>
<p>Building payroll architecture is complicated. It involves managing multiple systems (taxes, withholdings, filings, payments) in a reliable and compliant way. To run payroll correctly, a business must identify which taxes are applicable to which employee (there are thousands of options, usually determined by where an employee lives and works). The business must calculate and withhold the right tax amount, at the local, state, and federal levels. Then the business must determine how the taxes get paid, which is an equally complicated process. Some states want checks, others ACH debit/credit, and states and counties often require different payment timing. And then there are filings. Every destination for tax requires a separate filing—some printed, some faxed, some electronic. There are thousands of these filings, and the forms are each very different. Finally, the business needs to send the payment to the employee via ACH typically 1–2 days after running payroll, or write them a check by hand.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/1-Gusto-Overview.png" alt="Gusto Payroll Overview" width="1950" height="1070" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1104909" srcset="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/1-Gusto-Overview.png 1950w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/1-Gusto-Overview-300x165.png 300w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/1-Gusto-Overview-1024x562.png 1024w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/1-Gusto-Overview-768x421.png 768w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/1-Gusto-Overview-1536x843.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1950px) 100vw, 1950px" /></p>
<p>Gusto knew that payroll was a product which had to work, because people depended on it. So some of the normal Silicon Valley approaches to building quickly, and fixing later, wouldn’t work. Gusto’s product needed to provide reliable, timely, and precise tax calculations, filings, and payments to earn the trust of customers. The team initially focused on a narrow segment: businesses in California (1) that did not offer benefits or other deductions, (2) whose employees did not mind getting paid four business days after the company ran payroll and, (3) only had salaried employees. The goal was to solve the basics of payroll first and then to expand to more segments. This focus proved to be very beneficial, since it helped the company build a more solid foundation, and validate that its product was indeed much easier to use, and loved by customers.</p>
<p>The founders were their own first customers, only paying themselves after they were able to run their paychecks seamlessly through their software. It took a year to get to a public beta. One year after public launch, Gusto reached 1,500 customers. Today, Gusto is available nationwide and customers can onboard employees and run payroll in a matter of minutes. The company serves over 200,000 businesses, and they’ve made payroll much more efficient: 72% of customers spend five minutes or less to run payroll.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/2-gusto-img-payroll-portal.png" alt="Gusto&#039;s Payroll Portal" width="2199" height="1558" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1104910" srcset="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/2-gusto-img-payroll-portal.png 2199w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/2-gusto-img-payroll-portal-300x213.png 300w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/2-gusto-img-payroll-portal-1024x726.png 1024w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/2-gusto-img-payroll-portal-768x544.png 768w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/2-gusto-img-payroll-portal-1536x1088.png 1536w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/2-gusto-img-payroll-portal-2048x1451.png 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px" /></p>
<p>With its software up and running, Gusto needed to figure out its go-to-market strategy. SMBs had historically been hard to reach. Incumbents relied primarily on sales teams, which Gusto suspected actually limited their reach among SMBs. Cloud software had the potential to transform this process. For the first time, businesses could reach and serve customers with an entirely online strategy. And on top of that, the Gusto team knew that time was precious for SMB owners. What they needed was a product that worked, which was accurate, powerful, and also simple and easy to use. Gusto believed this is what modern software should be all about: a product that made life easier for its users, not more stressful. Gusto leaned into an online referral and brand-based go-to-market strategy rather than building out a direct outbound sales force. If the product was truly great, the company believed customer love and word-of-mouth would power growth. In fact, it would need to: Given the lower annual contract values of SMBs, they needed a strong inbound engine to make the economics work. This was a risky bet, but it worked. Within the first three years of launching, Gusto was serving more than 20,000 SMBs, with growth largely coming from referrals and word-of-mouth. Customers loved the product and wanted to tell other business owners about it.</p>
<h1>Act 2: All-in-one People Platform</h1>
<p>Starting with payroll made sense for two reasons. First, every business needs it. Second, building payroll architecture requires collecting and structuring a lot of data (where employees live, name, email, start date, dependents, salary, etc.). Once in place, this structured data positioned Gusto for its second act: to leverage the payroll core, keep investing in it, but also expand around it a “people platform” that would help SMBs build great places to work.</p>
<p>One of the main drivers of this thinking was a desire to bring to SMBs all of the benefits, resources, tools, and advantages big companies have historically had. Large companies have whole departments helping with HR, IT, benefits, and more, plus a wide variety of technologies and tools at their disposal. SMBs have historically been on their own. Gusto wanted to change that. And today, Gusto has expanded to provide a wide swath of functionality: (1) employee onboarding that helps manage identity across the different tools used by the business, (2) more accessible benefits, (3) access to tax credits, (4) financial optimization tools for employees, and more. With Gusto, SMB owners are able to spend more time running their businesses and less time on back-office work, while actually making their employees happier.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/3-gusto-blog-img-2.png" alt="Gusto - The People Platform" width="2050" height="1070" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1104911" srcset="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/3-gusto-blog-img-2.png 2050w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/3-gusto-blog-img-2-300x157.png 300w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/3-gusto-blog-img-2-1024x534.png 1024w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/3-gusto-blog-img-2-768x401.png 768w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/3-gusto-blog-img-2-1536x802.png 1536w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/3-gusto-blog-img-2-2048x1069.png 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2050px) 100vw, 2050px" /></p>
<h3>People software for SMBs</h3>
<p>Gusto began by making its product the central source of truth for hiring, onboarding, and employee communication. With Gusto, SMBs can create offer letters, complete onboarding checklists, and set-up software for new hires—traditionally manual and time-consuming processes. When a new employee signs on, Gusto tracks progress of offer signing, distributes forms and plans, and makes sure the employee has access to the software they need. After onboarding, Gusto enables time tracking, employee surveys, and distribution of the employee’s documents.</p>
<p>Beyond massively reducing process inefficiency, Gusto has focused on customer delight permeating all aspects of its product. When a candidate receives an offer, the experience feels akin to a wedding invitation, versus the typical &#8220;check-the-box&#8221; paperwork. When a new hire joins, employees can post welcome messages on Gusto’s internal message board. On payday, employees receive a celebratory email, which the employer can add a personal message to. All of this transforms what was once a purely transactional experience to one that is more people centric, in which employees are treated as valued members of the company.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/4-gusto-img-payday-email-e1630292881349.png" alt="Gusto Payday Email" width="750" height="1074" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1104912" /></p>
<p>On the employer side, customer delight manifests in saved time and helpful guidance. When it is time to run payroll, Gusto sends managers a reminder to sign forms, approve expenses, and initiate payroll. Each quarter, Gusto sends an email to employers summarizing employee changes and all the background tasks that have been completed automatically by Gusto, with no action needed from the employer. Gusto also integrates with expense and accounting tools, eliminating the manual work of recording payroll entries and approving expenses. And employers are able to use Gusto as a system of record for their employees, which means employees are easily able to access benefits and other employment-related information on their own even after leaving their company, all through the Gusto mobile app. All of this results in massive time savings for employers, allowing them to focus on actually running their business.</p>
<p>Whereas incumbents designed their products to be reactive to customer needs, the Gusto product experience more closely resembles a human HR advisor, something SMBs typically do not have. This support system creates a relationship built on trust, where Gusto is valued as an opinionated partner rather than just another payroll tool. SMBs want a partner they can trust, that also provides great service and great technology; Gusto has strived to be great at both.</p>
<h3>Improving access to health benefits</h3>
<p>Providing health benefits to employees is costly, complicated, and time-consuming for SMBs. Traditionally, SMBs work with benefits brokers in a largely offline process. First, they have to find a broker. Then, they have to go through the tedium of gathering the business and employee information the broker needs. The broker then shares benefit options based on their specific carrier relationships, which are often limited and result in suboptimal and expensive options for SMBs. Once a plan is chosen, employers and brokers put together an enrollment program to drive adoption within the organization. There is then continuing overhead as employers work with brokers to manage renewals, new hires, and plan changes, often in a very manual fashion. Because of this complex process, basic benefits like health insurance are often too much for a small business to manage. Data suggest that only 56% of companies with fewer than 100 employees offer health benefits (versus 90% for 500+ employee businesses).<sup id="footnoteid5"><a href="#footnote5">5</a></sup></p>
<p>Gusto reduces all this friction. As a licensed broker with payroll data already, Gusto makes it possible for a business to buy health insurance in a few clicks, rather than having to resubmit the information over and over again. And if the customer wants to speak with someone, Gusto has licensed benefits advisors on staff. Gusto also lowers the cost of benefits. Traditionally, pricing varies significantly because different providers have different loss ratios. Gusto applies algorithms to thousands of health plans to help customers choose the most cost-effective and appropriate plans for their situation. And for employers who cannot afford small group insurance, Gusto offers QSEHRA, a health reimbursement account built into payroll that employers can contribute pre-tax dollars to every month. Long-term, we believe Gusto may even be able to use its scale to reduce insurance costs by creating its own health plans in partnership with insurance carriers, further lowering costs for SMBs.</p>
<p>Gusto also enables customers to access government programs and benefits as they arise in real time. The best example of this happened during the COVID-19 lockdown. While small businesses were struggling, Gusto created a <a href="https://covidresources.gusto.com/">COVID-19 resources</a> tool for its customers to take advantage of programs like the Payroll Protection Program (PPP). Gusto simplified complex forms and enabled customers to easily apply for PPP loans through their partners. With this program, Gusto helped generate billions of dollars in assistance for its customers.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/5-gusto-img-benefits-experience.png" alt="Gusto&#039;s Benefits Experience" width="1832" height="1954" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1104913" srcset="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/5-gusto-img-benefits-experience.png 1832w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/5-gusto-img-benefits-experience-281x300.png 281w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/5-gusto-img-benefits-experience-960x1024.png 960w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/5-gusto-img-benefits-experience-768x819.png 768w, https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/5-gusto-img-benefits-experience-1440x1536.png 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 1832px) 100vw, 1832px" /></p>
<h3>Helping employees optimize their finances</h3>
<p>Gusto has endeavored to treat the employee as an equal stakeholder from day one. And in the past few years, the company has been making meaningful investments to help employees with their personal finances. Payroll is the inception of one’s income. Gusto had the simple insight that, if they could make personal finance choices (like saving) much simpler and easier, then people would make these choices more often. Gusto first launched <a href="https://gusto.com/product/cashout">Cashout</a>, a product to help employees avoid payday loans and high-interest credit card debt by giving them early access to paychecks at no cost. In a tight labor market, companies have turned to this type of benefit to attract and retain employees, and the number of businesses with employees enrolled in Cashout has more than doubled since January 2021. Cashout has helped 73% of users prevent bank overdrafts, and 52% of employees say having access to Cashout would impact whether they accept a job or not.</p>
<p>But Gusto’s broader goal is for employees to not need Cashout in the first place. If an individual had savings in place, then during an emergency, they would have the funds they need already. To help employees with savings, banking, and more, Gusto introduced <a href="https://gusto.com/wallet">Gusto Wallet</a> in 2020, a free banking app that lets employees put their paycheck, banking, savings, and emergency funds in one place. Employees are able to put aside part of their paycheck into savings, creating a rainy day fund for emergencies. Plus, they’re able to connect payroll &amp; banking in one holistic experience. Looking ahead, Gusto is well-positioned to continue launching new employee services with seamless integration processes. These products are a win-win-win: Employers get value with free benefits for employees, employees have access to powerful spending and savings tools, and Gusto further differentiates its product.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/6-gusto-img-wallet-e1630292853481.png" alt="Gusto Wallet" width="750" height="1074" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1104914" /></p>
<h3>A people platform powered by people</h3>
<p>Gusto&#8217;s approach to customer service and product has led to levels of customer love previously unheard of in the SMB software space. In the decade since its launch, Gusto has become a beloved nationwide brand, helping 200,000+ SMBs across the US (over 3% market share<sup id="footnoteid6"><a href="#footnote6">6</a></sup>) process hundreds of billion dollars of payroll, all while maintaining an NPS that is typically only seen among popular consumer companies. Its significant market share and growth trajectory signal to us that Gusto is already filling a long-standing gap in the SMB landscape. We believe that Gusto will continue to grow and compound for decades to come, as the platform expands and gains a wider reputation as a better and more cost-effective alternative to incumbents.</p>
<h1>Act 3: New Ways to Empower Teams</h1>
<p>Looking ahead, we believe Gusto has two major opportunities to build on top of the solid foundation they’ve created.</p>
<p>The first is to simply build more products for businesses and their employees. Because Gusto sits at the intersection of employees and employers, it is in a prime position to launch new products for both parties. Gusto can keep making their lives easier, help employers run better businesses, and help employees accomplish their work goals. On the employee side, Gusto could become a primary bank account, seamlessly setting up direct deposits. In time, Gusto could layer on investment products and even peer-to-peer payment tools. On the employer side, Gusto is positioned to help solve many other pain points, including further streamlining government compliance and reporting, making healthcare even more accessible, making business financials easier, and more.</p>
<p>In 2021, Gusto expanded into new services through acquisitions. Gusto recently acquired <a href="https://gusto.com/company-news/welcoming-ardius-to-gusto">Ardius</a>, an AI-powered tax credit solution, to help SMBs access valuable R&amp;D tax credits that historically have been too cumbersome to apply for. Because Gusto already manages its customers’ payroll documentation, it’s now infinitely easier for SMBs to access these credits and improve their cash flow. Gusto also acquired <a href="https://gusto.com/company-news/welcoming-symmetry-to-gusto">Symmetry</a>, an infrastructure company that builds APIs for payroll tax calculations. Together, Symmetry and Gusto will be able to make advances that benefit the entire payroll industry. For example, they could develop an early alert system for tax code changes, notifying business owners when state or local minimum wage requirements change, and ensuring employees complete the required withholding forms.</p>
<p>The second major opportunity we see is in embedded services. Gusto recently launched <a href="https://gusto.com/company-news/introducing-gusto-embedded-payroll">Gusto Embedded Payroll</a> to allow business-to-business (B2B) software companies to offer payroll capabilities to their own customers via APIs. For example, Squire (YC S16), a company that builds software and tools for barbershops, will offer payroll features in its own app using Gusto’s functionality. This provides a better experience for barbershops, generates more revenue for Squire, and extends Gusto’s payroll platform beyond their direct customers. Embedded services not only unlocks new opportunities to serve SMBs within vertical SaaS, fintech, and business operations, but it also exposes millions of new businesses to modern payroll. And as we’ve seen, payroll is just the beginning. Gusto is working to provide developers with APIs to embed its suite of people products into their own platforms, as a full-fledged Infrastructure-as-a-Service (IaaS) solution.</p>
<h1>Conclusion</h1>
<p><em>“Software is better at following rules but people make the experience incredible.”</em></p>
<p>This quote from Josh Reeves embodies the ethos of Gusto. The company’s powerful software has modernized the way SMBs run and empowered employees to be in the driver&#8217;s seat of their finances, but the real key to its success has been the insight that people are the foundation of any business. People are what make SMBs special. With Gusto, SMBs in the US and the people that work in them are positioned better than ever to succeed.</p>
<p><em>Thank you to Mia Mabanta and Chloe Gordon for reading multiple drafts of this essay, and to Zain Ali for designing and editing the graphics.</em></p>
<hr />
<p><sup><b id="footnote1">1</b></sup> US Census: Firms and Establishments by State, Industry (2018; released May 2021) <a href="#footnoteid1"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a><br />
<sup><b id="footnote2">2</b></sup> 2018 Small Business Taxation Survey <a href="#footnoteid2"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a><br />
<sup><b id="footnote3">3</b></sup> 2018 Small Business Taxation Survey <a href="#footnoteid3"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a><br />
<sup><b id="footnote4">4</b></sup> 2018 Internal Revenue Services estimates <a href="#footnoteid4"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a><br />
<sup><b id="footnote5">5</b></sup> Bureau of Labor Statistics: Employee Benefits in the United States (March 2020). <a href="#footnoteid5"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a><br />
<sup><b id="footnote6">6</b></sup> There are approximately 6 million employers in the US. <a href="#footnoteid6"><img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/13.1.0/72x72/21a9.png" alt="↩" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>YC Jobs Series: Women Eng in Startups</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/yc-jobs-series-women-eng-in-startups/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kat Mañalac]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 17:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Ask a Female Engineer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Women Founders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Work at a Startup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YC Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104901</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This fall, YC and Elpha (S19) will bring together a cohort of women engineers who are interested in finding roles at fast growing startups.

YC will host a month-long series where participants will meet once a week for two-hour sessions. During sessions, you will hear from women who joined startups as early engineers, meet YC alumni and alumni company engineering managers, and build a community of peers. The program will culminate in at least two interviews for each participant.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This fall, YC and <a href="https://elpha.com/">Elpha (S19)</a> will bring together a cohort of women engineers who are interested in finding roles at fast growing startups.</p>
<p>YC will host a month-long series where participants will meet once a week for two-hour sessions. During sessions, you will hear from women who joined startups as early engineers, meet YC alumni and alumni company engineering managers, and build a community of peers. The program will culminate in at least two interviews for each participant.</p>
<p>Topics discussed will include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Why join a startup? What are the pros and cons? </li>
<li>How do you determine where you should work and what should you look for in a startup and founding team?</li>
<li>How to prepare for the interview process and interview practice</li>
</ul>
<p>Each session, we will also host small breakout sessions with founders, engineers and managers across a range of YC startups &#8212; from early stage to growth &#8212; including:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2021">Christina Caccioppo, Cofounder &#038; CEO of Vanta</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2021">Cadran Cowansage, Cofounder &#038; CEO of Elpha</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2021">Diana Hu, Cofounder &#038; CTO of Escher Reality and YC Visiting Partner</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2021">Lucia Huang, Cofounder &#038; CEO of Osmind</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2021">Reshma Khilnani, Cofounder &#038; CTO of MedXT and YC Visiting Partner</a></li>
</ul>
<p>If you are currently an engineer working at a tech company and you’re looking for your next role and might want to transition to a startup, this series is for you.</p>
<p>To apply for the program, visit <a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2021">YC&#8217;s Work at a Startup</a> and create a profile by September 13th. (Note that profiles are visible to YC founders and hiring managers at YC startups. If you&#8217;re not ready to share your profile or look for a job, please specify so on the application.)</p>
<p><b><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2021">https://www.workatastartup.com/events/yc-women-eng-in-startups-2021</a></b></p>
<p><i>At YC, we use an inclusive definition of “women” and welcome trans women as well as genderqueer and non-binary people who identify as women or femme in any way.</i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Venture Debt 101: Basics and Approach</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/venture-debt-101-basics-and-approach/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jon Levy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 15:59:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Advice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Essay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104897</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In this guide, YC Managing Director Jon Levy talks about venture debt. He covers what it is, walks through some of its benefits and risks, and gives advice on how to approach the process of taking on venture debt. He also highlights Brex's newly launched venture debt offering. Brex is a YC portfolio company that provides an all-in-one finance solution to their customers. With Brex's new offering, they have plans to make the venture debt process simple and transparent. 
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>In this guide, YC Managing Director Jon Levy talks about venture debt. He covers what it is, walks through some of its benefits and risks, and gives advice on how to approach the process of taking on venture debt. He also highlights Brex&#8217;s newly launched venture debt offering. Brex is a YC portfolio company that provides an all-in-one finance solution to their customers. With Brex&#8217;s new offering, they have plans to make the venture debt process simple and transparent.</em></p>
<h2>What is Venture Debt?</h2>
<p>Venture debt is a loan to companies that have raised money from venture capital investors (“VCs”). Traditionally, banks only loan money to companies that have collateral (i.e. assets, cash flow, profits); venture debt is different in that venture debt lenders will offer debt financing to promising companies that are not cash flow positive, without existing collateral,  provided that these emerging companies have raised money from VCs and show strong growth potential.</p>
<p>Money is essential for companies to grow, and venture debt can be helpful. It can boost a company’s cash reserves and extend its runway. It can provide a bridge so that a founder can delay raising an equity round, grow the company and attract higher valuations. Venture debt interest rates often are based off of WSJ Prime (currently at an all-time low percentage), and venture debt may protect a founder’s ownership by allowing a founder to retain a higher percentage ownership of his/her company. While venture debt can help a founder by protecting ownership, it also carries risks and founders should understand the pros and cons before accepting venture debt.</p>
<p>Venture debt investors are fundamentally different from equity investors. Equity investors understand that one successful investment can make up for a number of losses (<a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/swan.html">http://www.paulgraham.com/swan.html</a>); venture debt investors expect to get repaid on every investment. With venture debt investors, repayment is contractually required: every cent must be repaid. Venture debt investors typically tie their investment to business plan milestones, metrics like accounts receivable and revenue, or events, whereas most equity investors allow startups leeway to pivot. Unlike equity investors, venture debt investors are less flexible. These investors are not as concerned with reputational damage: while an equity investor may support a startup that “pivots” to find product market fit, a venture debt investor is less understanding, given the need to get repaid. Venture debt lenders are thus more apt to enforce a contract to make sure their money is returned, even if the company would be killed from such enforcement. These investors are myopically focused on losing as little money as possible; they rarely are interested in any other considerations.</p>
<h2>Strategy: How to Approach Venture Debt</h2>
<p>First, founders need to understand basic venture debt terminology. Founders do not need to be venture debt experts, but do need to understand their contractual obligations, particularly because venture debt lenders will rely on these contractual terms to protect their investment<a id="footnote1a"><a href="#footnote1"><b><sup>1</sup></b></a></a>. Founders need to assess which terms are important, and which ones may place their company at risk. At the bottom of this essay is a short glossary and explanation of some key terms that founders will encounter in a venture debt financing.</p>
<p>Second, after understanding the basics, founders should consider evaluating multiple venture debt lenders in order to make the process competitive. Far too often, Y Combinator founders tell me that they met a venture debt lender, got a term sheet and quickly signed and agreed to terms.  A founder would never speak to only one equity investor when raising a Series A round, but in my experience, it is common for founders to speak to only one venture debt investor.  Fortunately, there are more lenders and new entrants offering venture debt, and founders now have additional options (more on this topic below). Working with a more friendly lender that you know well can make all the difference in a downside case, but you also should not drag on the venture debt raise process for months – you have a business to run.</p>
<p>Third, founders must involve legal counsel when entering into a venture debt relationship. Again, the terms and conditions of venture debt financings arguably matter more than equity financings because lenders do not hesitate to assert their rights and will apply assertive tactics to recover every dollar they can. For example, there are important differences in the types of “defaults” that may trigger a loan to be due immediately, and experienced counsel will help protect a company and make sure that it is better positioned if things go awry. Often a startup involves counsel after a term sheet is signed, but it is better to involve counsel earlier in the process, which typically is when a company has more leverage.</p>
<p>Please note that while venture debt investors need to protect their investment, they also deserve to be treated fairly. There are many instances where venture lenders have complained that companies were not forthcoming about their circumstances and did not provide relevant information such as their cash burn, or the loss of a significant lost contract. It does not help a company to hide from its lenders – the worst possible way to treat your lender is to make them think that everything is going according to plan, and then drop a bombshell on them when it’s too late to course-correct. Because there may be ways to restructure debt, it inures to a company’s benefit to treat its lenders fairly.</p>
<h2>Good news: New Entrant: Brex</h2>
<p>I mentioned there are new entrants in the venture debt space, and Y Combinator is glad that our portfolio company Brex is now offering venture debt financings to startup companies. Understanding startups’ financial needs is in Brex’s DNA: the company grew quickly because it understood the challenges startups had with accessing basic credit. Brex knows how to serve startups and young companies with a variety of credit solutions and is a welcome addition to this market. YC has shared our concerns with Brex about the pitfalls of venture debt, and Brex has plans to make its venture debt financing terms simple and transparent. While we are confident in Brex’s ability to compete in any market, we continue to believe that all startups should reach out to multiple parties when accessing venture debt. To learn more about Brex’s offering, see <b><a href="https://www.brex.com/product/venture-debt/">here</a></b>.</p>
<h2>Conclusion:</h2>
<p>Venture debt clearly has many benefits &#8212; it offers startups a less dilutive way to inject capital into a healthy, growing business, a business that most traditional banks ignore today.  At its best, venture debt is an effective complement to equity financing, and helps accelerate a company’s growth. But accessing venture debt is not without risks<a id="footnote2a"><a href="#footnote2"><sup><b>2</b></sup></a></a>. Founders should be realistic and ask themselves whether they are taking on a burden that can be repaid. A company is best positioned to assume venture debt when it is confident in its ability to repay the loan, which will eliminate all associated risks.</p>
<h3>GLOSSARY: BASIC TERMINOLOGY (for familiarity only; counsel needs to be hired):</h3>
<p><u>Commitment</u>:  What type of commitment is your venture debt investor making? How much money is being offered? When can your company access the money? Does the company need to “draw-down” over time? Can the company access all the capital at once?</p>
<p><u>Term Loan/ Revolver</u>:  Term loans are for a set time period (i.e. 3 years) and have a fixed payment schedule. The payment schedule can be “amortized” meaning that both the principal and interest is paid through periodic payments e.g. a mortgage; a “bullet” payment means the interest payment is made throughout and the principal is paid at the end of the term (aka the “maturity” date).</p>
<p>Revolvers are like credit cards or a line of credit: a borrowing limit is set by the lender. Most venture lenders charge a “commitment fee” – the fee can be a flat fee or a fixed percentage of the commitment and is intended to compensate the lender for keeping open access to the money. Make sure to understand how much money is being paid on fees: venture lenders tend to nickel and dime companies with tiny fees.</p>
<p><u>Interest Rate</u>:  Interest rate is a crucial term and varies on a company’s ability to repay; the rate may vary from ~6-10%. Term sheets often express interest as “Prime rate plus x%”.  Many lenders offer an interest only period prior to requiring repayment of principal.</p>
<p><u>Warrants</u>:  Warrants are another critical term and provide the lender with potential upside as a stockholder in a venture backed company. Warrants are typically a percentage of the commitment (i.e. 5% of $2mm). Most lenders ask for preferred stock based on a company’s last round, but an increasing amount of recent term sheets request a set percentage of common stock. Obviously, it is important to speak to multiple lenders when negotiating interest rates and warrant coverage.</p>
<p><u>Prepayment Penalties</u>:  Founders should make sure there are no charges for paying back their loan early (can be very useful if the market improves).</p>
<p><u>Investor Abandonment</u>:  A clause that allows the lender to demand repayment if a company’s investor doesn’t invest in the company’s future round.</p>
<p><u>Negative Pledge on IP</u>: A clause that prevents a company from pledging its intellectual property to another party while the loan is outstanding. Sometimes lenders ask for a first-priority security interest on a company’s IP &#8212; this is a term companies should not accept.</p>
<p><u>Field exams/ legal costs</u>:  Beware of hidden fees! Look for clauses that allow the lender to conduct on site exams (at the company’s expense). Make sure to cap legal fees and do not pay the lender for documents that have been drafted a hundred times.</p>
<p><u>Current Ratio/ Quick Ratio</u>:  These financial terms measure a company’s liquidity and may impact how large a commitment a lender makes. The “current ratio” measures a company’s assets by dividing the company’s assets by the amount of liabilities. The “quick ratio” only includes the most liquid current assets that can be turned to cash quickly, and does not include inventory, supplies, etc. Venture debt lenders often use these ratios in covenants to monitor liquidity.</p>
<p><u>Default Provisions</u>: Defaulting on a loan allows the lender to ask for its money back and can kill a company. There are different types of defaults in venture loan contracts: technical default (violating a covenant); monetary default (missing a payment); change in status default (legal judgment); and there are subjective defaults: “material adverse change” or “investor abandonment”.  It is important to maintain a good relationship with your lender, especially if there is a subjective default provision that may be triggered. In these circumstances, a lender bank may choose to revise its debt, or make the more draconian decision to send the loan to its bank’s workout group.</p>
<hr />
<p><a id="footnote1"><a href="#footnote1a"><sup><b>1</b></sup></a></a> Venture debt terms and concepts are very simple; the language may seem daunting because it is unfamiliar. The dynamic is similar to equity financings: it is disconcerting for founders when they first hear preferred stock financing terminology (e.g. liquidation preference, broad-based weighted average anti-dilution, right of first refusal and co-sale rights).  But all YC founders quickly get up to speed and understand the meaning of these simple concepts.  Venture debt terminology may seem unfamiliar, but also can be understood quickly.</p>
<p><a id="footnote2"><a href="#footnote2a"><sup><b>2</b></sup></a></a> I have not listed all the risks associated with venture debt. It is important to note that unlike equity, venture debt requires a startup to agree to financial “covenants” &#8212; e.g. a startup needs approval before incurring additional indebtedness, selling assets, etc.. More important, in a downside scenario, a venture lender often influences a company’s ultimate exit. That means if a company is running out of capital and has two options, one which employees prefer and one which is better for the bank, the company probably will have to choose the option that is better for the bank. These risks further highlight why founders need to be realistic about their ability to repay. To emphasize, founders should remember that venture debt is a debt that needs to be paid back.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Inside YC: The Admissions Team</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/inside-yc-the-admissions-team/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mark Thurman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 19 Aug 2021 16:00:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Admissions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104891</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Twice a year, YC accepts applications from startups around the world. The Admissions Team is responsible for designing that process and reviewing the tens of thousands of applications we receive each year. 

How do we review that many applications? Mostly, it's lots of people reading lots of applications! There's no secret machine learning model that can find companies with great potential. Instead, we build lots of custom software to help our team work efficiently. Our app reading software allows us to quickly read applications, send messages to founders if we have any questions, and decide which teams we want to interview.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Twice a year, YC accepts <a href="http://ycombinator.com/apply">applications</a> from startups around the world. The Admissions Team is responsible for designing that process and reviewing the tens of thousands of applications we receive each year.</p>
<p>How do we review that many applications? Mostly, it&#8217;s lots of people reading lots of applications! There&#8217;s no secret machine learning model that can find companies with great potential. Instead, we build lots of custom software to help our team work efficiently. Our app reading software allows us to quickly read applications, send messages to founders if we have any questions, and decide which teams we want to interview.</p>
<h2>History of the Admissions Team</h2>
<p>When YC first started, the admissions process was pretty manual. YC’s 4 founders printed out the applications, wrote comments in the margin, and passed them around the room. As the batches started to grow, Paul Graham wrote the first software to accept and process applications (it was originally part of the same code that powered <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com">Hacker News</a>!). By 2014, YC was receiving 3,000 applications per batch, PG retired, and we moved to our current application software. Then in 2016, the Admissions Team was created and began to hire more people to review applications, analyze data, and update the application. Today, a team of 5 runs the admissions process.</p>
<h2>What’s unique about the Admissions Team?</h2>
<p>The Admissions Team is powered by human judgement, but it couldn’t work at YC’s scale without software. Sometimes, our problems can be solved by software (like automatic parsing of a founder’s responses), but sometimes it&#8217;s a human problem (how should we evaluate teams that haven’t launched yet?). This interaction between humans and software is always changing. Each admissions cycle brings more applications than the previous one and our system is always being pushed to the limit in unexpected ways.</p>
<h2>What are some projects we&#8217;ve recently worked on?</h2>
<ul>
<li>Rewriting our software to video interview teams (instead of flying<br />
teams to California).</li>
<li>Building new internal tools to allow us to do interviews more often<br />
(like the <a href="https://blog.ycombinator.com/early-deadline-for-yc-winter-2022/">early interviews</a> we&#8217;ve been running this year).</li>
<li>Reviewing applications we didn’t fund but that raised money from<br />
other investors, to learn how to improve our application reading and<br />
interview process.</li>
<li>Analyzing YC application data — for example, we looked at whether<br />
repeat applications hurt a team’s chances of being funded. (It turns<br />
out they don’t! Teams that re-apply and have made progress since<br />
their first app are much more likely to get into YC.)</li>
<li>Working with the Outreach and <a href="https://www.startupschool.org/">Startup School</a> teams to get more teams<br />
applying to YC.</li>
</ul>
<p>The thing I love about the Admissions Team is that we have a lot of autonomy to experiment and change our process. It’s also incredibly exciting to read all of these ideas which may someday change the world. If you&#8217;re interested in joining our team, we&#8217;re hiring <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=ef00c8d1-76e7-4cc3-82fe-7cc3e4679652">Software Engineers</a> to improve our software and <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=c8a4c1c8-9410-479f-86e7-cb2c1ca35e32">Admissions Associates</a> to read applications.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>11 YC startups hiring for biology, life sciences, chemistry and data informatics roles</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/11-yc-startups-hiring-for-biology-life-sciences-chemistry-and-data-informatics-roles/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ryan Choi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Aug 2021 17:59:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Biotech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Work at a Startup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104880</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[YC funded our first biotech company, Ginkgo Bioworks, in 2014. Since then, we’ve expanded aggressively into all areas of biotech and the life sciences. Today, YC funds more&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>YC funded our first biotech company, <a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/ginkgo-bioworks">Ginkgo Bioworks</a>, in 2014. Since then, we’ve expanded aggressively into all areas of biotech and the life sciences. Today, YC funds more seed stage biotech companies than any other investor.</p>
<p>To help further the mission of our biotech and hard science startups, YC is now expanding <a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/jobs?role=science">YC&#8217;s job platform</a> to support science-related roles. The inaugural YC startups range from 3-person companies in our most recent Winter 21 batch to the nearly-public <a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/ginkgo-bioworks">Ginko Bioworks</a> itself.</p>
<p>Some highlights of open roles on the platform:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/noya">Founding Chemist/Material Scientist at Noya (W21)</a>.</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/gilgamesh-pharmaceuticals">Director of Medicinal Chemistry at Gilgamesh Pharmaceutical (W20)</a>.</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/rev-genomics">Plant Biologist at Rev Genomics (S17)</a>.</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/shasqi">Director of Tumor Genomics at Shasqi (S19)</a>.</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/shasqi">Lead Scientist, Genome Engineer at MoGen (W21)</a>.</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/ginkgo-bioworks">Senior Data Engineer at Ginko Bioworks (S14)</a>.</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>At Work at a Startup, you can find hundreds of fast-growing startups and create a single profile to apply to them all. And as YC funds new startups in biotech and life sciences, founders can find your profile and reach out to you directly.</p>
<p>We welcome you to check out some of the first bio and life science YC startups hiring on the platform, and stay tuned as more go live over the next few months.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Find a remote or in-person job at a YC startup from the most recent Winter ’21 batch</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/find-a-remote-or-in-person-job-at-a-yc-startup-from-the-most-recent-winter-21-batch/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ryan Choi]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 18:41:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Work at a Startup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YC Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104875</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Y Combinator hosted our Summer 2021 Career Expo last month, which included 34 founders -- many of whom graduated from YC's most recent W21 batch. Many have customers and revenue and completed a fundraise; all are hiring early team members in engineering, product, design, sales and more. The event was fully virtual and included YC startups from across the world, including Seattle, Toronto, New York, Barcelona, San Francisco and more. We're sharing the founder pitches on Work at a Startup where you can create a profile to meet the founders and learn about open roles. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Y Combinator hosted our <a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/startup-tech-expo-summer-2021">Summer 2021 Career Expo</a> last month, which included 34 founders &#8212; many of whom graduated from YC&#8217;s most recent W21 batch. Many have customers and revenue and completed a fundraise; all are hiring early team members in engineering, product, design, sales and more.</p>
<p>This event was fully virtual and included YC startups from across the world, including Seattle, Toronto, New York, Barcelona, San Francisco and more. We&#8217;re sharing the founder pitches on <a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/">Work at a Startup</a>, where you can create a profile to meet the founders and learn about open roles.</p>
<p>Startups include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/smartcuts">Smartcuts (W21)</a></strong> is building a Chrome extension to turn clicks &amp; keystrokes into no-code automations. Join as an early engineer or designer and learn directly from a multi-time YC founder.</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/modernloop">ModernLoop (W21)</a></strong> helps teams automate and streamline recruiting operations. Their founding team is from Facebook, Slack and Brex, and they&#8217;re looking for a great fullstack engineer. </li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/per-diem">Per Diem (W21)</a></strong> enables local businesses to offer subscriptions to their customers. The team is based in New York, and they&#8217;re hiring for engineers, PMs and salespeople. </li>
<li><strong><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/companies/magicbell">MagicBell (W21)</a></strong> has created a notification inbox you can plug directly into your own web or mobile application. They&#8217;re based in Barcelona and also hiring for fully-remote back-end and frontend software engineers.</li>
</ul>
<p>View all the pitches on Work at Startup and create a profile to connect directly with founders:</p>
<p><b><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/startup-tech-expo-summer-2021">https://www.workatastartup.com/events/startup-tech-expo-summer-2021</a></b></p>
<p><a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/events/startup-tech-expo-summer-2021"><br />
<img loading="lazy" src="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/07/Screen-Shot-202
1-07-25-at-10.53.11-PM-1024x615.png" alt="YC Summer 21 Tech Expo" width="780" height="468" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-1104877" /><br />
</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Come Work at YC – July 2021</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/come-work-at-yc-july-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Y Combinator]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 16:15:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Work at a Startup]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104864</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[YC’s Admissions, Continuity and Software teams are hiring. Find out more about the open roles.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>YC’s Admissions, Continuity and Software teams are hiring. Find out more about the open roles <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers">here</a>.</p>
<p><strong>ADMISSIONS</strong><br />
<a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=c8a4c1c8-9410-479f-86e7-cb2c1ca35e32"><strong>Admissions Associate</strong></a>: Twice a year, Y Combinator receives tens of thousands of applications from promising startups all around the world. Reviewing these applications is fundamental to our core business and we&#8217;re looking for an Admissions Associate to review those applications and help manage the overall admissions process. <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=c8a4c1c8-9410-479f-86e7-cb2c1ca35e32">Learn more</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=ef00c8d1-76e7-4cc3-82fe-7cc3e4679652"><strong>Product Engineer</strong></a>: The YC admissions team uses lots of custom software to process the tens of thousands of applications we receive every year. We’re looking for a Product Engineer to help us improve that software. In the last year we’ve rewritten our software to do video interviews (instead of in person), analyzed admissions data to understand how our <a href="https://blog.ycombinator.com/early-deadline-for-yc-winter-2022/">Early Deadline</a> performed, and changed how we ask questions in the application. We’re planning lots more improvements and looking for someone to own projects from idea to implementation. <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=ef00c8d1-76e7-4cc3-82fe-7cc3e4679652">Learn more.</a></p>
<p><strong>CONTINUITY</strong><br />
<a href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/ycombinator/e38a08e5-71e9-4165-b4bc-59254cf95bff"><strong>First Data Engineer at YC</strong></a>: YC Continuity is hiring our first Data Engineer to help us identify promising investment opportunities using data. This is an innovative role for somebody to build YC’s data infrastructure from the ground up. <a href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/ycombinator/e38a08e5-71e9-4165-b4bc-59254cf95bff">Learn more.</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/ycombinator/8aa099e3-8dab-41db-946e-69a3a4209c11">Research Associate</a></strong>: YC Continuity is seeking a Research Associate to evaluate investment opportunities, lead market research, and help our portfolio companies grow. This is a unique opportunity for somebody who loves data and startups to help us build definitive points of view to guide investment decisions. <a href="https://jobs.ashbyhq.com/ycombinator/8aa099e3-8dab-41db-946e-69a3a4209c11">Learn more.</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=c093ffa1-e638-4fd9-86bc-97663ab6d0b8">Series A Program Manager</a></strong>: YC Continuity is seeking a Program Manager to lead the YC Series A Program. The program offers all YC founders resources to help them achieve the best possible outcomes when raising capital: year-round workshops, detailed fundraising guides &amp; templates, and 1:1 support. This is a great role for someone who is passionate about startups and interested in learning more about them. Given the number of YC companies raising Series As every year, you&#8217;ll have an unparalleled understanding of how these financings happen and the early-stage funding ecosystem. <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=c093ffa1-e638-4fd9-86bc-97663ab6d0b8">Learn more.</a></p>
<p><strong><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=242ef73e-c89e-4a50-9cd4-e91f275805f8">Investment Associate</strong></a>: YC Continuity is seeking an Associate to help analyze and invest in growth stage companies. Our primary goal is to support YC alumni companies by investing in their subsequent funding rounds. <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=242ef73e-c89e-4a50-9cd4-e91f275805f8">Learn more.</a></p>
<p><strong>SOFTWARE</strong><br />
<strong><a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=ef00c8d1-76e7-4cc3-82fe-7cc3e4679652">Product Engineer</a></strong>: As YC has gone remote in the last year, our small-but-mighty software team has been busy building the OS that runs all of YC. In the last six months alone, we&#8217;ve rewritten our entire Demo Day experience (to connect founders with potential investors), re-created the batch experience with both in-house tools and 3rd party integrations, and written software to help founders connect with one another for advice, intros, deals, networking and so much more. We have a ton more to deliver, so we&#8217;re looking to hire multiple product engineers to join the team. This is a great role for somebody who loves helping startups, is eager to talk with YC founders (our customers!), and wants to own projects from start-to-finish. <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/careers?ashby_jid=ef00c8d1-76e7-4cc3-82fe-7cc3e4679652">Learn more.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>YC S21 Virtual Demo Day</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/yc-s21-virtual-demo-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michael Seibel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 16:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[YC Events]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104859</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On the morning of August 31st and September 1st, YC will host our 33rd Demo Day live on Zoom. This two day event will feature founders from over&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>On the morning of August 31st and September 1st, YC will host our 33rd Demo Day live on Zoom.</strong> This two day event will feature founders from over 46 countries and startups in every sector — from healthcare and fintech to consumer and B2B software. Every company will have one minute to present.</p>
<p>At the start of the day, a single-slide company summary, short company description, and team bio will be available through the YC Demo Day website. The same website will also provide access to the live stream and the capability to connect with each company. By the end of the week, recordings of the presentations will be published on the website.</p>
<p>If you are an investor or member of the press, you can find more information about attending Demo Day at <a href="https://demoday.ycombinator.com/">demoday.ycombinator.com</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Y Combinator Launches Co-Founder Matching Platform</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/co-founder-matching/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Catheryn Li]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2021 16:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Startup School]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104838</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We’re excited to announce Y Combinator’s co-founder matching platform is now available for everyone through Startup School, our free online program and community for founders. Anyone actively looking&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We’re excited to announce Y Combinator’s co-founder matching platform is now available for everyone through <a href="https://www.startupschool.org/">Startup School</a>, our free online program and community for founders. Anyone actively looking for a co-founder can sign up at <a href="https://www.startupschool.org/cofounder-matching">startupschool.org/cofounder-matching</a>. The platform has been in beta for the past few months, as we’ve experimented with the process within the Startup School community. To date, we’ve made 9,000 matches across 4,500 founders.</p>
<p>Finding the right co-founder is an incredibly important step in the startup journey. At YC, we have endless anecdotes that show building a company with a co-founder greatly helps with productivity and morale. This is supported by our data: while we do <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/library/7P-does-yc-fund-solo-founders/">fund solo founders</a>, only four of the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies/">top 100 YC companies</a> came to YC without a co-founder.</p>
<p>But finding a co-founder who is compatible with you — and ready to take that leap when you are — can be very difficult. Within the Startup School community, 20% of active founders report that they’re seeking a co-founder, and 25% of aspiring founders cite not having a co-founder as a blocker to starting their company full-time. Many of our users have tried many avenues for a long time, with little success.</p>
<p>We built our co-founder matching platform to tackle this problem. When you sign up, you tell us a number of things about yourself and your preferences for a co-founder (e.g. interests, location, skills). We then show you profiles of candidates that most closely match your ideal co-founder. When you find a candidate that piques your interest, you can send them a message, and if they accept, we match the two of you. The platform is optimized for rapid review to maximize the chances you find the right fit.</p>
<p>If that sounds a bit like online dating, that&#8217;s no coincidence. Like a romantic partner, a co-founder is someone you&#8217;ll depend on and spend a great deal of time with, hopefully for many years. You probably shouldn&#8217;t marry someone after just one date, and similarly, it&#8217;ll take more than one video call to decide whether to co-found a company with someone. We encourage matched co-founders to meet and, when appropriate, work together on a time-boxed trial project with clear expectations and goals in order to vet co-founder compatibility. One interesting commonality our founders can usually count on sharing — having all gone through Startup School — is alignment on the <a href="https://www.startupschool.org/curriculum">YC playbook</a> on how to run a startup.</p>
<p>We have seen some early signs of success: two companies who met through the platform earlier this year were accepted into the YC Summer 2021 batch! We’re really excited for them, and we hope to see more success stories as we continue to experiment and iterate on our solution to a big problem.</p>
<p><img src="https://blog.ycombinator.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/cofounder-matching.png" alt="YC's co-founder matching platform" /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Y Combinator Top Companies — July 2021</title>
		<link>https://blog.ycombinator.com/top-companies-july-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Y Combinator]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 16:00:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[YC News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.ycombinator.com/?p=1104834</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[YC companies raise money year round — leading to the YC Top Companies list becoming outdated almost as soon as it’s published. To combat this, moving forward the&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>YC companies raise money year round — leading to the <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/topcompanies">YC Top Companies list</a> becoming outdated almost as soon as it’s published. To combat this, moving forward the list will be refreshed every six months, in February and July. With that said, explore our newest list, which now includes more than 160 companies valued at $150M+. Together, the companies on July’s list are valued at more than $400B+ and have created more than 70,000 full-time jobs.</p>
<p>We put this list together to help potential employees, partners, and late stage investors get to know a wider set of YC companies. One thing to note is that this is not an exhaustive list of the top YC companies; companies could opt out of being listed for any reason. To see a full list of YC companies, go <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/companies">here</a>.</p>
<p>Here are interesting stats about this list:</p>
<ul>
<li>We now have more than 160 companies valued at $150M+ and more than 40 companies at $1B+.</li>
<li>59% of the companies are headquartered in the Bay Area. 17% of the companies are headquartered in the U.S. but outside of the Bay Area. 14% of the companies are headquartered outside of the U.S. 10% of the companies are remote. </li>
<li>27 of the companies received growth-stage capital and company building support through <a href="https://www.ycombinator.com/continuity/">YC Continuity</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Here’s a sector breakdown of the companies on the list:<div class="wptb-table-container wptb-table-1104836"><div class="wptb-table-container-matrix"><table class="wptb-preview-table wptb-element-main-table_setting-1104641 edit-active" data-reconstraction="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); float: left;" data-wptb-table-tds-sum-max-width="377" role="table" data-wptb-td-width-auto="138" data-wptb-even-row-background-color="#ffffff" data-wptb-odd-row-background-color="#ffffff" data-wptb-header-background-color="#ffffff" data-wptb-responsive-directives="eyJyZXNwb25zaXZlRW5hYmxlZCI6ZmFsc2UsInJlc3BvbnNpdmVNb2RlIjoiYXV0byIsInByZXNlcnZlUm93Q29sb3IiOmZhbHNlLCJyZWxhdGl2ZVdpZHRoIjoiY29udGFpbmVyIiwiaGVhZGVyRnVsbHlNZXJnZWQiOmZhbHNlLCJtb2RlT3B0aW9ucyI6eyJhdXRvIjp7InRvcFJvd0FzSGVhZGVyIjp7ImRlc2t0b3AiOmZhbHNlLCJ0YWJsZXQiOnRydWUsIm1vYmlsZSI6dHJ1ZX0sInJlcGVhdE1lcmdlZEhlYWRlciI6eyJkZXNrdG9wIjp0cnVlLCJ0YWJsZXQiOnRydWUsIm1vYmlsZSI6dHJ1ZX0sInN0YXRpY1RvcFJvdyI6eyJkZXNrdG9wIjpmYWxzZSwidGFibGV0IjpmYWxzZSwibW9iaWxlIjpmYWxzZX0sImNlbGxTdGFja0RpcmVjdGlvbiI6eyJkZXNrdG9wIjoicm93IiwidGFibGV0Ijoicm93IiwibW9iaWxlIjoicm93In0sImNlbGxzUGVyUm93Ijp7ImRlc2t0b3AiOjEsInRhYmxldCI6MSwibW9iaWxlIjoxfX19LCJicmVha3BvaW50cyI6eyJkZXNrdG9wIjp7Im5hbWUiOiJkZXNrdG9wIiwid2lkdGgiOjEwMjR9LCJ0YWJsZXQiOnsibmFtZSI6InRhYmxldCIsIndpZHRoIjo3MDB9LCJtb2JpbGUiOnsibmFtZSI6Im1vYmlsZSIsIndpZHRoIjozMDB9fX0=" data-wptb-adaptive-table="0" data-wptb-table-alignment="left" data-table-columns="2" data-wptb-extra-styles="LyogRW50ZXIgeW91ciBjdXN0b20gQ1NTIHJ1bGVzIGhlcmUgKi8="><tbody><tr class="wptb-row" data-wptb-bg-color="#ffffff" style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="0" data-x-index="0" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 244px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>B2B Software and Services</p></div></div></td><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="0" data-x-index="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 50px;" data-wptb-cell-vertical-alignment="center"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>44%</p></div></div></td></tr><tr class="wptb-row" data-wptb-bg-color="#ffffff" style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="1" data-x-index="0" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 244px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>Financial Technology and Services</p></div></div></td><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="1" data-x-index="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 50px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>16%</p><p></p></div></div></td></tr><tr class="wptb-row" data-wptb-bg-color="#ffffff" style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="2" data-x-index="0" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 244px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>Consumer</p></div></div></td><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="2" data-x-index="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 50px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>16%</p><p></p></div></div></td></tr><tr class="wptb-row" data-wptb-bg-color="#ffffff" style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="3" data-x-index="0" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 244px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>Healthcare</p></div></div></td><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="3" data-x-index="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 50px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>9%</p><p></p></div></div></td></tr><tr class="wptb-row" data-wptb-bg-color="#ffffff" style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="4" data-x-index="0" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 244px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>Industrials</p></div></div></td><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="4" data-x-index="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 50px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>6%</p><p></p></div></div></td></tr><tr class="wptb-row" data-wptb-bg-color="#ffffff" style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="5" data-x-index="0" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 244px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>Real Estate and Construction</p></div></div></td><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="5" data-x-index="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 50px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>4%</p><p></p></div></div></td></tr><tr class="wptb-row" data-wptb-bg-color="#ffffff" style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="6" data-x-index="0" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 244px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>Education</p></div></div></td><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="6" data-x-index="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 50px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>4%</p><p></p></div></div></td></tr><tr class="wptb-row" data-wptb-bg-color="#ffffff" style="background-color: rgb(255, 255, 255);"><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="7" data-x-index="0" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 244px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>Government</p></div></div></td><td class="wptb-cell" data-y-index="7" data-x-index="1" style="border: 1px solid rgb(209, 209, 209); padding: 20px; width: 50px;"><div class="wptb-text-container wptb-ph-element wptb-element-text-1" style="font-size: 15px;"><div class="" style="position: relative;"><p>1%</p><p></p></div></div></td></tr></tbody></table></div></div>
</p>
<p>We are honored to have worked with the founders behind these companies and be part of their stories — from idea stage to a YC top company.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
