<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"><updated>2022-11-14T17:52:30+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ruby on Rails</title><subtitle>A web-app framework that includes everything needed to create database-backed web applications according to the Model-View-Controller (MVC) pattern.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Rails Foundation kicks off with one million dollars</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/14/the-rails-foundation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rails Foundation kicks off with one million dollars"><published>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/14/the-rails-foundation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/14/the-rails-foundation">&lt;p&gt;Today, we are excited to announce the launch of &lt;a href=&quot;/foundation&quot;&gt;The Rails Foundation&lt;/a&gt;. Its mission is to improve the documentation, education, marketing, and events in our ecosystem to the benefit of all new and existing Rails developers. It’s been started by some of the most important companies involved with Rails, and will work to ensure a prosperous ecosystem that continues to improve, and becomes even more attractive to newcomers going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-was-the-foundation-started&quot;&gt;Why was the foundation started?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been over 18 years since Ruby on Rails was first released, and since then, an incredible ecosystem has emerged around it. Millions of applications have been built using Rails by hundreds of thousands of happy developers over the years. Companies have gone all the way from HELLO WORLD to IPO using Rails, creating billions of dollars in value along the way. It’s been a glorious run, and we’re still going!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the technical side, we’ve also never stood stronger than we do with Rails 7. The Rails Core Team, together with thousands of contributors, have steered us forward with fixes, enhancements, and improvements in release after release. The code we all depend on is in great condition and under great care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after all these years, it’s also become clear that building a strong ecosystem depends on more than just great code. There have never been more options for new web developers than there are today, and if we want to continue to celebrate the success of Rails in another two decades from now, we need to make the best case possible for why someone should come join us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, that case isn’t being made as well as it could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for that is largely a question of documentation, education, marketing, and events. It’s not nearly easy enough for a developer interested in learning Rails to find their way through decades of often outdated books, blog posts, and screencasts, connect with others learning at the same time, make the case to coworkers or bosses why Rails is the right choice, or meet up with fellow practitioners at events solely dedicated to Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rails Foundation has been formed to address all of these points and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;who-is-a-part-of-the-foundation&quot;&gt;Who is a part of the foundation?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In alphabetical order, the eight founding core members of The Rails Foundation are: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cookpad.com&quot;&gt;Cookpad&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.doximity.com&quot;&gt;Doximity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fleetio.com&quot;&gt;Fleetio&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.intercom.com&quot;&gt;Intercom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.procore.com&quot;&gt;Procore&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shopify.com&quot;&gt;Shopify&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://37signals.com&quot;&gt;37signals&lt;/a&gt;. These corporate members have together generously endowed the foundation with $1,000,000 USD in seed funding to make a real difference on all the aforementioned areas of improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The founding core members are each represented on the foundation’s board, which is then chaired by the creator of Ruby on Rails, David Heinemeier Hansson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The board’s first task will be to hire a full-time executive director who will run the daily operations of this new non-profit 501(c)6 foundation, and work with freelancers and contributors to fulfill the foundation’s mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rails Foundation has secured a long-term exclusive license to all the Ruby on Rails trademarks, and will be responsible for the maintenance and evolution of the rubyonrails.org website, social media channels, and all other outlets that may serve to further its mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rails Core Team will continue to be fully responsible for the technical evolution of the framework, managing code contributions, and shepherding new releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, The Rails Foundation and The Rails Core Team will work to ensure that our ecosystem stays healthy, continues to improve, and becomes even more attractive to newcomers going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next-for-the-foundation&quot;&gt;What’s next for the foundation?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the foundation’s side, there are a million ideas on how this might be done, and now there’s a million dollars to make it happen. But we will not stop there either. The Rails Foundation is also immediately open to new contributing corporate members, who may apply for membership by writing to foundation@rubyonrails.org for more details. If your company has been benefiting from Rails over the years, but not sure how it might give back to the ecosystem, now there’s a clear and obvious choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re excited to get started on this new era for the Ruby on Rails ecosystem!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>The Rails Foundation</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Today, we are excited to announce the launch of The Rails Foundation. Its mission is to improve the documentation, education, marketing, and events in our ecosystem to the benefit of all new and existing Rails developers. It’s been started by some of the most important companies involved with Rails, and will work to ensure a prosperous ecosystem that continues to improve, and becomes even more attractive to newcomers going forward.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">This Week in Rails: A bugfix and improvements!</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/11/this-week-in-rails-this-week-in-rails-a-bugfix-and-improvements-5cb2ec4e" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="This Week in Rails: A bugfix and improvements!"><published>2022-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/11/this-week-in-rails-this-week-in-rails-a-bugfix-and-improvements-5cb2ec4e</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/11/this-week-in-rails-this-week-in-rails-a-bugfix-and-improvements-5cb2ec4e">&lt;p&gt;Hi there,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gregmolnar&quot;&gt;Greg&lt;/a&gt;, bringing you the latest changes in Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46448&quot;&gt;Fix Enumerable#many? to handle all block parameters&lt;/a&gt;
Before this fix, &lt;em&gt;Enumerable#many?&lt;/em&gt; didn’t forward the block parameters to the block, so if someone called it in a chain with &lt;em&gt;each_with_index&lt;/em&gt;, the index wasn’t passed to the block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46461&quot;&gt;Use filename when printing pending migrations&lt;/a&gt;
By using &lt;em&gt;filename&lt;/em&gt;, instead of &lt;em&gt;basename&lt;/em&gt;, the full path of the migration will be displayed, which can be useful when migration files are stored in multiple directories, for instance in a multi-db app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46425&quot;&gt;Make error highlight readable on dark mode&lt;/a&gt;
The recently introduced error highlighting on the error pages were hard to read in dark mode, but not anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46469&quot;&gt;Improve the MissingExactTemplate error page&lt;/a&gt;
This improvement to the MissingExactTemplate error page adds the actual controller and action name to the page, replacing the generic example there before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20221104-20221111&quot;&gt;19 people&lt;/a&gt; contributed to Rails this past week! Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>gregmolnar</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Hi there,</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An improved error page, groundwork for composite primary keys and Stimulus 3.1.1</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/4/this-week-in-rails-an-improved-error-page-groundwork-for-composite-primary-keys-and-stimulus-3-1-1-5b1f824a" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An improved error page, groundwork for composite primary keys and Stimulus 3.1.1"><published>2022-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/4/this-week-in-rails-an-improved-error-page-groundwork-for-composite-primary-keys-and-stimulus-3-1-1-5b1f824a</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/11/4/this-week-in-rails-an-improved-error-page-groundwork-for-composite-primary-keys-and-stimulus-3-1-1-5b1f824a">&lt;p&gt;Hi, Petrik here with this week’s news from the Rails world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46342&quot;&gt;Improve the “missing template” error page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This error page got a nice overhaul with clearer wording, making it more helpful, especially for beginners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46331&quot;&gt;Allow specifying columns to use in ActiveRecord::Base object queries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Support for composite primary keys in Rails is &lt;a href=&quot;https://discuss.rubyonrails.org/t/rfc-finally-support-composite-primary-keys/81368/12&quot;&gt;getting prioritized&lt;/a&gt;. This change is fundamental for supporting composite primary keys in Rails and utilizing tenant based sharding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46251&quot;&gt;Fix &lt;em&gt;Time#change&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Time#advance&lt;/em&gt; for times around the end of Daylight Saving Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Previously, when &lt;em&gt;Time#change&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Time#advance&lt;/em&gt; constructed a time inside the final stretch of Daylight Saving Time (DST), the non-DST offset would always be chosen for local times. This commit fixes &lt;em&gt;Time#change&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Time#advance&lt;/em&gt; to choose the offset that matches the original time’s offset when possible.&lt;br /&gt;
If you are like me and find Daylight Saving Time confusing, the PR has better examples. 😄&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hotwired/stimulus/releases/tag/v3.1.1&quot;&gt;Stimulus 3.1.1 has been released&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This release fixes a memory leak and adds support for support custom Action Options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were &lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20221028-20221104&quot;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt; contributors to Rails this week. You can browse all the changes &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/compare/@%7B2022-10-22%7D...main@%7B2022-10-28%7D&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Until next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>petrik</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Hi, Petrik here with this week’s news from the Rails world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">More intuitive checking of form check boxes and radio buttons</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/28/this-week-in-rails-more-intuitive-checking-of-form-check-boxes-and-radio-buttons-2c4b3e21" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More intuitive checking of form check boxes and radio buttons"><published>2022-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/28/this-week-in-rails-more-intuitive-checking-of-form-check-boxes-and-radio-buttons-2c4b3e21</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/28/this-week-in-rails-more-intuitive-checking-of-form-check-boxes-and-radio-buttons-2c4b3e21">&lt;p&gt;Hi, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/morgoth85&quot;&gt;Wojtek&lt;/a&gt; here with this week’s news from the Rails world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45527&quot;&gt;Support checked as a keyword argument in check_box_tag and radio_button_tag&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Now the form helper&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;f.check_box &quot;admin&quot;, checked: false
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;works as expected. Previously it had to be passed as positional argument.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46273&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Allow Active Record adapter “execute” to retry on connection-related exception&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Setting &lt;em&gt;allow_retry&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; causes the database to reconnect and retry executing the SQL statement in case of a connection-related exception. Should only be used for known idempotent queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46280&quot;&gt;Expose the “request.parameter_filter”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Feature is useful when one wants to filter some hashes based on the same parameter filter as the request:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;request.parameter_filter.filter(&quot;secret&quot; =&amp;gt; &quot;foo&quot;, &quot;something&quot; =&amp;gt; &quot;bar&quot;))
#=&amp;gt; { &quot;secret&quot; =&amp;gt; &quot;[FILTERED]&quot;, &quot;something&quot; =&amp;gt; &quot;bar&quot; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46339&quot;&gt;Adds “validate” to foreign keys and check constraints in database schema file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 Previously, &lt;em&gt;schema.rb&lt;/em&gt; would not record if &lt;em&gt;validate: false&lt;/em&gt; had been used when adding a foreign key or check&lt;br /&gt;
 constraint, so restoring a database from the schema could result in foreign keys or check constraints being&lt;br /&gt;
 incorrectly validated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46305&quot;&gt;Fix “MemoryStore” to preserve entries TTL when incrementing or decrementing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The change is to be consistent with how &lt;em&gt;MemCachedStore&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;RedisCacheStore&lt;/em&gt; behaves, ie don’t remove the expiration value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were &lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20221022-20221028&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt; contributors to Rails this week. You can browse all the changes &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/compare/@%7B2022-10-22%7D...main@%7B2022-10-28%7D&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Until next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>morgoth85</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Hi, Wojtek here with this week’s news from the Rails world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Active Record improvement, performance gains and a bugfix!</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/21/this-week-in-rails-activerecord-querymethods-reselect-now-accepts-a-hash-performance-gains-and-a-fix-for-ciphertext_for-5254976c" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Active Record improvement, performance gains and a bugfix!"><published>2022-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/21/this-week-in-rails-activerecord-querymethods-reselect-now-accepts-a-hash-performance-gains-and-a-fix-for-ciphertext_for-5254976c</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/21/this-week-in-rails-activerecord-querymethods-reselect-now-accepts-a-hash-performance-gains-and-a-fix-for-ciphertext_for-5254976c">&lt;p&gt;Guten Tag! &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/siaw23&quot;&gt;Emmanuel&lt;/a&gt; here again, with some updates from Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46197&quot;&gt;Don’t trigger after_commit :destroy callback again on destroy if record previously was destroyed&lt;/a&gt;
The &lt;em&gt;after_commit :destroy&lt;/em&gt; callback would always run even if a record was destroyed previously. This PR fixes that. Essentially, we don’t want to call &lt;em&gt;after_commit :destroy&lt;/em&gt; on unpersisted records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46299&quot;&gt;Allow ErrorReporter to handle several error classes&lt;/a&gt;
ErrorReporter now allows you to handle several error classes in one go. You can now handle multiple error classes like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rails.error.handle(ArgumentError, TypeError) do
  # Do some work
end&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46284&quot;&gt;Fix ciphertext_for for yet-to-be-encrypted values&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ciphertext_for&lt;/em&gt; should return the encrypted value of an attribute that’s encrypted even when the record has not been persisted, before this commit, this wasn’t what we were getting, instead, for an unpersisted record, &lt;em&gt;ciphertext_for&lt;/em&gt; returned the plain text value of the attribute. This PR fixes that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46231&quot;&gt;Avoid unnecessary serialize calls after save&lt;/a&gt;
We’ve got some performance gains with this one: This commit memoizes &lt;em&gt;value_for_database&lt;/em&gt; so that &lt;em&gt;serialize&lt;/em&gt; is not called a 2nd time after save. Because &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; is the single source of truth and can change in place, the memoization carefully checks for when &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; differs from the memoized &lt;em&gt;@value_for_database&lt;/em&gt;. Verbatim from the commit message. 😎&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46253&quot;&gt;Allow ActiveRecord::QueryMethods#reselect to accept a hash&lt;/a&gt;
This PR allows &lt;em&gt;ActiveRecord::QueryMethods#reselect&lt;/em&gt; to receive hash values, similar to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45612&quot;&gt;this PR&lt;/a&gt; that allowed &lt;em&gt;ActiveRecord::QueryMethods#select&lt;/em&gt; to accept hashes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20221014-20221021&quot;&gt;21 contributors improved&lt;/a&gt; Rails in the past week. We’ll bring you more updates next week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>siaw23</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Guten Tag! Emmanuel here again, with some updates from Rails.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Column information in ERB template exceptions, migration option validation and more!</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/14/this-week-in-rails-column-information-in-erb-template-exceptions-migration-option-validation-and-more-05773303" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Column information in ERB template exceptions, migration option validation and more!"><published>2022-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/14/this-week-in-rails-column-information-in-erb-template-exceptions-migration-option-validation-and-more-05773303</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/14/this-week-in-rails-column-information-in-erb-template-exceptions-migration-option-validation-and-more-05773303">&lt;p&gt;Hey, this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gregmolnar&quot;&gt;Greg&lt;/a&gt; bringing you the latest news from the Rails world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46171&quot;&gt;Add column information to exceptions inside ERB templates&lt;/a&gt;
This PR adds column information to exceptions that occured inside ERB templates. There are before and after screenshots of the Rails error page, and a great explanation of the change in the PR description.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46178&quot;&gt;Validate options when managing columns and tables in migration&lt;/a&gt;
With this change, when an invalid option is passed to a migration method(&lt;em&gt;create_table&lt;/em&gt; for instance), an error will be raised. The options validation is only applied to newly created migrations, to make it backward compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46230&quot;&gt;Update documentation of Range#to_s&lt;/a&gt;
Rails 7 deprecated passing a format option to &lt;em&gt;to_s&lt;/em&gt;, and added &lt;em&gt;to_fs&lt;/em&gt; as a replacement, and the documentation has also been updated now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46049&quot;&gt;Add Rails.application.deprecators&lt;/a&gt;
 With this change, &lt;em&gt;deprecators&lt;/em&gt; added by gem maintainers can be configured for the whole application. So when the user sets &lt;em&gt;Rails.application.deprecators.behavior = :raise&lt;/em&gt;, this behavior will be applied to all &lt;em&gt;deprecators&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hotwired/turbo/releases/tag/v7.2.2&quot;&gt;Turbo 7.2.2 release&lt;/a&gt;
A new minor version of Turbo has been released this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20221007-20221014&quot;&gt;18 people&lt;/a&gt; contributed to Rails this week! If you want the be part of that, checkout the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/issues&quot;&gt;list of open issues&lt;/a&gt;!
Until next week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>gregmolnar</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Hey, this is Greg bringing you the latest news from the Rails world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Updated Permissions-Policy directives and LSP support?</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/8/this-week-in-rails-updated-permissions-policy-directives-and-lsp-support-d0a52e70" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Updated Permissions-Policy directives and LSP support?"><published>2022-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/8/this-week-in-rails-updated-permissions-policy-directives-and-lsp-support-d0a52e70</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/10/8/this-week-in-rails-updated-permissions-policy-directives-and-lsp-support-d0a52e70">&lt;p&gt;Hi, this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/four54&quot;&gt;Petrik&lt;/a&gt; with this weeks updates in the Rails world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45427&quot;&gt;Support more Permissions-Policy directives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With the &lt;a href=&quot;https://edgeguides.rubyonrails.org/security.html#feature-policy-header&quot;&gt;Permissions-Policy header&lt;/a&gt; you can allow or block the use of browser features.&lt;br /&gt;
This pull request adds support for directives for the following features: &lt;em&gt;hid&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;idle-detection, screen-wake-lock, serial, sync-xhr&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;web-share&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46199&quot;&gt;Deprecate obsolete Permissions-Policy directives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The &lt;em&gt;speaker&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;vibrate&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;vr&lt;/em&gt; permissions policy directives are now deprecated. There is no browser support for these directives, and no plan for browser support in the future. You can just remove these directives from your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45992&quot;&gt;Allow direct uploads to work within engines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Calling direct uploads from inside a Rails Engine failed because &lt;em&gt;rails_direct_uploads_url&lt;/em&gt; was looked up in the engine’s routes instead of the application’s routes. It now uses the &lt;em&gt;main_app&lt;/em&gt; helper to verify if the &lt;em&gt;rails_direct_uploads_url&lt;/em&gt; exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tenderlove/status/1573459777354862592&quot;&gt;Language Server support for Rails apps (WIP)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This is very much a work in progress but it looks very promising. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tenderlove/refreshing&quot;&gt;Refreshing&lt;/a&gt; is a Language Server that refreshes the Rails app every time you save your buffer. It also communicates errors back to the editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we had &lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20221001-20221007&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt; contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bye!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>petrik</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Hi, this is Petrik with this weeks updates in the Rails world.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ERB in YAML keys, performance boosts, a new option for QueryLogs!</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/30/this-week-in-rails-erb-in-yaml-keys-performance-boosts-a-new-option-for-querylogs-2b63a564" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ERB in YAML keys, performance boosts, a new option for QueryLogs!"><published>2022-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/30/this-week-in-rails-erb-in-yaml-keys-performance-boosts-a-new-option-for-querylogs-2b63a564</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/30/this-week-in-rails-erb-in-yaml-keys-performance-boosts-a-new-option-for-querylogs-2b63a564">&lt;p&gt;こんにちは。I’m &lt;a href=&quot;https://manny.codes/&quot;&gt;Emmanuel&lt;/a&gt;, and I’ve got some updates for you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/44625&quot;&gt;Avoid double type cast when serialising attributes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ActiveModel::Attribute#value&lt;/em&gt; already casts model attributes when persisting models, however some model attribute types try to cast a given value before serialising it. This means casting is done twice in most cases. This PR fixes that, giving us some performance boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45081&quot;&gt;Add ability to set the tags_format for QueryLogs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ActiveRecord::QueryLogs&lt;/em&gt; gets a new &lt;em&gt;tags_format&lt;/em&gt; option. This makes it possible to specify if we want to use the default &lt;em&gt;:legacy&lt;/em&gt; formatter or &lt;em&gt;:sqlcommenter&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46134&quot;&gt;Facilitate use of any regular ERB in database.yml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;DummyCompiler&lt;/em&gt; has been replaced with &lt;em&gt;ERB::Compiler&lt;/em&gt;. True to what &lt;em&gt;dummy&lt;/em&gt; compilers do, it’d blow up when one tried to use ERB in a YAML key. This PR makes it possible to use ERB in YAML keys. While at it, we also deprecated &lt;em&gt;config.active_record.suppress_multiple_database_warning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46131&quot;&gt;Rails.error.report now marks errors as reported&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Rails.error.report&lt;/em&gt; now marks errors as reported to avoid reporting them twice. This PR also enables catching and reporting errors outside of the execution context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20220923-20220930&quot;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt; contributors in the last seven days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. Until next week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>siaw23</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">こんにちは。I’m Emmanuel, and I’ve got some updates for you! Avoid double type cast when serialising attributes ActiveModel::Attribute#value already casts model attributes when persisting models, however some model attribute types try to cast a given value before serialising it. This means casting is done twice in most cases. This PR fixes that, giving us some performance boost. Add ability to set the tags_format for QueryLogs ActiveRecord::QueryLogs gets a new tags_format option. This makes it possible to specify if we want to use the default :legacy formatter or :sqlcommenter. Facilitate use of any regular ERB in database.yml DummyCompiler has been replaced with ERB::Compiler. True to what dummy compilers do, it’d blow up when one tried to use ERB in a YAML key. This PR makes it possible to use ERB in YAML keys. While at it, we also deprecated config.active_record.suppress_multiple_database_warning. Rails.error.report now marks errors as reported Rails.error.report now marks errors as reported to avoid reporting them twice. This PR also enables catching and reporting errors outside of the execution context. We saw 23 contributors in the last seven days. That’s it. Until next week!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Improved assert_redirected_to, improved error messages and more!</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/23/this-week-in-rails-improved-assert_redirected_to-improved-error-messages-and-more-787f42d0" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improved assert_redirected_to, improved error messages and more!"><published>2022-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/23/this-week-in-rails-improved-assert_redirected_to-improved-error-messages-and-more-787f42d0</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/23/this-week-in-rails-improved-assert_redirected_to-improved-error-messages-and-more-787f42d0">&lt;p&gt;Hi, this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gregmolnar&quot;&gt;Greg&lt;/a&gt;, bringing you the latest changes in the Rails framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46057&quot;&gt;Allow specifying the HTTP status code in assert_redirected_to&lt;/a&gt;
Before this change, &lt;em&gt;assert_redirect_to&lt;/em&gt; asserted any &lt;em&gt;3XX&lt;/em&gt; response, but with this change, it is possible to assert a specific response code, like &lt;em&gt;301&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46068&quot;&gt;Allow passing classes to dom_id&lt;/a&gt;
Allowing &lt;em&gt;dom_id&lt;/em&gt; to receive a Ruby class, instead of an instance of a class, makes it behave like &lt;em&gt;dom_class&lt;/em&gt;, and besides saving a few keystrokes, it saves memory too, because Ruby doesn’t need to instantiate an entire object with all its callbacks and such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46064&quot;&gt;Improve error messages on bin/setup
&lt;/a&gt;Changing &lt;em&gt;bin/setup&lt;/em&gt; to use &lt;em&gt;system(…, exception: true)&lt;/em&gt; gives more information when a command fails, and makes debugging easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46086&quot;&gt;Allow to pass –force to db:system:change
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;db:system:change&lt;/em&gt; always prompts to confirm the overwriting of &lt;em&gt;database.yml&lt;/em&gt;, but now there is a &lt;em&gt;–force&lt;/em&gt; option to skip the confirmation prompt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hotwired/turbo/releases/tag/v7.2.0&quot;&gt;Turbo 7.2.0 was released&lt;/a&gt;
There is a new release for Turbo, which is also available via &lt;em&gt;turbo-rails 1.3.0&lt;/em&gt;. You can read the list of changes on the link above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had &lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20220917-20220923&quot;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt; contributors to Rails this week! If you want to be part of that, checkout the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/issues&quot;&gt;issues list&lt;/a&gt;!
Until next time! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>gregmolnar</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Hi, this is Greg, bringing you the latest changes in the Rails framework.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Handling reconnects in Action Cable, no more Coffeescript and a new guide.</title><link href="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/17/this-week-in-rails-handling-reconnects-in-action-cable-no-more-coffeescript-and-a-new-guide-ae13f499" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Handling reconnects in Action Cable, no more Coffeescript and a new guide."><published>2022-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/17/this-week-in-rails-handling-reconnects-in-action-cable-no-more-coffeescript-and-a-new-guide-ae13f499</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rubyonrails.org/2022/9/17/this-week-in-rails-handling-reconnects-in-action-cable-no-more-coffeescript-and-a-new-guide-ae13f499">&lt;p&gt;Hi, this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/four54&quot;&gt;Petrik&lt;/a&gt; with this week’s Rails updates and some Hotwire news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45887&quot;&gt;Add exclude? method to ActionController::Parameters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;exclude?&lt;/em&gt; returns &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; if the given key is not present in the parameters. It is the inverse of &lt;em&gt;include?.&lt;/em&gt;
Adding this method keeps things a little more consistent with a Hash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;params = ActionController::Parameters.new(id: 1)
params.exclude?(:name) # =&amp;gt; true
params.exclude?(:id) # =&amp;gt; false
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45738&quot;&gt;Add ability to handle reconnects with the connected callback&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a subscriber misses some messages when the connection is lost, this allows them to handle reconnects with the &lt;em&gt;connected()&lt;/em&gt; callback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;consumer.subscriptions.create(&quot;ExampleChannel&quot;, {
  connected({reconnected}) {
    if (reconnected) {
      ...
    }
    else {
      ...
    }
  }
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45950&quot;&gt;Add Puma to an engine’s Gemfile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ruby/ruby/pull/3729&quot;&gt;removal&lt;/a&gt;of WEBrick from the Ruby standard library, the dummy application in an engine would not start. Adding Puma to the Gemfile makes sure it works out-of-the-box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/46008&quot;&gt;Add ssl-mode option to dbconsole command and MySQLDatabaseTasks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For MySQL, verifying the identity of the database server requires setting the ssl-mode option to VERIFY_CA or VERIFY_IDENTITY. This option was previously ignored for the dbconsole command and database tasks like creating a database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45546&quot;&gt;Convert rails-ujs to ES2015 modules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rails-ujs code base was the only Coffeescript left in the Rails code base. It has now been migrated to use ES2015 modules and Rollup instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/45946&quot;&gt;Add the Error Reporter Guide&lt;/a&gt;
In Rails 7.0 an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rails/rails/pull/43625&quot;&gt;error reporter&lt;/a&gt; interface was introduced. It provides a generic interface to report errors, with an adapter API to allow using the service of your choice.
It now has its own guide!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rails had &lt;a href=&quot;https://contributors.rubyonrails.org/contributors/in-time-window/20220910-20220917&quot;&gt;23 contributors&lt;/a&gt; since last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Hotwire world there was a new release for Turbo this week:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hotwired/turbo/releases/tag/v7.2.0-rc.2&quot;&gt;v7.2.0-rc.2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for this week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/this.week.in.rails&quot;&gt;Subscribe&lt;/a&gt; to get these updates mailed to you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>petrik</name></author><category term="news"/><summary type="html">Hi, this is Petrik with this week’s Rails updates and some Hotwire news.</summary></entry></feed>