<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>JetRockets</title>
    <link>https://jetrockets.com/blog</link>
    <image>
      <url>https://jetrockets.com/assets/og-thumb-6963279940c80af44e9fd530eec7d090c56e883a.jpg</url>
      <title>JetRockets</title>
      <link>https://jetrockets.com/blog</link>
    </image>
    <language>en-EN</language>
    <item turbo="true">
      <title>Mobile Apps Vs Web Apps: Which Is Best For Your Business?</title>
      <description>![Mobile Apps Vs Web Apps: Which Is Best For Your Business?](https://i.postimg.cc/V670qL6t/Green-and-Peach-Modern-Dots-The-Latest-Gadget-Available-Banner.png)
Offering an app can be a great way to connect with your customers. They can provide services such as technical support, data transfer, location discovery, and more.
Businesses that want an app for themselves face a choice: **Web App or Mobile App?**</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:47:17 +0300</pubDate>
      <link>https://jetrockets.com/blog/mobile-apps-vs-web-apps-which-is-best-for-your-business</link>
      <guid>https://jetrockets.com/blog/mobile-apps-vs-web-apps-which-is-best-for-your-business</guid>
      <turbo:content>
        <![CDATA[<p>Although they might sound the same, they offer very different user experiences and come at different development costs. What works for one business might not work for another.</p>

<p>The key difference is that mobile apps need to be downloaded and installed, while web apps can be accessed through a web browser. This, in turn, means that mobile apps can offer faster performance and more functionality at the cost of more expensive development and the commitment to installation.</p>

<p>Businesses that want to offer an app should examine their core business model to determine which path is best for them.</p>

<h2>Mobile Apps Pros and Cons</h2>

<p>Mobile apps are popular - <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/271644/worldwide-free-and-paid-mobile-app-store-downloads/">over 200 billion</a> are downloaded each year. But that means they need to be installed on a mobile phone before they can be used. This makes them ideal for businesses with loyal, repeat customers.</p>

<p><em>Some advantages of mobile apps include:</em></p>

<p><strong>Faster Performance.</strong> Installing an app directly to the phone helps take advantage of existing efficiencies.</p>

<p><strong>More personalization.</strong> Users can set preferences and developers can integrate with more data.</p>

<p><strong>Working without internet.</strong> Basic functions that only involve local data can work.</p>

<p><strong>Better integration with hardware.</strong> This includes the GPS and camera.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/XvbjpSV0/statistic-id271644-annual-number-of-global-mobile-app-downloads-2016-2021.png" alt="© Statista 2022"></p>

<p><em>Mobile apps also have several disadvantages, including:</em></p>

<p><strong>Downloading and Installing.</strong> Not everyone will want to.</p>

<p><strong>Longer and more expensive development.</strong> Many apps will have to be ported to both iOS and Android.</p>

<p><strong>Requiring App Store approval.</strong> Apple and Google don’t let any old apps on their marketplace- you must follow strict rules and regulations.</p>

<h2><strong>Web Apps Pros and Cons</strong></h2>

<p>Web apps don’t need to be fully downloaded and installed before use. Instead, they are accessed through a web browser. Although this makes them more accessible to many people, it does cut down on some functionality.</p>

<p><em>Some advantages of web apps include:</em></p>

<p><strong>No installation is required.</strong> This is particularly appealing to people who might use the app once or twice and don’t want to download anything.</p>

<p><strong>Faster and cheaper development.</strong> Web apps just need to work on a browser, which means only one version is necessary.</p>

<p><strong>No approval is needed.</strong> Anyone can put a web app online.</p>

<p><em>Web apps also have disadvantages, including:</em></p>

<p><strong>Slower performance.</strong> Because they are not installed directly on your phone, they may run a bit slower than mobile apps.</p>

<p><strong>Limited hardware support.</strong> Web apps may make it more difficult to integrate features like cameras or GPS.</p>

<p><strong>Requiring internet.</strong> Since they are effective web pages, traditional web apps won’t work at all without the internet. However, some new web app models, like Progressive Web Apps, offer some offline functionality. PWAs are growing in popularity, and are expected to reach <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.emergenresearch.com/industry-report/progressive-web-application-market">$10 billion in market size in 2027.</a></p>

<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/mgQcdSkB/progressive-web-application-market-trend.png" alt="© Emergen Research 2022"></p>

<h3>Which Is Best For Your Business?</h3>

<p>Both mobile apps and web apps can be great tools for your business. Neither is intrinsically better or worse than the other. Which one you should use often depends more on the specific needs of your business.</p>

<p><em>To decide which path to take, consider these questions:</em></p>

<h5>What kind of customer relationships do I want to build?</h5>

<p>If regular, long-term, loyal customer relationships are the core of your business, then mobile apps make a lot of sense. A customer that interacts with you regularly over the course of many years might as well download an app and reap all the advantages.</p>

<p>On the other hand, if most of your business comes from irregular customers, they might not be willing to download an app for a company they won’t interact with again for several years, if ever. Installing an app is a commitment, and customers will never be more committed to your app than they are to your product.</p>

<h5>What kind of technologies do you need to use?</h5>

<p>Mobile apps generally offer more technological functionality than web apps. They can work offline, and they can access the camera and GPS. </p>

<p>If those features aren’t important to you, then maybe you can go with a web app. But if your plan absolutely needs a camera, GPS, or offline access, then you probably need a mobile app.</p>

<h5>What kind of online marketing do you already use?</h5>

<p>Web apps can benefit from existing marketing tools, like SEO or AdSense. If your business is already experienced with those frameworks, you can tap into their power to boost your brand.</p>

<p>Mobile apps, on the other hand, operate somewhat outside the web marketing ecosystem. They are usually found through search keywords in an app marketplace, rather than on Google.</p>

<p>If you are interested in building an app for your business, consider working with JetRockets. We build web apps and mobile apps using a range of technologies, including Ruby and Ruby on Rails, React, and Javascript. </p>
]]>
      </turbo:content>
    </item>
    <item turbo="true">
      <title>2023 IT &amp; Development Outlook Report</title>
      <description>### How Tech Leaders Are Tackling Digital Transformation Amidst Talent Shortages &amp; Economic Uncertainty

While the entire C-suite has been tested over the last couple years, few roles have been impacted as much as the role of the CIO and CTO. Tasked with scaling their organizations’ digitization efforts, these tech leaders have been in the eye of the storm since the onset of the pandemic, with its fallout causing companies to grapple with the many challenges and complexities that have arisen since.
</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 03:24:56 +0300</pubDate>
      <link>https://jetrockets.com/blog/jetrockets-2023-it-development-outlook-report</link>
      <guid>https://jetrockets.com/blog/jetrockets-2023-it-development-outlook-report</guid>
      <turbo:content>
        <![CDATA[<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/dQ2KDn9C/Article-Graphic-Images-Final-File-updated-hero-image-option-2.png" alt="2023 IT &amp; Development Outlook Report"></p>

<p>On the positive side, however, we’ve watched the roles of CIO and CTO elevate in the past few years from managing technology as a support function to driving strategy to fortify operations and adapt to new business and technological shifts. An evolution that has truly been imperative for every organizations’ survival. </p>

<p>But while this newfound spotlight has given them more prominence, it’s also ratcheted up the pressure on these IT leaders who are shouldering more responsibility as the race for strategic digitization intensifies. Further, new challenges, such as economic uncertainties and geopolitical tensions, have led to mass layoffs and resource constraints. These have created new obstacles and further complicated the role of leaders. The war in Ukraine, for instance, is proving to be a massive obstacle for those tech leaders who outsource to eastern Europe.</p>

<p>As a result, perhaps it’s not surprising that <strong>more than 1-in-3 tech leaders (39%) say they are either feeling“burnt out” (22%), or worried that they don’t have the resources and support needed to do their job (17%)</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/ZKvprBC6/Article-Graphic-Images-Final-File-updated-01.png" alt="More than 1-in-3 tech leaders (39%) say they are either feeling“burnt out” (22%), or worried that they don’t have the resources and support needed to do their job (17%)"></p>

<p>With all of this as a backdrop, the team at <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://jetrockets.com/">JetRockets</a>, a leading software development agency for disruptive organizations, commissioned a study to more than 450 U.S.- based IT leaders in CIO and CTO roles to analyze the challenges they face amidst the digitization arms race, as well as the decisions they will be making in the coming months to keep their organizations on the road towards recovery.</p>

<h3>The State of Development Post-Covid</h3>

<p>Digital transformation is a challenging task in ordinary times. But the truth is, these times are far from ordinary. Indeed, CIOs and CTOs are facing enormous challenges as they continue to work to recover from the pandemic&#39;s impact on their organization.</p>

<p>70% of leaders say that their team’s productivity levels have not yet returned to pre-pandemic levels. With that in mind, it’s unsurprising that many CIOs and CTOs are mandating their teams to be back in the office full-time.</p>

<p>After all, tech leaders are under significant pressure to articulate quick answers and make decisions immediately. With the urgency of digitization soaring – which is a foundational piece of IT leaders&#39; roles - this wide-reaching call for workers to return to the office is a sign that these leaders feel they need to run a tighter ship to steer their organization toward success. A ship that is smaller than it ever was.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/4dn17Xqd/Article-Graphic-Images-Final-File-updated-02.png" alt="89% of CIOs &amp; CTOs say that they have been impacted by the global shortage of software developers"></p>

<p><strong>89% of CIOs &amp; CTOs say that they have been impacted by the global shortage of software developers</strong>, with nearly half (49%) saying they’ve been impacted “significantly”. Again, it’s important to note the impact that the war in eastern Europe is having here. For example, Russia’s invasion of Ukraine has forced tens of thousands of top software developers and tech leaders from both countries to flee. With Russia and Ukraine becoming hotbeds for tech talent in recent years and IT outsourcing powerhouses, it’s left an indelible mark on the lives of many young professionals trying to rebuild their careers amidst the war. Or, for talent stuck in Russia, they’ve been all but cut off from Western business, creating enormous challenges for organizations that have relied on it. </p>

<p>But staffing challenges in tech are not new. During the early stages of the pandemic, we also watched the mass exodus of talent from major tech hubs to areas that fit their lifestyles better. But for many CIOs and CTOs, the war in Ukraine adds complications they perhaps never imagined they’d have to deal with at any stage of their careers. </p>

<p>So how are tech leaders dealing with this? <strong>60% say they are increasing salaries and benefits, and 56% say they are creating greater work flexibility</strong>. Nearly a third (30%) say they are reducing specific requirements from candidates such as degrees, certifications, and other credentials. While increasing salaries and benefits makes sense, thes last finding is undeniably worrisome. Forecasts suggest that a lack of IT skills worldwide, coupled with the resulting inability to solve business problems, will fuel a<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.openasapp.com/no-code-and-skills-shortage-in-it/"> $390 billion loss each year by 2025.</a> The fact that organizations are choosing to proliferate this skills gap by hiring underequipped talent to fill roles is less than ideal. </p>

<p>It is interesting to note, however, that <strong>28% of CIOs and CTOs say they are now outsourcing their software and development needs</strong>. Just as the pandemic accelerated the freelance economy as organizations realized the value of tapping into an on-demand workforce, outsourcing software development has snowballed. In fact, according to data from <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.statista.com/topics/1900/it-outsourcing/#dossierKeyfigures">Statista</a>, the global IT outsourcing market already surpassed $92 billion this year with the software development outsourcing sector making a significant contribution to it.</p>

<p>Indeed, the ability to deploy a third party dev team when hiring complications or cost challenges prohibit you from building your own team from scratch is proving to be an alluring option. Just because talent shortages are making today’s IT leaders’ jobs much more difficult, doesn’t mean the need for high-performance software solutions has dwindled. In fact, <strong>more than 70% of organizations reporting that they are releasing code faster</strong> than they were pre-pandemic despite having fewer resources.</p>

<p>This illustrates the acceleration of digitization and the need for IT teams to find ways to do more with less. A need that has led to new development approaches.</p>

<h3>Rise of Low-Code Vs. No-Code Increases Complexities</h3>

<p>Low-Code and No-Code development allows individuals with limited or no coding experience to build limited functionality or simple apps and solutions for their organization. The rise of these citizen developers has increased as organizations look for ways to combat talent shortages and resource constraints. In fact, <strong>63% of CIOs &amp; CTOs say they are adopting low-code vs. no-code as much as possible, with the primary reasons being speed and affordability</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/qM2xCbb8/Article-Graphic-Images-Final-File-updated-03.png" alt="63% of CIOs &amp; CTOs say they are adopting low-code vs. no-code as much as possible, with the primary reasons being speed and affordability"></p>

<p>However, this requires us to ask the question: are we facing a situation of <em>“Faster, better, cheaper — pick two”?</em></p>

<p>While certain use cases of Low-Code and No-Code can provide some business functions with more control over their tasks, workflows and speed time to market, these platforms generally lack flexibility and often require real development support to reach their full potential. </p>

<p>Moreover, in an age where security is of the utmost importance, turning over the development reigns of an entire organization to a team with minimal coding experience is certainly cause for concern. In fact, <strong>77% of IT leaders say they worry about employees in their organizations without coding experience building applications with no-code solutions rather than with IT-approved technology</strong>.</p>

<p>Yet, as highlighted above, a vast majority are still prioritizing it. </p>

<p>To help combat these issues, every Low-Code or No-Code development project must include a built-in government and security strategy to restrict the chances of creating unsafe applications or code. Even more effective would be layering in the talents of a third-party development team, who can provide the coding, design, and engineering skills needed to ensure the security and efficacy of the software project. Many of these businesses offer additional support with efficient training and team-building services. </p>

<p>With market complexities requiring IT leaders to get more creative with their resources, the reality is that traditional means of developing software in-house is becoming far less common. And even though more CIOs and CTOs are turning to Low-Code and No-Code solutions, the fact remains that today’s leaders know that the best talent is needed to create the best solutions in a way that doesn&#39;t compromise the safety of their organization.</p>

<p>Still, innovation is likely to continue to evolve alongside the role of today’s developer, as evidenced by the fact that <strong>63% of tech leaders say they are currently utilizing AI/ML for software testing, and an additional 26% say they are looking into it</strong>.</p>

<p>But in an environment where developers are increasingly forced to do more with less, these innovations should be seen as support, not replacements. </p>

<h3>2023 Outlook on Key IT Themes</h3>

<p>While CIOs and CTOs have no shortage of challenges on hand, we wanted to get a sense of the issues that lie ahead in 2023. </p>

<p>When asked what their <strong>biggest fear as it pertains to their role is, the top three responses were: ‘being victimized by a cyberattack or breach of some sort’ (33%); ‘budget constraints’ (30%); and a ‘severe drop in team productivity’ (22%)</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/d3YLMB2Y/Article-Graphic-Images-Final-File-updated-04.png" alt="The top three responses were: ‘being victimized by a cyberattack or breach of some sort’ (33%); ‘budget constraints’ (30%); and a ‘severe drop in team productivity’ (22%)"></p>

<p>With data breaches becoming much more commonplace, it’s not surprising that security is CIOs and CTOs number one concern. The reality is the shift to online has also expanded organizations’ attack surface, with cyber attackers garnering much more success targeting remote or hybrid businesses with weak security protocols. Moreover, as consumers and business customers raise their expectations for privacy, these bad actors know that they can demand much higher ransoms from businesses determined to save their reputations. Now, the average cost of a data breach is <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.ibm.com/security/data-breach">$4.62 million.</a></p>

<p>Meanwhile, when asked what <strong>biggest priorities/initiatives you are looking towards for 2023. The top 3 were ‘data security’, ‘hiring the right talent’ and ‘fiscal prudence’</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/XYG3855c/Article-Graphic-Images-Final-File-updated-05.png" alt="Biggest priorities/initiatives you are looking towards for 2023. The top 3 were ‘data security’, ‘hiring the right talent’ and ‘fiscal prudence’."></p>

<p>With pervasive macroeconomic uncertainty, it’s easy to understand why fiscal prudence would be at the top of tech leaders’ lists. And it only becomes more apparent when you consider that nearly <strong>45% of tech leaders say that their organization is cutting their 2023 budget, with an additional 31% saying that while it hasn’t happened yet, they believe it will</strong>. Mid-sized businesses were the most likely (52%) to say with certainty that their organization would cut their 2023 budget. Meanwhile, small businesses were by far the most likely to say, “Not yet, but I believe they will.” </p>

<p>SMBs don’t have the same financial cushions as their larger counterparts and are, therefore, often forced to make difficult choices regarding their IT budgets. In fact, when these smaller businesses cut spending, many consider it to be a <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://fortune.com/2022/06/11/small-business-inflation-prices-hiring-recession-signal/">signal of a looming recession</a>. Moreover, they’ve already been massively impacted by inflation. Small companies, for example, watched their <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/09/23/small-businesses-say-inflation-is-cutting-into-profits-new-survey.html">profits drop by 4%</a> in the last year despite growing their revenues by 87%. This is causing CIOs and CTOs within small and mid-sized businesses to be <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.cio.com/article/408032/it-pros-say-tech-budgets-to-stay-strong-but-mainly-for-big-companies.html">disproportionately impacted</a> by budget constraints.</p>

<p>Today’s CIOs and CTOs have an enormous task on their hands. Aside from ushering in critical digital transformations that enable their organization to operate more efficiently and effectively, they are also being brought into areas that have become increasingly important boardroom discussions. This includes helping organizations stay on top of ESG and DEI efforts by leveraging digitization to provide transparency into these initiatives and to help track them. And while few question the importance of these initiatives, the truth is that this departure from traditional responsibilities isn’t making CIOs jobs easier.</p>

<p><strong>In fact, 82% of tech leaders say they are worried that their organization&#39;s focus on Environmental, Social, Governance (ESG) and Diversity, Equality, and Inclusion (DEI) initiatives conflict with their ability to focus on other areas of digital transformation that are crucial to their overall productivity and performance</strong>.</p>

<p>The reality is, however, that in today’s landscape, these initiatives are critical to meet stakeholder needs. Moreover, the fact that we’re seeing an emergence of new software designed specifically to help organizations meet their ESG and DEI goals is evidence of the interconnectedness between these initiatives and companies’ digital transformations.</p>

<p>Even so, there’s one crucial point we haven’t mentioned yet. A statistic proves there’s still a pervasive representation gap in technology – especially in tech leadership. Just 24% of the CIOs and CTOs we surveyed for this report identified as female. This is a hard truth to hear, given there has been a lot of focus on boosting female representation in the C-suite. But the fact is, women still occupy <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/benjaminlaker/2022/02/03/women-are-still-underrepresented-in-tech-leadership-heres-how-to-change-that/?sh=19490cdd6832">less than a quarter</a> of executive positions – suggesting organizations need to re-examine their DEI goals.</p>

<p><img src="https://i.postimg.cc/C5hSH6Cz/Article-Graphic-Images-Final-File-updated-06.png" alt="Just 24% of the CIOs and CTOs we surveyed for this report identified as female."></p>

<h3>What Does This All Mean?</h3>

<p>Tech leaders continue to face extraordinary pressure today as the need to digitize operations and create experiences for customers and employees that align with the widespread shifts that have taken place continue to increase.</p>

<p>And while their continued importance in the organization has presented unprecedented levels of opportunity, attaining it is only becoming harder in light of talent shortages, skills gaps and complexities brought on by new forms of development.</p>

<p>For these reasons, it’s unsurprising that we’ve started to see a shift in the way CIOs and CTOs are managing their organizations’ digital transformations. Furthermore, they’re having to get more creative with how they maintain productivity when market headwinds have made it incredibly difficult to do so.</p>

<p>A positive of this, however, has been the emergence of third-party development teams that’ve enabled IT leaders to leverage the skills of a dedicated product team without the pressure, cost restraints, and time constraints of managing them in-house. Not only is this giving them access to a larger pool of talent amidst the severe talent shortage, but we’ve already seen the time-to-market benefits with CIOs and CTOs admitting they’ve been able to release code faster this year.</p>

<p>After all, the tech world moves fast. It’s also growing increasingly competitive, giving organizations that are able to get to market early a significant advantage. </p>

<h3>Study Methodology</h3>

<p>A digital survey of more than 450 US-based individuals in CIO and CTO roles was conducted in October 2022.</p>

<h5>Company Size:</h5>

<ul>
<li><p>1-50 employees: 14%</p></li>
<li><p>50-249 employees: 28%</p></li>
<li><p>250+ employees: 58%</p></li>
</ul>

<h5>Age:</h5>

<ul>
<li><p>18-29: 14%</p></li>
<li><p>30-44: 66%</p></li>
<li><p>45-60: 17%</p></li>
<li><p>60+: 3%</p></li>
</ul>

<h5>Gender:</h5>

<ul>
<li><p>Male: 26%</p></li>
<li><p>Female: 24% </p></li>
</ul>
]]>
      </turbo:content>
    </item>
    <item turbo="true">
      <title>How to quickly get a random set of rows from a Postgres table!</title>
      <description/>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 20:39:18 +0300</pubDate>
      <link>https://jetrockets.com/blog/how-to-quickly-get-a-random-set-of-rows-from-a-postgres-table</link>
      <guid>https://jetrockets.com/blog/how-to-quickly-get-a-random-set-of-rows-from-a-postgres-table</guid>
      <turbo:content>
        <![CDATA[<p>In order to get random rows from a table, you can use the <strong>Postgres</strong> function <strong>TABLESAMPLE BERNOULLI</strong>,</p>

<p>percentages from 0 to 100 are accepted as arguments. </p>

<p>Database query example:</p>
<pre><code class="sql">
SELECT first_name FROM users TABLESAMPLE BERNOULLI(10)

</code></pre>
<p><strong>TABLESAMPLE BERNOULLI</strong> is many times faster than <strong>order by random()</strong>, this can be useful if your table contains many millions of rows</p>
]]>
      </turbo:content>
    </item>
    <item turbo="true">
      <title>Why Startups Should Outsource Software Development</title>
      <description>Running a tech startup is hard. You may have funding, but you need to get a product working, fast. There are two options for creating a minimum viable product: either hire a third party development team, or build your own team from scratch.</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 23:01:31 +0300</pubDate>
      <link>https://jetrockets.com/blog/why-startups-should-outsource-software-development</link>
      <guid>https://jetrockets.com/blog/why-startups-should-outsource-software-development</guid>
      <turbo:content>
        <![CDATA[<p>Building a team adds unnecessary complication, costs, and risk to your business. Many startups that build their own team run into hiring problems, take too long to get to market, or run out of money. Outsourcing software development, on the other hand, helps mitigate these issues.</p>

<p>Reasons why startups should outsource software development include:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Saving resources on hiring</p></li>
<li><p>More time for the rest of the business</p></li>
<li><p>Larger talent pool</p></li>
<li><p>Faster time to market</p></li>
<li><p>Prevents work interruption</p></li>
<li><p>Lower costs</p></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Saving resources on hiring</strong></p>

<p>A startup might begin with just one or two people. But building a product can take a whole team of developers. Hiring all those developers to create an in house team wastes time, costs resources, and can cause more problems down the road.</p>

<p>A <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://qz.com/682517/after-analyzing-200-founders-postmortems-researchers-say-these-are-the-reasons-startups-fail/">Quartz</a> analysis showed that 10% of startups fail due to hiring issues. It is difficult to tell ahead of time whether a new hire will be a good fit. They could turn out to lack key skills or discipline. Additionally, new hires usually do not know each other, and are not used to working together. It can take weeks or months for new developers to get up to speed working on their projects.</p>

<p>Hiring a development team solves all of these problems. Third party development teams consist of vetted developers who already work well together. They have had a long time to get used to their own workflow. Additionally, the team can include experts that would otherwise be hard to get by hiring a small in house team.</p>

<p><strong>More time for the rest of the business</strong></p>

<p>With any business, creating a viable product is only half the battle. Startup founders also have to take care of marketing, managing the business, and obtaining more funding. Outsourcing any part of the business can free up time and energy to focus on the rest of it.</p>

<p>With a third party developer, you save time on hiring, management, and development. An outsourced team will usually provide a project manager to take care of the process and make sure the team is aligning their goals with yours.</p>

<p><strong>Larger pool of talent</strong></p>

<p>If you only have three developers, you only have three developers. But if you hire a third party team, you may get access to the skills of 30 or 40 developers, even if three of them do the majority of the work on your product. This means you can get expert skills without having to hire additional expertise. It also means you can adjust over timing, scaling up the project as needs change.</p>

<p><strong>Faster time to market</strong></p>

<p>The tech world moves fast. Startups that get to market early have an advantage over those that get to market later. Third party software development speeds up development in several ways.</p>

<p>Outsourcing your development means you can skip the hiring process entirely, which could take weeks or months. You can also communicate your schedule to your outsourced team so they can plan time accordingly. Also, a larger team means you might not have to wait as long for expert input.</p>

<p><strong>Prevents work interruption</strong></p>

<p>Running a small in house team can be lean and cost efficient, but it is fragile to sudden changes. One member of the team may suddenly have an accident, quit, or go on parental leave. This can disrupt your workflow, leading to development issues, schedule conflicts, and a later market entry.</p>

<p>Hiring a third party team prevents this from happening. Because these teams are usually larger than the small in house team you would have hired, if one person leaves suddenly, there are other developers who can pick up the slack. Additionally, existing teams may have contingency plans built in for sudden personnel changes.</p>

<p><strong>Lower overall costs</strong></p>

<p>Quartz’s analysis suggested that 46% of startups fail because they run out of money.  Development is a major component of startup costs, so paying less for it can help your startup succeed. Hiring a development team can, in many cases, save significant costs in development fees compared to hiring an in house team.</p>

<p>Some third party development teams can be quite expensive. A reputable team in Silicon Valley may be more expensive than an in house team, but you will get your money’s worth. </p>

<p>An offshore team, on the other hand, can be much cheaper, because of lower costs of living in their country. But there are potential problems with hiring an offshore team. Language barriers can create communication issues that lead to problems in the development process. Working in different time zones can obstruct the development process. And different cultural norms can make it difficult to align goals.</p>

<p>Many businesses now turn to an alternative option, which is hybrid onshore and offshore teams. These teams have members in multiple countries, and they may all speak English. Because half the team is overseas, total costs can be much lower than with an expensive onshore team. And because half the team is onshore, communication issues are reduced to a minimum.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>If you run a startup, and need to build a product fast, consider outsourcing your development. This will likely save costs, prevent hiring problems, get the product to market quicker, and give you more time to focus on the rest of your business.</p>

<p>JetRockets offers onshore experience with offshore costs. Our development team is split between the United States and Georgia, bringing overall costs down. And all of our members speak fluent English and have years of experience working together. This allows us to take your vision and communicate it amongst ourselves, aligning our goals with yours.</p>

<p>We allow you to save time on hiring by providing an entire team of vetted developers up front. This frees you up to focus on the rest of your business. Additionally, our large talent pool provides ample access to special expertise. Our hybrid model allows us to offer lower costs than an in house team, while maintaining quality of product.</p>

<p>On the other hand, you could always build your own team. But be aware that this will mean hiring delays, a smaller pool of talent, and potentially later entry to market. </p>
]]>
      </turbo:content>
    </item>
    <item turbo="true">
      <title>Graphql files upload testing</title>
      <description>Graphql is not very convenient when it comes to uploading files, but it is possible, for example, gem [apollo-upload-server-ruby](https://github.com/jetruby/apollo_upload_server-ruby)  is often used for this purpose.</description>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jan 2022 19:49:51 +0300</pubDate>
      <link>https://jetrockets.com/blog/graphql-files-upload-testing</link>
      <guid>https://jetrockets.com/blog/graphql-files-upload-testing</guid>
      <turbo:content>
        <![CDATA[<p>To check file uploads with <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/jetruby/apollo_upload_server-ruby">apollo-upload-server-ruby</a>, I recommend using <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://altair.sirmuel.design/">Altair GraphQL Client</a> it allows you to easily upload files, unlike more well-known competitors such as <strong>insomnia</strong>.</p>

<p>Unit-testing file uploads with <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/jetruby/apollo_upload_server-ruby">apollo-upload-server-ruby</a> is not very obvious either, by examining the source code of the <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/jetruby/apollo_upload_server-ruby">apollo-upload-server-ruby</a> gem I found that in order for <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/jetruby/apollo_upload_server-ruby">apollo-upload-server-ruby</a> to properly respond to an uploaded file, the following code must be used:</p>
<pre><code class="ruby">
 RSpec.describe Mutations::YourMutation, type: :mutation do

  subject { YourSchema.execute(query, variables: graphql_variables).as_json }





let(:uploaded_file) { Rack::Test::UploadedFile.new(&#39;spec/fixtures/files/test.png&#39;) }

let(:graphql_variables) { { image: image } }



  let(:image) do

    ApolloUploadServer::Wrappers::UploadedFile.new(

      ActionDispatch::Http::UploadedFile.new(

        tempfile: uploaded_file, filename: File.basename(uploaded_file),

        type: &#39;image/png&#39;

      )

    )

  end



  def query

    &lt;&lt;~GRAPHQL

       mutation YourMutation($image: Upload!) {

        images(input: { image: $image }) {

          image {

            id

          }

        }

      }



    GRAPHQL

  end

</code></pre>
<p><strong><em>Happy Testing!</em></strong></p>
]]>
      </turbo:content>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
