<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Daring Fireball</title>
<subtitle>By John Gruber</subtitle>
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/">
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main">
<id>https://daringfireball.net/feeds/main</id>


<updated>2022-11-17T01:20:12Z</updated><rights>Copyright © 2022, John Gruber</rights><entry>
	<title>Apple Releases Rapid Security Response Update for iOS 16.2 Beta Users</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2022/11/16/rapid-security-response-ios-16-2-beta/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugl">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/16/ios-16-beta-rapid-security-response">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39477</id>
	<published>2022-11-17T01:20:12Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-17T01:20:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Speaking of iOS 16.2 betas, Eric Slivka at MacRumors reports:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One of the new features in iOS 16 is Rapid Security Response,
which lets Apple push out important security fixes to users
without requiring a full iOS update. For users running the iOS
16.2 beta, Apple today released one of those updates to deliver
unspecified bug fixes affecting the software.</p>

<p>iOS Security Response 16.2 (a) arrives via the standard Software
Update mechanism in the Settings app, but is a relatively quick
update, requiring just a couple of minutes to download and prepare
the update and then a quick restart and install process.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Apple Releases Rapid Security Response Update for iOS 16.2 Beta Users’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/16/ios-16-beta-rapid-security-response">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iOS 16.2 Includes Settings to Make the iPhone 14 Pro Always-on Display Not So ‘On’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.inverse.com/gear/how-to-turn-off-iphone-14-pro-always-on-display-wallpaper-notifications">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugk">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/16/wong-always-on-display">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39476</id>
	<published>2022-11-17T01:16:24Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-17T01:16:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Raymond Wong, writing at Inverse:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple released the latest iOS 16.2 beta 3 earlier this week, and
as usual, testers quickly picked it apart. Notably, there are two
new toggles within Settings → Display &amp; Brightness → Always On
Display, one for showing your wallpaper, and one for
notifications.</p>

<p>Toggle both to not show, and your iPhone 14 Pro’s lock screen will
turn black instead of dimming your wallpaper; only the date and
time will be visible when the always-on display setting is on.
This makes the iPhone 14 Pro’s always-on display work just like it
does on pretty much every Android phone’s always-on display. And
because the always-on display will be black when both settings are
turned off, it should reduce the amount of battery draw because
each black pixel in the OLED display is technically not turned on.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From my iPhone 14 Pro review back in September:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The second super interesting thing about the iPhones 14 Pro is the
always-on display. <em>It is really weird.</em> Not weird because it’s a
bad idea, but weird because battery life has always been, and
remains, a precious resource to be conserved on smartphones. And,
until now, one of the surest ways to run down your battery has
been to leave your phone in an unattended state while the display
remains on. When you look over to your side at your desk, where
your iPhone rests face up, and the screen is <em>on</em> despite your
knowing that you haven’t touched it in a while, it feels wrong.
Like there’s a bug in iOS that’s preventing the screen from going
to sleep or something. Over and over and over this past week, I’ve
glanced at this iPhone 14 Pro in the always-on state, and I
experienced a micro jolt of panic: <em>Whoa, why is the screen on?
Oh, yeah, always-on...</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Two months later and the always-on display <em>still</em> feels weird to me. My day-to-day battery life has been as good or better than with the iPhone 13 Pro, so I don’t think that’s a reason to turn it off. But for me, feeling weird is a reason.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iOS 16.2 Includes Settings to Make the iPhone 14 Pro Always-on Display Not So ‘On’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/16/wong-always-on-display">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Who Said It: Elon Musk or Mr. Burns?</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://newrepublic.com/article/168572/rich-guys-say-the-darndest-things">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugj">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/15/musk-or-burns">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39475</id>
	<published>2022-11-15T20:03:24Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-15T20:08:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The New Republic:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>The Simpsons</em>’s Mr. Burns and Elon Musk share an eerie number of similarities. Each is the richest person in his respective universe — Springfield for the former, planet Earth for the latter. They boast about their green energy initiatives of electric cars and nuclear power plants, but use their power to advance right-wing politics and fuel their petty personal grievances. Test yourself below to see how well you can separate our cartoonish reality from the world of The Simpsons.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I scored 92 percent — one wrong. But I had to think about each one, and often voted more on grammar than substance. I know how Monty Burns speaks.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Who Said It: Elon Musk or Mr. Burns?’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/15/musk-or-burns">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tesla Doesn’t Advertise</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://electrek.co/2022/06/22/elon-musk-tesla-advertise-counter-media-bias/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugh">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/14/tesla-ads">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39473</id>
	<published>2022-11-15T01:08:02Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-15T01:08:03Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>As a quick follow-up to my previous item <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/14/eli-lilly-twitter">on Elon Musk not having experience with brand advertisers</a>, it’s worth noting that Tesla, quite famously, doesn’t advertise. That’s highly unusual, if not unique, for a mass-market automaker.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tesla Doesn’t Advertise’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/14/tesla-ads">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Eli Lilly Stock Dipped After a Verified Twitter Imposter Claimed Insulin Would Now Be Free</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/eli-lilly-stock-takes-a-dip-after-verified-twitter-imposter-says-insulin-is-free_n_636ebe25e4b02901364207cb">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugg">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/14/eli-lilly-twitter">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39472</id>
	<published>2022-11-14T19:47:38Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-14T20:16:59Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sara Boboltz, reporting for HuffPost:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Eli Lilly’s stock dipped Friday morning after someone paid $8 to verify a Twitter handle resembling that of the pharmaceutical giant and posted: “We are excited to announce insulin is free now.”</p>

<p>Insulin, of course, is not free. In the U.S., one study released this summer found that the high price of the lifesaving drug puts an extreme financial burden on about 14% of the 7 million Americans who need it regularly. […]</p>

<p>The Eli Lilly imposter verified the handle @EliLillyandCo, taking advantage of Twitter’s new rules governing who gets to have a verified account. The company’s real handle is @LillyPad.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are, like, a thousand interesting stories about Twitter under Elon Musk’s ownership, and this is just one. But there are several interesting angles to just this one story:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The verified-but-parodic account, “@EliLillyandCo”, had a more serious-looking username than Eli Lilly’s actual account, “@LillyPad”.</p></li>
<li><p>This prank has done more to bring attention to the shameful state of insulin pricing in the U.S. than anything in decades.</p></li>
<li><p>The question I think most worth asking about Musk’s thus-far very tumultuous leadership of Twitter is this: What exactly has he been surprised by? Obviously quite a few of his changes, thus far, have angered/upset/offended people. But I don’t think most of that has surprised him. I think one thing that <em>has</em> surprised him is the lowercase-c conservative nature of advertisers. Elon Musk is, quite obviously, a polymath. There aren’t many similarities between PayPal, Tesla, and Space X, other than the fundamental truth that everything in the world (including payments, cars, and rockets) is getting computerized. Either turned into computers or turned into software running on computers somewhere. But none of Musk’s previous endeavors have involved serving advertisers. Reputable high-quality advertisers not only want to avoid controversy and polarization and especially <em>uncertainty</em>, they will flee from it. It doesn’t matter if Twitter today is more popular/used than it was three weeks ago — it is less desirable as a place to spend advertising budgets because it is more uncertain. Twitter (as it stands today and for the foreseeable future) needs advertisers; advertisers do not need Twitter. I don’t think Musk understood that until now.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>(I’m curious what else you think has surprised Musk about Twitter thus far. Not what you think Musk is wrong about, per se, but what he is already surprised about.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Eli Lilly Stock Dipped After a Verified Twitter Imposter Claimed Insulin Would Now Be Free’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/14/eli-lilly-twitter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Kolide</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://l.kolide.co/3yL3FcB">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugi">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/14/kolide">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39474</id>
	<published>2022-11-14T13:08:35Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-15T01:11:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks once again to Kolide for sponsoring last week at DF. Kolide is an endpoint security solution for Mac, Windows, and Linux devices. Kolide gives IT admins a single dashboard, through which you can prove that your fleet has the security measures in place that auditors care about. With Kolide, you can instantly see whether:</p>

<ul>
<li>Firewalls and screen lock are enabled.</li>
<li>Operating systems are up to date.</li>
<li>Password managers are installed.</li>
</ul>

<p>Kolide also provides visibility into nuanced issues that MDMs can’t address, like whether developers have unencrypted SSH keys or plaintext 2FA backup codes.</p>

<p><a href="https://l.kolide.co/3yL3FcB">Try Kolide for 14 days free of charge, with no credit card required</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Kolide’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/14/kolide">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Yours Truly on The MacRumors Show</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2022/11/09/the-macrumors-show-john-gruber-talks-macos-ventura/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugf">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/12/yours-truly-macrumors-show">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39471</id>
	<published>2022-11-12T23:00:10Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-13T19:55:14Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>MacRumors Show cohosts Dan Barbera and Hartley Charlton were kind enough to invite me on their show this week:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In this episode, we take a closer look at new features in macOS
Ventura like Stage Manager, Continuity Camera, and the redesigned
System Settings app. We discuss the current state of the Mac
lineup and our favorite models, whether the launch of new Mac
models is delayed, and upgrades from next-generation MacBook Pro
models. With Apple now passing the initial timeframe it set out to
transition the entire Mac lineup to Apple silicon, we also take a
look at what to expect from the upcoming Mac Pro.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A lot to talk about in just over an hour. One thing that occurred to me while were recording is that while there’s much to debate (and speculate about) regarding the company’s wide-ranging product lineups — hardware, software, wearables, services, original TV and movie content — you can’t complain that this is a boring time to be closely following Apple.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Yours Truly on The MacRumors Show’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/12/yours-truly-macrumors-show">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Film Composer Carter Burwell, Known as ‘the Third Coen Brother’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2022/11/14/the-polymath-film-composer-known-as-the-third-coen-brother">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uge">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/12/carter-burwell">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39470</id>
	<published>2022-11-12T22:54:24Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-12T22:59:40Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Fascinating profile by David Owen of composer Carter Burwell, a name I feel I should have known better beforehand. (I am an enormous fan of his collaborations with the Coen Brothers.)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a lecture at the Scottish Academy of Music and Drama, in Glasgow, in 2001, Burwell said that he usually urges directors to use as little music as possible, because movies, like life, are most interesting “when you don’t know what’s going on, and you’re uncomfortable about it.” Ron Sadoff, the director and founder of the screen-scoring program at N.Y.U., told me, “Carter doesn’t do what’s called Mickey Mousing, where you try to touch every little element of the film with music. His approach is much more conceptual.” In the score for <em>Fargo</em>, the Coens’ sixth film, Burwell used a Hardanger fiddle, a Norwegian instrument that has two sets of strings, one of which isn’t bowed but resonates with the other. (That choice was inspired by the Scandinavian names of some of the characters.) His goal was to help make a darkly improbable comedy seem as straightforward as a news bulletin, an effect established with the title sequence, in which a car is being towed across a white-out winter landscape, accompanied by a fiddle-and-percussion passage that swells into something like a funeral march. Ethan Coen told me, “People don’t realize how much of what they’re getting from a movie is from the score, delivered by the composer. It’s powerful, but, for the life of you, you can’t say what it means.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“To help make a darkly improbable comedy seem as straightforward as a news bulletin” — what a wonderful description of <em>Fargo</em>, but what a seemingly impossible task to pull off.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Film Composer Carter Burwell, Known as ‘the Third Coen Brother’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/12/carter-burwell">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Inside the Twitter Meltdown</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.platformer.news/p/inside-the-twitter-meltdown">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugd">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/11/twitter-meltdown">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39469</id>
	<published>2022-11-11T16:45:18Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-11T16:48:08Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Casey Newton and Zoë Schiffer, reporting for Platformer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Musk’s whim-based approach to product development, his rapidly depleting executive ranks, and the very real likelihood of hundreds or even thousands of additional departures at the company in coming weeks threaten to leave Twitter a shadow of its former self. And much of the reason for that is Musk himself: the way he treated his employees and the product they built; the sage advice he ignored; the business fundamentals that he misunderstood.</p>

<p>Musk’s takeover of the company had been so brutish and poorly planned that, we’re told, there was not even a proper handover of the company’s social accounts. As a result, having spent $44 billion to acquire Twitter, for his first week-plus of owning the company, Musk and his team were unable even to tweet from the @twitter account.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Jiminy.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Inside the Twitter Meltdown’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/11/twitter-meltdown">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://l.kolide.co/3yL3FcB">
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ugc">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2022/11/kolide_endpoint_security_for_t_3">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/feeds/sponsors//11.39468</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2022-11-08T18:50:38-05:00</published>
	<updated>2022-11-08T18:50:39-05:00</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>In 2021, our company went through the SOC 2 Type 1 audit, and we <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3OR7Ucr">found out just how challenging it can be</a> to prove compliance to a third-party auditor. We also learned firsthand something our customers had been telling us for a while: that we couldn’t have gotten our SOC certification without using our own product.</p>

<p>That product is Kolide, an endpoint security solution for Mac, Windows, and Linux devices. Kolide gives IT admins a single dashboard, through which you can prove that your fleet has the security measures that auditors care about.</p>

<p>With Kolide, you can instantly see whether:</p>

<ul>
<li>Firewalls and screen lock are enabled</li>
<li>Operating systems are up-to-date</li>
<li>Password managers are installed</li>
</ul>

<p>Kolide also provides visibility into nuanced issues that MDMs can’t address, like whether developers have unencrypted SSH keys or plaintext 2FA backup codes.</p>

<p>Moreover, Kolide balances this visibility with respect for user privacy and autonomy. Users can visit the Privacy Center to see what device data is being collected and why. And when Kolide detects a vulnerability on a user’s device, it reaches out via Slack to notify them of the problem and provides step-by-step instructions on how to solve it. </p>

<p>At Kolide, <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3yL3FcB">we’ve helped hundreds of customers achieve compliance</a> — for SOC 2, ISO27001, or their own internal security goals. And we’ve done so in ways that go beyond “checking the boxes” and actually increase transparency and collaboration between IT and end users.</p>

<p>If you want to know how you can get compliant without compromising your values, then we want to talk to you.</p>

<p><a href="https://l.kolide.co/3yL3FcB">Try Kolide for 14 days free; no credit card required</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Kolide — Endpoint Security for Teams That Slack’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2022/11/kolide_endpoint_security_for_t_3">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Kolide — Endpoint Security for Teams That Slack</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Atoms</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://atoms.com/df">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ugb">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/07/atoms">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39467</id>
	<published>2022-11-08T00:34:29Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-08T00:34:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Atoms for sponsoring last week at DF. I’m wearing Atoms right now, as I type this. They’re some of my favorite shoes I’ve ever owned. Atoms designed its Model 000 to be the shoe you’d want to wear every day. Thanks to their comfort and simplicity, they can become your go-to sneaker, and work with just about any outfit.</p>

<p>This holiday, Atoms is bringing back some of its popular limited edition colors. Daring Fireball readers get 15% off all Model 000 colors. Take advantage of the opportunity to stock up for the holidays. Just use code DARING at checkout.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Atoms’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/07/atoms">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Twitter, Cut in Half’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.platformer.news/p/twitter-cut-in-half">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uga">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/07/twitter-cut-in-half">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39466</id>
	<published>2022-11-07T17:32:14Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-07T17:33:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Casey Newton and Zoë Schiffer, writing at Platformer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Eight days into Musk’s ownership of Twitter, many pundits have begun to predict that this is the beginning of the end. No one can quite imagine a world without Twitter, but no one can quite imagine this version of Twitter surviving, either.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Twitter, Cut in Half’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/07/twitter-cut-in-half">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Chinese COVID-19 Restrictions Now Affecting Shipments of iPhones 14 Pro and Pro Max</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2022/11/update-on-supply-of-iphone-14-pro-and-iphone-14-pro-max/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug9">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/07/iphone-14-covid">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39465</id>
	<published>2022-11-07T16:32:05Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-07T16:46:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>COVID-19 restrictions have temporarily impacted the primary iPhone 14 Pro and iPhone 14 Pro Max assembly facility located in Zhengzhou, China. The facility is currently operating at significantly reduced capacity. As we have done throughout the COVID-19 pandemic, we are prioritizing the health and safety of the workers in our supply chain.</p>

<p>We continue to see strong demand for iPhone 14 Pro and iPhone 14 Pro Max models. However, we now expect lower iPhone 14 Pro and iPhone 14 Pro Max shipments than we previously anticipated and customers will experience longer wait times to receive their new products.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The writing <a href="https://www.taiwannews.com.tw/en/news/4705481">has been on the wall with this outbreak</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Chinese COVID-19 Restrictions Now Affecting Shipments of iPhones 14 Pro and Pro Max’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/07/iphone-14-covid">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tony Fadell Joins Arm Board of Directors</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.arm.com/company/news/2022/11/arm-announces-the-appointment-of-tony-fadell-to-the-board-of-directors">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug8">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/05/fadell-arm">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39464</id>
	<published>2022-11-05T18:22:19Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-05T18:23:20Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I <em>think</em> this is interesting, but I’m not sure what to make of it. Worth noting, though, no matter what.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tony Fadell Joins Arm Board of Directors’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/05/fadell-arm">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Substitute Web Fonts With StopTheMadness</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://underpassapp.com/news/2022-11-3.html">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug7">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/03/substitute-web-fonts-with-stopthemadness">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39463</id>
	<published>2022-11-03T20:41:52Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-03T20:43:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jeff Johnson:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I got a feature request from John Gruber, famous for <a href="https://daringfireball.net/">Daring
Fireball</a>, also famous for <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2020/08/17/apple-developer-program-license-agreement">despising the Arial
typeface</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Honestly, the most shocking thing about the Apple Developer
Program License Agreement is that <a href="https://developer.apple.com/services-account/agreement/XV2A27GUJ6/content/pdf">the PDF</a> is entirely
typeset in Arial. Clearly it should be San Francisco, but
Helvetica would be acceptable. Arial should be a firing offense.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What you may not know about Gruber, though, is that as much as he
despises Arial, he dislikes Courier New even more! If Arial
demands firing, then I suppose that Courier New demands… the
firing squad? Anyway, Gruber requested that my Safari extension
<a href="https://underpassapp.com/StopTheMadness/">StopTheMadness</a> add font substitution rules in order to
replace all instances of Arial on the web with Helvetica and all
instances of Courier New with Courier.</p>

<p>I told Gruber that he didn’t need to wait for me to add the feature,
  because substituting fonts was already possible in StopTheMadness on
  both desktop and mobile by using a <a href="https://underpassapp.com/StopTheMadness/support-safari.html#custom-elements">custom <code>&lt;style&gt;</code> element</a>
  containing some <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/@font-face"><code>@font-face</code> rules</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My favorite response to a feature request is always “Actually, you can do that now...”.</p>

<p>It’s such a little thing, and I know most people can’t detect the differences between Helvetica and Arial and don’t care, but it makes me so happy every day never to see the cursed fonts Arial and Courier New.</p>

<p>Also, if you prefer, you can substitute the system font — San Francisco — for Arial with the following CSS on the appropriate lines in Johnson’s rules:</p>

<pre><code>src: local("system-ui");
</code></pre>

<p>If you’re not using <a href="https://underpassapp.com/StopTheMadness/">StopTheMadness</a>, you’re missing out.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Substitute Web Fonts With StopTheMadness’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/03/substitute-web-fonts-with-stopthemadness">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Speed Running the Content Moderation Learning Curve</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.techdirt.com/2022/11/02/hey-elon-let-me-help-you-speed-run-the-content-moderation-learning-curve/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug6">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/03/masnick-content-moderation-speed-run">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39462</id>
	<published>2022-11-03T16:54:06Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-03T17:02:06Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Mike Masnick, Techdirt:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And because I do hope that Musk succeeds and Twitter remains
viable, I wanted to see if we might help him (and anyone else)
speed run the basics of the content moderation learning curve that
most newbies run into. The order of the levels and the seriousness
of each can change over time, and how it all fits together may be
somewhat different, but, in the end, basically every major social
media platform ends up in this same place eventually (the place
Twitter was already at when Musk insisted he needed to tear things
down and start again).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Keep that popcorn <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/right-wingers-turning-elon-musk-moderation-1234623259/">popping</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Speed Running the Content Moderation Learning Curve’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/03/masnick-content-moderation-speed-run">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>InAppBrowser.com: See What JavaScript Commands Get Injected Through an in-App Browser</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://krausefx.com/blog/announcing-inappbrowsercom-see-what-javascript-commands-get-executed-in-an-in-app-browser">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug5">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/03/in-app-browsers">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39461</id>
	<published>2022-11-03T16:22:38Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-03T16:22:38Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Felix Krause, back in September:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://krausefx.com/blog/ios-privacy-instagram-and-facebook-can-track-anything-you-do-on-any-website-in-their-in-app-browser">Last week I published a report</a> on the risks of mobile apps
using in-app browsers. Some apps, like Instagram and Facebook,
inject JavaScript code into third party websites that cause
potential security and privacy risks to the user.</p>

<p>I was so happy to see the article featured by major media outlets
across the globe, like <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2022/aug/11/meta-injecting-code-into-websites-visited-by-its-users-to-track-them-research-says">TheGuardian</a> and <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/08/12/meta_ios_privacy/">The
Register</a>, generated a <a href="https://twitter.com/KrauseFx/status/1557412468368052225">over a million impressions on
Twitter</a>, and was ranked <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=32415470">#1 on HackerNews</a> for more
than 12 hours. After reading through the replies and DMs, I saw a
common question across the community:</p>

<p><em>“How can I verify what apps do in their webviews?”</em></p>

<p>Introducing <a href="https://inappbrowser.com/">InAppBrowser.com</a>, a simple tool to list the
JavaScript commands executed by the iOS app rendering the page.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s pretty creepy that TikTok both injects a JavaScript keylogger <em>and</em> does not have a button to open the current page in Safari.</p>

<p>I understand why in-app browsers are a thing on iOS (and iPadOS) but not on MacOS, but when you really think about it, it’s quite strange, and a vestige of the past when multitasking on iOS was so much more limited. Whenever possible, open links in Safari (or whatever your default browser is).</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘InAppBrowser.com: See What JavaScript Commands Get Injected Through an in-App Browser’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/03/in-app-browsers">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Jony Ive on Life After Apple</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/jony-ive-apple-design-interview-profile-lovefrom-11666733971">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug4">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/02/ive-after-apple">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39460</id>
	<published>2022-11-02T23:53:32Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-02T23:53:32Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Elisa Lipsky-Karasz, writing for the WSJ:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One of the first employees hired by Ive was a full-time writer.
(There are now more than 30 employees, many of whom worked with
him at Apple.) Ive says LoveFrom is the only creative practice he
knows of to have an on-staff scribe whose job is, in part, to help
conjure into words the ideas that his team of graphic designers,
architects, sound engineers and industrial designers come up with
for its collaborations with Airbnb, Ferrari and others.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Interesting profile, but only insofar as I think it would be nearly impossible to write a profile of Ive that wasn’t interesting to some degree.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Jony Ive on Life After Apple’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/02/ive-after-apple">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Austin Mann’s iPhone 14 Pro Camera Review</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.austinmann.com/trek/iphone-14-pro-camera-review-scotland">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug3">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/02/mann-14-pro">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39459</id>
	<published>2022-11-02T23:50:59Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-02T23:51:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I should have linked to this a month ago, but better late than never.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Austin Mann’s iPhone 14 Pro Camera Review’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/02/mann-14-pro">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>iPhone 14 Pro Camera Review: A Small Step, a Huge Leap — Lux</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://lux.camera/iphone-14-pro-camera-review-a-small-step-a-huge-leap/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug2">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/02/lux-iphone-14-pro-camera-review">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39458</id>
	<published>2022-11-02T23:04:18Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-02T23:04:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Sebastiaan de With, writing for the Lux blog (the makers of Halide):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I took the iPhone 14 Pro on a trip around San Francisco and
Northern California, to the remote Himalayas and mountains of the
Kingdom of Bhutan, and Tokyo — to test every aspect of its
image-making, and I have to say that I was pretty blown away by
the results of the main camera.</p>

<p>While arguably, a quad-bayer sensor should not give true
48-megapixel sensor resolution as one might get from, say, a
comparable ‘proper’ digital camera, the results out of the iPhone
14 Pro gave me chills. I have simply never gotten image quality
like this out of a phone. There’s more here than just resolution;
the way the new 48 megapixel sensor renders the image is unique
and simply tremendously different than what I’ve seen before.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Inspiring and informative.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘iPhone 14 Pro Camera Review: A Small Step, a Huge Leap — Lux’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/02/lux-iphone-14-pro-camera-review">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Factory Run by Foxconn Placed Under Total COVID Lockdown in China</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.taiwannews.com.tw/en/news/4705481">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug1">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/02/foxconn-factory-lockdown">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39457</id>
	<published>2022-11-02T22:22:00Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-02T22:23:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Duncan DeAeth, reporting for The Taiwan News:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Chinese authorities in Zhengzhou on Wednesday (Nov. 2) placed the
world’s largest iPhone assembly site, run by Taiwan’s Foxconn, on
lockdown in response to a local COVID outbreak.</p>

<p>The move to quarantine the Zhengzhou Airport Economy Zone follows
reports that employees have been fleeing to escape the restrictive
environment over the past few days. Placing the factory under a
“static management” policy, a euphemism for total lockdown, also
comes a day after reports that Foxconn plans to decrease
production at the facility over the coming months.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/china/chinese-zone-that-hosts-foxconns-zhengzhou-plant-imposes-fresh-lockdown-2022-11-02/">Reuters</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>China ordered an industrial park that houses an iPhone factory
belonging to Foxconn to enter a seven-day lockdown on Wednesday,
in a move set to intensify pressure on the Apple supplier as it
scrambles to quell worker discontent at the base. The Zhengzhou
Airport Economy Zone in central China said it would impose “silent
management” measures with immediate effect, including barring all
residents from going out and only allowing approved vehicles on
roads within that area.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t have much to say about this other than that it feels like a situation worth keeping an eye on.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Factory Run by Foxconn Placed Under Total COVID Lockdown in China’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/02/foxconn-factory-lockdown">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Rolex’s First Titanium Watch</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://wornandwound.com/new-rolex-deepsea-challenge-touts-titanium-case-ultra-deep-bona-fides/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ug0">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/01/rolex-titanium">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39456</id>
	<published>2022-11-01T18:44:09Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-01T18:44:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Blake Buettner, writing for Worn &amp; Wound:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a surprising move this morning Rolex, along with
filmmaker/adventurer extraordinaire James Cameron, revealed a new
Deepsea Challenge in the reference 126067. Rolex enthusiasts will
immediately notice something new about that number, and that’s the
7 at the very end. That last digit denotes the case material, and
until now a 7 has never been used. That’s because this watch
represents the first commercially available Rolex crafted from
titanium. That may be a first, but this really a reference that
celebrates the past in a way rarely seen from the brand. That
said, the most exciting details of this watch are what it might
say about future releases.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The two most interesting new watches of the year, to me, are both exclusively made with titanium cases.</p>

<p><strong>See Also:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3GIx852sLRM">This video with James Cameron</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Rolex’s First Titanium Watch’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/01/rolex-titanium">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>UI Browser’s Future</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.pfiddlesoft.com/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufz">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/01/ui-browser-future">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39455</id>
	<published>2022-11-01T17:57:46Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-01T17:57:46Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Bill Cheeseman:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>UI Browser 3 reached its end of life and was retired on October
17, 2022. It can no longer be purchased. The last release of UI
Browser, version 3.0.2, will not be updated, and support is no
longer available. Owners of an existing license for UI Browser can
continue to download the <a href="https://latenightsw.com/freeware/ui-browser/">UI Browser 3.0.2</a> disk image from
Late Night Software’s Freeware website. It will remain available
for a limited time. [...]</p>

<p>UI Browser 4 is now available for development as a public <a href="https://github.com/alldritt/UIBrowser4">GitHub
open source project</a>, and it is open for discussion on the
<a href="https://forum.latenightsw.com/c/uibrowser/">UI Browser Discussion page</a> of the Late Night Software
Forum. It is written in Swift. As initially posted, it is only
minimally functional and requires much more work to become useful.
(While many of the code files refer to UI Browser 3, they are in
fact all part of UI Browser 4. Although they display a copyright
notice, Bill Cheeseman and PFiddlesoft hereby dedicate them to the
public domain.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You may recall <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/04/27/cheeseman-ui-browser">my post from back in April</a>, when Cheeseman first announced his and UI Browser’s retirement, singing UI Browser’s praises. UI Browser is truly an astonishing utility, and I’m hopeful it now has a future.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘UI Browser’s Future’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/01/ui-browser-future">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Uber Tests Push Notification Ads</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/10/31/uber-tests-push-notifications-a-feature-literally-no-one-wants/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufy">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/01/uber-push-notification-ads">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39454</id>
	<published>2022-11-01T17:53:09Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-01T18:59:09Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Rebecca Bellan, reporting for TechCrunch:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Uber recently launched its <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/10/19/dont-worry-uber-will-find-a-way-to-advertise-to-you/">new advertising division</a> and
in-app ads. Apparently, those ads aren’t staying within the app.</p>

<p>Instead, ads from other companies are being sent out as push
notifications, much to the chagrin of some Uber users. Over the
weekend, people turned to Twitter to complain about the
notifications, sharing <a href="https://twitter.com/matsonj/status/1586857522950209536">screenshots of ads</a>, including one
particularly popular one from <a href="https://twitter.com/MGTalksRetail/status/1586424119154728961">Peloton</a> that Uber had sent
out. One of the primary complaints: notifications are being sent
out when users aren’t engaging with the app.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2022/09/20/ep-357">A few weeks ago on my podcast</a>, Nilay Patel and I speculated about Uber putting ads in the Dynamic Island after you’ve hailed a ride. This isn’t that, but it exemplifies why we singled out Uber as a potential abuser.</p>

<p>I wish I had more confidence that Apple will enforce the clear <a href="https://developer.apple.com/app-store/review/guidelines/">App Store guidelines that forbid this</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>4.5.4 — Push Notifications must not be required for the app to
    function, and should not be used to send sensitive personal or
    confidential information. Push Notifications should not be
    used for promotions or direct marketing purposes unless
    customers have explicitly opted in to receive them via consent
    language displayed in your app’s UI, and you provide a method
    in your app for a user to opt out from receiving such
    messages. Abuse of these services may result in revocation of
    your privileges.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Uber Tests Push Notification Ads’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/11/01/uber-push-notification-ads">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘A Fit of Pique’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2022/10/31/ep-361">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufx">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/the-talk-show-361">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39453</id>
	<published>2022-11-01T01:47:29Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-01T01:47:29Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Federico Viticci returns to the show to talk about iPads, Stage Manager, and Apple’s ill-considered foray into expanding ads in the App Store.</p>

<p>Brought to you by these excellent sponsors:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="squarespace.com/talkshow">Squarespace</a>: Make your next move. Use code <strong>talkshow</strong> for 10% off your first order.</li>
<li><a href="https://memberful.com/talkshow">Memberful</a>: Monetize your passion with membership. Start your free trial today.</li>
<li><a href="http://hover.com/talkshow">Hover</a>: Find a domain name for your passion. Get 10% off your first purchase.</li>
<li><a href="http://kolide.com/thetalkshow">Kolide</a>: Cross-platform endpoint security solution for teams that value privacy and transparency. <a href="https://honest.security">Check out our manifesto</a>.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘A Fit of Pique’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/the-talk-show-361">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Verge Reviews the $140 Amazon Fire TV Cube</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/23429259/amazon-fire-tv-cube-2022-review">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufw">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/verge-amazon-fire-tv-cube">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39452</id>
	<published>2022-10-31T23:13:14Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-31T23:13:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Chris Welch writing for The Verge, “A Streaming Box With No Equal”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Advertising across Fire TV OS remains way more in your face than
I’d like. When the Cube is left idle and goes into screensaver
mode, you’ll see promoted movies and TV shows, sure, but there are
also ads for Lexus cars. At the top of the homescreen over the
last few days, there’s been a banner ad for <em>Call of Duty: Modern
Warfare II</em>, which doesn’t even seem relevant to the platform
outside of Twitch streams. And ads are now taking up room in the
live channel guide, which is <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/fireTV/comments/yeqqn5/ads_now_inserted_in_ota_recast_and_presumably_all/">frustrating some Fire TV
owners</a>. When you’re perusing through the carousels of
content on the homescreen, Amazon’s own selections still get the
lion’s share of promotion. The latter shouldn’t come as a surprise
on the company’s own hardware, but the dial really needs to be
turned down on the rest. It cheapens the whole user experience and
feels unwarranted on a $140 product. Ads are inevitable on $40
streaming sticks; that’s how they’re so affordable in the first
place. But Amazon should be able to detect when customers have
paid a premium for the Fire TV Cube and pull it back.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No equal indeed. The Apple TV streaming boxes don’t have any ads at all. They’re way behind. (Maybe I shouldn’t give Apple <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/app_store_ads_gone_wild">any ideas</a> about putting annoying ads in tvOS.)</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Verge Reviews the $140 Amazon Fire TV Cube’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/verge-amazon-fire-tv-cube">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/app_store_ads_gone_wild">
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ufu">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022://1.39450</id>
	<published>2022-10-31T23:00:18Z</published>
	<updated>2022-11-01T01:48:48Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">Apple’s business model is no longer the straightforward selling of great products, and these new ads in the App Store are not designed to make anything better other than Apple’s Services bottom line.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://developer.apple.com/news/?id=zj4stkq7&amp;1666721941">Apple, last Tuesday</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple Search Ads makes it easy to promote your app on the App
Store. And now with new Today tab and product page ad placements,
you can drive discovery of your app in more moments across the App
Store — when customers first arrive, search for something
specific, and browse apps to download.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Upon launching, feedback from the developers of various popular apps and Apple observers shared a common theme. <a href="https://twitter.com/simonbs/status/1585026888455659525">Simon B. Støvring</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With Apple’s recent changes to ads on the App Store, your product
pages may now show ads for gambling apps. One of my product pages
just did that 😞</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/marcoarment/status/1585054271627837441">Marco Arment</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Now my app’s product page shows gambling ads, which I’m really not
OK with.</p>

<p>Apple shouldn’t be OK with it, either.</p>

<p>The App Store has corrupted such a great company so deeply. They
make so much from gambling and manipulative IAPs that they don’t
even see the problem anymore.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/cabel/status/1585031539079139329">Cabel Sasser</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is really sad to me that Apple needs to start taking Casino
Game Ad Money in order to make their line go up for the
shareholders. When Steve introduced iAds and the whole pitch was,
“These ads aren’t garbage, you’ll like these ads.” This department
shouldn’t exist at all, imho.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/sdw/status/1585043114334785537">Sebastiaan de With</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I know it’s not as easily quantifiable, but Apple is utterly
annihilating brand value, trust and goodwill with these ads. How
is the revenue possibly worth it?</p>

<p>As a developer, this sucks. As a user, it sucks. As someone who
cares about Apple products it’s just profoundly sad.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/viticci/status/1585063085471047681">Federico Viticci</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Can you imagine having $48.2 billion cash on hand and YET still
thinking “ah yes, those House of Fun Casino ads will grow our
bottom line, let’s do it”.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/fromedome/status/1585042325361033217">Dan Frommer, quoting Steve Jobs</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>@cabel And then, a year later, while introducing
iCloud/MobileMe Mail:</p>

<p>“No ads. We build products that we want for ourselves, too, and we
just don’t want ads.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The gambling/casino-related ads were so dominating the auctions for these new ad slots that they were even being presented at the bottom of the product pages <a href="https://twitter.com/hot_doggin_jon/status/1585127116672114688">for apps intended to help people with gambling addiction</a>. Other scumminess included ads for <a href="https://twitter.com/BasicAppleGuy/status/1585090997431988225">“psychic” apps on the product page for Disney+</a> and ads for hookup dating apps on the pages for marriage counseling apps. You really couldn’t make this stuff up.</p>

<p>Within one day of the new ad slots going live, <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2022/10/26/app-store-gambling-ads-complaints/">Apple issued a terse statement</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We have paused ads related to gambling and a few other categories
on App Store product pages.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s now nearly a week later, and the gambling/hookup/psychic-type ads still don’t seem to be showing up (well, <a href="https://twitter.com/nickheer/status/1587222218848829440">mostly</a>), but it’s also just as hard to see why Apple is selling these spots in the first place. Well, duh, <em>for the money</em>, yes — that’s obviously the only plausible answer. But how much money can these ads be generating? How much can Apple hope they eventually generate? It can’t possibly be enough money to justify the damage it’s doing to Apple’s brand. These App Store ads are like the “Intel Inside” stickers on PC laptops — they’re worth money, but the money’s not worth it. <a href="https://www.cultofmac.com/227936/watch-steve-jobs-laugh-at-the-idea-of-intel-inside-stickers-on-the-side-of-every-mac-video/">Who’s laughing about those stickers now</a>?</p>

<p>“<em>No ads in the App Store, period</em>” would have been a powerful, appealing message. One that Apple could have used to justify its control over all software on the platform and its much-debated mandatory cut of all app and game transactions. “<em>We sell ads in the App Store, but they’re OK because they don’t track you</em>” seems to be the message Apple is going for, but that’s neither powerful nor appealing. It boils down to “Hey, it could be worse.”</p>

<p>Last month The Information published <a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/for-apples-app-boss-a-new-battle-nears?rc=jfy0lk">a piece by Wayne Ma on Phil Schiller’s leadership of the App Store</a>. It contained this bit regarding the Today tab, which is effectively the front page of the store (italic emphasis added):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In 2015, App Store employees pitched a redesign of the store to
Cue that required hiring and paying for a large editorial staff to
write stories about apps and their developers. The redesign was
meant to encourage users to visit the App Store every day to
discover new apps, rather than having the store act like a vending
machine that existed merely to peddle software. Cue wasn’t
receptive to the pitch as he didn’t believe it was worth the
money, given that the App Store was already performing well,
according to a person with direct knowledge of the discussions.</p>

<p>Schiller, however, approved the redesign in his first days on the
job, this person said. He believed the App Store had lost a lot of
the spontaneity and fun associated with discovering new apps. He
thought an editorial team could help bring those qualities back,
according to a second person with direct knowledge of the project.</p>

<p>In 2017, Apple launched the redesign, which included new tabs on
the App Store called Today, Games and Apps, highlighting various
apps and developers. <em>While the general perception among users
Apple surveyed after the redesign was that developers had to pay
to be featured on the App Store, that wasn’t the case</em>, according
to people familiar with the matter. Schiller gave the editorial
team the power to select which games and apps to promote or
feature on these tabs, without pressuring them to base those
decisions on business and partnership goals, those people said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I was reminded of that last week, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/apple/comments/yaoo24/apple_announces_more_ads_coming_to_app_store/">when I saw this exchange on Reddit in a thread about these new App Store ad units</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>sisco98: “Today tab, which until now has only displayed content
handpicked from the App Store’s editorial staff, without any paid
placement.” Up to now, I was pretty sure these picks were paid by
developers.</p>

<p>spack12: Yeah I always figured those were ads too.</p>

<p>rotates-potatoes: Probably why they created the ad unit. If
everyone’s going to assume it’s paid ads, might as well collect
revenue from it. Many years ago I had an app featured in the app
store. Was awesome, like 10× sales overnight. Was a complete
surprise to me when it happened.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple is actually scrupulous about labeling paid placements as “ads”, and using different background colors for them. One can certainly argue that ads should be even <em>more</em> clearly demarcated, but if you look for it, it’s always clear. But people don’t look. If the message were clear — that there are no ads or paid placements in the App Store, period — people might learn. But if the message is that there are ads, but not many, but now there are more than there used to be, and but if you look closely you’ll see that the ads have a blue background and a small “ad” label — almost everyone is going to assume that anything that <em>might</em> be an ad <em>is</em> an ad and the whole App Store is pay-for-play all the way down.</p>

<hr />

<p>Back in 2014, the front page of the Privacy section on Apple’s website was an open letter, signed simply by “Tim”. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20141013062201/http://www.apple.com/privacy/">Here’s an archived version from The Internet Archive</a>; <a href="https://archive.ph/lQASO#selection-649.0-660.0">here’s one from Archive.today</a>. Cook’s letter read in part:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A few years ago, users of Internet services began to realize that
when an online service is free, you’re not the customer. You’re
the product. But at Apple, we believe a great customer experience
shouldn’t come at the expense of your privacy.</p>

<p>Our business model is very straightforward: We sell great
products. We don’t build a profile based on your email content or
web browsing habits to sell to advertisers. We don’t “monetize”
the information you store on your iPhone or in iCloud. And we
don’t read your email or your messages to get information to
market to you. Our software and services are designed to make our
devices better. Plain and simple.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apple’s commitment to privacy is no less today than it was then. One can well argue that it’s even stronger. But there are aspects of Apple’s position on advertising eight years ago, unrelated to privacy, that don’t square with Apple’s position today. Cook has repeated variations of that “you’re not the customer, you’re the product” mantra umpteen times since 2014. But how are these ads in the App Store not making users the product, and advertisers the customers?</p>

<p>It remains true that Apple is not monetizing the information we store on our devices or in iCloud, but they’re clearly monetizing our attention and their exclusive hold on that attention for all apps and games for iOS. Apple’s business model is no longer the straightforward selling of great products, and these new ads in the App Store are not designed to make anything better other than Apple’s Services bottom line.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ App Store Ads Gone Wild</title></entry><entry>
	<title>The Math on Twitter’s Debt</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/10/30/technology/elon-musk-twitter-debt.html">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uft">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/math-on-twitters-debt">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39449</id>
	<published>2022-10-31T20:28:17Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-31T21:37:19Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Lauren Hirsch, The New York Times:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The numbers are already daunting. The $44 billion acquisition was
the largest leveraged buyout of a technology company in history.
To do the deal, Mr. Musk, the world’s richest man, loaded about
$13 billion in debt on the company, which had not turned a profit
for eight of the past 10 years. The deal was inked before the
global economy looked to be headed toward a recession as interest
rates surged higher. And digital advertising, which makes up 90
percent of Twitter’s revenue, has been falling at social media
companies. [...]</p>

<p>Last year, Twitter’s interest expense was about $50 million. With
the new debt taken on in the deal, that will now balloon to about
$1 billion a year. Yet the company’s operations last year
generated about $630 million in cash flow to meet its financial
obligations.</p>

<p>That means that Twitter is generating less money per year than
what it owes its lenders. The company also does not appear to have
a lot of extra cash on hand.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Interest payments are a bitch. The optimistic take on Musk taking Twitter private is that it frees Twitter from pursuing increased revenue at all costs to please shareholders. But what’s the point if Twitter now needs to pursue increased revenue at all costs to service its debt?</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Math on Twitter’s Debt’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/math-on-twitters-debt">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Scott Forstall Was Forced Out of Apple 10 Years Ago</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2012/10/29Apple-Announces-Changes-to-Increase-Collaboration-Across-Hardware-Software-Services/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufs">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/forstall-10">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39448</id>
	<published>2022-10-31T19:51:03Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-31T23:21:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Apple, 10 years ago:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple today announced executive management changes that will
encourage even more collaboration between the Company’s
world-class hardware, software and services teams. As part of
these changes, Jony Ive, Bob Mansfield, Eddy Cue and Craig
Federighi will add more responsibilities to their roles. Apple
also announced that Scott Forstall will be leaving Apple next year
and will serve as an advisor to CEO Tim Cook in the interim.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hard to believe it’s been 10 years. Also hard to believe that Forstall hasn’t done anything else in tech since. He obviously butted heads with the rest of the executive team, and did not last long without Steve Jobs providing him political cover. But he was incredibly successful, and people who worked in his organization loved him. He was demanding, yes, but he went to bat companywide for the people and teams that worked for him. (At least one time, <a href="https://twitter.com/jmfd/status/1587183553967628288">literally</a>.) “Scott had our backs” is a phrase I’ve heard from a slew of people at (or formerly at) Apple.</p>

<p>Less notable, from the same press release:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Additionally, John Browett is leaving Apple.</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Scott Forstall Was Forced Out of Apple 10 Years Ago’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/forstall-10">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Twitter Might Merge Twitter Blue and Verification, and Thus Charge for Being Verified</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/10/30/23431931/twitter-paid-verification-elon-musk-blue-monthly-subscription">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufr">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/twitter-verified-charge">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39447</id>
	<published>2022-10-31T19:30:34Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-31T23:28:44Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The Verge’s Alex Heath had the scoop over the weekend:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The directive is to change Twitter Blue, the company’s <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/7/28/23283166/twitter-blue-subscription-price-hike-4-99">optional,
$4.99 a month subscription that unlocks additional features</a>,
into a more expensive subscription that also verifies users,
according to people familiar with the matter and internal
correspondence seen by The Verge. Twitter is currently planning to
charge $19.99 for the new Twitter Blue subscription. Under the
current plan, verified users would have 90 days to subscribe or
lose their blue checkmark. Employees working on the project were
told on Sunday that they need to meet a deadline of November 7th
to launch the feature or they will be fired.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I can verify that a team has been tasked with this, but I heard the deadline was this Friday (November 4), not Monday (the 7th). But my real quibble is reporting anything going on at Twitter right now as a definitive plan. It’s a fact that Musk tasked a team at Twitter with building this and gave them “a week” to build it; it’s not a fact that it’s ever going to see the light of day.</p>

<p>As for the idea of charging verified users to remain verified (or, perhaps better put, requiring verified users to sign up for Twitter Blue), it strikes me as an idea that’s contrary to the reason verification exists. <a href="https://twitter.com/NateSilver538/status/1587094505202892800">Nate Silver</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m probably the perfect target for this, use Twitter a ton, can
afford $20/mo, not particularly anti-Elon, but my reaction is that
I’ve generated a ton of valuable free content for Twitter over the
years and they can go fuck themselves.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/StephenKing/status/1587042605627490304">Stephen King</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>$20 a month to keep my blue check? Fuck that, they should pay me.
If that gets instituted, I’m gone like Enron.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s a weirdly but unsurprisingly deeply insecure faction on the right that considers verified Twitter users to be one of their many enemy factions. They call them “bluechecks”. And while I’m sure there are some verified Twitter users who really do see it as some sort of prestige status thing, as Silver and King point out, in practical terms it’s for <em>Twitter’s</em> benefit, not for the verified users. It’s Twitter that benefits from millions of users being able to feel certain that the “Stephen King” with 7 million followers on Twitter is really <em>the</em> Stephen King. It’s Twitter that benefits from Nate Silver engaging with users and tweeting analysis. Popular tweeters aren’t getting paid to tweet. And now Elon Musk thinks they should pay <em>to</em> tweet?</p>

<p>Count me as skeptical that this is going to happen as currently discussed.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Twitter Might Merge Twitter Blue and Verification, and Thus Charge for Being Verified’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/31/twitter-verified-charge">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://atoms.com/df">
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ufv">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2022/10/atoms_1">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/feeds/sponsors//11.39451</id>
	<author><name>Daring Fireball Department of Commerce</name></author>
	<published>2022-10-31T19:05:19-05:00</published>
	<updated>2022-10-31T19:08:44-05:00</updated>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Atoms designed its Model 000 to be the shoe you’d want to wear every day. Using a combination of traditional craftsmanship, and pioneering materials like copper lining, stretch laces, and midsole foam, to achieve a magical comfortable experience that often surprises the first-time customers. What appears at first glance to be a relatively simple sneaker is full of several industry-first features. Quarter sizing gives you the perfect fit. Atoms’ stretch laces make them easy to slip on and off. Thanks to their magical comfort and simplicity, they can become your go-to sneaker, and work with just about any outfit.</p>

<p>This holiday, Atoms is bringing back some of its popular limited edition colors. Daring Fireball readers get 15% off all Model 000 colors. Take advantage of the opportunity to stock up for the holidays. Just use code DARING at checkout.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Atoms’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/feeds/sponsors/2022/10/atoms_1">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
	<title>[Sponsor] Atoms</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Decker 1.0</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://beyondloom.com/decker/index.html">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufp">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/30/decker">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39445</id>
	<published>2022-10-30T17:30:00Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-30T17:48:52Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>John Earnest:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Decker builds on the legacy of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HyperCard">HyperCard</a> and the visual
aesthetic of classic MacOS. It retains the simplicity and ease of
learning that HyperCard provided, while adding many subtle and
overt quality-of-life improvements, like deep undo history,
support for scroll wheels and touchscreens, more modern keyboard
navigation, and bulk editing operations.</p>

<p>Anyone can use Decker to create E-Zines, organize their notes,
give presentations, build adventure games, or even just doodle
some 1-bit pixel art. The holistic “ditherpunk” aesthetic is cozy,
a bit nostalgic, and provides fun and distinctive creative
constraints. As a prototyping tool, Decker encourages embracing a
sketchy, imperfect approach. Finished decks can be saved as
standalone .html documents which self-execute in a web browser and
can be shared anywhere you can host or embed a web page. Decker
also runs natively on MacOS, Windows, and Linux.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Decker is astonishing. At first glance you might mistake it as shallow, a fun nostalgic gimmick. How serious could something that looks so retro be? But it’s in fact quite deep: Earnest created his own custom scripting language, <a href="https://beyondloom.com/decker/lil.html">Lil</a>, which is very approachable but  includes things like an SQL-like query syntax for tabular data. The whole thing is beautiful and fun and useful and so engaging that I literally had a dream about using it last night. I don’t know what I’m going to make with Decker but I’ll be damned if I’m not going to make <em>something</em>. It’s that inspiring.</p>

<p>Even the names are perfect. “Decks” are to Decker what stacks were to HyperCard. Decks contain cards and cards contain widgets. The <a href="https://beyondloom.com/decker/format.html">file format is plain text</a> and very much human-readable. A deck shared on the web contains the whole runtime to present and run it in a browser, so all you need to do is publish a .html file. <a href="https://beyondloom.com/decker/tour.html">Decker’s Guided Tour</a> is a fine example — both for trying Decker out and for viewing the source. (You’ll want to try it in a desktop browser, or maybe an iPad with a keyboard and trackpad — it’s not meant for phones.)</p>

<p>The native Mac app is just 4 MB. It’s free of charge and open source, but Earnest is accepting voluntary payments on the downloads page. Be generous! And if you make any cool decks let me know.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Decker 1.0’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/30/decker">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Kolide</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://l.kolide.co/3c0AF7W">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufq">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/30/kolide">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39446</id>
	<published>2022-10-30T17:28:17Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-30T17:29:34Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Kolide for sponsoring Daring Fireball last week. Kolide is an endpoint security solution that gives IT teams a single dashboard for all devices, regardless of their operating system.</p>

<p>When you’re a small company dominated by engineers, you can keep up with fleet management with nothing more than trust and a spreadsheet. But once you start to hire marketers, designers, and the rest, the number of laptops balloons and the line between “work” and “personal” devices gets fuzzy. But fuzzy isn’t going to cut it. You have to prove you’ve got device security under control to close deals with customers, <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3NUh8mG">pass a third-party audit</a>, and prove you’re ready for acquisition or an IPO.</p>

<p>Kolide can answer questions MDMs can’t:</p>

<ul>
<li>Do you have production data being stored on devices?</li>
<li>Are all your developers’ SSH keys encrypted?</li>
<li>And a host of other data points you’d otherwise have to write a custom shell script to learn about.</li>
</ul>

<p>Want to see how it works for yourself? <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3c0AF7W">Kolide is offering DF readers a free trial</a>, no credit card required.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Kolide’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/30/kolide">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>‘Only the GOP Celebrates Political Violence’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2022/10/pelosi-republicans-partisan-political-violence/671934/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufo">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/30/gop-political-violence">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39444</id>
	<published>2022-10-30T15:20:46Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-30T17:22:24Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>David Frum:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But if both Republicans and Democrats, left and right, <em>suffer</em>
political violence, the same cannot be said of those who
<em>celebrate</em> political violence. That’s not a “both sides” affair
in 2020s America.</p>

<p>You don’t see Democratic House members wielding weapons in videos
and threatening to shoot candidates who want to cut capital-gains
taxes or slow the growth of Medicare. Democratic candidates for
Senate do not post video fantasies of hunting and executing
political rivals, or of using a firearm to discipline their
children’s romantic partners. It’s not because of Democratic
members that Speaker Nancy Pelosi
<a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/andrewsolender/2021/06/17/pelosi-says-house-metal-detectors-will-remain-indefinitely/">installed</a>
metal detectors to bar firearms from the floor of the House. No
Democratic equivalent exists of Donald Trump, who regularly
praises and encourages violence as a normal tool of politics, most
recently against his own party’s Senate leader, Mitch McConnell.
As the formerly Trump-leaning Wall Street Journal
<a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/trump-death-wish-rhetoric-mitch-mcconnell-elaine-chao-truth-social-violence-donald-11664735710">editorialized</a>
on October 2: “It’s all too easy to imagine some fanatic taking
Mr. Trump seriously and literally, and attempting to kill Mr.
McConnell. Many supporters took Mr. Trump’s rhetoric about former
Vice President <a href="https://www.wsj.com/topics/person/mike-pence">Mike
Pence</a> all too
seriously on Jan. 6.”</p>
</blockquote>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘‘Only the GOP Celebrates Political Violence’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/30/gop-political-violence">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Twitter, the Subway of the Internet</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://scripting.com/2022/10/27.html#a212435">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufn">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/29/twitter-subway">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39443</id>
	<published>2022-10-29T23:43:24Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-29T23:43:25Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Dave Winer:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Why would I leave Twitter? It’s like living in NY and not
taking the subway. Sure it’s dirty and smells bad, but it’s how
you get places.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sometimes you just have to tip your hat to a perfect analogy.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Twitter, the Subway of the Internet’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/29/twitter-subway">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Nilay Patel on Twitter, Content Moderation, and Elon Musk</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/10/28/23428132/elon-musk-twitter-acquisition-problems-speech-moderation">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufm">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/29/nilay-patel-musk-twitter-hell">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39442</id>
	<published>2022-10-29T16:32:34Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-29T16:35:12Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Nilay Patel, “Welcome to Hell, Elon”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The essential truth of every social network is that the product is content moderation, and everyone hates the people who decide how content moderation works. Content moderation is what Twitter <em>makes</em> — it is the thing that defines the user experience. It’s what YouTube makes, it’s what Instagram makes, it’s what TikTok makes. They all try to incentivize good stuff, disincentivize bad stuff, and delete the really bad stuff. Do you know why YouTube videos are <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2019/7/26/8888003/youtube-video-length-contrapoints-lindsay-ellis-shelby-church-ad-revenue">all eight to 10 minutes long</a>? Because that’s how long a video has to be to <a href="https://www.tubefilter.com/2020/07/07/youtube-lowering-minimum-video-length-mid-roll-ads/">qualify for a second ad slot</a> in the middle. That’s content moderation, baby — YouTube wants a certain kind of video, and it created incentives to get it. That’s the business you’re in now. The longer you fight it or pretend that you can sell something else, the more Twitter will drag you into the deepest possible muck of defending <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/10/9/23395490/twitter-lock-kanye-west-out-account-following-anti-semitic-post">indefensible speech</a>. And if you turn on a dime and accept that growth requires aggressive content moderation and pushing back against government speech regulations around the country and world, well, we’ll see how your fans react to that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t disagree with a word of Patel’s column. It’s good and smart and informed (with links) about the various content moderation problems Twitter faces and will continue to face around the world. And again, I can see this acquisition going badly — for Twitter as an institution, for Musk personally, or both. It’s high risk. That’s what makes it captivating. This is a $44 billion personal wager.</p>

<p>But I’m not sure any of us outside Musk’s circle know what he really wants to do content-moderation-wise. Musk personifies the axiom that you should judge someone by their actions, not their words. Musk says he envisions Twitter as a “free speech” haven that would allow even for speech most of us would consider hateful. A lot of people predicting doom for Twitter under Musk’s ownership take him at his word on that. <em>Here come the Nazis</em>, more or less.</p>

<p>But maybe — maybe! — there’s an “<a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/only_Nixon_could_go_to_China">Only Nixon could go to China</a>” element at play here. To wit: that Twitter can continue moderating content to block genuinely hateful and threatening posts but maintain broad credibility on the right side of the political spectrum because so many people on that side of the fence implicitly trust Musk.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Nilay Patel on Twitter, Content Moderation, and Elon Musk’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/29/nilay-patel-musk-twitter-hell">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>A Bigger iPad Would Just Be a Bigger iPad</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/apple-is-working-on-a-16-inch-ipad-further-blurring-line-with-laptops">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufl">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/27/sometimes-a-bigger-ipad-is-just-a-cigar">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39441</id>
	<published>2022-10-27T18:16:15Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-31T23:43:16Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Wayne Ma, reporting for The Information:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Apple is developing its largest iPad yet, a model with a 16-inch
screen that it hopes to release in the fourth quarter of next
year, according to a person familiar with the project. The device
would further blur the line between the iPad and MacBook, bringing
the tablet’s screen size in line with that of Apple’s largest
laptop, which also features a 16-inch display. Apple’s biggest
iPad currently sports a 12.9-inch screen. [...]</p>

<p>The move would again raise speculation about whether Apple will
one day merge the iPad and MacBook into a single product line or
merge the two operating systems given their overlapping features.
Apple executives have said they consider the MacBook and iPad
different products. MacBooks are designed to work best with
external inputs like keyboards and trackpads, while the iPad works
best with touch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A 16-inch iPad Pro would just be a 16-inch iPad Pro. It would neither mean nor suggest anything other than that some iPad users would enjoy and make good use of a larger display. This obsession with “merging” iPads and Macs is nonsense. “Apple executives have said they consider the MacBook and iPad different products” is the dumbest sentence I’ve read in weeks. They <em>are</em> different products. Even adding touchscreen displays to MacBooks — which I doubt will happen more than ever — would not imply a platform “merger” is in the works.</p>

<p>Only someone who has no understanding of one or both of the two platforms could even think a “merger” is possible. Any scenario where Apple unifies both platforms into one OS would be pointlessly destructive — utterly ruining one or the other platform (and most likely ruining both).</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘A Bigger iPad Would Just Be a Bigger iPad’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/27/sometimes-a-bigger-ipad-is-just-a-cigar">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>New iCloud Website Is Available in Public Beta</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.macrumors.com/2022/10/26/apple-icloud-website-redesign/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufk">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/27/beta-icloud-web">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39440</id>
	<published>2022-10-27T17:03:46Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-27T17:03:47Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Seems better all around: looks better, loads faster, and better navigation.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘New iCloud Website Is Available in Public Beta’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/27/beta-icloud-web">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Elon Musk Posts Open Letter to Twitter Advertisers on the Cusp of Completing His Acquisition</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1585619322239561728/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufj">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/27/musk-twitter-open-letter">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39439</id>
	<published>2022-10-27T15:02:36Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-27T18:24:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Elon Musk:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And I do so with humility, recognizing that failure in pursuing
this goal, despite our best efforts, is a very real possibility.</p>

<p>That said, Twitter obviously cannot become a free-for-all
hellscape, where anything can be said with no consequences! In
addition to adhering to the laws of the land, our platform must be
warm and welcoming to all, where you can choose your desired
experience according to your preferences, just as you can choose,
for example, to see movies or play video games ranging from all
ages to mature.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m more optimistic about Twitter’s future than I have been in years. Don’t get me wrong, I think there’s a very real chance that under Musk’s leadership, Twitter might break apart and fade into irrelevance. But Musk himself notes the same thing! Keeping Twitter open to a wide range of content, but making it easy to control what content <em>you</em> see, as user, is a worthy ideal. Pulling it off, that’s the trick. But as a privately-held company Musk is free to make changes that move Twitter away from being optimized for <em>engagement</em> and towards being optimized for <em>enjoyment</em>.</p>

<p>The risk of <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/exclusive-where-did-tweeters-go-twitter-is-losing-its-most-active-users-internal-2022-10-25/">fading into irrelevance</a> is far greater, if not nearly certain, under Twitter’s current leadership. I think Twitter is worth saving. I think Twitter requires massive changes in order to be saved — both outward-facing as a service and platform, and internally as a company. I would not have picked Elon Musk as the person to lead the company through those changes. But you dance with the one who bought the company and took it private.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I also very much believe that advertising, when done right, can
delight, entertain and inform you; it can show you a service or
product or medical treatment that you never knew existed, but is
right for you. For this to be true, it is essential to show
Twitter users advertising that is as relevant as possible to their
needs. Low relevancy ads are spam, but highly relevant ads are
actually content! Fundamentally, Twitter aspires to be the most
respected advertising platform in the world that strengthens your
brand and grows your enterprise.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a good North Star. Ads as desirable content has been my mantra at Daring Fireball ever since I <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2003/07/independent_days">turned on the revenue spigot</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Elon Musk Posts Open Letter to Twitter Advertisers on the Cusp of Completing His Acquisition’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/27/musk-twitter-open-letter">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/the_2022_ipad">
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ufi">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022://1.39438</id>
	<published>2022-10-26T18:04:27Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-26T19:09:35Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It looks good, feels good, comes in a selection of fun colors (Apple sent me yellow), and brings the just-plain-no-adjective iPad to the modern all-screen era.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>If you’ve used an iPad Air from the last two years — either the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/10/the_2020_ipad_air">4th-gen Air</a> from October 2020 or the <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/03/the_2022_ipad_air">5th-gen model</a> introduced earlier this year — the new 10th-generation iPad (no adjective) is remarkably familiar. Same size (well, <em>almost</em> — see below), and the same basic design: no home button, round display corners, all-screen, no Face ID, and Touch ID on the side button.</p>

<p>They’re even offered in the same two storage tiers: 64 and 256 GB. I’ll throw in the brand-new 11-inch iPad Pro and the 9th-gen iPad to boot for a price comparison of all the 11-ish-inch iPads in the lineup today:</p>

<!-- Markdown Table
| Storage    | 2021 iPad (9th-gen) | 2022 iPad (10th-gen) | 2022 iPad Air | 2022 iPad Pro 11″ |
| :--------: | :-----------------: | :------------------: | :-----------: | :---------------: |
|   64 GB    |        $330         |         $450         |     $600      |         —         |
|   128 GB   |          —          |          —           |       —       |       $800        |
|   256 GB   |        $480         |         $600         |     $750      |       $900        |
|   512 GB   |          —          |          —           |       —       |       $1100       |
|    1 TB    |          —          |          —           |       —       |       $1500       |
|    2 TB    |          —          |          —           |       —       |       $1900       |
| *Cellular* |       *+130*        |        *+150*        |    *+150*     |      *+200*       |
-->

<table style = "width: 500px; margin-left: -25px;">
<thead>
<tr>
  <th align="center">Storage</th>
  <th align="center">2021 iPad<br/>(9th-gen)</th>
  <th align="center">2022 iPad<br/>(10th-gen)</th>
  <th align="center">2022<br/>iPad Air</th>
  <th align="center">2022<br/>iPad Pro 11″</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td align="center">64 GB</td>
  <td align="center">$330</td>
  <td align="center">$450</td>
  <td align="center">$600</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center">128 GB</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">$800</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center">256 GB</td>
  <td align="center">$480</td>
  <td align="center">$600</td>
  <td align="center">$750</td>
  <td align="center">$900</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center">512 GB</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">$1100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center">1 TB</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">$1500</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center">2 TB</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">—</td>
  <td align="center">$1900</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center"><em>Cellular</em></td>
  <td align="center"><em>+130</em></td>
  <td align="center"><em>+150</em></td>
  <td align="center"><em>+150</em></td>
  <td align="center"><em>+200</em></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>A lot of people are now complaining that the iPad lineup is “confusing”. I disagree. There are specific <em>aspects</em> of the iPads in the lineup that are confusing, or at least disappointing. These aspects are mostly related to peripherals — which Pencils and which keyboard covers work with which iPads — and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/the_ipad_lineup_is_like_growing_out_its_bangs_or_something">I wrote about these issues last week</a>. But in terms of the fundamental question facing would-be buyers — “Which iPad should I get?” — I don’t think this lineup is confusing. I’d argue, in fact, that it’s less confusing, because the lineup is more complete. Prior to last week, there was a significant gap between the 9th-generation iPad (which remains in the lineup, unchanged in price) and the iPad Air. The 10th-gen iPad fills that gap.</p>

<p>With the exception of the $120 difference between the 9th- and 10th-gen iPads, there’s now a $150 difference in price between each 11-inch-ish iPad model. So what are the differences between the 10th-gen iPad and the 2022 iPad Air? Here’s what stands out to me <a href="https://www.apple.com/ipad/compare/?modelList=ipad-10th-gen,ipad-air-5th-gen,ipad-9th-gen">looking at the differences using Apple’s handy Compare tool</a>:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The Air’s display is fully-laminated and has an anti-reflective coating, and offers a P3 wide color gamut. The iPad 10 display is not laminated and only covers the sRGB color gamut. The iPad 10’s display looks good, but side-by-side, the iPad Air’s looks better. (Lamination puts the actual display closer to the surface of the glass — more like pixels <em>on</em> glass than pixels <em>under</em> glass.)</p></li>
<li><p>The iPad Air has the M1 chip with 8 GB of RAM; the iPad 10 uses the A14 chip that debuted with the iPhones 12 in 2020 and has only 4 GB of RAM. One reason to prefer the Air’s M1 chip: the iPad Air supports Stage Manager in iPadOS 16; the iPad 10 does not. There are all sorts of other silicon advantages to the M1, of course, including a “Media Engine” for hardware accelerated video encoding and decoding. But anyone who is concerned about hardware-accelerated video encoding and decoding is not shopping for the consumer-priced iPad 10. Stage Manager, to me, is the difference that might matter most to non-pro iPad users on the fence regarding which model to buy.</p></li>
<li><p>The iPad Air uses the superior Apple Pencil 2; the iPad 10 — seemingly inexplicably, but in fact for understandable but esoteric reasons (<a href="#pencils">see below</a>) — pairs only with the Pencil 1, for which it requires a new $9 USB-C-to-Lightning adapter.</p></li>
<li><p>Apple makes one keyboard cover for the new iPad 10: the new $250 two-piece kickstand-propped Magic Keyboard Folio. Apple makes two keyboard covers for the iPad Air (and the same two keyboards also work with the iPad Pro): the $300 turn-your-iPad-into-a-laptop Magic Keyboard, and the no-trackpad <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/22/in-praise-of-smart-keyboard-folio">thinner and lighter</a> $180 Smart Keyboard Folio. The new Magic Keyboard Folio only works with the new iPad 10, and the Magic Keyboard and Smart Keyboard Folio only work with the iPads Air and Pro.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>There are other subtle differences — the Air supports more Wi-Fi 6 bands, but the iPad 10 supports Bluetooth 5.2 while the Air only 5.0. But the above list is really it for practical differences. Do you think any of those bullet points are worth an extra $150? Then buy the iPad Air. If not, congrats, you can save $150 (and perhaps put it toward the pricey Magic Keyboard Folio).</p>

<h2>Pencil It In <span id = "pencils"></span></h2>

<p>I’ve been testing the iPad 10 since the end of last week.<sup id="fnr1-2022-10-26"><a href="#fn1-2022-10-26">1</a></sup> <sup id="fnr2-2022-10-26"><a href="#fn2-2022-10-26">2</a></sup> It occurred to me soon after setting it up that I haven’t used a Pencil 1 in years. Putting aside the issue of the USB-C-to-Lightning adapter, it’s striking how much less I like the original Pencil compared to the Pencil 2. When the Pencil 2 debuted in 2018 alongside that year’s iPad Pros, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2018/11/the_2018_ipad_pros#pencil-2">I wrote</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The new Apple Pencil is one of the best “2.0” products I’ve ever
seen. The original Apple Pencil is a terrific product, but the new
one nears perfection for the concept. New and improved:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Matte finish. I never really thought to complain about the
glossy texture of the original Pencil, but the moment I laid
hands on the new one I realized matte is better for this
product.</p></li>
<li><p>Magnetic charging and pairing. When rumors surfaced that the new
iPad Pros were moving from Lightning to USB-C, there was a lot
of speculation that Apple would need to make a new Pencil with
USB-C. This is so much better. As a nice touch, when you first
connect the Pencil to your iPad, iOS <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2018/11/apple-pencil.jpeg">shows you a Pencil on
screen and it’s the <em>exact</em> size of the actual
Pencil</a>. It’s adorable. With the original Pencil,
Apple didn’t provide a good answer for where you were supposed
to keep it when it wasn’t in your hand. The magnetic connection
answers that. It’s strong enough that I wouldn’t hesitate to
keep the Pencil connected magnetically when putting the iPad in
a backpack.</p></li>
<li><p>No cap, no dongle. It took me almost two years, but last month I
finally lost the cap to my original Pencil on a train. The new
Pencil has no pieces to lose.</p></li>
<li><p>Flat side. The old Pencil was weighted to keep it from rolling,
but a flat side works better. There’s a reason why most pens and
pencil either have clips or at least one flat side.</p></li>
<li><p>Optional engraving. I wonder how much of this is a “<em>Why not?</em>”
thing and how much is fueled by the real-world scenario of
coworkers or family members losing track of whose Pencil is
whose.</p></li>
<li><p>Double-tap. Seems like a such a small thing, but it really does
make accessing the eraser easier.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>The new Apple Pencil is so good I have no complaints and can only
think of one suggestion for the future: it’d be nice if there were
haptic feedback when you double-tap.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Four years later, that entire passage holds up. Now, though, I like the Pencil 1 <em>even less</em>. I don’t like the glossy/slippery surface material, I don’t like how it rolls around on a tabletop, and I find the cap downright silly. If the original Pencil had to have an integrated Lightning plug, it should have been retractible instead of permanently protruding and thus requiring a cap. Also, I’d forgotten that double-tapping (which, by default, switches between pen and eraser while drawing) was a new feature for Pencil 2. I spent a few minutes thinking the Pencil 1 Apple provided me with the iPad for testing was broken because double-tapping didn’t work.</p>

<p>As for the new adapter, once you’ve used it to pair a Pencil with your iPad 10, you can set it aside for occasionally charging the Pencil when needed. And if you misplace it, or leave it at home and find yourself needing to charge the Pencil 1 without it, you can in fact <em>charge</em> a Pencil 1 by plugging it into any iPhone. It of course doesn’t work as a stylus with an iPhone, and doesn’t even trigger an “Accessory Not Supported” alert (which is what you get if you try pairing a Pencil 1 with an iPad Pro or iPad Air using the USB-C adapter), but it does charge. If I owned an iPad 10 and Pencil 1, I’d probably just throw the Pencil’s cap away and keep the adapter attached to the Pencil. It even keeps the Pencil from rolling while attached.</p>

<p>If I didn’t already own a Pencil 1, though, I’d buy a <a href="https://www.apple.com/shop/product/HQ6Q2VC/A/logitech-crayon-for-ipad">Logitech Crayon</a> instead. Objective advantages of the Crayon:</p>

<ul>
<li>Price ($70 vs. $100).</li>
<li>Logitech’s new 2nd-gen Crayon charges by USB-C. It’s a female port, so you can simply charge it with any USB-C cable.</li>
<li>No pairing. I’m not sure how it works, but with Logitech’s Crayons, there’s no need to pair them with individual iPads. There’s a simple on/off switch on the barrel, and when on, it just works with any iPad from 2018 onward.</li>
<li>No cap or dongle to lose.</li>
</ul>

<p>Objective disadvantage of the Crayon:</p>

<ul>
<li>Unlike Apple’s Pencils, Logitech’s Crayon is not pressure sensitive. It does detect the angle of the stroke, but not pressure. If you’re an illustrator, that’s probably a dealbreaker. If — like me — you just use a stylus on your iPad to jot notes, make highlights, and make artistically challenged napkin sketches, you might not even notice or care about the lack of pressure sensitivity.</li>
</ul>

<p>Subjective differences between the Crayon and Pencil 1:</p>

<ul>
<li>Feel. Logitech’s Crayons are flat, like a carpenter’s pencil. I don’t mind that at all. They also have a matte finish that I much prefer to the slick glossy finish of the Pencil 1.</li>
<li>Because the Crayons don’t pair with your iPad, you can’t track the battery life of the Crayon in iPadOS. With an Apple Pencil, the Pencil’s battery life shows up in Settings → Apple Pencil and in the Battery widget. But the Crayon has three LEDs right on its barrel that show its battery life, which I consider as good or better than observing battery life through iPadOS for Apple Pencils.</li>
<li>The Crayons have an on/off switch. Apple Pencils manage their power state automatically. This is not a big deal to me at all — and leaving the Crayon switched on, but unused, for an extended period doesn’t seem to drain the battery quickly.</li>
</ul>

<p>Unless you need pressure sensitivity or dislike the feel of a carpenter’s pencil in your hand, Logitech’s new 2nd-gen Crayon is a clear winner compared to Apple’s Pencil 1. Even Logitech’s old 1st-gen Crayon is a better option — if I have to charge via Lightning, I’d rather my stylus have a simple female port and not require an adapter.</p>

<h2>Magic Keyboard Folio</h2>

<p>Let’s just get this out of the way: I’m not a kickstand guy. I much prefer the cantilevered hinge of the Magic Keyboard, with its laptop-style footprint and the ability to just pick up the iPad while attached to the keyboard and not have the keyboard half flop around. The two-piece design makes for twice as much work to attach and detach.</p>

<p>But I can see why some people dig a keyboard design like this. Attached to the kickstand back but detached from the keyboard, you have a nice stand for watching movies or just reading. While both pieces are attached, if you fold the keyboard behind the iPad, it somehow detects this and ignores key presses. That’s really clever. You can also attach the keyboard half “backwards” and key presses will always be ignored. </p>

<p>One disappointment is that the keyboard is not backlit. Apple’s Magic Keyboard has backlighting. So too does <a href="https://www.logitech.com/en-us/products/ipad-keyboards/combo-touch.html">Logitech’s $160 Combo Touch</a>, which is a fundamentally similar design. The key difference between the Combo Touch and Magic Keyboard Folio is how the kickstand back attaches — with the Combo Touch, it’s a case you snap the iPad into; the Magic Keyboard Folio back attaches magnetically. In addition to my general dislike for kickstands, I dislike that aspect of the Combo Touch — it’s clearly designed with the idea that you’ll keep your iPad in the case even while not attached to the keyboard. When I detach an iPad from a keyboard, I just want to hold it naked. (The iPad, that is.)</p>

<p>The keyboard itself feels great — with keys that feel identical or nearly so to those of the Magic Keyboard, and the same goes for the trackpad. My biggest gripe is that the key layout mimics a baffling design decision from the 11-inch Magic Keyboard and Smart Keyboard Folio: the left bracket key is full-width, but the right bracket key is half-width.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2022/10/ipad-magic-keyboard-folio-keys.jpeg class="noborder">
  <img 
    src="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2022/10/ipad-magic-keyboard-folio-keys.jpeg"
    alt="A close up of the right side of the Magic Keyboard Folio, centered on the bracket keys."
  /></a></p>

<p>These keyboards are much narrower than MacBook keyboards or the almost-MacBook-width 12.9-inch Magic Keyboard. Widths, by my ruler:</p>

<ul>
<li>MacBooks: 273 mm</li>
<li>12.9″ Magic Keyboard: 268 mm</li>
<li>11″ Magic Keyboard and Magic Keyboard Folio: 236 mm</li>
</ul>

<p>32 mm is about 1.25 inches. That’s quite a bit of width to reduce. All the keys are smaller than on a standard-sized keyboard. Measuring from the left edge of the A key to the right edge of the semicolon key (the home row):</p>

<ul>
<li>MacBooks and 12.9″ Magic Keyboard: 187 mm</li>
<li>11″ Magic Keyboard and Magic Keyboard Folio: 177 mm</li>
</ul>

<p>Even with smaller standard keys, though, these keyboards need to make additional concessions, with some punctuation and modifier keys reduced to partial widths. Apple made good decisions on these key cap widths, with the glaring exception of the bracket keys. Clearly these two keys are siblings or peers, and ought to be the same width. That there is not room to make both of them full-width is fine. But rather than make one full-width and the other half, clearly they should both be three-quarters width, like the Tab key or right Option key. Or just make them both half-width. Anything so long as they’re the same size. It makes no more sense for the left and right bracket keys to be different sizes than it would for the left and right arrow keys. Why Apple chose to do this with the 11-inch Magic Keyboard layout back in 2020 is beyond me; why they’re sticking with it is even more baffling.<sup id="fnr3-2022-10-26"><a href="#fn3-2022-10-26">3</a></sup></p>

<p>All of Apple’s iPad keyboard covers are somewhat expensive. The Smart Keyboard Folio for the iPad Air and 11-inch iPad Pro costs $180; the Magic Keyboard for the same two iPads costs $300. But given that the $250 Magic Keyboard Folio pairs only with the lower-priced iPad 10, it feels particularly expensive. It’s more than half the price of the $450 64 GB iPad 10, and paired with the $600 256 GB iPad 10, the combo costs a not-so-low-priced $850. And for $250 it feels wrong that it doesn’t offer backlighting. I can see omitting backlighting if it were, say, $150. But $250 is undeniably a premium price for a keyboard and trackpad.</p>

<p>Weight-wise, the new Magic Keyboard Folio is effectively a wash compared with the Magic Keyboard for the iPad Pro and Air. The Magic Keyboard Folio weighs 589 grams; the Magic Keyboard 598 grams. (Roughly 1.3 pounds.)</p>

<p>It’s a bit disappointing that the Magic Keyboard Folio is only available in white. I’d think Apple would at least offer white and black, like it does with the Magic Keyboard. (But the Smart Keyboard Folio is only available in one color, black.)</p>

<p>As for why the new Magic Keyboard Folio <em>only</em> pairs with the iPad 10, and why the iPad 10 doesn’t pair with either the Magic Keyboard or Smart Keyboard Folio, if you look at the <a href="https://www.apple.com/ipad/compare/?modelList=ipad-10th-gen,ipad-air-5th-gen,ipad-9th-gen">specs</a>, you’ll notice that the iPad 10 is <em>not</em> the same size as the iPad Air. It’s exactly 1 mm larger in all three dimensions: height, width, and most noticeably, depth. 1 mm is not a lot, but it’s enough to spoil any chance at case/cover compatibility, at least for a precision-fit-minded company like Apple.</p>

<h2>Miscellaneous</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>You can’t use a Pencil while charging it. This is true whether the Pencil is charging from the iPad itself or from a wall charger. For me this is merely a curiosity — it only takes 10-20 minutes to fully charge a fully depleted Pencil, and it only takes a few seconds to give it a charge to last 15 minutes. But it’s also just a curiosity to me that Apple’s Magic Mouse is designed to be unusable while charging, and people complain about that endlessly.</p></li>
<li><p>The very best new design element of the iPad 10 is the placement of the front-facing camera along the long “landscape” side, which puts it top center when propped laptop-style with a keyboard. I’m so used to my iPad Pro’s down-and-to-left camera placement in landscape that using this iPad with the camera in the “correct” location takes some getting used to. But this is clearly where all future iPad front-facing cameras should go (with the possible exception of the Mini).</p></li>
<li><p>Speaking of that camera placement, last week <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/the_ipad_lineup_is_like_growing_out_its_bangs_or_something#fn1-2022-10-21">I speculated in a footnote</a> that it might be difficult for Apple to move the front camera to the landscape side for the iPads Pro and iPad Air:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Here’s a spitball: Maybe my front-facing-camera-placement and all-iPads-should-support-Pencil-2 gripes are in conflict. The long side where the new iPad has the front-facing camera is the same long side where the iPad Pros, iPad Air, and iPad Mini have the magnetic attachment point for the Pencil 2. Maybe they both can’t fit in the middle of the same side?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A little birdie confirmed to me that this is in fact exactly the case. The internal mechanism for magnetically attaching, charging, and pairing Pencil 2 is both expensive and somewhat large. And cameras are surprisingly large internally once you count the flex connectors and everything else. You can actually see this for yourself by looking at <a href="https://www.ifixit.com/Teardown/iPad+Air+4+Teardown/141032">a teardown of a Pencil-2-compatible iPad</a>. It’s going to require significant new engineering to make future iPads that support Pencil 2 with the front camera on the landscape side. My guess — and this is truly a guess, with zero hints from any sources — is that Apple will swap the positions of the Pencil 2 connector and the front camera. But on current iPads Pro and Air, only the 12.9-inch Pro has room for a Pencil 2 on that side. On the 11-inch Pro and the Air, the side button gets in the way. Also: attaching a Pencil on that side, with the current iPad Pro and Air designs, might obstruct the speakers. Fun time to be an iPad hardware designer.</p></li>
<li><p>The Apple Pencil 1 has always shipped with <a href="https://www.idownloadblog.com/2015/11/20/apple-pencil-extra-tip-usb-charging-adapter/">a small adapter with female Lightning ports on both sides</a>, to allow you to charge the Pencil by connecting it to a Lightning cable. If you use that adapter and a USB-C Lighting cable to connect the Pencil to the iPad 10, it charges, but it doesn’t pair. The <em>only</em> way to pair a Pencil with the iPad 10 is using the new USB-C adapter.</p></li>
</ul>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The new 10th-generation iPad is a solid and welcome addition. It looks good, feels good, comes in a selection of fun colors (Apple sent me yellow), and brings the just-plain-no-adjective iPad to the modern all-screen era. It’s a shame it only supports the new Magic Keyboard Folio and not also the Magic Keyboard and Smart Keyboard Folio, and a bit frustrating that it pairs only with the first-gen Apple Pencil. But it’s an outstanding iPad for anyone looking to spend less than the price of an iPad Air or Pro, and feels designed for the future.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2022-10-26">
<p>Apple sent me a new 12.9-inch iPad Pro to test too, but my review of that model fits in this footnote: the M2 chip is about 15 percent faster than the previous version’s M1, and the new exclusive-to-the-2022-iPads-Pro hover effect for Apple Pencil is fun and cool and I think will prove indispensable to artists who draw on iPads.</p>
<p>Why are the new iPad Pros mere speed bump updates, rather than more significant ones? Perhaps this was the plan all along — all-new hardware designs take years to develop and produce. But these new 2022 M2 iPad Pros are based on a hardware design from 2018, so the physical dimensions are unchanged in four years. So I sort of suspect that this might be a downwind effect of COVID — work from home, greatly reduced travel between California and China, and the global supply chain congestion. I.e. that if not for COVID and all the chaos that ensued, we’d have been due for a new iPad Pro design in 2022, but instead, it’s been postponed. But Apple very much wants to keep the iPad Pros up to date with M-series chips, so, this year, it’s just a speed bump. That’s just purely conjecture on my part though.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2022-10-26"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2022-10-26">
<p>As is my wont, I wrote the entirety of the first draft of this review on the iPad itself, using the Magic Keyboard Folio. And as I always find, writing on an iPad is a great way to focus my attention on just one piece of long-form writing. It’s obvious why so many authors <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Cj_tRjzLvA4/">swear by them</a>. But — for me, with my Mac-ingrained habits and expertise — it’s a lousy, unproductive way to do everything else I typically do on a workday: writing shorter Linked List posts, reading and dealing with dozens of Safari tabs, looking at Twitter, reading and sending email and iMessages, etc. Going back to my Mac to catch up on everything else <em>other</em> than writing this article feels as liberating as taking off a pair of mittens while attempting to assemble a Lego kit. And even for the writing of this article, I’ve seldom gone more than a few minutes between missing some sort of utility or custom tool/script I rely upon on MacOS and which can’t be replicated on iPadOS. Using any iPad for my work feels like riding a bicycle uphill; using a Mac feels like riding one downhill. The best it gets for me on iPad is feeling like the slope isn’t too steep, but it <em>always</em> feels like pedaling uphill to some degree. Your mileage, of course, may vary — it’s folly to ignore the fact that some people find themselves <em>more</em> productive, or perhaps just more comfortable, on an iPad than a Mac or Windows PC. But not me.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2022-10-26"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn3-2022-10-26">
<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/2020/04/the_ipad_magic_keyboard">My review of the Magic Keyboard from April 2020</a> stands up very well, but I wish I’d complained about these mismatched bracket keys then. This mismatched key cap layout is so obviously wrong I just assumed it wouldn’t happen again.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr3-2022-10-26"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The 2022 iPad (and a Wee Note About the 2022 iPad Pros)</title></entry><entry>
	<title>Joanna Stern Interviews Federighi and Joz at WSJ Tech Live</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://twitter.com/WSJ/status/1585100274657419264">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufh">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/26/stern-federighi-joz">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39437</id>
	<published>2022-10-26T14:58:35Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-27T16:43:11Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>The bit that’s getting <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/10/26/apple-confirms-iphone-to-get-usb-c-charging-to-comply-with-eu-law.html">all</a> the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/10/26/23423977/iphone-usb-c-eu-law-joswiak-confirms-compliance-lightning">attention</a> is Joz’s “Obviously we’ll have to comply” remark about EU regulations mandating a USB-C port on phones starting at the end of 2024. I encourage you to make time to watch the whole interview — it’s really good, and it’s only 35 minutes long. But if you only watch one bit, <a href="https://twitter.com/JoannaStern/status/1585253746375737344">watch Joz’s two-minute answer to that question</a>. It’s far more nuanced than just “Obviously we’ll have to comply.”</p>

<p>(Also worth enjoying Federighi’s subtle chuckle at the question, because he knows answering that one is Joz’s problem.)</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m-ugwoEOMvg">Now available on YouTube</a>, too.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Joanna Stern Interviews Federighi and Joz at WSJ Tech Live’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/26/stern-federighi-joz">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>The Talk Show: ‘Neither Fish Nor Fowl’</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/thetalkshow/2022/10/25/ep-360">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/uff">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/25/the-talk-show-360">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39435</id>
	<published>2022-10-25T22:13:18Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-25T22:13:18Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Jason Snell returns to the show to talk about the new 10th-gen iPad and M2 iPads Pro.</p>

<p>Sponsored by:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://linode.com/thetalkshow">Linode</a>: Instantly deploy and manage an SSD server in the Linode Cloud. New accounts get $100 credit.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.drinktrade.com/thetalkshow">Trade Coffee</a>: Incredible coffee delivered fresh from the best roasters in the nation.</li>
<li><a href="http://indochino.com/">Indochino</a>: Made for you. Promo code: <strong>thetalkshow</strong>.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.backblaze.com/thetalkshow">Backblaze</a>: Backblaze makes backing up and accessing your data astonishingly easy.</li>
</ul>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘The Talk Show: ‘Neither Fish Nor Fowl’’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/25/the-talk-show-360">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Kolide</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://l.kolide.co/3yPxU2f">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufe">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/24/kolide">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39434</id>
	<published>2022-10-25T02:38:14Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-25T02:38:15Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>My thanks to Kolide for sponsoring last week at DF. Kolide is endpoint security and fleet management that takes a different approach from draconian MDMs. They help customers meet their compliance goals — whether for auditors, customers, or leadership — by enlisting the support of end users. Kolide works by notifying your employees of security issues via Slack, educating them on why these issues are important, and giving them step-by-step instructions to resolve them themselves.</p>

<p>For IT admins, Kolide helps you prove compliance via a single dashboard. From there, you can monitor the security of your entire fleet, whether they’re running on Mac, Windows, or Linux. (That’s right: Kolide can <a href="https://l.kolide.co/3PadCFV">finally provide visibility into your Linux users</a>.)</p>

<p><a href="https://l.kolide.co/3yPxU2f">Sign up for a free trial with no credit card required</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Kolide’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/24/kolide">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
	<title>Tim Cook Waved the Checkered Flag at the U.S. Grand Prix in Austin</title>
	<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.roadandtrack.com/news/a41752660/tim-cook-technically-waved-the-checkered-flag-at-the-usgp/">
	<link rel="shorturl" type="text/html" href="http://df4.us/ufd">
	<link rel="related" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/24/cook-usgp-checkered-flag">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022:/linked//6.39433</id>
	<published>2022-10-24T20:08:51Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-25T03:48:30Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/linked/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>I don’t know why people are <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/funny/comments/ybyheq/tim_cook_needs_to_settle_down_with_that_checkered/">poking fun</a> at Cook’s flag-waving enthusiasm. This <em>is</em> Tim Cook when he’s very excited.</p>

<p>(Whole thing does make me wonder if it’s a sign that Apple is close to inking a deal to stream Formula 1 races on Apple TV. <strong>Update, Minutes Later:</strong> Welp, so much for that idea — <a href="https://variety.com/2022/tv/news/espn-formula-sports-rights-deal-exte-1235411754/">Disney subsidiary ESPN just this weekend renewed the rights through 2025</a> for a <a href="https://www.sportico.com/business/media/2022/f1-and-disney-renew-for-255m-in-play-to-rev-up-espn-subs-1234692304/">purported</a> $85M per year.)</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Ah, now it makes sense. I had forgotten that back in June, <a href="https://www.apple.com/tv-pr/news/2022/06/apple-original-films-lands-formula-one-racing-feature-from-joseph-kosinski-plan-b-entertainment-and-jerry-bruckheimer-films-starring-brad-pitt/">Apple Original Films landed a Formula 1 major motion picture</a>, from director Joseph Kosinski (<em>Top Gun: Maverick</em>) and starring Brad Pitt. It’s <a href="https://variety.com/2022/film/news/brad-pitt-formula-one-racing-movie-apple-1235287135/#!">being pitched as <em>Top Gun: Maverick</em> on a race track</a>, in terms of verisimilitude and a visceral cinematic sense of speed and danger. <a href="https://www.statesman.com/picture-gallery/entertainment/2022/10/21/brad-pitt-movies-f-1-formula-one-austin-lewis-hamilton-mclaren-photos/10565425002/">Pitt was in attendance at the U.S. Grand Prix as well</a>.</p>

<div>
<a  title="Permanent link to ‘Tim Cook Waved the Checkered Flag at the U.S. Grand Prix in Austin’"  href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/24/cook-usgp-checkered-flag">&nbsp;★&nbsp;</a>
</div>

	]]></content>
  </entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/the_ipad_lineup_is_like_growing_out_its_bangs_or_something">
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/uf8">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022://1.39428</id>
	<published>2022-10-22T02:38:44Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-22T20:28:56Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">So the iPad lineup as of this week — including accessories — isn’t where anyone would want it to be.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>Let’s see if I’ve got every crooked detail straight from this week’s Apple product updates.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2022/10/apple-introduces-the-powerful-next-generation-apple-tv-4k/">On the Apple TV front</a>, the news is (almost) all good and the lineup actually makes <em>more</em> sense now. Apple has finally dropped the long-outdated 1080p Apple TV and now sells just two models, at reasonable prices: a 64 GB model for $130, and a 128 GB one for $150. Both now have the A15 chip that debuted in last year’s iPhone 13 lineup. The $130 model doesn’t have an Ethernet port and doesn’t support <a href="https://www.threadgroup.org/What-is-Thread/Thread-Benefits">Thread wireless networking</a> — the open protocol for smart home gadgets backed by Matter. The Ethernet port I can see. But I wish both models supported Thread. And we finally have a dead canary in the “<em>Is the iPhone switching from Lightning to USB-C next year?</em>” coal mine: the Apple TV Remote now charges via USB-C. (The remote is otherwise unchanged — including no support for Find My, alas, which is disappointing for the one Apple product I most frequently misplace.)</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2022/10/apple-unveils-completely-redesigned-ipad-in-four-vibrant-colors/">new 10th-generation (no adjective) iPad</a> moves to the modern <em>all-screen / no-home-button</em> design style. It gets the A14 chip that debuted with the iPhone 12 lineup two years ago, and has Touch ID on its side button. It comes in some pretty fun colors — yellow, pink, and blue — along with plain old silver. It looks a lot like the 5th-gen iPad Air that debuted in March this year, with one very significant difference: Apple moved the front-facing camera to the long (“landscape”) side, which positions the camera correctly when docked to a keyboard — which is exactly how most people who rely on the front-facing iPad cameras want to use them. And, like all the other <em>all-screen / no-home-button</em> iPads, it moves from Lightning to USB-C — but, bizarrely (on first consideration at least), is compatible only with the Apple Pencil 1, which has a male Lightning plug that is required both for charging the Pencil <em>and</em> pairing it with an iPad. So Apple now sells <a href="https://www.apple.com/shop/product/MQLU3AM/A/usb-c-to-apple-pencil-adapter">a $9 USB-C to Lightning adapter</a> — with female ports on both sides — just for using an Apple Pencil 1 with these new iPads. (The adapter will henceforth be included in the box with new Pencil 1’s.)</p>

<p>The new 10th-gen iPads do not replace the home-button/square-corner-display 9th-gen iPads, because the new iPads cost $450 for 64 GB and $600 for 256 GB. Thus the 9th-gen iPads remain, unchanged in price at $330 for 64 GB and $480 for 256 GB. It makes sense if you now think of the 9th-gen iPad as the iPad SE — just without the “SE” name. The SE name stands for “older hardware design at the lowest price in the lineup”. That’s the 9th-gen iPad now.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2022/10/apple-introduces-next-generation-ipad-pro-supercharged-by-the-m2-chip/">new 12.9-inch and 11-inch iPad Pros</a> go from the M1 to M2 chips, and gain an intriguing new ability when used with a Pencil: hovering. Put the Pencil tip within about 1 cm of the display (12 mm, to be precise) and Pencil-supporting apps can detect it and use it to present hover effects. This seems very clever. But otherwise nothing else has changed. It’s still the case that only the 12.9-inch iPad Pro has the superior mini-LED display (“XDR” in Apple parlance). More bizarrely, the front-facing cameras are still on the short (portrait) side, and thus are still awkwardly placed when the iPad Pro is docked in a keyboard, laptop-style. This, despite the fact that professional users are the iPad users who likely spend the most time in Zoom meetings.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.apple.com/ipad-keyboards/">On the iPad keyboard front</a>, the new 10th-gen iPad is not compatible with the Magic Keyboard used by the 11-inch iPad Pro and the iPad Air. Instead, Apple introduced a new product: the $250 Magic Keyboard Folio. It’s a two-part cover that depends on a kickstand on the back panel, which means it requires a flat surface (i.e. not your lap) and a deep amount of footprint space, such that it surely won’t fit on an airplane or train seatback tray. But its keyboard does have a function key row, including an Esc key. But as with the front-facing camera placement, I’d argue that it’s <em>professional</em> users who most use Esc, yet Apple’s iPad Pro keyboards — the $300/$350 Magic Keyboard and $180/$200 Smart Keyboard Folio (for the 11″/12.9″ iPad Pros, respectively) — are unchanged, and thus un-Esc-able.</p>

<hr />

<p>So the iPad lineup as of this week — including accessories — isn’t where anyone would want it to be.</p>

<p>The front-facing cameras ought to all be on the long side. <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2021/03/29/apple-planned-ipad-with-two-ports/">Whatever debate there was over this</a> 10 years ago when the iPad was new, it’s settled in today’s world of iPad-as-laptop keyboards and ubiquitous teleconferencing for meetings. But here we are with brand-new iPad Pros that <em>still</em> have the cameras on the short side. </p>

<p>There ought to be just one Apple Pencil. But here we are with a truly all-new no-adjective iPad that still supports only the Pencil 1, despite the fact that the new iPad has a USB-C port yet Pencil 1 uses Lightning both for charging and pairing, thus necessitating an awkward and easily lost $9 dongle.<sup id="fnr1-2022-10-21"><a href="#fn1-2022-10-21">1</a></sup></p>

<p>In an ideal world, all 11-ish-inch iPads would support the same keyboard accessories. But here we are, with the new 10th-gen iPad only supporting the new Magic Keyboard Folio and the iPad Pro and iPad Air only supporting the Magic Keyboard. (Those latter two iPads also support the no-trackpad Smart Keyboard Folio, but I honestly have no idea who buys that thing other than people who’ve never tried iPadOS with a trackpad and thus have no idea how fun and useful it is. [<strong>Update, One Day Later:</strong> <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/10/22/in-praise-of-smart-keyboard-folio">It’s about how much lighter it is</a>.])</p>

<p>These frustrations mostly do make sense, though, when considering the current lineup as only a snapshot in time.</p>

<p>The front-facing cameras on the iPad Pro will — I bet with the <em>next</em> revision — move to the long side. But new hardware designs take time, and they surely take even more time during a pandemic that restricted both in-person collaboration and travel between California and China. Sometimes you just get a chip speed bump, and this generation of iPads Pro is one of those times. If you really want an iPad Pro with the camera on the long side, sit this cycle out. The M3 is probably only a year away.</p>

<p>Pencil 2 support requires significant internal components to support pairing and charging the Pencil inductively. That’s a significant factor in the $150 price difference between the new 10th-gen iPad and the iPad Air. And if the decision came down to moving the new iPad to USB-C and requiring a dongle for Pencil 1 support, or sticking with a Lightning port <em>just to support Pencil 1</em>, Apple made the right call. Better a dongle for the Pencil than another generation of iPads on Lightning. It’s also the case that schools are major buyers of low-priced iPads, and thus are major owners of fleets of Pencil 1’s. “The 10th-gen iPads still work with Pencil 1” is a feature, not a shortcoming, for schools.<sup id="fnr2-2022-10-21"><a href="#fn2-2022-10-21">2</a></sup></p>

<p>The one that I just don’t get, though, is the keyboard accessory schism. I don’t see why the new iPads couldn’t have been designed to work with the Magic Keyboard. And if there’s a market for the new two-piece Magic Keyboard Folio in addition to the cantilever-hinged Magic Keyboard, why couldn’t it have been designed as an option that worked with the iPad Air and 11-inch iPad Pro, too?</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2022-10-21">
<p>Here’s a spitball: Maybe my front-facing-camera-placement and all-iPads-should-support-Pencil-2 gripes are in conflict. The long side where the new iPad has the front-facing camera is the same long side where the iPad Pros, iPad Air, and iPad Mini have the magnetic attachment point for the Pencil 2. Maybe they both can’t fit in the middle of the same side?&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2022-10-21"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn2-2022-10-21">
<p>It’s also worth noting that <a href="https://www.apple.com/shop/product/HQ6Q2VC/A/logitech-crayon-for-ipad">Logitech has a new version of their $70 Crayon</a> — a Pencil alternative developed in conjunction with Apple. Their Crayon 2 charges via USB-C and supports all iPads from 2018 onward, and, like their original Crayon, doesn’t require pairing. The biggest downside compared to Apple’s Pencils is that the Crayon isn’t pressure sensitive.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2022-10-21"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The iPad Lineup Is, Like, Growing Out Its Bangs or Something and Looks a Little Weird Right Now, but Apple TV Has Been Going to the Gym and Looks Great</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/10/everything">
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ue3">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022://1.39387</id>
	<published>2022-10-06T22:33:56Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-18T01:16:36Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">What we need isn’t an everything app. It’s an everything *device*, with small focused apps for features.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1577428272056389633">Elon Musk, in a tweet</a> (of course):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Buying Twitter is an accelerant to creating X, the everything app.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/karaswisher/status/1577497268118519809">Kara Swisher explains</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>He is essentially talking about a “super app,” which is common in
China but not the U.S. and might include payments, subscriptions,
entertainment etc. It’s the right idea but hard to pull off. Also,
X is the name of his first significant company back in the day.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t think I’d say the <em>idea</em> is common in China — just WeChat, specifically. And while I agree it’s “hard to pull off”, I vehemently disagree that it’s “the right idea”.</p>

<p><a href="https://stratechery.com/company/tencent/wechat/">Ben Thompson has written extensively</a> about WeChat’s impossible-to-overstate dominant role in China. In China, WeChat is <em>the</em> way to chat, <em>the</em> way to share photos, <em>the</em> way to pay for things with your phone, and a lot more. Back in 2015, Connie Chan of Andreessen Horowitz wrote a great piece explaining WeChat’s expansive domain, and if anything, WeChat’s dominance inside China has only grown since then. Her headline says it all: “<a href="https://a16z.com/2015/08/06/wechat-china-mobile-first/">When One App Rules Them All: The Case of WeChat and Mobile in China</a>”.</p>

<p>It’s no coincidence at all that WeChat is the only “everything app” anyone can cite, and it comes from China, an authoritarian regime. In practice, the concept really only makes sense there. It doesn’t benefit users that WeChat dominates all aspects of digital life — it benefits the authoritarian Chinese Communist Party. (And investors in Tencent, WeChat’s Chinese-government-controlled parent company.)</p>

<p>If you’re just spitballing wild ideas, it’s easy to get enthralled by such an idea. But give it any serious thought whatsoever and it starts falling apart. What you’re talking about is putting an entire OS inside an app. Not a computer science operating system but a user-facing <em>system</em> for “everything”. That’s certainly possible — WeChat proves it — but history shows that sprawling monolithic apps are never a good experience in practice. It is really hard to present a coherent, consistent, intuitive, explorable user interface for features as disparate as chat, news, entertainment, and payments. But we have such interfaces: OSes.</p>

<p>And as much as we all have pet peeves about the design cohesiveness of our current OSes, who looks at <em>Twitter</em> of all things and says “<em>I’d like to see</em> this <em>expand in scope such that a lot more, if not all, of my digital life can be here</em>”? Twitter, today, is already more confusing and less cohesive than the iOS or Android systems themselves. Both iOS and Android are actually both <em>really</em> good at offering interfaces for, well, everything. What Twitter needs is to do <em>less</em>, certainly not <em>more</em>. Would you buy a phone that only ran Twitter, even if Twitter added a lot more features? That’s the sort of vague thinking that led to <a href="https://www.cnet.com/tech/mobile/heres-why-the-facebook-phone-flopped/">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2014/7/22/5923697/amazon-fire-phone-review">Amazon</a> creating their own phones in the early years of the mobile revolution. Facebook and Amazon are both very effective, technically capable companies, and they failed, badly, at this a decade ago. Twitter is ineffective and <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/08/24/twitter-mudge">technically suspect</a>.</p>

<p>I hope we’re not done creating major new software platforms for consumer devices. But as time marches on, it grows ever more unlikely we’ll ever see a new rival to MacOS and Windows for desktops, or to iOS and Android for phones. The next frontiers, the next opportunities for a new OS, will almost certainly come with new hardware paradigms. Windows’s monopoly over all of computing was broken up not by an upstart PC operating system, but by an upstart hardware concept: the mobile phone as personal computer.</p>

<p>I genuinely wonder, though, whether we’re not still in the very early years — the early decades, perhaps — of phones as the dominant, if not only, computing devices in our lives. <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/radio-shack-ad_b_4612973">There’s a wonderful piece Steve Cichon wrote for the Huffington Post back in 2014</a>, after paging through some old newspapers from 1991:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The back page of the front section on Saturday, February 16, 1991
was four-fifths covered with a Radio Shack ad. There are 15
electronic gizmo type items on this page, being sold from
America’s Technology Store. 13 of the 15 you now always have in
your pocket.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Smartphones replaced everything Radio Shack sold 30 years ago: still cameras, video cameras, music players, radios, alarm clocks, calculators, tape recorders, and, yes, cellular dumbphones. (One of the advertised items Cichon cites as <em>not</em> being replaced by a 2014 smartphone was a radar detector — but today’s major mapping apps for turn-by-turn directions all warn about speed traps now.)</p>

<p>What we need isn’t an everything app. It’s an everything <em>device</em>, with small focused apps for features. You want to do more? Download — or better yet, create — a new app. And you’ve already got one in your pocket — or in your hand, as you read this very sentence on it — right now.</p>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Everything</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/09/apple_watch_ultra">
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/udf">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022://1.39363</id>
	<published>2022-09-21T21:29:37Z</published>
	<updated>2022-10-22T15:12:04Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">It *almost* feels more like having an adorable little iPhone Nano strapped to my wrist than a huge Apple Watch.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>If Apple Watch Ultra were the first (and thus only) Apple Watch, people would lose their minds. It’s big and very unsubtle. It makes a statement on the wrist.</p>

<p>But the Ultra is <em>not</em> the first Apple Watch. We’re eight generations in with the Series lineup. If anything, arguably Apple is overdue to offer something like the Ultra: an entirely different expression of what an Apple Watch can be. Ultra is definitely not for everyone. But it is also definitely <em>for</em> a lot of people.</p>

<p>I’ve neither dived nor climbed nor gotten lost nor really done anything a damn bit dangerous or exciting, but I’ve had a lot of fun wearing it for the last week.</p>

<p>Here’s a thing I’ve learned over the years as a somewhat serious watch enthusiast. A lot of people are very self conscious about wearing a large or even large-ish watch. “<em>I’ve got small wrists, I don’t know if I can pull it off</em>” is a sentiment expressed dozens of times per day, every day, on watch forums the world over. But it’s almost never the case that you, the wearer, look bad wearing a too-big watch. It’s that the watch itself looks too big. It’s the watch, not the wearer. But we humans are self-conscious beings, and a first-person perspective of your own wrist is not at all like the perspective of others looking at your wrist.</p>

<p>What I’m saying here is that if you go to a store and try on an Apple Watch Ultra, there is a very good chance your reaction is going to be “This is way too big for me.” If you’re thinking that because <em>you</em> don’t like the way it looks, well, then Ultra is not for you. Your watch should make you happy every time you look at it. But if you’re thinking “this is too big for me” because you’re worried about how <em>others</em> will think it looks on your wrist, you’re overthinking it. If you like it, wear it. People — men and women alike — with even small wrists can get away with surprisingly large watches. Buy the watch that makes <em>you</em> happy. That’s my advice for any watch.</p>

<p>If you’ve got large wrists, on the other hand, you might try on Apple Watch Ultra and react, “Finally.”</p>

<p>With the Series, uh, <em>series</em> of Apple Watch models, we’ve always and only had two sizes. Over the model generations, those sizes have been described by Apple in ever-increasing sizes:</p>

<ul>
<li>38/42mm (Series 0–3)</li>
<li>40/44mm (Series 4–6)</li>
<li>41/45mm (Series 7–8 and counting)</li>
</ul>

<p>From a subjective perspective though, these watches have been the same sizes: smaller and larger. Side-by-side, a new Series 8 41mm watch looks the same size as an original Series 0 38mm one, and a new Series 8 45mm looks the same size as an original 42mm model. This is most evident in the fact that the straps and bands made for the original Apple Watch still fit the Series 8 models, and vice-versa.</p>

<p>Even though there have been two sizes of Apple Watch cases from the get-go, the WatchOS experience on-screen has been unified. If you wear the smaller Apple Watch, you get the same on-screen experience as on the larger models, just scaled to fit the smaller display.</p>

<p>Apple Watch Ultra feels like a different size class entirely. For the most part, though, you get the same on-screen content from WatchOS as on the regular Series models. You just see more at a time, like when reading a text message or email. There is one watch face unique to Ultra, <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2022/09/apple-watch-ultra-wayfinder.jpeg">the Wayfinder face</a> that Apple is using in most promotional and marketing photos. But all the other WatchOS watch faces are more or less the same on Ultra, just scaled bigger.</p>

<p>The Ultra is thus not akin to the iPhone X — a dramatically new design that heralded the future of the entire platform. The rest of the Apple Watch lineup is not going to evolve in an Ultra-like direction in the coming years. But the larger and (for the first time on Apple Watch) perfectly flat display crystal gives it a different feel while using it. It’s unabashedly a computer on your wrist. The Calculator app, for the first time, feels perfectly usable without pecking at the buttons with particular care. The on-screen QWERTY keyboard that Apple added last year to WatchOS 8 is surprisingly usable. Switching between, say a 41mm and 45mm Series 8 feels like the same experience, just scaled differently. Switching between a 45mm Series 8 and the Apple Watch Ultra feels <em>different</em>, not just bigger.</p>

<p>Titanium is a remarkable material. I’ve been wearing the Ultra full-time for just short of a week, and every time I put it on, I expect it to be a lot heavier than it is. There’s no getting around the fact that the Ultra <em>looks</em> big. But it does not <em>feel</em> heavy on the wrist. The case surface has a different finish than the Series 5–7 models that were offered in titanium. On those Series models, the titanium surface had a brushed finish. On the Ultra, it has a sort of textured finish. <em>Micro-pebbled</em> perhaps describes it. It’s definitely not perfectly smooth, let alone polished, but it’s also just as definitely not brushed. However the texture is best described, it very much befits a rugged sports watch. It feels good and in my opinion looks good.</p>

<p>The lip surrounding the display crystal is raised, but not by much. Perhaps by the thickness of an index card.</p>

<p>The orange accent color of the Action button and Digital Crown are a delightfully opinionated touch. (You can get your Action button in whatever color you want, so long as it’s international orange.) The larger Digital Crown with far more pronounced knurling is a delight to twist. Good resistance, great haptic feedback.</p>

<p>The Action button is, functionally, the biggest difference between the Ultra and the Series models. <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/09/thoughts_and_observations_on_last_weeks_far_out_apple_event">As I wrote last week</a>, an extra button is a big addition to a device that heretofore only had two, and even moreso given that the Action button is the first hardware button on Apple Watch that’s user-configurable at the system level and can be assigned app-specific functions by third-party developers. The Digital Crown and side button are controlled by the system.<sup id="fnr1-2022-09-21"><a href="#fn1-2022-09-21">1</a></sup> The Action button is controlled by the user, via a new top-level section in Settings. Options for what happens when you press the button:</p>

<ul>
<li>Workout</li>
<li>Stopwatch</li>
<li>Waypoint</li>
<li>Backtrack</li>
<li>Dive</li>
<li>Flashlight</li>
<li>Shortcut</li>
</ul>

<p>On the watch itself, you just get to change which of these actions the button performs. To configure them — say, to choose <em>which</em> Workout to start, or <em>which</em> Shortcut to run — you need to use the Watch app on your paired iPhone. Unadventurous me has, thus far, assigned the Action button to the stopwatch, flashlight, and Shortcuts. I’ve found the flashlight and Shortcuts options the most useful (mainly because, if I want quick access to the stopwatch, I’ve always been able to add a stopwatch complication to a watch face). Assigning a shortcut to the button has infinite potential, but it sure seems to take Shortcuts a long time to launch them on WatchOS. The flashlight is surprisingly useful, which speaks to how bright the Ultra’s 2,000-nit-max display can be. (The Series 8 and SE displays have a maximum brightness of 1,000 nits.)</p>

<p>There’s also a toggle (on by default) to press-and-hold the Action button to activate the (surprisingly loud) siren. </p>

<p>One learning-curve issue with the Action button is that at first, you can inadvertently press both the Action and side buttons when you only intend to press one or the other. If you squeeze them at the same time, the Action button wins out. It’s a muscle-memory thing though, and I quickly adapted my grip on the watch when trying to press either button, so as not to press both.</p>

<p>A week wearing an Apple Watch Ultra makes me wish the Series models had an Action button too. Why not? Three total buttons is <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2022/09/13/casio-pro-trek">not a lot of buttons</a> for a digital watch.</p>

<h2>Bands</h2>

<p>Apple continues to excel with original watch strap design and engineering. My review unit kit included two of <a href="https://www.apple.com/shop/watch/bands/apple-watch-ultra">the three new straps designed specifically for Apple Watch Ultra</a>: the nylon Alpine Loop, in both orange and green, and the “high performance elastomer” (read: very nice rubber) Ocean Band, in yellow.</p>

<p>The Alpine Loop comes in three lengths; Apple sent me both large (orange) and medium (green). The large strap fits me, but the medium fits me better. What you want with a strap like the Alpine Loop is for the G-shaped buckle — which, of course, is made of titanium with the same finish as the Ultra watch case — to fall on the underside of your wrist, opposite the watch. If it’s too long — as the size large is on my wrist — you can still fasten the strap, but you wind up with a double layer of strap almost all the way around your wrist.</p>

<p>The Ocean Band is nice, and is one size fits all. (There’s an optional extra-long bottom piece meant for fitting over a diving wetsuit.) It also sports titanium hardware for the buckle and cleverly adjustable keeper. I find it to be very comfortable, particularly because the rubber has a nice stretch to it. The shade of yellow on the one Apple provided me is a little Big Bird-y to my eyes. I’d like to see the Ocean Band in orange.</p>

<p>Given how much larger the Ultra case is, it’s a very nice touch that it still shares the same-size strap connector slot as the 42/44/45mm Series watches. I’ve tried a few of the bands from my 45mm collection on the Ultra, and I’ve tried the new designed-for-Ultra bands on my Series 7 and the Series 8 review unit Apple sent me. They all fit each other, but to my eyes, “regular” 45mm straps look better on the Ultra than the designed-for-Ultra 49mm straps look on a Series watch. A regular 45mm strap on the Ultra just looks a bit narrow and tapered. It looks like you’re dressing the Ultra up by slimming the strap down. The 49mm straps look too wide on a 45mm watch. There’s no accounting for taste in watch straps, though.</p>

<p>There’s a long tradition in dive watches of metal bracelets. <a href="https://www.rolex.com/en-us/watches/submariner.html">The Rolex Submariner</a> — the most iconic of dive watches — comes exclusively on bracelets that match the material of the case (stainless steel or gold). Apple’s <a href="https://www.apple.com/shop/watch/bands/stainless-steel">stainless steel Link Bracelets</a> are among the few original Apple Watch bands the company still makes, but they don’t get much attention. I own the space black Link Bracelet — it’s the one that came with my Series 0 watch, and thanks to the DLC coating, it still looks almost as good as new. I kind of dig the way it looks attached to the Ultra — the space black bracelet and untinted titanium case make for a nice contrast. It plays.</p>

<p><a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2022/09/ultra-space-black-link.jpeg" class="noborder">
  <img
    width = 525
    src="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2022/09/ultra-space-black-link.jpeg"
    alt="Apple Watch Ultra, paired with a space black Link Bracelet."
  /></a></p>

<p>I don’t own the silver link bracelet to try it, but I suspect it <em>doesn’t</em> play paired with the Ultra. Brushed stainless steel and titanium are too different to be considered a match, but too similar to have deliberate contrast. I wish Apple were committed enough to the Link Bracelet to make a new one in titanium to match the case of the Ultra. (I also hope that future generations of Apple Watch Ultra are available with a space gray or black coating.)</p>

<h2>Battery Life</h2>

<p>According to Apple, the Ultra case is 34 percent bigger by volume than the 45mm Series 8, but the battery inside the Ultra is 76 percent bigger. I think this is mostly because titanium’s high strength allows the Ultra case to have more room inside than if it were made from aluminum or steel. Regardless of the reasons, battery life on the Ultra is, as promised, seemingly double that of a Series model. 24 hours after a full charge, it has still had between 45–50 percent remaining. And — see below — I’ve been wearing it to sleep.</p>

<h2>Wayfinder Face</h2>

<p>The Ultra-exclusive Wayfinder watch face uses distinctive typographic features of the San Francisco font family. Numerals have alternative glyphs (crossed <em>0</em>, <em>1</em> with bottom bars, open-topped <em>4</em>, and alternative designs for the <em>6</em> and <em>9</em>), and the uppercase <em>I</em> has bars. It’s a neat look that befits the Ultra’s rugged, sporty brand image.</p>

<p>By default, Wayfinder starts with 8 complications — 4 in the display corners, and 4 inside the analog dial. Like the Infograph face, that’s a lot of information, if you want it. Personally, I find the in-dial complications distracting, so I removed all the in-dial complications other than the date. It’s my favorite face for the Ultra, and might be my second-favorite Apple Watch face overall. (Utility remains my favorite for the Series models.)</p>

<p>Wayfinder has a Night Mode feature that isn’t available on any other watch face. Twist the Digital Crown and the dial changes from full color to <a href="https://daringfireball.net/misc/2022/09/apple-watch-ultra-red-on-black.png">red-on-black</a>, a retina-friendly color scheme in dark lighting. Night Mode looks cool, and I wish other watch faces (for all Apple Watch models) had this ability.<sup id="fnr2-2022-09-21"><a href="#fn2-2022-09-21">2</a></sup></p>

<h2>Temperature and Crash Detection Sensors</h2>

<p>I’ve been fortunate so far not to have any experience with crash detection. Glad it’s there, though. (I asked Apple, and if you’re in a car crash while wearing a new Apple Watch <em>and</em> carrying an iPhone 14, if both devices detect the crash, they’ll communicate with each other and place just one emergency call.)</p>

<p>The flagship feature for the thermometer is retroactive ovulation prediction, which is a fantastic feature for women. When HealthKit debuted in 2014, it was <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2014/9/25/6844021/apple-promised-an-expansive-health-app-so-why-cant-i-track">controversial that it didn’t include menstruation tracking</a> as a feature. Now we have an entire generation of Apple Watch hardware with temperature sensors whose primary purpose is ovulation prediction.</p>

<p>The temperature sensors do work for everyone, though. But not in the sense of a normal “<em>What’s my body temperature right now?</em>” thermometer. If you wear your Apple Watch Series 8 or Ultra to sleep, <em>and</em> use the explicit Sleep Focus mode, after five nights you should see data appear in the Health app under “Wrist Temperature”. <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT213275">Apple’s documentation explains this in detail</a>, and has a screenshot showing what the data should look like in Health. I do like wearing an Apple Watch to sleep, because I can see it in the dark, and I’m vaguely interested in the basic gist of my sleep patterns. But I do not like or want to explicitly put it into Sleep Mode when I go to bed. For one thing, Sleep Mode turns the entire watch face off; to check the time in the middle of the night, you need to twist the digital crown or tap the display for an extended moment. I just want to blearily glance at the watch. For another thing, I find it fiddly to need to “do something” before I nod off, like putting the watch into a specific mode.<sup id="fnr3-2022-09-21"><a href="#fn3-2022-09-21">3</a></sup> It would be a significant improvement for future generations of Apple Watch if the wrist thermometer were like the other health sensors and just worked all the time. This initial thermometer is better than nothing, but seems like a stopgap.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>I’m tempted to make the following analogy: Apple Watch Ultra is to the Series watch models as the first iPad was to the iPhone. That analogy is an exaggeration, though — the Ultra is bigger, but it’s not <em>that</em> much bigger.</p>

<p>As I wrote at the outset, it’s good that the Ultra isn’t the first and only Apple Watch. It’s too big (and too expensive) for most people’s tastes and needs. But it’s not <em>that</em> big. It’ll look big and chunky on smaller wrists, but I saw several women trying it out in the hands-on area after its introduction, and it totally works as a big and chunky women’s watch. It’s also not <em>that</em> expensive for a titanium watch packing a lot of technology inside — GPS, cellular networking, Bluetooth, Wi-Fi, compass, a rich library of third-party apps, and all the various health sensors. But I can’t shake the feeling that if Apple Watch Ultra <em>were</em> the one and only Apple Watch, WatchOS would allow it to do more. In the way that iPad, to this day, has seemed hamstrung by the fact that iOS is designed first and foremost for iPhones, the Ultra seems limited by the fact that WatchOS is designed first and foremost for the Series models.</p>

<p>If WatchOS allowed it, I think one could credibly use Apple Watch Ultra as their only cellular device. It’s not going to happen, but that’s because I can’t imagine ever seeing Apple launch a “<em>Who needs an iPhone?</em>” marketing campaign. But if some other company could make a watch with Ultra’s feature set, cellular capabilities, and battery life, I think they <em>would</em> pitch it as an alternative to carrying a smartphone. You want to cut down on your screen time? Cut down your cell phone to the size of a large watch. The biggest missing feature would be a camera. Very few people have any desire <em>not</em> to carry a modern smartphone with them, of course, but the Ultra seems <em>that</em> capable as a standalone device. The display is that big, the speakers that loud, the battery life that long.</p>

<p>I’ll emphasize again that my analogy to the iPad is exaggerated. But I can’t shake the feeling that I ought to be able to do <em>more</em> with the Ultra. Something about the flat display makes it feel meant to be touched, not just viewed. It <em>almost</em> feels more like having an adorable little iPhone Nano strapped to my wrist than a huge Apple Watch. If WatchOS were more capable and independent, it really could be more of an iPhone Nano.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2022-09-21">
<p>One arguable exception to this is the side button, which can be configured in Settings to pause a workout in the Workout app — e.g. if you want to pause a running workout while waiting at a traffic light. But while that’s a setting in the user’s control, I’d still argue the side button is wholly a system button. Only Workouts — a first-party app from Apple — has the ability to offer this setting.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2022-09-21"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn2-2022-09-21">
<p>I was chatting with <a href="https://www.austinmann.com/">Austin Mann</a> after the keynote event two weeks ago, and he suggested that the Ultra’s red-on-black night mode would be a useful feature for the Camera app on iPhone. That seems like such a clever idea that I couldn’t bring myself to steal it without giving him credit.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2022-09-21"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

<li id="fn3-2022-09-21">
<p>If you just wear an Apple Watch to bed without putting it in Sleep Focus mode, the watch will still collect sleep-related data. I’ve been using <a href="https://david-smith.org/apps/">David Smith</a>’s excellent <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/sleep/id1038440371">Sleep++</a> app to collect and view this data for years. Sleep++ is even more useful if you <em>do</em> use the explicit Sleep Focus mode.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr3-2022-09-21"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ Apple Watch Ultra</title></entry><entry>
    
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://daringfireball.net/2022/09/the_iphones_14_pro">
	<link rel="shorturl" href="http://df4.us/ud3">
	<id>tag:daringfireball.net,2022://1.39351</id>
	<published>2022-09-16T03:59:00Z</published>
	<updated>2022-09-19T23:47:00Z</updated>
	<author>
		<name>John Gruber</name>
		<uri>http://daringfireball.net/</uri>
	</author>
	<summary type="text">There are two super interesting innovations with the iPhone 14 Pro and Pro Max. There aren’t any interesting innovations with the iPhone 14 or 14 Plus — which fact itself is actually pretty interesting, strategically.</summary>
	<content type="html" xml:base="https://daringfireball.net/" xml:lang="en"><![CDATA[
<p>There are two super interesting innovations with the iPhone 14 Pro and Pro Max. There aren’t any interesting innovations with the iPhone 14 or 14 Plus — which fact itself is actually pretty interesting, strategically.</p>

<h2>The Dynamic Island</h2>

<p>The first super interesting thing about the iPhone 14 Pro models is the most obvious. It’s the feature Apple is highlighting, including putting its name on a title card, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WuEH265pUy4">in TV commercials</a> that began running last week. It’s the feature every other major phone maker has, I’ll bet, already assigned teams to rip off.</p>

<p>The best ideas in any creative field often follow a counterintuitive pattern. The ideas are, in fact, original, highly innovative, and spring from very creative minds. But if well-executed — <a href="https://sive.rs/multiply">always a big “if”</a> — once experienced, they seem incredibly obvious. The Dynamic Island is one of those ideas. Not only does the Dynamic Island now strike me as <em>the</em> obvious answer to what should be done with a sensor array cutout in a phone display,<sup id="fnr1-2022-09-15"><a href="#fn1-2022-09-15">1</a></sup> it’s so cool, so fun, so useful that it feels like an obvious reason why you should have a sensor array cutout in a phone display in the first place. When the iPhone X introduced the notch, there were a lot of people who thought Apple should have <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/notcho/id1294836169">hidden it</a> by drawing a black notch-height border across the top of the display. Only a fool would argue that the Dynamic Island would be better off hidden like that.</p>

<p>The Dynamic Island feels like a user interface element that deserves to be there, almost exactly as it looks, <em>even if there were no front-facing sensor cutouts</em>. It’s not merely some clever idea to do <em>something</em> useful with the cutout space, it’s an incredibly clever idea for a permanent on-screen UI for live activities, status, certain notifications, and small interactions. The fact that it completely and elegantly disguises the sensor cutout array is just the icing on the cake. It’s like watching <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i0m8CC7Ovj8">expert sleight-of-hand magicians vanish an object</a>. The fact that you know you’re being fooled makes it even more fun. Dynamic Island is a genius idea and Apple has knocked the initial implementation out of the park.</p>

<p>I’ve been using an iPhone 14 Pro (space black) since last Thursday. One week in and I’m hooked. I have a regular iPhone 14 to test too, and I’m doing side-by-side comparisons with my year-old iPhone 13 Pro, but those phones feel outdated. Inert. Less fun and less useful. The Dynamic Island is that good.</p>

<p>I was walking around in Manhattan yesterday using turn-by-turn directions in Apple Maps and listening to a podcast in <a href="https://overcast.fm/">Overcast</a> and I was keeping track of both, at the same time, while texting in Messages. The interactions are so lightweight it doesn’t feel like multitasking in a traditional sense because it doesn’t feel like you’re doing any context switching. Apple Maps, of course, has been updated to fully support Dynamic Island-specific APIs. Overcast, of course, has not (yet). But because Overcast uses Apple’s existing NowPlaying APIs, and Apple has connected those NowPlaying APIs to the Dynamic Island, Overcast — as well as any other third-party apps that support NowPlaying (just about every major audio playback app) or CallKit (e.g. Skype, WhatsApp, and Google Voice) — get very credible Dynamic Island support for “free”, right now, including audio waveforms. Long-press on Overcast’s minimal view in the Dynamic Island and, with a bit of haptic feedback, it morphs with a delightfully organic animation into an expanded view with playback controls, larger album art, etc. Everything you get in the Lock Screen widget-like view. This expanded view can be used creatively by developers. As suggested last week in Apple’s keynote, a sports app using Live Activities to show the score of a game could use the expanded view to show rich details about the current state of the game. Who’s on base in the Yankees game? How close to another three-and-out punt are the Dallas Cowboys?</p>

<p>These expanded views are like little versions of the apps that just live up there in the Dynamic Island. The Music app on MacOS — née iTunes — has had a miniplayer window right from the start. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?app=desktop&amp;v=qL6QfvFu8fM&amp;t=254">Here’s Steve Jobs demoing it</a> — “Boom”. In Music’s preferences, you can set the miniplayer to float atop all other windows on your desktop, so you can see it and use it even when using other applications. It’s a very new experience on iOS but instantly feels natural and completely unobtrusive.</p>

<p>There are a lot of different ways Apple could have gone with the basic idea of the Dynamic Island. They could have enabled a lot more functionality — made it more like vertical split-screen multitasking. But instead of increasing complexity system-wide, the Dynamic Island increases <em>simplicity</em>. It’s a major new feature but it <em>reduces</em> the cognitive load of using or checking the status of more than one app at a time. “Useful new feature” always sounds good, but new features generally increase complexity. The Dynamic Island is that rare gem that reduces complexity while adding utility.</p>

<p>Here’s a nice touch: When you start playing audio in an app, or initiate a phone or VoIP call, and you swipe up from the bottom of the screen to go to the home screen, the app you’re leaving doesn’t minimize into its home screen icon like it usually would. Instead, the app minimizes <em>into</em> the Dynamic Island, and the Dynamic Island sort of <em>absorbs</em> the app in a very organic animation. The Dynamic Island feels not merely like a shape or dedicated area at the top of the screen, but like a real <em>thing</em> with personality.<sup id="fnr2-2022-09-15"><a href="#fn2-2022-09-15">2</a></sup> I have genuine affection for it already.</p>

<h2>Live Activities Without the Dynamic Island</h2>

<p>As a postscript related to the Dynamic Island, there’s a fascinating and important question that, as I publish this, I’m not sure we know the answer to. To wit: how are all these <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/activitykit/displaying-live-data-with-live-activities">Live Activity features</a> going to work with notched iPhones, including the brand-new iPhone 14 and 14 Plus? Apple is not going to turn the notch into a Dynamic Peninsula. But so where are things like live sports scores or updates on the arrival time for your hailed Uber or Lyft going to be displayed on iPhones other than the 14 Pro models? The answer seems to be that for iPhones without the Dynamic Island — which is to say every iPhone other than the 14 Pro models — <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2022/09/14/apple-live-activities-ios-16-1/">Live Activities will only be viewable on the Lock Screen</a>, or when the app responsible for them sends an update. Without the Dynamic Island, there’s no way for the <em>user</em> to invoke a Live Activity except by pulling down from the top left of the screen to go to the Lock Screen. Here’s what Apple’s <a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/activitykit/displaying-live-data-with-live-activities">developer documentation</a> currently states:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Live Activities come in different views for the Lock Screen and
the Dynamic Island. The Lock Screen view appears on all devices.
Devices that support the Dynamic Island display Live Activities
using the following views: a compact leading view, a compact
trailing view, a minimal view, and an expanded view for the
Dynamic Island.</p>

<p>The expanded view appears when a person touches and holds a
compact or minimal view in the Dynamic Island and when a Live
Activity updates. On an unlocked device that doesn’t support the
Dynamic Island, the expanded view appears as a banner for Live
Activity updates.</p>

<p>To make sure the system can display your Live Activity in each
position, you must support all views.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This means that Dynamic Island isn’t just a cooler-looking presentation of a feature on other iPhones. It’s an entire incredibly useful interaction model <em>and</em> set of features that are exclusive to the iPhone 14 Pro and Pro Max. If this remains the case, I’d say that the Dynamic Island alone is a reason to upgrade to a 14 Pro, and a reason not to even consider buying the 14 or 14 Plus. Would I pay $200 — the price delta between the same-sized Pro and regular iPhone 14 models — just to get the Dynamic Island? Yes.</p>

<h2>Always-On Display</h2>

<p>The second super interesting thing about the iPhones 14 Pro is the always-on display. <em>It is really weird.</em> Not weird because it’s a bad idea, but weird because battery life has always been, and remains, a precious resource to be conserved on smartphones. And, until now, one of the surest ways to run down your battery has been to leave your phone in an unattended state while the display remains on. When you look over to your side at your desk, where your iPhone rests face up, and the screen is <em>on</em> despite your knowing that you haven’t touched it in a while, it feels wrong. Like there’s a bug in iOS that’s preventing the screen from going to sleep or something. Over and over and over this past week, I’ve glanced at this iPhone 14 Pro in the always-on state, and I experienced a micro jolt of panic: <em>Whoa, why is the screen on? Oh, yeah, always-on...</em>.</p>

<p>The first thing I’ll emphasize is that always-on mode is pretty darn bright, and it is full color. If you use a colorful Lock Screen wallpaper, you’ll be looking at a colorful always-on display. It’s bright enough that you could use the phone without much concern even if the always-on state were the brightest the display ever got. You can see it clearly in bright sunlight. There have been Android phones with always-on displays for years, but many of them — when locked — are just black screens with dim white text for the time and date. On those phones, the always-on state is very distinctive from the actually-on state. On iPhone 14 Pro, at a glance, the always-on state looks like the actually-on state.</p>

<p>The always-on display I’m most familiar with is on Apple Watch, which added the feature three years ago <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2019/09/apple_watch_series_5">with the Series 5 models</a>. As a lifelong watch wearer, gaining an always-on display never seemed weird for Apple Watch. What seemed weird to me were the first four generations that <em>didn’t</em> offer it. (I spent a lot of words in <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2015/04/the_apple_watch">my review of the original Apple Watch</a> complaining about the not-always-on display.) I did not expect an always-on display for iPhone to be hard to grow accustomed to, but for me, so far, it has been.</p>

<p>In a way, the always-on display mode for iPhone 14 Pro is the opposite of the Dynamic Island. The Dynamic Island I took to immediately — a <em>where’ve you been all my life?</em> feature. The always-on display is still startling me every time I glance at it. I suspect I will get used to it, but if I still feel so unsettled by it a few weeks from now, I might try turning it off and seeing if I miss it. Because the other difference from the Dynamic Island is that I’m still not sure what purpose it serves. (The answer, I suspect, is Live Activities, which aren’t shipping until iOS 16.1. Being able to see updates to a Live Activity on an always-on display sounds potentially useful.)</p>

<p>Technically, the always-on display is impressive. I don’t know what kind of difference in battery life it makes by disabling it, because I’ve just left it on, as it is by default, for the week I’ve been using this phone. While testing new iPhones, I tend to use them far more than I do in day-to-day life. I’m shooting more photos, taking more videos, and running battery-sucking tasks like benchmarks that I seldom run during the other 51 weeks of the year. It’s hard to test and examine a new phone for a week while simultaneously gauging typical-day, typical-use battery life. That said, I’ve been getting the general battery life I’d expect from a new iPhone that <em>didn’t</em> have an always-on display. I don’t know if that perception is going to hold up in the long run, with my actual day-to-day usage, but at the moment, battery life is not a factor in my ambivalence toward the feature.</p>

<h2>Camera System</h2>

<p>Onward to the interesting, but not super interesting, aspects of the iPhone 14 Pro. It’s another solid year of camera improvements for the 14 Pro models. A nomenclatural change from Apple that I fully endorse is that they’re now calling the 1× camera the “main camera” instead of the “wide camera”. Calling 1× “wide” and 0.5× “ultra wide” broke my brain. The 1× camera is what most people use most of the time, and what some people use almost all the time. It <em>is</em> the main camera.</p>

<p>This year’s main camera is unlike any previous iPhone camera. Instead of a 12 MP sensor, its sensor is 48 MP. But unless you’re shooting RAW,<sup id="fnr3-2022-09-15"><a href="#fn3-2022-09-15">3</a></sup> it produces 12 MP photos. In 1× mode, the main camera is <a href="https://www.cnet.com/tech/mobile/samsung-s21-ultra-pixel-binning-adapts-photos-for-detail-or-the-dark/">binning</a> those 48 megapixels to increase image quality by treating each 2 × 2 square of 4 actual pixels as a single virtual pixel to produce 12 MP images. And the main camera now offers, in addition to 1×, a 2× focal length. Because it’s a 48 MP sensor, the main camera doesn’t need to upscale (a.k.a. “digital zoom”) from a 1× original to produce 2× output. Instead, 2× just uses a crop of the sensor’s center 12 megapixels — without binning — to produce an optical 12 MP image. It’s two focal lengths from one camera and lens.</p>

<p>I did not have time over the past week to create a deep investigation into the iPhone 14 Pro’s image and video quality. But from what I’ve seen so far, 2× mode looks great. It should produce higher quality output than the dedicated 2× camera on, say, the iPhone 12 Pro — particularly in low light — and so far, I think it does.</p>

<!-- Markdown Table
| iPhone 14 Pro | 35mm Equivalent |
| :-----------: | :-------------: |
| 0.5×          | 13mm            |
| 1×            | 24mm            |
| 2×            | 48mm            |
| 3×            | 77mm            |
-->

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th align="center">iPhone 14 Pro</th>
  <th align="center">35mm Equivalent</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td align="center">0.5×</td>
  <td align="center">13mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center">1×</td>
  <td align="center">24mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center">2×</td>
  <td align="center">48mm</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="center">3×</td>
  <td align="center">77mm</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>Having spent the last year with an iPhone 13 Pro — equipped with 0.5×, 1×, and 3×  cameras — I’m delighted to have 2× back as an optical focal length. In day-to-day usage, I’ve found 3× to be an awkward focal length — too zoomed-in for most of the scenes and portraits I’ve wanted to shoot, but not long enough for situations where I’d want a telephoto lens with a <em>lot</em> of throw. 2× iPhone lenses have always been roughly equivalent to 50mm lenses in traditional photography, and that focal length is considered normal. That’s really the term photographers use to describe a lens that is neither wide angle nor telephoto: <em>normal</em>. It’s the closest to the way our eyes perceive the world. When I shot on film 20 years ago, I seldom took my 50mm prime lens off my camera. It’s just a terrific focal length, and I expect to use the 2× focal length on the main camera a lot.<sup id="fnr4-2022-09-15"><a href="#fn4-2022-09-15">4</a></sup></p>

<p>Action mode is a new feature for video on all iPhone 14 models, pro and non-pro. It’s effectively a much more effective image stabilizer, sort of like a software gimbal. I used it while chasing some of my nieces and nephews around at a backyard birthday party over the weekend, and the results are impressive. It does require a lot of light — computationally it’s doing so much with each frame that it requires a fast shutter speed. But outdoors is where most “action” scenes occur.</p>

<h2>Our eSIM Future Is Here</h2>

<p>All of the iPhone 14 models being sold in the U.S. this year are eSIM-only. iPhones have supported eSIMs since 2018, but I’d never used them before. For obvious reasons, when you review and test multiple phones per year, throughout the year, just swapping a SIM card between phones is super convenient. You just pop the SIM out of phone A and stick it into phone B and boom, your cellular connection is now active on phone B. No waiting for your carrier to deactivate phone A and activate phone B. But surely the overwhelming majority of iPhone users have <em>never</em> taken their SIM cards out. For almost everyone, physical SIM cards are antiquated, and I think Apple made the right move going eSIM-only here. SIM trays are the new floppy drives.</p>

<p>I went ahead and moved my own personal Verizon account from a SIM card to eSIM on this review phone so I could truly use it as my own. I did the transfer during the setup process for the new phone, while choosing how to transfer/restore data from my old (personal) iPhone 13 Pro to the new (review unit) iPhone 14 Pro. It took a few minutes for Verizon to process, but it just worked. Thumbs up from me. We’ll see how it goes when I try moving the eSIM to other devices throughout the year. But for the overwhelming majority of people, this seems great.<sup id="fnr5-2022-09-15"><a href="#fn5-2022-09-15">5</a></sup></p>

<p>Apple also provided reviewers with pre-paid eSIMs, so I’ve been able to test dual SIM support. It works pretty well, overall, but even after adding my temporary review unit secondary phone number to my iCloud ID, my group chats in iMessage have been fragmented for reasons I don’t understand. Maybe it’s just me, but I’ve found that iMessage never works consistently if you have more than one phone number in your iCloud ID. Multiple email addresses: fine. Multiple phone numbers: inconsistent confusion.</p>

<p>One concern I’ve heard from DF readers is about international travel. The old way of getting cell service while traveling internationally is to stop by a vending machine at the airport upon arrival and purchase a prepaid SIM card with a certain amount of data. You don’t need to do that anymore. You can prepay — before you leave home — for eSIMs from a bunch of different companies for over 190 different countries. <a href="https://www.gigsky.com/">GigSky</a> is one such company. <a href="https://www.airalo.com/">Airalo</a> is another. There are a bunch of others. You get an eSIM with 10 GB of data, for 30 days, for about $20 for just about any country in Europe.</p>

<p>All iPhone 14 models support up to 8 eSIMs, with up to 2 in active use. So you can just buy a prepaid eSIM before you leave home, set it up on your iPhone, and activate it when you arrive. I asked a few friends who travel internationally frequently and they all raved about the eSIM experience for temporary local data service. So not only are eSIM-only iPhones not a problem for international travel, eSIMs seem <em>superior</em> to the physical SIM way of doing things for that. (You can’t lose an eSIM, for one thing.)</p>

<p>Speaking of losing things, Apple’s talking points promoting eSIMs mention security. This actually never occurred to me before, but apparently thieves know it all too well: pop the SIM card out of a lost or stolen phone, and location tracking for the phone is greatly hindered. That can’t happen with eSIMs.</p>

<p>Last but not least: Apple has been putting U.S. customers on eSIMs for <em>all</em> new iPhones purchased in Apple retail stores since last year. I was not aware of this until Apple informed me, which means it doesn’t seem to have been a problem.</p>

<h2>Silicon</h2>

<p>The regular iPhone 14 is clearly just an iterative improvement over the iPhone 13. Chip-wise, the iPhone 14 stays on the A15 “Bionic” from last year. But it is a very small upgrade from the iPhone 13. This was an uncomfortable marketing dance for Apple during the keynote, because heretofore, the non-Pro new iPhones got the latest version of the A-series chips each year. Last year, the regular iPhone 13 models (including the 13 Mini) got an A15 chip with a 4-core GPU. The iPhones 13 Pro, however, got A15 chips with a 5-core GPU. That 5-core GPU A15 is the chip in the iPhone 14 and 14 Plus. “One more GPU core” sounds like no big deal. “25 percent more GPU processing” sounds like a nice year-over-year upgrade. (More on this <em>last year’s Pro chip goes in this year’s non-pro phone</em> strategy below.)</p>

<p>The A16 chip in the iPhones 14 Pro seems, in my decidedly non-rigorous testing, to be about 10-15 percent faster than the 5-core A15, both in CPU and GPU processing. That’s not jaw-dropping, but it’s about the best we could hope for in a year when the chips haven’t moved to a next-generation fabrication process at TSMC. It’s also the case that benchmarking CPU and GPU performance and getting “scores” to compare for peak performance is just a terrible way of evaluating chips for mobile phones. For desktop computers, for computationally-expensive tasks, yes, benchmarks like that still matter. But what in the world is anyone doing with their phones that makes these benchmarks all that relevant regarding 10 or 20 percent differences in performance? Nothing. Using benchmarks like this to evaluate phone chips is like taking an electric vehicle to a racetrack and driving it with the pedal to the metal until the battery is dead, and using that to decide how efficient it is for daily driving in the real world.</p>

<p>Consider this hypothetical example. Let’s say a company comes out with a new system-on-a-chip for phones. Call it the X1 chip. A year later, they come out with the X2. In every single benchmark — single- and multi-core CPU, GPU, machine learning — the scores for the X2 are exactly the same as those of the X1. But, phones with the X2 get 20 percent longer battery life than phones with the X1. Is the X2 a significant year-over-year upgrade? Yes! A 20-percent improvement in battery life while maintaining CPU and GPU performance would be impressive (presuming performance and energy efficiency were already “good” in the X1 chip).</p>

<p>That’s the factor that gets overlooked in year-over-year silicon improvements when you only look at benchmark scores. The A16 is a bit faster. But battery life, according to Apple’s published specs, is effectively unchanged. Getting faster without reducing efficiency is a significant win. One step forward, without a step back.</p>

<p>The other silicon-related news this year is what Apple is calling the Photonic Engine. Here’s how Apple describes it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This dramatically improves photos taken in mid to low light, like
indoors, right before the sun sets. Photonic Engine builds on the
incredible computational photography capabilities of iPhone and
furthers our image pipeline by doing Deep Fusion earlier in the
process. Deep Fusion uses our powerful Neural Engine to take the
best parts of multiple images on a pixel-by-pixel basis and
combine them into an image that increases dynamic range and brings
out extraordinary detail in low light. Photonic Engine now applies
Deep Fusion to uncompressed images, enabling use of
more data for more detail, more colors, and brighter colors.
Photonic Engine combines with hardware capabilities for a big leap
forward in low-light photo capabilities. Photonic Engine is a big
advancement in computational photography and delivers better
results in challenging lighting environments.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Basically, on the iPhone 13 models and earlier, Deep Fusion worked on the compressed JPEG or HEIC imagery; now it works on the RAW data direct from the sensor. This isn’t an A16-exclusive feature, because the non-pro iPhone 14 models have it too, but it is exclusive to this year’s new phones. iPhone 13 Pros running iOS 16 don’t get the Photonic Engine, because, I presume, it’s a hardware improvement to the pipeline between the camera sensors and the image signaling processor on the chips. Apple “silicon” isn’t just the SoC; it’s everything inside the phone that connects to the SoC. This level of integration across <em>everything</em> related to “hardware” is very difficult for the Android world to compete with.</p>

<p>In terms of room for improvement for future A-series chips and image signal processing, 4K ProRes video is still limited to 30 FPS max on the iPhone 14 Pro. Get your shit together, Apple. (It would be a lot of fun to transfer 4K 60 FPS ProRes video files at the USB 2.0 data speeds offered by Lightning.)</p>

<h2>Colorways and Materials</h2>

<p>As mentioned above, the iPhone 14 Pro I’ve been using as my main phone for the last week is space black. It’s my favorite stainless steel iPhone colorway ever, by far, no question. In the entire history of the iPhone, I think it’s second only to the black/slate iPhone 5 from 2012. (Yes, <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/sp655?locale=en_US">the one</a> whose coating chipped over time. That visible wear and tear made the iPhone 5 look better, not worse — like a leather wallet or denim jeans. And yes, I dug my own iPhone 5 out of my museum to check if I still have as much affection for it as I recall. I do.<sup id="fnr6-2022-09-15"><a href="#fn6-2022-09-15">6</a></sup>) I generally like buying anything that’s available in black in black. But this space black is a terrific black. For me, this might be as good as Apple’s ever going to get with stainless steel and a matte glass back.</p>

<p>I’m pretty sure I’ve registered this same complaint every year since the iPhone X, but I still wish Apple weren’t using stainless steel for the iPhone Pro models. It certainly looks nice that it’s polished to a high gloss, but steel is just so damn heavy. My tastes run toward smaller phones (pour one out for the Mini lineup, which, I fear, is gone for good), but also toward <em>lighter</em> phones. There’s no accounting for taste in colors, of course, so setting color aside, every single thing about the iPhone Pro models is better than the non-pro ones except for weight (206g vs. 172g, a factor of 1.2×). <em>But weight really matters for something you carry with you almost everywhere.</em> Two years ago I purchased an iPhone 12 rather than 12 Pro simply because I preferred the feel of it, both in hand and in pocket, and because by the fall of 2020 it seemed pretty clear I wouldn’t be traveling much, if at all, before the iPhones 13 arrived the next year and thus wouldn’t regret carrying the second-tier camera system. I miss the weight and feel of that phone to this day.</p>

<p>If ceramic is impractical as a material for iPhones (and I suspect it is, but man, those ceramic Apple Watch Edition models were <em>nice</em>), I hope that the Apple Watch Ultra heralds a possible switch from stainless steel to titanium for the iPhone Pro next year or thereafter.<sup id="fnr7-2022-09-15"><a href="#fn7-2022-09-15">7</a></sup></p>

<p>The iPhone 14 Pro Max unit Apple provided me with is deep purple. It’s fine, but it’s not as fun and nowhere near as purple as the purple iPhone 12 (non-pro) Apple released in April last year. <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2021/04/apple-introduces-iphone-12-and-iphone-12-mini-in-a-stunning-new-purple/">Look at that purple iPhone 12</a>. That’s a fun color. I really don’t get why Apple doesn’t release <em>any</em> iPhone Pro models in <a href="https://basicappleguy.com/basicappleblog/nanochromatic">bold fun colorways</a>. The “deep” in “deep purple” translates, to my eyes (and those of <a href="https://twitter.com/AmyJane/status/1570524339958853632">others</a>), to “<em>clearly but subtly tinted in good lighting when viewed from just the right angle, but otherwise looks gray</em>”. Personally I’m as happy as Darth Vader with a freshly polished helmet with the 14 Pro’s space black, but for the untold millions of people out there who love fun colors, there remains no such thing in the iPhone Pro lineup. Seems inexplicable to me that “fun bold colors” and “best possible iPhone” have been mutually exclusive since <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2017/03/apple-introduces-iphone-7-and-iphone-7-plus-productred-special-edition/">the Product Red iPhone 7 special edition</a> in March 2017.</p>

<p>Apple also provided me with a blue iPhone 14. It seems a bit unsatisfying to my eyes — too baby blue for anyone who wants a neutral colorway, but not nearly bold enough for someone seeking something <em>fun</em>. But it’s definitely blue, in all light, from all angles.</p>

<h2>The iPhones 14</h2>

<p>In 2013, the new flagship iPhone was <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2013/09/the_iphone_5s_and_5c">the iPhone 5S</a>. If they’d followed their pattern from the previous few years, they’d have kept <a href="https://daringfireball.net/2012/09/iphone_5">2012’s iPhone 5</a> in the lineup at reduced prices. Instead, the new 5S replaced the 5 at the top of the lineup, and Apple introduced the iPhone 5C — a phone with the iPhone 5’s internal specs, but on the outside, an all-new and distinctive design that Jony Ive described, quite aptly, as “<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2013/09/10/iphone-5c/">beautifully, unapologetically plastic</a>”.</p>

<p>Apple, of course, didn’t explain why. Conventional wisdom speculated that the chamfered edges of the iPhone 5 were too expensive to produce, or that the black/slate model chipped too easily. (The dark version of the iPhone 5S was space gray, not black/slate.) I don’t think that was the reason at all. I simply think Apple wanted one iPhone and one iPhone alone to <em>look</em> like the best one, the king of the hill. Both from the outside — and from the inside, looking at the specs. The problem with the idea of selling the iPhone 5 at a lower price alongside the then-new 5S was that next to each other, the 5S didn’t look newer enough.</p>

<p>That strategy didn’t seem to work at the time. People I know who owned the 5C loved the thing and loved its “unapologetically plastic” design, but it didn’t seem to sell particularly well. In the 6 / 6S / 7 era, Apple went back to selling the prior years’ models at $100-increment lower prices. But Apple clearly never gave up on the basic idea of introducing two distinct tiers of new iPhones each year, with the flagship design sitting distinctively atop the lineup. Starting with the iPhone X and iPhone 8 five years ago, there have been two new iPhones each year: a good one, and an even better one. Even before they started using the word “pro” for iPhone names, there’s been one new model that’s pro (and pro-priced), and another new model that isn’t.</p>

<!-- Markdown Table
|      | Pro                  | Regular          |
| ---- | -------------------- | ---------------- |
| 2017 | X                    | 8 (and 8 Plus)   |
| 2018 | XS (and XS Max)      | XR               |
| 2019 | 11 Pro (and Pro Max) | 11               |
| 2020 | 12 Pro (and Pro Max) | 12 (and 12 Mini) |
| 2021 | 13 Pro (and Pro Max) | 13 (and 13 Mini) |
| 2022 | 14 Pro (and Pro Max) | 14 (and 14 Plus) |
-->

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th></th>
  <th>Pro</th>
  <th>Regular</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td>2017</td>
  <td>X</td>
  <td>8 (and 8 Plus)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>2018</td>
  <td>XS (and XS Max)</td>
  <td>XR</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>2019</td>
  <td>11 Pro (and Pro Max)</td>
  <td>11</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>2020</td>
  <td>12 Pro (and Pro Max)</td>
  <td>12 (and 12 Mini)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>2021</td>
  <td>13 Pro (and Pro Max)</td>
  <td>13 (and 13 Mini)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>2022</td>
  <td>14 Pro (and Pro Max)</td>
  <td>14 (and 14 Plus)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The basic idea of introducing two tiers of a product each year is simple: market segmentation. Considering that the iPhone is Apple’s most popular product ever — and quite arguably the most successful product any company has ever made — it makes a lot of sense. But more subtle is Apple’s strategy for moving older models down the lineup at lower prices each year. <em>Only the non-pro iPhones move down the line.</em> The iPhone X was <em>replaced</em> by the XS. The XS was <em>replaced</em> by the 11 Pro. And no iPhone named “Pro” has ever moved down the lineup at a reduced price. If you want to buy an iPhone 14 Pro or Pro Max, you better buy it sometime between now and next year’s iPhone 15 event.</p>

<p>That means no 6.7-inch iPhone has ever been sold at less than the $1,100 starting price of the first one, the 11 Pro Max. (Which only had 64 GB of storage!) The iPhone 14 Plus breaks that pattern, starting at $900 (with a reasonable 128 GB of storage). And, I expect both the iPhone 14 and 14 Plus to remain in the lineup a year from now at $100 lower prices. If Apple keeps both sizes in the lineup for <em>two</em> years, you’ll be able to buy a 6.7-inch iPhone 14 Plus in 2024 for just $700. Big displays are no longer an exclusive upsell to the iPhone Pro tier.</p>

<p>Now, though, a new pattern has been introduced: only the iPhones Pro get the new generation A-series chip. The iPhone 14 thus is sort of a modern version of the iPhone 5C concept: an industrial design that is less premium-looking but more fun and colorful than the pro models, with the SoC from the previous year’s pro models. I’ll eat my hat if, next year, the A17 isn’t exclusive to the iPhones 15 Pro and the regular iPhones 15 don’t get this year’s A16. Chips now join display quality, camera quality, telephoto lenses, and premium materials as differentiating factors between the iPhones Pro — which, I’ll repeat, are <em>only</em> sold at the very highest prices — and the non-pro iPhones. Hardware costs money.</p>

<p>More interestingly — super interestingly, even — the Dynamic Island now introduces a <em>software</em> user experience differentiator. Because Live Activity views are only available on the Lock Screen of notched iPhones (and as fleeting non-user-invokable notifications, like Apple Maps’s turn-by-turn directions have been for years), Apple has now introduced major new <em>software</em> features that are only available on the iPhones Pro, via the Dynamic Island. There is a hardware component — the smaller sensor array and behind-the-display proximity sensor — but all of the Dynamic Island functionality could be exposed to notched iPhones, just in less cool-looking ways. That’s a design choice Apple has (apparently) made, not a function of production costs. It’s not just that the Dynamic Island looks better than the notch. It provides utility that just about any iPhone user would enjoy. At least any iPhone user who ever listens to music or podcasts, makes phone calls, hails rides with Uber or Lyft, or follows live sports. And the only way to get it is with a new iPhone 14 <em>Pro</em>.</p>

<p>I don’t think it’s a coincidence that the very same year Apple stopped holding 6.7-inch displays as an exclusive feature for the premium-priced Pro models is the same year they introduced the compelling Dynamic Island. I expect the Dynamic Island to remain iPhone-Pro-exclusive for years to come. It might come to the non-pro new iPhones in a few years, but if it does, that will coincide with some <em>new</em> iPhone-Pro-only flagship star-of-the-TV-commercials feature.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<hr />
<ol>

<li id="fn1-2022-09-15">
<p>For a few days after last week’s keynote, I was thinking, vaguely, that perhaps MacBook Pros could go from a notch to a Dynamic Island eventually. Upon further consideration, though, I don’t think it would work. For one thing, the mouse cursor would disappear under the parts of the Dynamic Island that really are housing sensors. Yes, the cursor disappears under the MacBook Pro notch today, but it disappears under the <em>whole</em> notch, not patches of it. The entire point of the Dynamic Island is to create the convincing illusion that there is no sensor array cutout on the display, but a mouse cursor would continually spoil that illusion. The Dynamic Island concept is inherently touchscreen-exclusive. (Another factor: it’s weird enough that the MacBook Pro notch interrupts the menu bar. It’d be downright annoying for a Dynamic Island to dynamically push menus around as it expands and contracts. I suppose, on the Mac, the Dynamic Island could be of fixed width to avoid that issue, but then it would lose a lot of its playfulness and personality. “The Static Island” doesn’t have quite the same ring to it.) Lastly, the Mac just doesn’t need it.</p>

<p>I don’t think an iPhone-style Dynamic Island will ever come to iPads, either. For one thing, I’m inclined to think iPad bezels will never shrink to the point where the sensor array won’t fit behind them. For another, iPads now have mouse pointer support when connected to a trackpad and the same illusion-ruining factor I mentioned about the Mac would apply. But here’s an idea: perhaps the Dynamic Island would come to the iPad <em>purely in software</em>. The iPad hardware sensor array would still be hidden in the bezel surrounding the display, but iPadOS could render a pure software Dynamic Island on screen. That, I think, would work completely. You could rotate the iPad and the Dynamic Island would always be at the top. The mouse pointer wouldn’t disappear under any actual hardware sensors. It’d just be a black <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stadium_(geometry)">stadium</a> rendered entirely by software. It could actually be more elegant than the iPhone’s Dynamic Island because there’d be no sensors to disguise.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr1-2022-09-15"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn2-2022-09-15">
<p>I strongly suspect that Apple considers the ProMotion display to be essential to the Dynamic Island experience. Running its animations at 120 FPS makes the Dynamic Island feel alive. It sells the illusion that this ever-present black stadium is entirely a feature, not a tradeoff. Again I’ll turn to the analogy to sleight-of-hand magic: it’s not enough to perform the trick with the correct mechanics, the motion has to be perfectly smooth, too.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr2-2022-09-15"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn3-2022-09-15">
<p>In Settings → Camera → Formats, you can choose between 12 and 48 MP resolution for ProRAW. Approximate file sizes: 25 and 75 MB.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr3-2022-09-15"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn4-2022-09-15">
<p>If you tend to shoot almost everything on your iPhone at 1× simply because that’s the default, I encourage you to try using 2× for more day-to-day shooting if you have an iPhone that offers it. Using a normal lens does for your photography muscles what lifting weights does for your actual muscles. (I wish there were an option in Settings → Camera → Preserve Settings that allowed you to keep your last-used focal length each time you open the Camera app. There are times when I’d like to leave it at 2×.)&nbsp;<a href="#fnr4-2022-09-15"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn5-2022-09-15">
<p>While I’m talking about initial setup, let me repeat <a href="https://daringfireball.net/linked/2021/09/24/how-to-set-up-a-new-iphone-or-ipad">my recommendation from last year</a>: I cloned my existing iPhone 13 Pro to new iPhone 14 devices this week both by restoring from iCloud Backup and using the direct device-to-device Quick Start transfer. I highly recommend the device-to-device transfer. It might take a bit longer, but it moves almost <em>everything</em>, including your login credentials for almost every app. My biggest complaint about restoring from iCloud Backup is that while your data all gets restored, your login credentials don’t.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr5-2022-09-15"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn6-2022-09-15">
<p>I also have extraordinarily fond affection for the original iPhone. Is the original my favorite iPhone design ever? In some ways, of course. For chrissake <a href="https://www.macg.co/aapl/2019/06/evans-hankey-le-nouveau-visage-du-design-produit-dapple-106737">just look at Evans Hankey’s personal original iPhone</a>, after years of use. It might be the single most beautiful object in the entire <em><a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2016/11/designed-by-apple-in-california-chronicles-20-years-of-apple-design/">Designed by Apple in California</a></em> book.&nbsp;<a href="#fnr6-2022-09-15"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 6 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>


<li id="fn7-2022-09-15">
<p>Regarding titanium’s advantages versus steel, <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/SP860?viewlocale=en_US&amp;locale=en_US">consider last year’s Apple Watch Series 7 lineup</a> at 45mm:</p>

<p>
Aluminum: 38.8g<br/>
Titanium: 45.1g<br/>
Stainless Steel: 51.5g
</p>

<p>Titanium sits almost exactly halfway between aluminum and steel, weight-wise. And a device designed to be solely available in titanium might prove even lighter, as the structure can be designed with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titanium">titanium’s extraordinary strength-to-density</a> ratio in mind. Another comparison: the Apple Watch Ultra weighs 61.3g and the 45mm stainless steel Series 8 weighs 51.5g, but the Ultra is a <em>lot</em> bigger. The Apple Watch Ultra is closer in weight to the 45mm steel Series 8 than the steel Series 8 is to the aluminum one (38.8g).&nbsp;<a href="#fnr7-2022-09-15"  class="footnoteBackLink"  title="Jump back to footnote 7 in the text.">&#x21A9;&#xFE0E;︎</a></p>
</li>

</ol>
</div>



    ]]></content>
  <title>★ The iPhones 14 Pro (and iPhones 14)</title></entry></feed><!-- THE END -->
