<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>



<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Collab Fund</title>
    <description>Collab Fund is a leading source of capital for entrepreneurs pushing the world forward.</description>
    <link>https://collabfund.com</link>
    <atom:link href="https://collabfund.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 06:10:55 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 06:10:55 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Siteleaf</generator>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>A Few Good Stories</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had lunch with a guy who’s close with Warren Buffett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guy – we’ll call him Jim (not his real name) – was driving around Omaha with Buffett in late 2009. The global economy was crippled at this point, and Omaha was no exception. Stores were closed, businesses were boarded up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jim said to Warren, “It’s so bad right now. How does the economy ever bounce back from this?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warren said, “Jim, do you know what the best-selling candy bar was in 1962?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No.” Jim said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Snickers,” said Warren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And do you know what the best-selling candy bar is today?” Warren said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No,” said Jim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Snickers,” said Warren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then silence. That was the end of the conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think what Buffett meant was: Focusing on what’s never going to change is more important than trying to anticipate how something might change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virtually everything was in short supply during World War II. The U.S. Army produced over 100 million uniforms to supply the Allies, which left little fabric left over for civilian clothes. It got worse in 1943 when the Army mandated that the synthetic material typically used in bathing suits had to be reserved for making military parachutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clothing companies got creative by designing bathing suits with less and less fabric. One French designer named Louis Réard took it to the extreme, designing a bathing suit with as little fabric as he could get away with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Réard introduced the new bathing suit in 1946. When deciding what to call it, he read in a newspaper about nuclear bomb tests that were taking place on a thin strip of rocks in the Pacific and were catching the public’s attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thin strip catching people’s attention? That’s exactly what Réard was trying to do, too. So he named his swimsuit after the atoll where the nuclear tests were taking place – Bikini.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When giving tests, Stanford professor Ronald Howard used to make students put the percentage odds they thought they were correct next to each answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you said you were 100% confident that your answer was correct and it turned out to be wrong, you failed the entire test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you said you were 0% confident and your answer happened to be correct, you got no credit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything in between gave you a confidence-adjusted score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never heard of a better way to teach people that life is about probabilities, not certainties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1907, author William Dawson wrote about how the feeling of wealth is relative to what you’re accustomed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A man of education, accustomed to easy means, would suffer tortures unspeakable if he were made to live in a single room of a populous and squalid tenement, and had to subsist upon a wage at once niggardly and precarious. He would be tormented with that memory of happier things, which we are told is a ‘sorrow’s crown of sorrow.’&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But the man who has known no other condition of life is unconscious of its misery. He has no standard of comparison. An environment which would drive a man of refinement to thoughts of suicide, does not produce so much as dissatisfaction in him. Hence there is far more happiness among the poor than we imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To drive home his point: Dawson was himself an educated man, fairly successful and accustomed to easy means by the standard of his day. But Dawson, who died in 1928, spent most of his life without electricity or air conditioning. He never had antibiotics, Advil, or a Polio vaccine. He never experienced reasonably accurate weather forecasts, or an interstate highway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An average American today sent back in time to experience Dawson’s life would suffer the same “tortures unspeakable” he wrote about. But he didn’t have modern times to compare his life to, so it felt luxurious to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything good in life is just &lt;a href=&quot;https://collabfund.com/blog/expectations-and-reality/&quot;&gt;the gap between expectations and reality.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America’s decision to invade Northern Africa in November 1942 was extremely unpopular with military leaders, even President Roosevelt’s closest advisors. By almost every account, the troops weren’t ready, the planning was rushed, and the target goals were too ambitious. The top generals saw no downside to waiting a few more months. Dwight Eisenhower, then a general, predicted that Roosevelt’s hasty order to invade would become “the blackest day in history.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invasion worked. But looking back after the war, the president’s advisors wondered why he was in such a hurray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation was that the American people were antsy for something – anything – to happen after Pearl Harbor and Germany’s declaration of war. Roosevelt’s own son wrote him a letter saying he and his fellow soldiers were sitting around and “not having any fun … just waiting our turn.” Scratching those itches may have superseded military strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Marshall, then Army chief of staff, said after the war: “The leader in a democracy has to keep the people entertained. That may sound like the wrong word, but it conveys the thought.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most decisions aren’t made on a spreadsheet, where you just add up the numbers and a rational answer pops out. There’s a human element that’s hard to quantify, hard to explain, and can seem totally detached from the original goal, yet carries more influence than anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martin Luther King’s famous speech at the Lincoln Memorial on August 28th, 1963, did not go down as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;King’s advisor and speechwriter, Clarence Jones, drafted a full speech for King to deliver, based on, he recalled, a “summary of ideas we had talked about.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first few minutes of King’s speech follow the script. Video shows him constantly looking down at his notes, reading verbatim. “Go back to Georgia, go back to Louisiana, go back to the slums and ghettos of our northern cities, knowing that somehow this situation can and will be changed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just then, around halfway through the speech, gospel singer Mahalia Jackson – who was standing to King’s left, maybe 10 feet away – shouts out, “Tell ‘em about the dream Martin! Tell ‘em about the dream!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones recalls: “[King] looks over at her in real time, then he takes the text of the written speech and he slides it to the left side of the lectern. He grabs the lectern and looks out on more than 250,000 people.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s then a six-second pause before King looks up at the sky and says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have a dream. It is a dream deeply rooted in the American dream.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a dream that one day this nation will rise up and live out the true meaning of its creed: “We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a dream that my four little children will one day live in a nation where they will not be judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I have a dream today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest was history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones says: “That portion of the speech, which is most celebrated in this country and around the world, is not the speech that he planned to give.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best story – not the most prepared, or the most thought out, or the most analytical – wins.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 08:59:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/a-few-stories-i-like/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/a-few-stories-i-like/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Shared Future: What We’ve Learned So Far</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We launched Collab’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://sharedfuture.xyz/&quot;&gt;Shared Future&lt;/a&gt; in March 2022. A lot has changed since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Russia-Ukraine war has led to severe energy shortfalls and skyrocketing energy prices. Supply chains have snarled even more, pushing inflation to double digits. The remedy—higher interest rates—then caused a funding contraction across the capital stack, making it harder for founders to raise venture funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the world has recommitted to the fight against climate change: the US passed $400B+ in climate funding across several bills, including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ctvc.co/inflation-reduction-acts-climate-tech-impact-111/&quot;&gt;IRA&lt;/a&gt;; California and New York banned combustion-engine vehicles starting in 2035; and one of China’s main coal regions will invest $87B to construct 60 GW of carbon-free energy (the equivalent of 3 million solar panels).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These changes—global and local, positive and negative—underscore the need for programs like Shared Future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;launching-shared-future&quot;&gt;Launching Shared Future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impetus for Shared Future was to address the growing climate crisis – one that has only accelerated through record-breaking hurricanes, headline-grabbing droughts, and devastating wildfires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we were also motivated by the less visible effects of climate change: encroaching insurance premiums for homeowners, temporary blackouts for families trying to stay warm in the winter, and once-in-a-generation heat waves that now bake cities year after year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We launched Shared Future because we knew that the tectonic shift required to limit climate change calls for an unprecedented wave of innovation. From Meta’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2022/07/30/facebook-former-cto-mike-schroepfer-on-his-new-climate-change-focus.html&quot;&gt;former CTO&lt;/a&gt; to new university graduates around the globe, the fight against climate change is drawing the best talent. True to Collab’s ethos, Shared Future is an opportunity to bet on the intersection of for-profit and for-good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is why we structured Shared Future as an index fund of the most promising climate startups. We believe this vintage of climate founders, like the wave of social media, fintech and crypto entrepreneurs before them, will generate incredible returns. And we set up the fund to create an opportunity for Collaborative’s core funds to double down on the best of the best with additional funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modeled after the successful Covid-19 initiative &lt;a href=&quot;https://fastgrants.org/&quot;&gt;Fast Grants&lt;/a&gt;, the original vision for Shared Future was simple: An application form that would take entrepreneurs less than an hour to complete, programmatic funding decisions within 48 hours, bank wires following in 10 days or less. Collaborative raised $10 million, gathered a coalition of mission-aligned partners, and started funding companies. We were much more worried about missing out on supporting important work than looking silly. With a “Let’s-do-it!” attitude and an understanding we would learn along the way, we started funding companies in just a matter of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-progress-to-date&quot;&gt;Our Progress to Date&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could not be more excited about what Shared Future has already achieved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we decided to fund a few cohorts of startups at leading innovation hubs like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.activate.org/fellowship&quot;&gt;Activate Fellows&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ycombinator.com/&quot;&gt;Y Combinator&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://airminers.org/&quot;&gt;Airminers&lt;/a&gt;. At launch, our hypothesis was that innovation hubs would enable us to quickly and programmatically find top-quality entrepreneurs. Our Activate partnership demonstrates just how much value this model can generate: we offered 40+ slots to Activate companies this year, frequently collaborate on programming, and have even funded Activate alumni. Today, we see Shared Future as a ‘network of networks’ that will enable ‘collisions’ between the best founders, capital, and tools dedicated to solving climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we are on track to meet our goal of backing 100 companies this year. We have allocated capital to 90+ and have already sent wires to 60+ startups. Examples of companies in our portfolio include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alga.bio/&quot;&gt;Alga Biosciences&lt;/a&gt; has developed a kelp-based feed additive and a proprietary production method that reduces cow methane emissions by 95%. These results are not only best-in-class, but the feed additive can be produced at scale for a fraction of the cost of current alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carboncrusher.io/&quot;&gt;Carbon Crusher&lt;/a&gt; has pioneered a bitumen-free (meaning asphalt-free) road creation process that is cheaper, faster, and carbon-negative. The team is already operating in four countries in Europe and is looking to enter the US market this year.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seabound.co/&quot;&gt;Seabound&lt;/a&gt; is leading the charge to decarbonize shipping, a major contributor to climate change, by developing a ship-based carbon capture system. Since launch in late 2021, the team built 2 working prototypes, signed 6 letters of intent with major shipowners, and raised $4.6M in seed funding from Lowercarbon Capital, Y Combinator, Soma Capital, and others.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.phasebiolabs.com/&quot;&gt;Phase Biolabs&lt;/a&gt; is making carbon negative chemicals and carbon neutral e-fuels from CO2 using fermentation. The team was recently accepted into the prestigious Breakthrough Fellows program.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://channingcopper.com/&quot;&gt;Channing St. Copper Co.&lt;/a&gt; is on a mission to improve people’s lives through home electrification. Their first product is an induction electric range that does not require major electrical upgrades. This allows  homeowners and renters to easily access the superior cooking experience of induction as well as the personal and planetary health benefits that come from eliminating the toxic emissions created when burning fossil fuels in the home.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we have seen clear examples of how Shared Future’s participation in a round enables companies to accelerate their funding – the definition of catalytic capital. One company, for example, struggled to raise a pre-seed round until investors found out that Collab had invested; after that, the team was able to quickly close &amp;gt;$1M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, we are thrilled that founders are seeking out Shared Future both because of the impact of the capital for their operations and what it means for their long-term journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-surprised-us--where-were-doubling-down&quot;&gt;What Surprised Us &amp;amp; Where We’re Doubling Down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, Shared Future’s inaugural year has also been filled with the unexpected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we were blown away by the level of enthusiasm with which our initiative was received. Within hours after launching publicly, we received an extraordinary amount of requests to contribute to our efforts. This led us to identify a group of ‘accelerants:’ partners that can deliver exceptional value to our companies. Accelerants range from one of the largest mining companies in the world, which has offered to explore pilot opportunities with our portfolio founders, to highly successful founders that want to mentor new Shared Future leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, we were pleasantly surprised that our vision of a ‘network of networks’ has already started to materialize. For example, we recently connected an EV policy expert and a leading mileage-tracking company with our portfolio companies that are focused on this sector. We also saw an overwhelming response to our in-person event in San Francisco this July. The 70+ attendees made the room buzz with energy – and we’re now working on upcoming events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, we predicted upon launching Shared Future that similar initiatives would follow, which would require us to develop a value proposition beyond just rapid capital. This trend has been particularly true in climate tech, where dry powder continues to be abundant. Today, we are excited to see more Shared Future-like programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of similar capital coming online, we are doubling down on adding value to startups. This is also where we need to invest the most time and attention this coming quarter. This means fostering a strong, founder-driven community alongside the right set of tools and accelerants. We now invite Shared Future teams to Collab’s Wednesday ‘Founder Talks,’ wherein an experienced founder walks through their journey and what they’ve learned. We see teams that regularly attend Founder Talks ask for specific introductions. We want to replicate and augment such learning opportunities. Over the next two quarters we will continue to find ways to foster founder-to-founder introductions, programming, and general communication tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-does-shared-future-tell-us-about-climate-funding-models&quot;&gt;What Does Shared Future Tell Us About Climate Funding Models?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coupled with the desire to alleviate the climate crisis, Shared Future was born to address a set of challenges in the climate tech funding model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, founders at the lab stage often struggle to make progress as quickly as they’d like because they cannot get funding; but they cannot get funding because they need to make progress. Second, funding climate tech startups has significantly more uncertainty than in other sectors, so many investors will only dip their toes in if an established investor signals interest first. Third, moving atoms and carbon molecules is inherently CapEx intensive, so startups need more funding and help than their software-only counterparts. Finally, most climate founders are first-time entrepreneurs, often coming from academic backgrounds, and would benefit greatly from tapping a high-quality network of like-minded leaders. Despite high-profile new climate tech funds announced over the past years, these challenges still ring true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still much work to be done to support our existing companies and to identify the next batch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are deeply grateful to our partners (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sweetgreen.com/&quot;&gt;Sweetgreen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://goldhirshfoundation.org/&quot;&gt;Goldhirsh Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.banffadvisors.com/&quot;&gt;Banff Advisors&lt;/a&gt;) as well as our LPs. Without your commitment and trust, Shared Future would not exist. As we continue to build, we hope to earn the worth of your partnership each and every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, the Collab team has been hard at work to truly embody our mission of providing catalytic capital and support. We live for and are energized by finding the best climate tech founders. We believe that the next world-defining founder is out there, ready to leave the lab, waiting for a first check and the right partner to begin their journey. At Shared Future, we intend to be that first partner, ready to catalyze hundreds of climate solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 12:08:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/shared-future-what-weve-learned/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/shared-future-what-weve-learned/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Attention</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In school they tell you your paper must be a minimum of five pages long. In the real world you have five seconds to catch someone’s attention before they’re bored and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting people’s attention has never been easy, but social media made it a nightmare. Someone reading a book 20 years ago had few other distractions in front of them. Today your phone offers an Olympic competition for your dopamine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution for many writers has been a combination of clickbait, pandering, and fear-mongering. The loudest voice wins. But that’s short-sighted – it’s exhausting for readers, comes at the expense of long-term trust, and it’s easy to mistake people gawking at you for people paying attention to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there’s a middle ground between gaining and maintaining someone’s attention:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get to the point&lt;/strong&gt;. Communicating is a two-party transaction: The writer supplies content and the reader invests their precious time and attention. Both are valuable, but it’s easy for writers who labor over their words to only consider their own efforts. When a writer respects readers’ time as much as they value their own words, trust is built, and the irony is that trust makes readers want to read more of your words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good stories &amp;gt; deep lectures.&lt;/strong&gt; You can hear a nursery rhyme as a child and remember it for life, but forget everything you learned about organic chemistry a week after the final exam. Stories stick with people in a way that a data dump of facts and formulas never can. They bind data with emotion in a way that can turn 2 + 2 into six. Matt Bird writes in his book &lt;em&gt;The Secrets of Story&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Beginners believe their ideas are valuable, and will protect them with secrecy and copyright symbols on the title page. Professionals know that ideas are a dime a dozen and nobody wants to steal them. It’s only the unique expression of an idea that’s valuable. Ideas are ephemeral and the only marketable skill is good writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transform gut feelings into words, explaining something people intuitively know is true but haven’t yet put into words.&lt;/strong&gt; A new way of explaining something the reader already knows can be more powerful than teaching something new, because it generates an “ah-ha” moment without asking them to strain their brains too hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be broad&lt;/strong&gt;. Years ago I briefly wrote for the &lt;em&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/em&gt;, and an editor told me: “Your job is to write something that a hedge fund manager will find informative but a complete novice will understand.” It sounds lofty, but I think it’s possible in almost any field. Writing in clear language anyone can comprehend does not mean dumbing it down – if anything it forces you to focus on the broad skills that matter most but tend to be ignored. Stephen Hawking once said of his bestselling physics books: “Someone told me that each equation I included in the book would halve the sales.” Probably not wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduce a new topic through the lens of something readers already know&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s hard to ask people to make room in their brain for entirely new information. Asking them to leverage what they already understand to grasp a new topic is much easier. A lot of good communication is teaching by analogy – watch Richard Feynman &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=N1pIYI5JQLE&amp;amp;ab_channel=nebulajr&quot;&gt;explain the physics and chemistry of fire&lt;/a&gt; by telling a story about bowling balls on a trampoline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be timeless.&lt;/strong&gt; With rare exceptions, I never understood promoting advice that has a shelf life. It encourages you to pander to the news cycle, and comment on things even when you have nothing to say. You also build trust when readers find value in something you wrote years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are three types of written content: You can give people information; you can give them an opinion; or you can try to change the way they think&lt;/strong&gt;. The first is ultra-competitive. The second pulls you towards pandering. The third is, I think, by far the most powerful, and the best way to not only get but keep people’s attention.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 13:38:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/attention/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/attention/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Very Important and Hard to Teach</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The most important decisions in your life may be whether to marry, who to marry, and whether to have kids. But none of those topics are taught in school. They’re hardly even discussed. How could they be? They aren’t problems you can distill down to an equation, or even a broad principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have different personalities, goals, experiences, and levels of chance and serendipity, all of which make universal truths hard to find and difficult to teach. No matter how smart the world becomes, the best answer will always be, “You’ve got to figure it out for yourself.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of things work like that. Some of the most important topics are the hardest to teach, and real world experience is the only school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few others:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to get along with people you disagree with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to respect the views of people who’ve had different life experiences than you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to recognize that your own views would be different if you were born in a different country or era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to recognize and appreciate luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to deal with regret.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where to live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to advertise your skills and accomplishments without being insufferable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to avoid being swayed by bullshit and charlatans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to manage the balance between confidence and ego, recognizing that you might be unique but you’re not special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to accept your own faults without guilt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to be curious about fields that have nothing to do with your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to change your mind, especially about things that were once core to your identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to deal with a certain level of hassle and nonsense without losing your cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to experience the agony of financial loss even when you’re aware of the odds of a bad outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to accept critical feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to be inspired by others’ success while avoiding envy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing how incentives affect your behavior, often for the worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to accept things that are easy to ignore because it’s painful to admit they’re true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to recognize the long-term consequences of your actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to balance optimism and pessimism so you can exploit opportunities with realistic expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no easy rules to learn and memorize – you’ve got to figure those out for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 15:48:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/very-important-and-hard-to-teach/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/very-important-and-hard-to-teach/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cumulative vs. Cyclical Knowledge</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;President James Garfield died because the best doctors in the country didn’t believe in germs, probing Garfield’s bullet wound after an assassination attempt with ungloved, unwashed fingers that almost certainly contributed to his fatal infection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds crazy – 1881 wasn’t &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; long ago – but historian Candice Millard writes in her book &lt;em&gt;Destiny of the Republic&lt;/em&gt; how controversial germ theory was to 19th-century doctors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They found the notion of “invisible germs” to be ridiculous, and they refused to even consider the idea that they could be the cause of so much disease and death.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Even the editor of the highly respected Medical Record found more to fear than to admire in [antiseptic pioneer] Lister’s theory. “Judging the future by the past,” he wrote, “we are likely to be as much ridiculed in the next century for our blind belief in the power of unseen germs as our forefathers were for their faith in the influence of spirits.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Not only did many American doctors not believe in germs, they took pride in the particular brand of filth that defined their profession.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;They spoke fondly of the “good old surgical stink” that pervaded their hospitals and operating rooms, and they resisted making too many concessions even to basic hygiene … They believed that the thicker the layers of dried blood and pus, black and crumbling as they bent over their patients, the greater the tribute to their years of experience … They preferred, moreover, to rely on their own methods of treatment, which not infrequently involved applying a hot poultice of cow manure to an open wound.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even a child reading this today recognizes how insane this is. And it’s hardly an isolated example. Doctors used to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(02)88719-0/fulltext&quot;&gt;prescribe chloroform&lt;/a&gt; for asthma and cigarettes for hay fever. They &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigthink.com/health/milk-transfusion/&quot;&gt;injected cow’s milk&lt;/a&gt; into the veins of tuberculosis patients, hoping the fat would transform into white blood cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mercifully, we’ve moved on. We believe new crazy stuff, but not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; crazy stuff. Everyone learned, those learnings were universally accepted and passed down the generations who are now better off because of it. Reading about medicine from 100 years ago makes you feel utterly disconnected from today’s world, like you’re reading about a different topic altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But take something like money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These lines were written 130 years ago by author William Dawson:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It would seem that the anxieties of getting money only beget the more torturing anxiety of how to keep it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;More lives have been spoiled by competence than by poverty; indeed, I doubt whether poverty has any effect at all upon a strong character, except as a stimulus to exertion.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The thing that is least perceived about wealth is that all pleasure in money ends at the point where economy becomes unnecessary. The man who can buy anything he covets values nothing that he buys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or this, written by Earnest Hemingway in 1936:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;He remembered poor Scott Fitzgerald and his romantic awe of [the rich] … He thought they were a special glamorous race and when he found they weren’t it wrecked him as much as any other thing that wrecked him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or this, written by a lawyer in 1934, taking account of the bubble preceding the Great Depression:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In normal times the average professional man makes just a living and lives up to the limit of his income because he must dress well, etc. In times of depression he not only fails to make a living but has no surplus capital to buy bargains in stocks and real estate. I see now how very important it is for the professional man to build up a surplus in normal times. Without it he is at the mercy of the economic winds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or this, describing the 1920s Florida real estate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From 1919 to 1929, both forms of personal debt—mortgages and installment credit—soared. The volume of home mortgages more than tripled, and the amount of outstanding installment debt more than doubled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/books/2015/mar/27/seneca-fat-cat-philosopher-emily-wilson-a-life&quot;&gt;account&lt;/a&gt; of Seneca, who lived 2,000 years ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Enemies accused him of preying on affluent elderly people in the hope of being remembered in their wills, and of “sucking the provinces dry” by lending money at a steep rate of interest to those in the distant parts of the empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all so relatable. Like nothing has changed. We’ve always been asking the same questions, dealing with the same problems, and falling for the same false solutions. We probably always will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading old finance articles makes you feel like the ancient past was no different than today – the opposite feeling you get reading old medical commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there are things we knew about medicine 200 years ago that were true and things we believed about money 100 years ago that were false. But in degree there is no comparison – there’s no financial equivalent of everyone denying germs only to eventually agree that it’s so obviously true it’s not worth debating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some fields our knowledge is seamlessly passed down across generations. In others, it’s fleeting. To paraphrase investor Jim Grant: Knowledge in some fields is cumulative. In other fields it’s cyclical (at best).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are occasional periods when society learns that debt can be dangerous, greed backfires, and more money won’t solve all your problems. But it quickly forgets and moves on. Again and again. Generation after generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think there are a few reasons this happens, and what it means we have to accept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some fields have quantifiable truths, while others are guided by vague beliefs and individual circumstances&lt;/strong&gt;. Physicist Richard Feynman said, “Imagine how much harder physics would be if electrons had feelings.” Well, people do. So any topic guided by behavior – money, philosophy, relationships, etc. – can’t be solved with a formula like physics and math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil deGrasse Tyson says, “The good thing about science is that it’s true whether or not you believe in it.” You can disagree and say science is the practice of continuous exploration and changing your mind, but in general he’s right. Germ theory is true and we know it’s true. But what about the proper level of savings and spending to live a good life? Or how much risk to take? Or the right investing strategy given today’s economy? Those kinds of questions do not lend themselves to scientific answers. They’re subjective, nuanced, and impacted by how the economy changes over time. So often there simply isn’t relevant information to pass down to the next generations. Even when firm financial rules exist, some truths have to be experienced firsthand to be understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cyclical knowledge, and the inability to fully learn from others’ past experiences, means you have to accept a level of volatility and fragility not found in other fields&lt;/strong&gt;. I can imagine a world in 50 years where things like cancer and heart disease are either non-existent or effectively controlled. I cannot ever imagine a world where economic volatility is tamed and people stop making financial decisions they eventually regret – no matter how much history of past mistakes we have to study.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 16:55:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/cumulative-vs-cyclical-knowledge/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/cumulative-vs-cyclical-knowledge/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Handle Hard Well</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been writing these articles for close to a decade now. In doing so I have covered many topics, but none have resonated more than this issue of adversity. As a result, my antenna is up. This is why I happened to notice something this past Sunday afternoon while watching the Buffalo Bills play the Kansas City Chiefs, specifically the two starting quarterbacks — Josh Allen and Patrick Mahomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allen and Mahomes may be the two best quarterbacks in the NFL today. Allen is currently the frontrunner to be this year’s MVP, while Patrick Mahomes was the League MVP in 2018 and Super Bowl MVP in 2020. Yet, neither was expected to even make it to the NFL. In fact, Mahomes wasn’t even ranked in the top 50 recruits in his home state of Texas and Allen failed to receive &lt;em&gt;a single&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;scholarship&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;offer&lt;/em&gt; coming out of high school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intrigued, I started doing some more digging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Josh Allen, Aaron Rodgers, the four-time and two-time reigning NFL MVP, also didn’t receive a scholarship offer coming out of high school. He was then passed over by &lt;em&gt;21 other teams&lt;/em&gt; and had to back up Brett Favre for three seasons before starting his first NFL game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about the 2019 MVP, the year between Rodgers and Mahomes? Lamar Jackson was a three star recruit (out of five) who wasn’t even among the top 400 recruits his senior year in high school. He was also strongly encouraged by the “experts” to play a position other than quarterback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The the last MVP outside of this group? Tom Brady, who has become the greatest quarterback of all time &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o5fdhfVrg1I&quot;&gt;after being passed over by &lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o5fdhfVrg1I&quot;&gt;every&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o5fdhfVrg1I&quot;&gt; NFL franchise multiple times&lt;/a&gt; in the 2000 NFL draft until the Patriots finally drafted him in the 6th round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list doesn’t end there. Of the top ten quarterbacks heading into this season, only &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; was rated a five-star recruit coming out of high school. Of the 32 starting quarterbacks in the NFL today, you can count the number of five-star recruits on just &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; hand. The fact is, this group of predominantly three-star quarterbacks was considered by many to be too short, slow, inaccurate, or raw to become regular starters. Yet, they are currently occupying the most demanding job in all of sports, while countless five-star “sure things” have flamed out along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Duke women’s head basketball coach, Kara Lawson, said it better than I ever could in a recent speech to her team about how important it is to “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oDzfZOfNki4&quot;&gt;handle hard wel&lt;/a&gt;l.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Most people think things are going to get easier. Life is going to get easier. Basketball is going to get easier. School is going to get easier. It never gets easier. What happens is you become someone who handles hard stuff better. And if you think life when you leave college is going to all of a sudden get easier because you graduated and you got a Duke degree, it’s not going to get easier. It’s going to get harder. &lt;em&gt;So make yourself a person that ‘handles hard well’&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does this relate to NFL quarterbacks? While five-star football recruits likely expected to start immediately when they reached campus, three-star recruits had to compete to win their starting spots. While five-stars were reading their own press clippings, three-stars likely didn’t have any clippings to read. While many five-stars maxed out in high school by maturing physically early or focusing exclusively on football, many three-stars matured later, played multiple sports growing up, and juggled other responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/sports/story/2021-01-23/josh-allen-firebaugh-california-town-buffalo-bills-nfl&quot;&gt;Josh Allen&lt;/a&gt; is the poster child. He was an undersized kid from a two stop-light town better known for producing melons than athletes. Instead of traveling around the country to attend elite quarterback camps, he was playing three sports, busing tables at his mother’s restaurant, and working on the family farm weeding fields, moving irrigation pipes and driving the tractor. Instead of transferring to a larger high school after a breakout junior season, he and his parents decided to pass on the opportunity. Why? Because they believed that, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://buffalonews.com/sports/bills/you-bloom-where-youre-planted-the-cultivation-of-josh-allen-part-1/video_edd08018-6274-583b-b9fe-0166eed45576.html&quot;&gt;you bloom where you’re planted&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after a strong senior season, Allen didn’t receive a single Division 1 offer. Without one, he went to junior college where he had to win the starting job. After generating nearly 450 yards per game, Allen &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; only received one Division 1 offer (The University of Wyoming). He sat for much of his first season in Laramie, but won the starting job his junior and senior seasons where he excelled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, even with this success, countless pundits were skeptical about his professional prospects, pointing to the fact that he had faced weak competition and was not accurate enough to play in the NFL. Yet, the Buffalo Bills were willing to take a chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because they needed someone who had repeatedly beaten the odds. After all, the Bills hadn’t won their division or a playoff game in close to two-and-a-half decades, and had &lt;em&gt;twenty&lt;/em&gt; starting quarterbacks along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why did the Bills think this unpolished 22-year-old quarterback who had not received a single scholarship offer out of high school could turn this beleaguered franchise around?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Because Allen knew how to “handle hard well.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since he was drafted, Allen has started more than 60 games, thrown over 110 touchdowns, passed for more than 15,000 yards, and rushed for close to 2,500 yards. He is arguably the most exciting player in the NFL today. Most importantly, he has led the Bills to the playoffs for three consecutive seasons, helped them win their division the past two seasons, and has them atop the NFL this year. Allen has literally &lt;em&gt;saved the franchise&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why does this matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It matters because when the majority of the starting quarterbacks in the NFL were middle-of-the-road college recruits, a lot of “experts” missed something. When the past four NFL MVPs either didn’t receive a college scholarship, were advised to play another position, or not drafted until the 6th round, it is worth looking into why. When the common thread among each of these quarterbacks is that they have had to overcome significant adversity and have “handled hard well”, there should be lessons that go well beyond football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the financial markets, we may be in the midst of learning one of these lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade of historically low interest rates lulled investors into a sense of complacency. Even the best among us came to believe it was normal for the NASDAQ to compound at 20% annually, venture capital firms to produce billion dollar unicorns, mortgage rates to remain below 3% (since 1971 the average mortgage rate has been close to 8%), and diversification to no longer matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the sirens from Greek mythology, low interest rates seduced investors into speculating in cryptocurrencies, meme stocks, and get-rich-quick schemes. In pursuit of higher returns, investors’ due diligence waned and their perception of risk became skewed, especially as nearly every investment they touched appreciated in value. &lt;em&gt;It all felt too easy&lt;/em&gt;. In short, low rates convinced a lot of investors they were five-star recruits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is nothing new. This sort of behavior stretches across generations. As Walter Bagehot, the British journalist and businessman, said in the mid-1800’s,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“It is a fact of experience that when the interest of money is 2% (or less), capital habitually emigrates and is wasted on foolish speculations, which never yield any adequate return. If the old, tried, and safe investments no longer yield their accustomed returns, we must take what they do yield, or try what is untried. We must either be poorer or less safe; less opulent or less secure.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad news is that when investors have historically chosen the latter, trouble has followed. Unfortunately, in pursuit of higher returns, many investors this time around once again chose what is untried, less safe, and less secure. This means we are likely in for a tough sled. It is going to be hard. Interest rates are the price of money and that price has gone up. A lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These periods aren’t fun. They never are, but the good news is that in their wake something positive happens. The adversity will separate the wheat from the chaff, the three-stars with upside from five-stars without it, and those who can “handle hard well” from those who cannot. As a result, while I don’t know how long this economic downturn will last or how severe it will be, I do expect that those who have overcome adversity in the past and have excelled in multiple endeavors (as opposed to having a singular focus) will separate themselves from those who haven’t. Like the Buffalo Bills with Josh Allen, this period will create an opportunity for investors to find their quarterback for the next decade, be it in funds, companies, or business divisions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 13:24:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/handle-hard-well/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/handle-hard-well/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Expectations and Reality</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2004 the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; interviewed Stephen Hawking, the late scientist whose motor-neuron disease left him paralyzed and unable to talk since age 21.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently in a good mood, the &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; asked Hawking: “Are you always this cheerful? Seriously, how do you keep your spirits up?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“My expectations were reduced to zero when I was 21,” Hawking said. “Everything since then has been a bonus.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite a lesson, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s one that applies to a lot of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what makes any joke funny is the surprise. The setup leads you down one path (“Someone gets in a car accident every nine seconds”), then the punchline comes in a direction you didn’t expect (“Imagine how bad a driver that guy is.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The setup of that (very bad) joke is sad. The punchline is meaningless. It’s the gap between the two – the punchline deviating from your expectations – that might make you laugh. Few one-line jokes are funny; there’s not enough potential to set someone’s expectations, so it’s harder to surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So many things work like that. People get excited when they’re surprised. Not when something big happens, or when they find the right answer. They get happy, mad, scared, amused, and astounded when they stumble across a gap between expectations and reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many examples of this that defy intuition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will Smith writes in his biography that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Becoming famous is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Being famous is a mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Losing fame is miserable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of fame almost doesn’t matter. Going from a nobody to a little famous creates a huge gap between what you expected your life to be and what it became – same on the way down, in the other direction. But being famous merely meets expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tennis player Naomi Osaka said last summer that she got to a point in her career where winning a major world tournament didn’t bring any joy – “I feel more like a relief,” she &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tennis.com/news/articles/naomi-osaka-isn-t-enjoying-herself-even-when-she-wins-so-you-can-understand-her-&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a friend who grew up in abject poverty in Africa. He now works in tech in California. He says to this day he is still blown away when a hot meal is put in front of him. It’s astounding to him how abundant food is in America. Part of me is a little envious of that trait – he finds immense pleasure from something I don’t think twice about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry Truman – a failed retailer, failed farmer, failed zinc miner, failed oil driller, and senator held on leash by local Missouri businessmen – was almost universally panned when he became President after Franklin Roosevelt died. The &lt;em&gt;Washington Post&lt;/em&gt; wrote: “We should be less than candid at this grave moment if we did not recognize the great disparity between Mr. Truman’s experience and the responsibilities that have been thrust upon him.” Historian David McCoullough wrote: “To many it was not just that the greatest of men had fallen, but that the least of men— or at any rate the least likely of men— had assumed his place.” Today, Truman is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Historical_rankings_of_presidents_of_the_United_States&quot;&gt;consistently ranked &lt;/a&gt;among historians’ top-10 presidents of all time, often ahead of Roosevelt. Part of that, I’ve come to believe, is that expectations for Truman’s abilities were so low that any leadership qualities he put forth blew people’s minds. A little success was a win; a big success felt like a miracle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual circumstances don’t make much difference in all of these cases. What generates all the emotion is just how big the gap is between expectations and reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think of it like that you realize how powerful expectations are. They can make the best tennis player in the world feel miserable and a paralyzed man feel amazing. It’s astounding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone, everywhere, doing almost any task, is just in pursuit of finding some space between expectations and reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that’s so easy to overlook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Kaufman, CEO of Glenair and one of the smartest people you will ever come across, wrote once:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We tend to take every precaution to safeguard our material possessions because we know what they cost. But at the same time we neglect things which are much more precious because they don’t come with price tags attached: The real value of things like our eyesight or relationships or freedom can be hidden to us, because money is not changing hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same with expectations – they’re easy to ignore because their value isn’t on a price tag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But your happiness completely relies on expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your boss’s impression of your career relies on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumer confidence relies on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What moves the stock market relies on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why do we pay so little attention to them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent so much effort trying to improve our income, skills, and ability to forecast the future – all good stuff worthy of our attention. But on the other side there’s almost a complete ignorance of expectations, especially managing them with as much effort as we put into changing our circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aldous Huxley said, “Most human beings have an almost infinite capacity for taking things for granted.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How true, and how scary. Imagine a life where almost everything gets better but you never appreciate it because your expectations rise as fast as your circumstances. It’s terrifying, and almost as bad a world where nothing gets better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked, “You seem extremely happy and content. What’s your secret to living a happy life?” 98-year-old Charlie Munger recently replied:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The first rule of a happy life is low expectations. If you have unrealistic expectations you’re going to be miserable your whole life. You want to have reasonable expectations and take life’s results good and bad as they happen with a certain amount of stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend Brent has a related theory about marriage: It only works when both people want to help their spouse while expecting nothing in return. If you both do that, you’re both pleasantly surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of those are easier said than done. I think it’s often hard to distinguish high expectations from motivation. Low expectations feels like giving up and minimizing your potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way around that might be recognizing two things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One, the realization that most good outcomes come from a minority of the actions you take, so it’s normal if most of what you do doesn’t work out. Failing nine times and having a big win on the tenth attempt is about as good as it gets in a lot of things – investments, relationships, careers, etc. When you accept that losing often is the only path to winning occasionally, it’s easier to keep your expectations low without losing ambition and motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two, understand how the expectation game is played. It’s a mental game, and it’s often a crazy and agonizing game, but it’s a game that everyone is forced to play, so you should be aware of the rules and strategies. It goes like this: You think you want progress, both for yourself and for the world. But most of the time that’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://collabfund.com/blog/death-taxes-and-a-few-other-things/&quot;&gt;not actually what you want&lt;/a&gt;. You want to feel a gap between what you expected and what actually happened. And the expectation side of that equation is not only important, but often it’s more in your control than managing your circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 18:36:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/expectations-and-reality/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/expectations-and-reality/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Little Rules About Big Things</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few things I’ve come to terms with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is rarely more or less economic uncertainty; just &lt;a href=&quot;https://collabfund.com/blog/endless-uncertainty/&quot;&gt;changes in how ignorant people are&lt;/a&gt; to potential risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should obsess over risks that do permanent damage and care little about risks that do temporary harm, but the opposite is more common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to build wealth is to have a gap between your ego and your income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone belongs to a tribe and underestimates how influential that tribe is on their thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of financial debates are just people with different time horizons talking over each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to mistake “I’m good at this” with “Others are bad at this” in a way that makes you overestimate how valuable your skills are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to know the difference between rosy optimism and periods of chaos that trend upward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your expectations grow faster than your income you’ll never be happy with your money no matter how much you accumulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inability to forecast the past has no impact on our desire to forecast the future. Certainty is so valuable that we’ll never give up the quest for it, and most people couldn’t get out of bed in the morning if they were honest about how uncertain the future is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having no FOMO might be the most important investing skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few things are as valuable in the modern world as a good bullshit detector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of what people call “conviction” is a willful disregard for new information that might make you change your mind. That’s when beliefs turn dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have vastly different desires, except for three things: Respect, feeling useful, and control over their time. Those are nearly universal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The market is rational but investors play different games and those games look irrational to people playing a different game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a sweet spot where you grasp the important stuff but you’re not smart enough to be bored with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big takeaway from economic history is that the past wasn’t as good as you remember, the present isn’t as bad as you think, and the future will be better than you anticipate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most assholes are going through something terrible in their life. People hide their skeletons, which requires blind forgiveness of their quirks and moods because you’re unaware of what they’re dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History is driven by surprising events but forecasting is driven by obvious ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pessimism always sounds smarter than optimism because optimism sounds like a sales pitch while pessimism sounds like someone trying to help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every past decline looks like an opportunity and every future decline looks like a risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A comforting delusion is thinking that other people’s bad circumstances couldn’t also happen to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many people the process of becoming wealthier feels better than having wealth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something can be factually true but contextually nonsense. Bad ideas often have at least some seed of truth that gives their followers confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every market valuation is a number from today multiplied by a story about tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comedians are the only good thought leaders because they understand how the world works but they want to make you laugh rather than make themselves feel smart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People learn when they’re surprised. Not when they read the right answer, or are told they’re doing it wrong, but when they experience a gap between expectations and reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People tend to know what makes them angry with more certainty than what might make them happy. Happiness is complicated because you keep moving the goalposts. Misery is more predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting rich and staying rich are different things that require different skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money’s greatest intrinsic value is its ability to give you control over your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Past success always seems easier than it was because you now know how the story ends, and you can’t unremember what you know today when trying to remember how you felt in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Learn enough from history to respect one another’s delusions.” -Will Durant&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s more to learn from people who endured risk than those who seemingly conquered it, because the kind of skills you need to endure risk are more likely repeatable and relevant to future risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing too good or too bad stays that way forever, because great times plant the seeds of their own destruction through complacency and leverage, and bad times plant the seeds of their own turnaround through opportunity and panic-driven problem-solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people can afford to not be a great investor. But they can’t afford to be a bad investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What money can and can’t do for you isn’t intuitive, so most people are surprised at how they feel when they suddenly have more or less than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your personal experiences make up maybe 0.00000001% of what’s happened in the world but maybe 80% of how you think the world works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsustainable things can last longer than you anticipate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The thing that is least perceived about wealth is that all pleasure in money ends at the point where economy becomes unnecessary. The man who can buy anything he covets, without any consultation with his banker, values nothing that he buys.” - William Dawson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Napoleon’s definition of a military genius was “The man who can do the average thing when everyone else around him is losing his mind.” It’s the same in business and investing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to tell the difference between boldness and recklessness, greed and ambition, contrarian and wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Woodrow Wilson talked about whether something was accountable to Darwin or accountable to Newton. It’s a useful idea. Everything is accountable to one of the two, and you have to know whether something adapts and changes over time or perpetually stays the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk has two stages: First, when it actually hits. Then, when its scars influence our subsequent decisions. The recession, and the lingering pessimism that does as much damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell people what they want to hear and you can be wrong indefinitely without penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimism and pessimism always overshoot because the only way to know the boundaries of either is to go a little bit past them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reputations have momentum in both directions because people want to associate with winners and avoid losers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easier to lie with numbers than words, because people understand stories but their eyes glaze over with numbers. As the saying goes, more fiction has been written in Excel than Word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to take advantage of people. It’s also easy to underestimate the power and influence of groups of people who have been taken advantage of for too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have five seconds to get people’s attention. Books, blogs, emails, reports, it doesn’t matter – if you don’t sell them in five seconds you’ve exhausted most of their patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It always looks like we haven’t innovated in 10 or 20 years because it can take10 or 20 years before an innovation is an obvious success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When and where you were born can have a bigger impact on your outcome in life than anything you do intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people are good at learning facts but not great at learning rules – the broad lessons from events that will apply to future events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone is making a bet on an unknown future. It’s only called speculation when you disagree with someone else’s bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two types of information: stuff you’ll still care about in the future, and stuff that matters less and less over time. Long-term vs. expiring knowledge. It’s critical to identify which is which when you come across something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same traits needed for outlier success are the same traits that increase the odds of failure. The line between bold and reckless is thin. So be careful blindly praising successes or criticizing failures, as they often made similar decisions with slightly different levels of luck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When communicating, “know your audience” easily becomes “pander to your audience.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most financial mistakes come when you try to force things to happen faster than is required. Compounding doesn’t like when you try to use a cheat code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an optimal net worth for most people, after which not only does happiness stop increasing but more money becomes a social and psychological liability. The number is different for everyone, but is probably lower than most people think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk is what you can’t see, think only happens to other people, aren’t paying attention to, are willfully ignoring, and isn’t in the news. A little surprise usually does more damage than something big that’s been in the news for months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Innovation and economics can be miles apart. Twitter directly influences geopolitics between nuclear states and is worth half as much as Progressive Auto Insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk management is less about how you respond to risk and more about recognizing how many things can go wrong before they actually do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is too much marketing (waving your arms) and not enough branding (building trust).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of people don’t realize what bet they’re making. Maybe they thought they were betting on disruptive technology, but it turned out they were betting on low interest rates. Or they thought they were betting on alternative energy, but it turned out they were betting on subsidies and tax credits. Many bets don’t work not because your bet was wrong, but because you didn’t realize the bet you were making in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Housing is often a liability masquerading as a safe asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asking what the biggest risks are is like asking what you expect to be surprised about. If you knew what the biggest risk was you would do something about it, and doing something about it makes it less risky. What your imagination can’t fathom is the dangerous stuff, and it’s why risk can never be mastered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of good writing makes points that people already intuitively know but haven’t yet put into words. It works because readers learn something new without having to expend much energy questioning whether it’s true. The alternatives are points that are obvious and well known (boring) or something that’s non-obvious and unknown (often takes too much effort to understand and impatient readers leave).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotions can override any level of intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small risks are overblown because they’re easy to talk about, big risks are discounted and ignored because they seem preposterous before they arrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have an idea but think “someone has already done that,” just remember there are 1,010 published biographies of Winston Churchill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one is thinking about you as much as you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John D. Rockefeller was worth the equivalent of $400 billion, but he never had penicillin, sunscreen, or Advil. For most of his adult life he didn’t have electric lights, air conditioning, or sunglasses. Everything about wealth is circumstances in the context of expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read fewer forecasts and more history. Study more failures and fewer successes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an optimal amount of bullshit in life. Having no tolerance for hassle, nonsense and inefficiency is not an admirable trait; it’s denying reality. Once you accept a certain level of BS, you stop denying its existence and have a clearer view of how the world works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most problems are more complicated than they look but most solutions should be simpler than they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About once a decade people forget that bubbles form and burst about once a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If something is impossible to know you are better off not being very smart, because smart people fool themselves into thinking they know while average people are more likely to shrug their shoulders and end up closer to reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t believe in risk without also believing in luck because they are fundamentally the same thing—an acknowledgment that things outside of your control can have a bigger impact on outcomes than anything you do on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Reality will pay you back in equal proportion to your delusion.” – Will Smith&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common irony goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Paranoia leads to success because it keeps you on your toes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But paranoia is stressful, so you abandon it quickly once you achieve success.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Now you’ve abandoned what made you successful and you begin to decline – which is even more stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk’s greatest fuels are leverage, overconfidence, ego, and impatience. Its greatest antidote is having options, humility, and other people’s trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once-in-a-century events happen all the time because lots of unrelated things can go wrong. If there’s a 1% chance of a new disastrous pandemic, a 1% chance of a crippling depression, a 1% chance of a catastrophic flood, a 1% chance of political collapse, and on and on, then the odds that &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; bad will happen next year – or any year – are … pretty good. It’s why Arnold Toynbee says history is “just one damn thing after another.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People suffering from sudden, unexpected hardship can adopt views they previously would have considered unthinkable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easiest to convince people that you’re special if they don’t know you well enough to see all the ways you’re not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large group of people can become better informed over time. But they can’t, on average, become more patient, less greedy, or more level-headed during periods of upheaval. That will never change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good ideas are easy to write, bad ideas are hard. Difficulty is a quality signal, and writer’s block usually indicates more about your ideas than your writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More people wake up every morning wanting to solve problems than wake up looking to cause harm. But people who cause harm get the most attention. So slow progress amid a drumbeat of bad news is the normal state of affairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything is sales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 17:54:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/little-rules-about-big-things/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/little-rules-about-big-things/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Few Good Books</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple I’ve enjoyed lately:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Sonic-Boom-Impossible-Records-Fleetwood/dp/1250301564&quot;&gt;Sonic Boom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Peter Ames Carlin&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of Warner Brothers Music, and how to build a business with a durable competitive advantage. There are two ways to treat customers and business partners: As opportunities to exploit, in which case they’ll eventually leave, or with transparency and fairness, in which case they’ll stick with you for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Mindwise-Misunderstand-Others-Think-Believe/dp/030774356X&quot;&gt;Mindwise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Nicholas Epley&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We aren’t good at knowing what other people are thinking, even those we’re closest with (spouses, parents, children). Worse, we’re not aware of how bad we are, massively underestimating our ability to understand other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Scoundrel-Convicted-Persuaded-Conservative-Establishment/dp/0062899767&quot;&gt;Scoundrel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Sarah Weinman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true story of a man who committed a heinous murder, was sentenced to death, used his media connections to sweet talk his way to parole, then after being released immediately committed another violent crime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Long-Gray-Line-American-Journey/dp/080509122X&quot;&gt;The Long Gray Line&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Rick Atkinson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of the West Point class of 1966, who began their military journey with confidence and bravado, were thrust into the Vietnam War, then struggled in its aftermath to make sense of their place in the world and find a new path forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Trillion-Dollar-Triage-President-Pandemic/dp/0316272817&quot;&gt;Trillion Dollar Triage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Nick Timiraos&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An incredible read on how close the financial system was to collapse in March, 2020, during Covid’s initial panic and economic lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Where-Buck-Stops-Personal-Writings/dp/0446514942&quot;&gt;Where The Buck Stops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Harry Truman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After he left the White House Harry Truman wrote and dictated his unfiltered thoughts on America, former presidents, and world order. They are so unvarnished and brutally honest that he demanded the book not be published until after he and his wife were dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Salinger-Biography-Paul-Alexander/dp/0312673345&quot;&gt;Salinger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, by Paul Alexander&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best biography I’ve seen on one of the most complicated men on the 20th century: The most famous writer of his era who abruptly shut off the outside world and resigned to his remote cabin, rarely heard from and only seen a few times for the next half-century.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 12:52:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/a-few-good-books-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/a-few-good-books-2/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Expectations (Five Short Stories)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;David Cassidy seemed to have the best life you could imagine. A teenage heartthrob who sold out arenas and was so popular his shows turned into stampede risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the outside it looked like as interesting and lucky a life anyone could hope for. Everyone loved him. He was rich. He was on top of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after he died in 2017, Cassidy’s daughter revealed that his last words were, “So much wasted time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s never &lt;a href=&quot;https://collabfund.com/blog/hard/&quot;&gt;as good as it looks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apollo 11 was the first time in history humans visited another celestial body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think that would be an overwhelming experience – literally the coolest thing any human had ever done. But as the spacecraft hovered over the moon, Michael Collins turned to Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin and said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s amazing how quickly you adapt. It doesn’t seem weird at all to me to look out there and see the moon going by, you know?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later, after Al Bean walked on the moon during Apollo 12, he turned to astronaut Pete Conrad and said, “It’s kind of like the song: &lt;em&gt;Is that all there is?&lt;/em&gt;” Conrad was relieved, because he secretly felt the same, describing his moonwalk as spectacular but not momentous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most mental upside comes from the thrill of anticipation – actual experiences tend to fall flat, and your mind quickly moves on to anticipating the next event. That’s how dopamine works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If walking on the moon left astronauts underwhelmed, what does it say about our own earthly goals and expectations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirty-seven thousand Americans died in car accidents in 1955, six times today’s rate adjusted for miles driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ford began offering seat belts in every model that year. It was a $27 upgrade, equivalent to about $190 today. Research showed they reduced traffic fatalities by nearly 70%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But only 2% of customers opted for the upgrade. Ninety-eight percent of buyers chose to remain at the mercy of inertia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things eventually changed, but it took decades. Seatbelt usage &lt;a href=&quot;https://crashstats.nhtsa.dot.gov/Api/Public/ViewPublication/810962&quot;&gt;was still under 15%&lt;/a&gt; in the early 1980s. It didn’t exceed 80% until the early 2000s – almost half a century after Ford offered them in all cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to underestimate how social norms stall change, even when the change is an obvious improvement. One of the strongest forces in the world is the urge to keep doing things as you’ve always done them, because people don’t like to be told they’ve been doing things wrong. Change eventually comes, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://collabfund.com/blog/when-you-change-the-world-and-no-one-notices/&quot;&gt;agonizingly slower than you might assume&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Black Death plague entered England in 1348, the Scots laughed at their good fortune. With the English crippled by disease, now was a perfect time for Scotland to stage an attack on its neighbor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Scots huddled together thousands of troops in preparation for battle. Which, of course, is the worst possible move during a pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Before they could move, the savage mortality fell upon them too, scattering some in death and the rest in panic,” historian Barbara Tuchman writes in her book &lt;em&gt;A Distant Mirror&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a powerful urge to think risk is something that happens to other people. Other people get unlucky, other people make dumb decisions, other people get swayed by the seduction of greed and fear. But &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;? &lt;em&gt;Me&lt;/em&gt;? No, never us. False confidence makes the eventual reality all the more shocking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some are more susceptible to risk than others, but no one is exempt from being humbled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Dan Goodman once performed surgery on a middle-aged woman whose cataract had left her blind since childhood. The cataract was removed, leaving the woman with near-perfect vision. A miraculous success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patient returned for a checkup a few weeks later. The book &lt;em&gt;Crashing Through&lt;/em&gt; writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Her reaction startled Goodman. She had been happy and content as a blind person. Now sighted, she became anxious and depressed. She told him that she had spent her adult life on welfare and had never worked, married, or ventured far from home – a small existence to which she had become comfortably accustomed. Now, however, government officials told her that she no longer qualified for disability, and they expected her to get a job. Society wanted her to function normally. It was, she told Goldman, too much to handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every goal you dream about has a downside that’s easy to overlook.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2022 13:48:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://collabfund.com/blog/five-short-stories/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://collabfund.com/blog/five-short-stories/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
