<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
	<title>Planet Lisp</title>
	<link>http://planet.lisp.org/</link>
	<description>Planet Lisp</description>
	<language>en</language>


<item>
	<title>Joe Marshall: Tail recursion and fold-left</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">http://funcall.blogspot.com/2021/08/tail-recursion-and-fold-left.html</guid>
	<link>http://funcall.blogspot.com/2021/08/tail-recursion-and-fold-left.html</link>
	
	<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;fold-left&lt;/code&gt; has this basic recursion:&lt;pre&gt;(fold-left f init ())      = init
(fold-left f init (a . d)) = (fold-left f (f init a) d)&lt;/pre&gt;
A straightforward implementation of this is&lt;pre&gt;(defun fold-left (f init list)
  (if (null list)
      init
      (fold-left f (funcall f init (car list)) (cdr list))))&lt;/pre&gt;
The straightforward implementation uses a slightly more space than
necessary.  The call to &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt; occurs in a subproblem
position, so there the stack frame for &lt;code&gt;fold-left&lt;/code&gt; is
preserved on each call and the result of the call is returned to that
stack frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the result of &lt;code&gt;fold-left&lt;/code&gt; is the result of the last
call to &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt;, so we don't need to retain the stack frame
for &lt;code&gt;fold-left&lt;/code&gt; on the last call.  We can end the iteration on a tail call
to &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt; on the final element by unrolling the loop
once:&lt;pre&gt;(defun fold-left (f init list)
  (if (null list)
      init
      (fold-left-1 f init (car list) (cdr list))))

(defun fold-left-1 (f init head tail)
  (if (null tail)
      (funcall f init head)
      (fold-left-1 f (funcall f init head) (car tail) (cdr tail))))&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There aren't many problems where this would make a difference (a
  challenge to readers is to come up with a program that runs fine
  with the unrolled loop but causes a stack overflow with the
  straightforward implementation), but depending on how extreme your
  position on tail recursion is, this might be worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Mon, 30 Aug 2021 13:29:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Joe Marshall: A Floating-point Problem</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">http://funcall.blogspot.com/2021/08/a-floating-point-problem.html</guid>
	<link>http://funcall.blogspot.com/2021/08/a-floating-point-problem.html</link>
	
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Here's a 2x2 matrix:&lt;pre&gt;[64919121   -159018721]
[41869520.5 -102558961]&lt;/pre&gt;We can multiply it by a 2 element vector like this:&lt;pre&gt;(defun mxv (a b
            c d

            x
            y

            receiver)
  (funcall receiver
           (+ (* a x) (* b y))
           (+ (* c x) (* d y))))

* (mxv 64919121     -159018721
       41869520.5d0 -102558961
 
       3
       1

       #'list)

(35738642 2.30496005d7)&lt;/pre&gt;Given a matrix and a result, we want to
  find the 2 element vector that produces that result.  To do this, we
  compute the inverse of the matrix:&lt;pre&gt;(defun m-inverse (a b
                  c d

                  receiver)
  (let ((det (- (* a d) (* b c))))
    (funcall receiver
             (/ d det) (/ (- b) det)
             (/ (- c) det) (/ a det))))&lt;/pre&gt;and multiply the inverse
  matrix by the result:&lt;pre&gt;(defun solve (a b
              c d

              x
              y

              receiver)
  (m-inverse a b
             c d
             (lambda (ia ib
                      ic id)
               (mxv ia ib
                    ic id

                    x
                    y
                    receiver))))&lt;/pre&gt;So we can try this on our matrix&lt;pre&gt;* (solve 64919121     -159018721
         41869520.5d0 -102558961

         1
         0
         #'list)

(1.02558961d8 4.18695205d7)&lt;/pre&gt;and we get the wrong answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's the right answer?&lt;pre&gt;* (solve 64919121         -159018721
         (+ 41869520 1/2) -102558961

         1
         0
         #'list)

(205117922 83739041)&lt;/pre&gt;If we use double precision floating point, we get
  the wrong answer by a considerable margin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm used to floating point calculations being off a little in the least
  significant digits, and I've seen how the errors can accumulate in an iterative
  calculation, but here we've lost all the significant digits in a straightforward
  non-iterative calculation.  Here's what happened:  The determinant of our matrix is
  computed by subtracting the product of the two diagonals.  One
  diagonal is &lt;code&gt;(* 64919121 -102558961) =
  -6658037598793281&lt;/code&gt;, where the other diagonal is &lt;code&gt;(* (+
  41869520 1/2) -159018721) = -6658037598793280.5&lt;/code&gt;  This second
  diagonal product cannot be represented in double precision floating
  point, so it is rounded down to -6658037598793280.  This is where
  the error is introduced.  An error of .5 in a quantity of
  -6658037598793281 is small indeed, but we amplify this error when we
  subtract out the other diagonal.  We still have an absolute error of
  .5, but now it occurs within a quantity of 1, which makes it
  relatively huge.  This is called &amp;ldquo;catastrophic cancellation&amp;rdquo;
  because the subtraction &amp;ldquo;cancelled&amp;rdquo; all the significant digits
(the &amp;ldquo;catastrophe&amp;rdquo; is presumably the amplification of the error).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don't care for the term &amp;ldquo;catastrophic cancellation&amp;rdquo;
  because it places the blame on the operation of subtraction.  But
  the subtraction did nothing wrong.  The difference betweeen
  -6658037598793280 and -6658037598793281 is 1 and that is the result
  we got.  It was the rounding in the prior step that introduced an
  incorrect value into the calculation.  The subtraction just exposed
  this and made it obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One could be cynical and reject floating point operations as being too
  unreliable.  When we used exact rationals, we got the exactly correct result.
  But rational numbers are much slower than floating point and they have a tendancy
  to occupy larger and larger amounts of memory as the computation continues.
  Floating point is fast and efficient, but you have to be careful when you use it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 13:47:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Joe Marshall: Fold right</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">http://funcall.blogspot.com/2021/08/fold-right.html</guid>
	<link>http://funcall.blogspot.com/2021/08/fold-right.html</link>
	
	<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;fold-left&lt;/code&gt; takes arguments like
this:&lt;pre&gt;(fold-left &lt;i&gt;function&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;init&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;list&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/pre&gt;and
  computes&lt;pre&gt;* (fold-left (lambda (l r) `(f ,l ,r)) 'init '(a b c))
(F (F (F INIT A) B) C)&lt;/pre&gt;Notice how &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; is the leftmost
of all the arguments to the function, and each argument appears left
  to right as it is folded in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now look at the usual way &lt;code&gt;fold-right&lt;/code&gt; is
  defined:&lt;pre&gt;(fold-right &lt;i&gt;function&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;init&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;list&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/pre&gt;It
  computes &lt;pre&gt;* (fold-right (lambda (l r) `(f ,l ,r)) 'init '(a b c))
(F A (F B (F C INIT)))&lt;/pre&gt;although &lt;code&gt;init&lt;/code&gt; appears first
  and to the left of &lt;code&gt;'(a b c)&lt;/code&gt; in the arguments
  to &lt;code&gt;fold-right&lt;/code&gt;, it is actually used as the rightmost
  argument to the last application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems to me that the arguments to &lt;code&gt;fold-right&lt;/code&gt; should
  be in this order:&lt;pre&gt;; (fold-right &lt;i&gt;function&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;list&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;final&lt;/i&gt;)
* (fold-right (lambda (l r) `(f ,l ,r)) '(a b c) 'final)
(F A (F B (F C FINAL)))&lt;/pre&gt;
The argument lists to &lt;code&gt;fold-left&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;fold-right&lt;/code&gt; would no longer match, but I think
  switching things around so that the anti-symmetry of the arguments
  matches the anti-symmetry of the folding makes things clearer.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2021 12:35:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Quicklisp news: August 2021 Quicklisp dist update now available</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.quicklisp.org/2021/08/august-2021-quicklisp-dist-update-now.html</guid>
	<link>http://blog.quicklisp.org/2021/08/august-2021-quicklisp-dist-update-now.html</link>
	
	<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;New projects&lt;/b&gt;:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/charje/cache-while/&quot;&gt;cache-while&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; A Common Lisp macro for defining temporary caches that invalidate based on expressions evaluating to different values. &amp;mdash; LLGPL&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/K1D77A/cl-coinpayments/&quot;&gt;cl-coinpayments&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Helpers for working with the coinpayments.net api. &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Goheeca/cl-drawille/&quot;&gt;cl-drawille&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; cl-drawille: Drawing in terminal with Unicode Braille characters. &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/naryl/sha1/&quot;&gt;cl-sha1&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; SHA1 Digest and HMAC for LispWorks. &amp;mdash; Apache 2.0&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/copyleft/cl-webdriver-client/&quot;&gt;cl-webdriver-client&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; cl-webdriver-client is a binding library to the Selenium 4.0 &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dtenny/clj-con/&quot;&gt;clj-con&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Implements Clojure-styled concurrency operations such as `future` and `promise`. &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dtenny/clj-re/&quot;&gt;clj-re&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Implements Clojure-styled regexp operations such as `re-matches` and `re-find`. &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://shinmera.github.io/depot&quot;&gt;depot&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Protocol for transparent collections of files. &amp;mdash; zlib&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/ambrevar/fof&quot;&gt;fof&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Enable rapid file search, inspection and manipulation &amp;mdash; GPL3+&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hyotang666/hash-table-ext/&quot;&gt;hash-table-ext&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Tiny extensions for common lisp hash-tables. &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/interactive-ssr/hunchenissr-routes/&quot;&gt;hunchenissr-routes&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Better routes to be used with Hunchenissr. &amp;mdash; LLGPL&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hemml/OMGlib/&quot;&gt;omglib&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; A Common Lisp library to build fully dynamic web interfaces &amp;mdash; GPL3&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hyotang666/query-repl/&quot;&gt;query-repl&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; REPL for user query. &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tdrhq/slite/&quot;&gt;slite&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; SLIME based Test-runner for FiveAM tests (and possibly others in the future) &amp;mdash; Apache License, Version 2.0&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/y2q-actionman/with-c-syntax/&quot;&gt;with-c-syntax&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; with-c-syntax is a fun package which introduces the C language syntax into Common Lisp. &amp;mdash; WTFPL&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Updated projects&lt;/b&gt;: 3d-vectors, alexandria, also-alsa, april, architecture.builder-protocol, bdef, caveman, check-bnf, chipz, chirp, cl+ssl, cl-ana, cl-collider, cl-cuda, cl-debug-print, cl-environments, cl-form-types, cl-gamepad, cl-gserver, cl-i18n, cl-kraken, cl-las, cl-liballegro, cl-migratum, cl-mixed, cl-opencl, cl-opencl-utils, cl-patterns, cl-ses4, cl-sse, cl-utils, cl-webkit, clack, clem, clog, closer-mop, cmd, colored, command-line-arguments, common-doc, common-html, common-lisp-jupyter, consfigurator, core-reader, croatoan, cserial-port, cytoscape-clj, dartscluuid, data-frame, dexador, dfio, drakma, drakma-async, file-attributes, flexi-streams, gendl, generic-cl, harmony, imago, introspect-environment, jingoh, kekule-clj, lack, lisp-binary, lisp-stat, lispbuilder, lyrics, markup, mcclim, mito, mnas-package, mnas-string, mutility, neural-classifier, null-package, nyxt, overlord, parachute, petalisp, portable-condition-system, postmodern, prompt-for, qlot, quickutil, quilc, read-as-string, rove, sanity-clause, screamer, sel, serapeum, shasht, shop3, sketch, sly, snappy, snooze, special-functions, speechless, static-dispatch, stumpwm, tailrec, ten, tfeb-lisp-hax, tfeb-lisp-tools, trestrul, trivial-ed-functions, trivial-inspector-hook, ufo, uiop, uncursed, vellum, vellum-csv, vgplot, vk, websocket-driver, whirlog, zacl.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Removed projects&lt;/b&gt;: lucerne&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To get this update, use (ql:update-dist &quot;quicklisp&quot;). Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2021 18:40:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Nicolas Hafner: GDC, fighting, and more - August Kandria Update</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/399</guid>
	<link>https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/399</link>
	
	<description>&lt;img alt=&quot;https://studio.tymoon.eu/api/studio/file?id=2017&quot; src=&quot;https://studio.tymoon.eu/api/studio/file?id=2017&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;A big ole update for Kandria this month! &lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;GDC&quot;&gt;GDC&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the main events this month was GDC. This was my first time attending, and I'm really glad that I was offered the chance to with the great support by Pro Helvetia and SwissNex. Thank you very much again for all of your support this year!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The highlight of the event for me were the daily video networking sessions, where you were led onto a virtual floor with a bunch of tables. Each table could seat up to six people and you'd chat over audio and video. It was really cool to hang out and chat with fellow attendees about... well, pretty much whatever!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What wasn't so cool about those sessions, was that they only lasted for an hour, at the end of which you were unceremoniously booted out, without even the ability to see who you were at the table with, nor the accompanying text chat. I do not understand at all why that platform was not just up throughout the entirety of the conference. It's not like there were ever that many people there to begin with, I never saw the total number rise above 120.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With regards to the booth that we had at the Swiss country pavilion, that unfortunately turned out to be almost pointless. Everyone I talked to at the virtual meet wasn't even aware that booths existed at all, let alone the ones in the country pavilions. Being buried under ten links almost guaranteed that we wouldn't be found except by the most vigilant. It isn't surprising then that we didn't get any contact requests through the booth's message box.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm really confused as to why they had practically zero visibility for the showfloors and booths. It seems to me that those are a rather large part of a usual conference, so advertising them so poorly is strange. I can't even imagine what SwissNex had to pay to get our booths set up, and I feel sorry for what they got for that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hope that next year the presentation is going to be better, as for the amount of money involved in the tickets and everything, I have to say I'm quite disappointed with the GDC organisers. We'll see how Gamescom goes next month, I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Combat developments&quot;&gt;Combat developments&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This month was meant to be devoted to combat revisions. I did get a number of those done, so movement is now a lot more satisfying and you can actually juggle enemies in the air:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;However, due to the mass of feedback amounted by the playtesting, GDC interruptions, and my general reluctance to work on it there hasn't been as much progress as I would like. I'll definitely have to revisit this again later down the road. In the very least though I feel like we have the features required in the engine now to make the system work well, it's &amp;quot;just&amp;quot; down to tweaking the parameters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To give you some perspective on why tweaking of these parameters is a pain though, let me show you a screenshot of our in-house animation editor:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNME1BPT0=&quot; src=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNME1BPT0=&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;For each frame (the player has around 700 frames of animation at this point), you can set a mass of different properties that change combat behaviour and movement. Tweaking them one by one, performing the attack, going back to tweak it again, and repeating that is an extremely arduous process.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tried my best to keep at it throughout the month, but the tedium of it made it quite difficult. I hope I can instead gradually improve it with time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;UI look and feel&quot;&gt;UI look and feel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've taken some time to change the look and feel of the UI in the game. Most notably the button prompts now look a &lt;strong&gt;lot&lt;/strong&gt; better than they used to. The fishing minigame shows that best:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The textbox also got a revision and it's now capable of doing text effects:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek9RPT0=&quot; src=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek9RPT0=&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aside from those tweaks there were a myriad of changes from the further blind playtest sessions as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Eternia update&quot;&gt;Eternia update&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1605720/Eternia_Pet_Whisperer/&quot;&gt;new update for Eternia: Pet Whisperer&lt;/a&gt; was rolled out. This update took two days to put together and includes important stability fixes for MacOS and Windows users. On MacOS the behaviour on Retina displays is improved and audio output on devices with samplerates above 44.1kHz has been fixed. General performance has also been improved. On Windows spurious crashes caused by antivirus software should now no longer occur.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eternia will also likely be on sale during the upcoming Gamescom Steam sale, so keep an eye out for that!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Tim&quot;&gt;Tim&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This month has been about press and polish. With GDC happening, I helped prioritise the press list and reach out to the most relevant people; we didn't get a huge response, which isn't unexpected (press are inundated at the best of times, never mind during GDC) - but it's been encouraging to get some replies; and most importantly, it's getting the game on peoples' radars.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've also been working through tons of feedback Nick has gathered from blind playtests of the game, using it to make the quests easier to understand and more accessible: finessing spawn locations, clarifying objectives more in dialogue, etc. I ran a few tests myself, and it's amazing how things you thought were obvious sometimes don't translate to the player. A highlight was watching my brother return to the surface after the first quest: he didn't know the rest of the settlement was over to the right, and instead went left, all the way back to the tutorial area; since Catherine was following him at the time, it re-triggered all her tutorial dialogue! Noooooooooo! (But in a good way :) )&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nick also made some cool new features like random spawners that can add a myriad of world-building items to the levels (and which later you'll be able to sell to Sahil); I spent time organising and placing these. Also, text effects and colouring! I went a bit bananas with this at first, using the swirly rainbow effect right off the bat in the tutorial, when Catherine gets excited; to be fair it's probably the only point in the game I could've justified using it. But I've since toned things back, as although the game has quirk, we need to watch the tone and make sure we don't go too cartoony. I've also established a basic visual language for using these effects and colours (hint: sparingly).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Fred&quot;&gt;Fred&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fred has been working on new sets of animations and some concept work. Some of the new animations are for expanded combat moves, so there's now a heavy and light charge attack:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek9BPT0=&quot; src=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek9BPT0=&quot; /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Mikel&quot;&gt;Mikel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mikel finished a couple more tracks, well on ... track to make the September release date with all the music for the current areas included! These tracks are for the camp area, and as such convey a more chill atmosphere:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek5nPT0=&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek53PT0=&quot;&gt;Medium Vocal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek5RPT0=&quot;&gt;Ambient&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aside from the music there's also been more audio changes, by way of a new team member:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Cai&quot;&gt;Cai&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://courier.tymoon.eu/api/courier/link/resolve?id=fdlp74XgDCmO2sRvXxoTKU1Ea2dPREU9&quot;&gt;Cai&lt;/a&gt;, I'm a Sound Designer for video games. I've been in the industry for 2 years! I focus on making impactful, meaningful sounds that help to immerse the player in the world we create! Kandria is a really exciting project to be involved with! The story and atmosphere of the game are both compelling and exciting so I'm thrilled to have the opportunity to contribute to this through the sound!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cai has been hard at work remaking the existing sounds and adding new ones. One of the bigger changes in that respect is the addition of atmospheric sound layers that now underlay each music track. The atmospherics and music both change independently depending on the area the player is currently in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It still needs some tuning, though. We need to make sure the loudness levels of each track work properly in conjunction with the atmospherics, and that the transitions between areas work smoothly without calling too much attention to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Roadmap&quot;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's look at the roadmap from &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/398&quot;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt; with the updates from this month:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Polish the ProHelvetia submission material&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Polish and revise the combat design&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Finish the desert music tracks&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Further blind playtesting and bugfixing&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Revise the general UI look and feel&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Implement a main menu, map, and other UI elements (partially done)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Create and integrate new sound effects for 90% of the interactions in the game&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explore platforming items and mechanics&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Practise platforming level design&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start work on the horizontal slice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm quite confident I can get all the UI stuff done in time, so we should be well set for the Pro Helvetia submission!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until the submission is done, be sure to check our &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/#subscribe&quot;&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt; for weekly updates, and the &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/discord&quot;&gt;discord community&lt;/a&gt; for fan discussions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 09:48:57 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Michał Herda: Common Lisp Recipes, 2nd Edition</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://mov.im/?blog/phoe%40movim.eu/ee18159d-a6ed-4487-a3cc-56eb800c536e</guid>
	<link>https://mov.im/?blog/phoe%40movim.eu/ee18159d-a6ed-4487-a3cc-56eb800c536e</link>
	
	<description>&lt;div&gt;
        &lt;div&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Let's talk a little about the second edition of Edi Weitz's &lt;a href=&quot;http://weitz.de/cl-recipes/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Common Lisp Recipes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;! What would you like to see added or changed in it? What problems have you possibly faced that could be described in a new recipe?&lt;/p&gt;
          &lt;p&gt;Please let me know via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:phoe@disroot.org&quot;&gt;mail&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://functional.cafe/@phoe&quot;&gt;Fediverse&lt;/a&gt;, IRC (&lt;code&gt;phoe&lt;/code&gt; at Libera Chat), or, if you absolutely have to, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/phoe_krk&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Thu, 29 Jul 2021 19:30:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>McCLIM: Progress report #12</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://common-lisp.net/project/mcclim/posts/Progress-report-12.html</guid>
	<link>https://common-lisp.net/project/mcclim/posts/Progress-report-12.html</link>
	
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Community,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of time passed since the last blog entry. I'm sorry for neglecting this.
In this post, I'll try to summarize the past two and a half year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Finances and bounties&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you might have noticed that the bounty program has been suspended. The
BountySource platform lost our trust around a year ago when they have changed
their ToS to include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no Solution is accepted within two years after a Bounty is posted, then the
Bounty will be withdrawn, and the amount posted for the Bounty will be
retained by Bountysource.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They've quickly retracted from that change, but the trust was already lost. Soon
after, I've suspended the account and all donations with this platform were
suspended. BountySource refunded all our pending bounties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All paid bounties were summarized in previous posts. Between 2016-08-16 and
2020-06-16 (46 months of donations) we have collected in total $18700. The
Bounty Source comission was 10% collected upon withdrawal - all amounts
mentioned below are presented for &lt;strong&gt;before&lt;/strong&gt; the comission was claimed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During that time $3200 was paid to bounty hunters who solved various issues in
McCLIM. The bounty program was a limited success - solutions that were
contributed were important, however harder problems with bounties were not
solved. That said, a few developers who contribute today to McCLIM joined in the
meantime and that might be partially thanks to the bounty program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the fundraiser was announced, I've declared I would withdraw $600 monthly
from the project account. In the meantime I've had a profitable contract and for
two years I stopped withdrawing money. During the remaining three years I've
withdrawn $15500 ($440/month) from the account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of now we don't have funds and there is no official way to donate money to
the project (however, this may change in the near future). I hope that this
summary is sufficient regarding the fundraiser. If you have further questions,
please don't hesitate to contact me, and I'll do my best to answer them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'd like to thank all people who donated to the project. Your financial support
made it possible for me to work on the project more than I would be able without
it. The fact that people care about McCLIM enough to contribute to it money
gives me the motivation and faith that working on the codebase is an important
effort that benefits the Common Lisp community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last update was in 2018-12-31. A lot of changes accumulated in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bordered output bug fixes and improvements -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gadget UX improvements (many of them) -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Text styles fixes and refactor -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freetype text renderer improvements -- Elias Mårtenson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extended input stream abstraction rewrite -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implementation of presentation methods for dialog-views -- admich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encapsulating stream missing methods implementation -- admich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;indenting-output-stream fixes -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;drawing-tests demo rewrite -- José Ronquillo Rivera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Line wrap on the word boundaries -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New margin implementation (extended text formatting) -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presentation types and presentation translators refactor -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input completion and accept methods bug fixes and reports -- Howard Shrobe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clipboard implementation (and the selection translators) -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CLIM-Fig demo improvements and bug fixes -- Christoph Keßler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pointer implementation (fix the specification conformance) -- admich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drei kill ring improvements -- Christoph Keßler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;McCLIM manual improvements -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frame icon and pretty name change extensions -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cleanups and extensive testing -- Nisar Ahmad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pointer-tracking rewrite -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;drag-and-drop translators rewrite -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Complete rewrite of the inspector Clouseau -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rewrite of the function distribute-event -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski and Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding new tests and organizing them in modules -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various fixes to the delayed repaint mechanism -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CLX backend performance and stability fixes -- Christoph Keßler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PS/PDF/Raster backends cleanups and improvements -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drei regression fixes and stability improvements -- Nisar Ahmad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geometry module refactor and improvements -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separating McCLIM code into multiple modules -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski and Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frames and frame managers improvements -- Jan Moringen and Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frame reinitialization -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PDF/PS backends functionality improvements -- admich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Menu code cleanup -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pane geometry and graph formatting fixes -- Nisar Ahmad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Numerous CLX cleanups and bug fixes -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski and Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Render backend stability, performance and functionality fixes -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presentation types more strict interpretation -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;External Continuous Integration support -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous Integration support -- Nisar Ahmad&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved macros for recording and table formatting -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better option parsing for define-application-frame -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Separation between the event queue and the stream input buffer -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples cleanup -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graph formatting cleanup -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stream panes defined in define-application-frames refactor -- admich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Menu bar rewrite (keyboard navigation, click to activate) -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thread-safe execute-frame-command function -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mirroring code simplification for clx-derived backends -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Arbitrary native transformations for sheets (i.e. zooming) -- Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extended-streams event matching improvements -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Render backend performance improvements -- death&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;drei fixes for various issues -- death&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;drei various cleanups -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;clim-debugger improvements -- Jan Moringen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manual spelling fixes and proofreading -- contrapunctus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not an exhaustive list of changes. For more details, please consult the
repository history. Many changes I've introduced during this iteration were a
subject of a careful (and time-consuming) peer review from Jan Moringen which
resulted in a better code quality. Continuous integration provided by Nisar
Ahmad definitely made my life simpler. I'd like to thank all contributors for
their time and energy spent on improving McCLIM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Pending work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are working on some exciting improvement for McCLIM which is not ready,
you may make a &amp;quot;draft&amp;quot; pull request in the McCLIM repository. Currently, there
are three such branches:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the SLIME-based &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/McCLIM/McCLIM/pull/1193&quot;&gt;backend&lt;/a&gt; for CLIM
by Luke Gorrie&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the dot-based graph layout
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/McCLIM/McCLIM/pull/1197&quot;&gt;extension&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Timmons&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;the xrender &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/McCLIM/McCLIM/pull/1196&quot;&gt;backend&lt;/a&gt; by Daniel
Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than that, I've recently implemented the polygon triangulation algorithm
that is meant to be used in the xrender backend (but could be reused i.e. for
opengl). Currently, I'm refining the new rendering for clx (xrender). After that,
I want to introduce a portable double buffering and a new repaint queue. Having
these things in place after extensive testing, I want to roll out a new release
of McCLIM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sincerely yours,&lt;br /&gt;
Daniel Kochma&amp;#324;ski&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Nicolas Hafner: Testing events - July Kandria Update</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/398</guid>
	<link>https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/398</link>
	
	<description>&lt;img alt=&quot;https://studio.tymoon.eu/api/studio/file?id=2002&quot; src=&quot;https://studio.tymoon.eu/api/studio/file?id=2002&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another month filled with a lot of different stuff! We have a lot of conferences coming up, there was a bunch to do for marketing, the game has seen a lot of visual and gameplay tweaks, and we've started doing a lot of direct playtesting. Finally, the music has also made a lot of progress and the first few tracks are now done!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;GDC, Gamescom, and GIC&quot;&gt;GDC, Gamescom, and GIC&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the very generous support from &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://prohelvetia.ch/en/&quot;&gt;Prohelvetia&lt;/a&gt; we're part of the Swiss Games delegation to &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://gdconf.com&quot;&gt;GDC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://www.gamescom.global&quot;&gt;Gamescom&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://gic.gd/&quot;&gt;GIC&lt;/a&gt;. GDC is coming up this month, and we have our own virtual booth set up for that. Given that both GDC and Gamescom are virtual this year, I honestly don't really know what to expect from them, it's going to be quite different. At least GIC is in person (Poznan, Poland) so I'm really looking forward to that!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So far we've invested quite a bit of time into looking at journalists to reach out to during GDC, and who knows, perhaps we'll also be contacted by publishers or something during the event. In any case, it's going to be an exciting week, for sure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Gamescom/Devcom are coming up in August, right before the submission deadline for the Prohelvetia grant, so that's going to be a tight squeeze, too. September is gonna be a calmer month, as we've settled for a two weeks holiday for the team during that month. Then in October it's going to be GIC for a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Marketing&quot;&gt;Marketing&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also thanks to Prohelvetia we now have direct mentoring from &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://howtomarketagame.com&quot;&gt;Chris Zukowski&lt;/a&gt; with a monthly meeting for the next six months. His first advice was to focus a lot more on top of the funnel marketing (like imgur, reddit, festivals, influencers), and cut down on all the middle stuff we've been doing (like discord, mailing list, blogs, streams).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I actually quite like doing the weekly and monthly updates though, so I'm going to keep doing those. The Sunday streams have also proven quite productive for me, so I'll use them for that purpose too, rather than for any marketing intent. I am going to cut down drastically on Twitter though, as that does not seem to really bring us much of anything at all, and I'm going to stay away from Discord more in general (not just the &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/discord&quot;&gt;Kandria one&lt;/a&gt;.).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After some brief experiments with imgur (and &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://imgur.com/gallery/VfeSh4f&quot;&gt;once even making it into most viral&lt;/a&gt;) I haven't returned to that yet though, as I've found it to be quite exhausting to figure out what to even post and how to post it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We'll definitely have to try reaching out to influencers and journalists, but we're going to hold off on that until the september demo update is done, as a more polished demo should help a lot to make us look more presentable and respectable. We should also try out Reddit, but we haven't done the necessary research yet into how exactly to post on there without getting downvoted into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second advice Chris had for us was to do more....&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Playtesting&quot;&gt;Playtesting&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We've started inviting people to do blind playtesting. The blind here meaning that they never played the game before, which gives us quite valuable insight into parts of the game that are confusing or annoying. We've done four sessions so far, and even with them being carried out over Discord, the feedback has been very useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've also been inviting people for local playtesting, as being able to observe people in person is a lot better than doing it over the net. We haven't done any of that yet, but there's several appointments scheduled already. If you're near Zürich and would be up for a playtest session, please &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://calendly.com/shinmera/kandria-playtest&quot;&gt;book a date&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And if you, like most, aren't close to Zürich, but would still like to help us out with testing, &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;mailto:shinmera@tymoon.eu&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt; anyway and we can arrange something over the net!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Tutorial&quot;&gt;Tutorial&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;We finally finished a tutorial area for the game, giving it a proper starting point, and introducing people to the controls. It doesn't explain all of them in detail though, as I think we should instead keep the more intricate controls to challenges throughout the game, rather than trying to teach everything at once.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Designing the levels to teach the various control parts is going to be challenging, but I think ultimately it is going to be worth it, especially as it allows us to keep the tutorial in the beginning very short.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The only actual tutorial part still missing is a combat primer, for which we haven't worked out a good way of teaching it yet. I'm sure we'll find a way, though.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Tim&quot;&gt;Tim&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I took a holiday for part of this month, though otherwise it's been full steam ahead on the marketing research. I've added more reference games and potential contacts to our press &amp;amp; influencer document; while doing this I've taken into account the advice we got from Chris Zukowski, about not looking too closely at games with distinct differences to Kandria (e.g. Celeste has no combat; Dead Cells is a roguelike). I've also done more research on Steam short descriptions, and worked with Nick to redraft ours. It needs a few more edits, but it's nearly there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I haven't totally forgotten the game though! With the new tutorial prologue in place, I added dialogue. This is now your first meeting with Catherine, after she reactivates you deep underground; but I've deliberately kept things short and sweet, as she guides you back up to the surface. The player has enough to think about at this stage without getting overwhelmed with dialogue; only once the tutorial segues into the settlement introduction from before, does the dialogue really begin.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Mikel&quot;&gt;Mikel&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mikel's been very busy and completed 6 different versions of the region 1 track:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNeU9BPT0=&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNeU9RPT0=&quot;&gt;Medium Vocal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek1BPT0=&quot;&gt;Quiet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNek1RPT0=&quot;&gt;Quiet Vocal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNeU5nPT0=&quot;&gt;Ambient&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNeU53PT0=&quot;&gt;Ambient Vocal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which the game can use to do vertical mixing:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Roadmap&quot;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's look at the roadmap from &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/397&quot;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt; with the updates from this month:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Build and add the tutorial sequence to the beginning of the game&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Finish the region 1 music tracks&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Add a fishing minigame&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Improve the UI for the game and editor&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Implement several editor improvements&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Compile data on journalists, influencers, and communities&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Implement a UI animation system&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Implement a cutscene system&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polish the ProHelvetia submission material (partially done)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polish and revise the combat design (partially done)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Implement a main menu, map, and other UI elements&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reach out to journalists, streamers, and other communities&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explore platforming items and mechanics&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Practise platforming level design&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start work on the horizontal slice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first three are scheduled to be done by September 1st, and so far it looks quite doable. The events are going to jumble things up a bit, but I hope that we still have enough time scheduled around to get it all done in time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until then be sure to check our &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/#subscribe&quot;&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt; for weekly updates, and the &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/discord&quot;&gt;discord community&lt;/a&gt; for fan discussions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jul 2021 19:08:41 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Quicklisp news: June 2021 Quicklisp dist update now available</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.quicklisp.org/2021/07/june-2021-quicklisp-dist-update-now.html</guid>
	<link>http://blog.quicklisp.org/2021/07/june-2021-quicklisp-dist-update-now.html</link>
	
	<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;New projects&lt;/b&gt;:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/K1D77A/cl-megolm/&quot;&gt;cl-megolm&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; A copy of the python functionality provided as bindings for Olm. &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/pokepay/cl-openapi-parser/&quot;&gt;cl-openapi-parser&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; OpenAPI 3.0.1 and 3.1.0 parser/validator &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ghollisjr/cl-opencl-utils/&quot;&gt;cl-opencl-utils&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; OpenCL utility library built on cl-opencl &amp;mdash; GPLv3&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dtenny/cl-sse/&quot;&gt;cl-sse&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; Use sse-server + a web service to serve SSE events to a browser. &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yitzchak.github.io/trivial-ed-functions/&quot;&gt;trivial-ed-functions&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; A simple compatibility layer for *ed-functions* &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yitzchak.github.io/trivial-inspector-hook/&quot;&gt;trivial-inspector-hook&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; A simple compatibility layer CDR6 &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fukamachi/webapi/&quot;&gt;webapi&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; CLOS-based wrapper builder for Web APIs &amp;mdash; BSD 2-Clause&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/codr7/whirlog/&quot;&gt;whirlog&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;mdash; a minimal versioned log structured relational DB &amp;mdash; MIT&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Updated projects&lt;/b&gt;: also-alsa, april, atomics, bdef, binding-arrows, bp, chirp, cl+ssl, cl-ana, cl-collider, cl-conllu, cl-cxx-jit, cl-data-structures, cl-environments, cl-form-types, cl-gamepad, cl-gserver, cl-heredoc, cl-incognia, cl-ipfs-api2, cl-kraken, cl-maxminddb, cl-mixed, cl-mock, cl-murmurhash, cl-naive-store, cl-ntp-client, cl-opencl, cl-patterns, cl-schedule, cl-smt-lib, cl-string-generator, cl-torrents, cl-utils, cl-webkit, clack-pretend, closer-mop, cluffer, clunit2, clx, cmd, common-lisp-jupyter, conium, consfigurator, core-reader, croatoan, defmain, deploy, dexador, djula, doc, easy-routes, eclector, fiveam-asdf, fresnel, functional-trees, gendl, generic-cl, gute, harmony, herodotus, hunchentoot-multi-acceptor, hyperluminal-mem, iolib, lack, lichat-protocol, lichat-tcp-client, lispqr, markup, mcclim, md5, mito, mnas-package, mnas-string, modularize-interfaces, multiposter, neural-classifier, numerical-utilities, nyxt, origin, osmpbf, overlord, plot, plump, portal, postmodern, py4cl2, qlot, quilc, quri, qvm, re, replic, sc-extensions, sel, serapeum, shasht, shop3, sly, smart-buffer, special-functions, spinneret, st-json, static-dispatch, static-vectors, stumpwm, sxql, tailrec, tfeb-lisp-hax, tooter, trivia, trivial-with-current-source-form, trucler, vellum, vk, wasm-encoder, woo, zippy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Removed projects&lt;/b&gt;: with-c-syntax.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To get this update, use (ql:update-dist &quot;quicklisp&quot;). Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 21:47:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>

<item>
	<title>Nicolas Hafner: Updates Galore - June Kandria Update</title>
	<guid isPermaLink="true">https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/397</guid>
	<link>https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/397</link>
	
	<description>&lt;img alt=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNeU1RPT0=&quot; src=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNeU1RPT0=&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of different news to talk about this month, so strap in!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;The New Trailer&quot;&gt;The New Trailer&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most important thing to come out of this month is the new trailer! Check it out if you haven't yet:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm overall really happy with how it came together, and we all had a part in the end result. I'd also like to give a special commendation to &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://www.adoxtalks.com&quot;&gt;Elissa Park&lt;/a&gt; who did the amazing voice over for the trailer. It was a pleasure to work together!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's also been great to finally get some custom music by Mikel into an official part of the game. He's also been working on the first music tracks that'll be in the game, and I've been working on a music system to support horizontal mixing with the tracks. I'm very excited to get all that together into the game and see how it all feels! I hope that by next month's update we'll have a short preview of that for you.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;0.1.1 Release&quot;&gt;0.1.1 Release&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile we also pushed out an update to the vertical slice release that makes use of the new linear quest system we put together. It should overall also be a lot more stable and includes many fixes for &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://gitea.tymoon.eu/shinmera/kandria/src/branch/master/CHANGES.mess#L93&quot;&gt;issues people reported to us&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As always, if you want to have a look at the demo yourself, you can do so &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/prototype&quot;&gt;free of charge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think this will be the last patch we put out until September. I can't afford to backport fixes even if more bug reports come in, as the overhead of managing that is just too high. I can't just push out new versions that follow internal development either, as those are frequently in flight and have more regressions that we typically stamp out over time, but would in the meantime provide a more buggy experience.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNeU1BPT0=&quot; src=&quot;https://filebox.tymoon.eu//file/TWpNeU1BPT0=&quot; /&gt;We started working on fishing just recently!&lt;h2 id=&quot;Dev Streams&quot;&gt;Dev Streams&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm heavily considering doing regular weekly development streams, both to see if we can attract some more interest for the project, and to be more open about the process in general. I feel like we're already very open about everything with our weekly updates, but having an immediate insight into how the game is made is another thing entirely. I think it would be really cool to show that side of development off more often!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to coordinate what time would suit the most people, please fill out this &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://doodle.com/poll/7gfcb8t38e34k8c2#calendar&quot;&gt;Doodle form&lt;/a&gt;. The exact dates don't matter, just watch for the day of the week and the time. Don't worry about the name it asks for either, it won't be public!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'll probably close the poll in a weeks, so make sure to submit an answer soon if you're interested. Streams will happen both on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitch.tv/shinmera&quot;&gt;https://twitch.tv/shinmera&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/shinmera,&quot;&gt;https://youtube.com/shinmera,&lt;/a&gt; with both being reachable through the official stream page at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stream.shinmera.com&quot;&gt;https://stream.shinmera.com&lt;/a&gt; . See you there!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Palestinian Aid Bundle&quot;&gt;Palestinian Aid Bundle&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some good folks have put together a bundle on itch.io gathering money for Palestinian aid. I'm very happy to say that our game, &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/eternia&quot;&gt;Eternia: Pet Whisperer&lt;/a&gt; is a part of this bundle!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want to support this cause and get a huge collection of amazing games in the process, &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://itch.io/b/902/indie-bundle-for-palestinian-aid&quot;&gt;head on over to itch.io&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Tim&quot;&gt;Tim&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This month I had a varied mix of tasks: working on the script for the new trailer; updating the quests in the vertical slice demo to work closer to our original vision; researching press and influencer contacts as we plan more of Kandria's marketing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The trailer came out great, and I'm really happy with the voice acting that Nick produced with Elissa Park. It was a great idea Nick had to use the character of Fi as the narrator here (originally we were going to use Catherine) - her serious outlook, and reflection on the events of the story, was just what we needed to fit the epic music from Mikel, and the epic gameplay and exploration that Nick captured on screen. The whole thing just screams epic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The quests were vastly improved too. The first quest now uses Nick's new sequencing system, so that triggers fire automatically (and more robustly) when the player arrives at the correct location, and when combat encounters are completed. The logic is also much quicker to write, so linear quests will be much faster to produce in the future. The mushroom quest also had a big refactor; now you can organically collect mushrooms out in the world, rather than going to specific enabled points. You can even sell what you find to the trader, including those poisonous black knights. It really makes the world feel more interactive. There's been general tweaks to the other quests from playtesting, and I'll continue to refine them from my own playing and players' feedback up until the Pro Helvetia submission later in the year. I'm also planning to add a couple more sidequest diversions based on the new fishing (!) minigame being added at the moment; we think a combat-focused sidequest will work well too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally on the marketing side, it's been rewarding to collect tons of potential press and influencer contacts we could approach in the future. I've basically been taking games that are strong influences and have similarities to Kandria - from hugely popular games like Celeste and Dead Cells, to lesser known ones like Kunai and Armed with Wings - then cataloguing key journalists and influencers who've streamed, made videos, or written about them. This will hopefully highlight some of the right people we can contact to help spread the word about the game.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Roadmap&quot;&gt;Roadmap&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's look at the roadmap from &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://reader.tymoon.eu/article/396&quot;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt; with the updates from this month:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Make the combat more flashy&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Finish a new trailer&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;s&gt;Revise the quest system's handling of linear quest lines&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Design and outline the factions for the rest of the game&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Develop the soundscape for Kandria and start working on the tracks for region 1&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;s&gt;Add a music system that can do layering and timed transitions&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Build and add the tutorial sequence to the beginning of the game&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finish the region 1 music tracks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reach out to journalists, streamers, and other communities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polish the ProHelvetia submission material&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Polish and revise the combat design&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explore platforming items and mechanics&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Practise platforming level design&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Start work on the horizontal slice&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;As always there's some smaller tasks that aren't in the overall roadmap. We seem to be doing pretty well keeping on track with what needs done, which is really good! It's all too easy to misjudge the time required to complete things, especially in games.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In any case, time is flying fast, and there's a lot to do. In the meantime be sure to check our &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/#subscribe&quot;&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt; for weekly updates, and the &lt;a class=&quot;external-link&quot; href=&quot;https://kandria.com/discord&quot;&gt;discord community&lt;/a&gt; for fan discussions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	
	<pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 15:49:46 GMT</pubDate>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
