<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet  type="text/xsl" media="screen" href="/~d/styles/rss2full.xsl"?><?xml-stylesheet  type="text/css" media="screen" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~d/styles/itemcontent.css"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:feedburner="http://rssnamespace.org/feedburner/ext/1.0" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Collaborative Fund</title>
    <description>Collaborative Fund is a leading source of capital for entrepreneurs pushing the world forward.</description>
    <link>http://www.collaborativefund.com</link>
    
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 12:39:01 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 12:39:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Siteleaf</generator>
    
    
      <atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/collabfund"/><feedburner:info uri="collabfund"/><atom10:link xmlns:atom10="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" rel="hub" href="http://pubsubhubbub.appspot.com/"/><item>
        <title>Rules, Truths, Beliefs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The luckier&lt;/strong&gt; you are the nicer you should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past performance&lt;/strong&gt; increases confidence more than ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There’s a sweet spot&lt;/strong&gt; where you grasp the important stuff but you’re not smart enough to be bored with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The line&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;between bold and reckless&lt;/strong&gt; is thin and often only visible with hindsight, so be careful who you admire and what you admire them for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Everyone has&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/foolsbookie/status/1419744570183766017?s=20&quot;&gt;a story but few&lt;/a&gt; have an audience,” so there’s so much going on in the world that almost everyone is blind to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Few things&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;are more persuasive&lt;/strong&gt; than the opinion you desperately want or need to be true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Average returns&lt;/strong&gt; sustained for an above-average period of time leads to extraordinary returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Every investor is making a bet on the future&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s only called speculation when you disagree with someone else’s bet or time horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statistics and probability are&lt;/strong&gt; the most relevant but perhaps least-taught maths in schools. They have so many real-world consequences about how people think about everyday risk. And yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price drives&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;narrative and narrative drives price&lt;/strong&gt;, so crazy things can last a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;People who&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;are exceptionally good&lt;/strong&gt; at one thing tend to be exceptionally bad at other things, but if you’re good at one thing people will try to emulate everything you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The market&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;is rational&lt;/strong&gt; but investors play different games and those games look irrational to people playing a different game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s easy&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;to ignore the power of tail events&lt;/strong&gt; because it’s painful to accept that most of what happens isn’t that important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“It’s very common&lt;/strong&gt; to be utterly brilliant and still think you’re way smarter than you actually are.” – Charlie Munger&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t debate&lt;/strong&gt; someone if the outcome can’t be objectively measured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Baseball player Dan Quisenberry&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;once said, “The future is much like the present, only longer.”&lt;/strong&gt; I like that idea and think it has two takeaways. One, by the time one problem ends a new one has already arrived; there’s no glorious time when everyone can relax. Two, the scenes change, but people don’t. They’re motivated and flawed the same way today that they were 100 years ago and will be 100 years from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To paraphrase&lt;/strong&gt; Jon Stewart: The only reason the world seemed like a better place during your childhood is because you were a child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Be more patient”&lt;/strong&gt; in investing is the “sleep 8 hours” of health. It sounds too simple to take seriously but will probably make a bigger difference than anything else you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“We’re all&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;just guessing&lt;/strong&gt;, but some of us have fancier math.” – Josh Brown&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You’re not&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;a machine&lt;/strong&gt;, so don’t expect to always be rational. Aiming to be reasonable is the best anyone can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncertainty&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;amid danger feels awful.&lt;/strong&gt; So it’s comforting to have strong opinions even if you have no idea what you’re talking about, because shrugging your shoulders feels reckless when the stakes are high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Human beings&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;cannot comprehend&lt;/strong&gt; very large or very small numbers. It would be useful for us to acknowledge that fact.” – Kahneman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The best story&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;always wins&lt;/strong&gt;. “What you do in this world is a matter of no consequence. The question is what can you make people believe you have done.” - Sherlock Holmes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investors as a group&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;don’t learn from booms and busts&lt;/strong&gt; because when people say they’ve learned their lesson they underestimate how much of their previous mistakes were caused by emotions that will return when faced with similar circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;don’t know why an asset has gone up&lt;/strong&gt; you’ll probably be quick to bail when it goes down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When asked&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;what it takes to win a Nobel prize&lt;/strong&gt;, Francis Crick said, “Oh, it’s very simple. My secret has been I know what to ignore.” Avoiding can be more important than finding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The best way&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;to get someone to believe something&lt;/strong&gt; is not to show them facts, because facts can be interpreted in different ways. It’s to make their income or approval in a social circle depend on believing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lots of&lt;/strong&gt; contrarianism is actually cynicism and lots of patience is actually stubbornness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s easiest&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;to convince people that you’re special&lt;/strong&gt; if they don’t know you well enough to see all the ways you’re not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comedians are&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;the best thought leaders&lt;/strong&gt; because they understand how the world works but they want to make you laugh rather than making themselves feel smart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/_sEAAJfEUnk&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 15:32:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/_sEAAJfEUnk/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/rules-truths-beliefs/</guid>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/rules-truths-beliefs/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Locker Room</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have played on a lot of teams in my life. Along the way, there have been a number of winning seasons, but just a few that ended with a championship. The winning seasons were nearly always a matter of talent. If we had more of it, we typically won more than we lost. If we had less, we did not. Since talent tends to be the defining factor in most competitive pursuits, this should not come as a surprise. What is less obvious, however, is what drove those special championship seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Growing Up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I played little league baseball, football, and hockey growing up, the gap between the best and the worst players was enormous. Some kids could barely swing a bat, throw a ball, or skate, while other kids could hit a curveball, throw a perfect spiral, and/or skate backwards with ease. As I got older though, the gap narrowed….a lot. Many of the weaker players quit and some of the best players regressed, but the biggest difference was that the competition increased dramatically as those who kept playing got better and a crop of talented younger players kept emerging. This pattern happens in nearly every sport and each generation. Just look at U.S. swimming legend Michael Phelps. At his peak, he held close to 30 world records. Today, just a decade later, that number is down to 4, including just 1 individual record. I did not give this dynamic much consideration when I was younger, but it is something I think about a lot as an adult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we age, it becomes increasingly clear that talent only gets us so far. Whether it is in sports, school, business, investing, or countless other competitive pursuits, the increase in the concentration of talent makes it more difficult to differentiate ourselves on talent alone. Look no further than Harvard’s class of 2024 class. Among its 29,000 applicants, it included 8,500 perfect GPAs, 3,500 perfect SAT math scores, and 2,700 perfect SAT verbal scores, despite the fact that Harvard only accepted ~1,700 students. Or at the fact that there are over 12,000 college football players in a given year who are all heavier, faster, and stronger than the vast majority of the players that came before them, yet still only ~200 will be drafted into the NFL (~1.6%). Intelligence and athleticism at the highest levels are no longer enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates an interesting dilemma. While someone may be improving on an absolute basis, they are often getting worse relative to their competition. Michael Mauboussin refers to this concept as the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://research-doc.credit-suisse.com/docView?language=ENG&amp;amp;format=PDF&amp;amp;source_id=em&amp;amp;document_id=805456950&amp;amp;serialid=LsvBuE4wt3XNGE0V%2B3ec251NK9soTQqcMVQ9q2QuF2I%3D&quot;&gt;Paradox of Skill&lt;/a&gt;”, which simply means that even though people may becoming more skilled at a certain pursuit, it is often &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; difficult for them to succeed because their competition is also becoming more skilled. This means that eventually the most talented people end up competing against one another, making it very difficult to become a bonafide superstar. Hence the paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this reality, what should talented people in competitive industries do? Mauboussin suggests they should “pursue easier games”. Intuitively, this advice makes a lot of sense. If you seek out less talented people to compete against, your chances of success should increase. But what if there are no easier games to play? Or, what if you are not able to or want to play a different game? If I told one of my sons to quit playing soccer, lacrosse, or flag football and go play tiddlywinks because they would have a better chance of being a star, they would tell me to go pound sand. The same goes for public equity investors. Sure, there might be less competition &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/economy/his-next-career-move-came-to-him-on-a-stretcher--and-now-its-a-400-million-business/2018/01/05/e205471c-df50-11e7-bbd0-9dfb2e37492a_story.html&quot;&gt;selling residential real estate&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/ncaaf/2020/10/15/college-footballs-biggest-bargain-coastal-carolinas-joe-moglia/5900394002/&quot;&gt;coaching football&lt;/a&gt;, or investing in private companies in more remote parts of the world, but are these types of options realistic or desirable? For many, I would guess not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if either my sons or a public equity investor were to recognize that talent alone may not be enough, easier games are not a realistic option, and/or they want to keep playing their current games despite the challenge, what would I tell them? I would advise them to keep pursuing what they love, but to seek out teams with great “locker rooms” to pursue them with. Doing so will give them a long lasting edge that isn’t talked about nearly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Team’s Composition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many U.S. sports fans agree that the greatest victory in this country’s history was when a group of unknown college kids, led by head coach Herb Brooks, stunned the Soviets 4-3 in the 1980 Winter Olympics and went on to win the gold medal in ice hockey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked how he assembled the team, as well as his University of Minnesota hockey teams (Brooks had taken Minnesota from a perpetual doormat to winning three Division 1 National Championships in 7 years), Brooks responded,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“The key to my recruiting was that I looked for people first, athletes second. I wanted people with sound value systems because you cannot buy values. You are only as good as your values. I learned early on that you do not put greatness into people…but somehow try to pull it out.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have ever played athletics, you know exactly what Brooks is talking about. A great locker room brings out the best in people. It elevates the true leaders, convinces those with selfish streaks to put them aside, and enables a team to play beyond their talent level. Most importantly, when things are not going well, a strong locker room is what allows you to look each other in the eye and know you are going to turn things around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are in one of these locker rooms, it is obvious. You can feel it. However, the trouble is that if you are not, you cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Business Locker Room&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In business, a firm’s culture is its locker room and, I would argue, the most important determinant of long term success. Look no further than a discussion AirBnB founder Brian Chesky had with Peter Thiel. Chesky recounted that,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“After we closed our Series C with Peter Thiel in 2012, we invited him to our office. Half way through the conversation, I asked him what was the single most important piece of advice he had for us. He replied, ‘Don’t f*ck up the culture.’“&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thiel is far from alone. Sequoia Capital, widely regarded as the world’s best venture firm, has a section on their website titled “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sequoiacap.com/newsletter&quot;&gt;Seven Questions With&lt;/a&gt;”, which is a series of interviews with various partners, executives, and investors. In nearly every interview I have read, “culture” is referenced as the most important contributor to a company’s success. Jamie Dimon has mandated that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/jackkelly/2021/04/28/jp-morgan-requires-employees-to-return-to-their-offices-by-july-striking-a-blow-to-the-remote-work-trend/?sh=47abde554cdc&quot;&gt;JP Morgan employees return to the office&lt;/a&gt;, presumably due to concerns about the work-from-home impact on the firm’s culture. Legendary investor Steve Mandel &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/steve-mandel-investing-behind-change/id1154105909?i=1000529443256&quot;&gt;recently commented&lt;/a&gt; that the number one thing his mentor, Julian Robertson, taught him was how important people are, starting with their integrity. &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/capital-allocators/id1223764016?i=1000529671820&quot;&gt;Bill Ford&lt;/a&gt; of General Atlantic and &lt;a href=&quot;https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/private-equity-masters-7-orlando-bravo-thoma-bravo/id1223764016?i=1000530727528&quot;&gt;Orlando Bravo&lt;/a&gt; of Thomo Bravo said something similar in recent interviews with Ted Seides on Capital Allocators. Maybe most notably, there appears to be a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simpplr.com/blog/2019/glassdoor-ratings-stock-market-performance/#:\~:text=strengthen%20our%20hypothesis%3A-,Companies%20with%20an%20above%2Daverage%20overall%20Glassdoor%20rating%20experience%20a,prices%20by%20a%20%3C1%25.&quot;&gt;growing correlation between companies’ stock prices and their Glassdoor reviews&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/2-3b7a84.png&quot; alt=&quot;2-3b7a84.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Model Locker Room&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most difficult parts about determining whether a team, fund, or company has a good culture is that there is no such thing as a model “locker room”. They come in all shapes and sizes. In my experience, some have leaders with the ability to motivate and unite the team, others have strong entrenched cultures created by prior generations, while others fit somewhere else on a vast spectrum of organizations. There is no magic formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meet with a lot of funds and investors as a part of my job. For every one that we choose to partner with, we will often meet with more than 100 others. Almost all are full of talented people with impressive resumes and degrees, so checking the box for talent is relatively easy. This is no surprise given the fact that institutional investing is one of the more competitive careers one can pursue. The hard part is determining what is behind these resumes and track records because this is where a key edge and source of endurance resides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why is it hard to identify the strong “locker rooms”? Because it is not easily quantifiable. As data has proliferated, the vast majority of people have become obsessed with what they can quantify. In baseball, this equates to “Moneyball Stats” (on-base percentage, walks, etc.). In basketball, it is three point percentage and possessions per game. In investing, we have wrung the stats towel so tightly with measurements like the sharpe ratio, beta, alpha, PME’s, and r-squared that my head spins when I read through attribution reports. It is not that statistics are not helpful. It is just that in isolation, they do not tell us much about whether a fund will be successful five, ten, and fifteen years down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What to Look For&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since there are no hard and fast rules regarding what defines a strong locker room or a culture, my preference is to keep it simple at the start. I ask everyone I meet with the first time to define the source of their “edge” and “endurance”. I want to hear why they think their fund has an advantage and why this edge is sustainable? More importantly, I want to see if there is consistency or dispersion in the team’s answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of the positive indications I look for are (a) shared ownership in the business, (b) low employee turnover, (c) diversity of thought, experience, and backgrounds, and (d) an aligned incentive structure. Dig a little deeper though and there are some less obvious indications of a good locker room. Namely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mentors&lt;/strong&gt; – Does the firm prioritize mentorship? Do employees feel like they have advocates within the firm? Do the mentees eventually become the mentors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt; – Do people at the firm trust those around and above them? If younger employees look left and right in a meeting, do they admire these people? Do they aspire to be in their bosses’ shoes in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy&lt;/strong&gt; – Do the “higher ups” value their employees’ opinions? Do they encourage open discussions or do they “steer” the conversation? Do they value differing opinions or just say they do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recruiting&lt;/strong&gt; – What types of qualities does the firm prioritize when hiring? How much emphasis is placed on character versus sheer intellectual horsepower? Where do they recruit from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability&lt;/strong&gt; – How has the firm handled disruptive colleagues? Are the most talented colleagues given exceptions or are they held to the same standard? How are good team players acknowledged and rewarded?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each case, the more examples, the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are not hard and fast rules. There never are. They are just some of the observations I have made after spending considerable time in a wide variety of locker rooms and offices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Long Season&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most careers, investing in particular, have plenty of highs, a number of lows, and a lot of mundane moments that fall somewhere in between. The high and mundane periods have a tendency to take care of themselves. The lows are what define you and the relationships you choose. They are the moments you realize how important your locker room is. Or, as Doug Leone, the current managing partner of Sequoia Capital, recently said in response to a question about how and why Sequoia was able to escape the dot.com bust with positive numbers, unlike the vast majority of venture firms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“It was a sense of camaraderie. It was the fact that each one of the cells in our bodies could not do that (walk away from those funds). It had nothing to do with, ‘we have to save our careers, our money, none of that’. It had to do with being a badass and doing what nobody else would do. That’s what it had to do with. Doing the right thing when it’s inconvenient for you.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tough times are the ones that make you realize how much you cherish having teammates and partners who are going to get you to the other side because this is what truly adds long term value.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/7xMjXYPnltY&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 18:33:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/7xMjXYPnltY/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/the-locker-room/</guid>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/the-locker-room/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fresh Insights Into The Growing Home Garden Trend</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;62% of Americans want to grow their own food, according to Collaborative Fund’s latest research into micro-farming and the home garden craze. Innovative indoor systems are making it easier than ever.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distance from farm to table may be shrinking, as new options for growing produce at home crop up. To understand the potential market for in-home veggie stands, Collaborative Fund surveyed 267 Americans. We asked about home gardening to gauge people’s interest in growing their own food, and to uncover potential barriers. While many people turned to gardening during pandemic lockdowns, how do they feel about it now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/CollaborativeFund_GreenThumbsGraphic6-ef61a6.png&quot; alt=&quot;CollaborativeFund_GreenThumbsGraphic6-ef61a6.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOT NICHE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a broad market for home garden products. Almost two-thirds of those we surveyed said they bought at least one plant in the past 12 months. They are also frequent salad shoppers: 73% are buying produce at least weekly; only 7% said they bought produce “rarely” or “never.” Most people are interested in growing their own produce at home. 62% said they are interested or open to it. There was substantial enthusiasm, with 23% of respondents saying they were “definitely” interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/Alt_GreenThumbs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alt_GreenThumbs.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LOTS OF PLANT-BUYERS, FEWER GREEN THUMBS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While 63% of respondents said they buy plants, only 34% think they have a green thumb (top 2 box). Another 29% have a mixed record. This low confidence opens the door for systems that claim to be fool-proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FRESH TASTE IS THE TOP MOTIVATOR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We asked the best reason to grow your own greens. “Freshness / Taste” was the top answer, chosen the most (29%), followed by “Food safety / security (knowing how it is grown)” (14%). Saving money, health, and a “fun or relaxing hobby” rounded out the top 5 reasons. Environmental benefits like reducing one’s carbon footprint or reducing waste were less motivating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HIGH POTENTIAL WITH LAPSED GARDENERS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research uncovered a large potential market for easier growing systems: lapsed gardeners. Only 27% of respondents are currently raising their own gardens, but a hefty 45% said that they used to. We asked them why they gave it up. The top response was a lack of space; many people mentioned moving to a city or apartment. The #2 reason was lack of time, and the #3 answer was “too much work.” Other respondents mentioned pests like squirrels that always thwarted their gardening efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/CollaborativeFund_GreenThumbsGraphic4.png&quot; alt=&quot;CollaborativeFund_GreenThumbsGraphic4.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THE NEW GARDEN: EASY, STYLISH, AND EARTH-FRIENDLY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aspiring home gardeners who lack space, time, or a green thumb are getting some help from the latest systems. These kits or hydroponic structures are delivered to your door and offer a choice of plants, from salad greens to herbs to edible flowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indoor systems with built-in lights like &lt;a href=&quot;https://risegardens.com/&quot;&gt;Rise Gardens&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ivegebox.com/&quot;&gt;Vegebox&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mygardyn.com/&quot;&gt;My Gardyn&lt;/a&gt; remove the need for outdoor garden space. Families might enjoy the &lt;a href=&quot;https://backtotheroots.com/&quot;&gt;Back to the Roots&lt;/a&gt; water garden, a planter that sits atop a fish tank (apparently plants like fish poop, and the roots clean the tank).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lettucegrow.com/&quot;&gt;Lettuce Grow&lt;/a&gt; offers flexibility with their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lettucegrow.com/the-farmstand&quot;&gt;Farmstand&lt;/a&gt;, a stylish and expandable garden tower that can live outdoors or stay inside with additional lights. It was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://heavy.com/garden/hydroponic-garden/&quot;&gt;top pick&lt;/a&gt; in hydroponic gardens from the editors at Heavy, who liked that it only takes five minutes per week, uses very little water, and reduces your carbon footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like your fresh greens with an even fresher attitude, check out the plant kits from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.growgardenio.com/&quot;&gt;Gardenio&lt;/a&gt;. According to their website, “We are latinx, womxn, lgbtqia+ owned. We give a s–t. We’re the new face of gardening and don’t even wear flannel. Lots of denim tho.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/CollaborativeFund_GreenThumbsGraphic5.png&quot; alt=&quot;CollaborativeFund_GreenThumbsGraphic5.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OUTDOOR SPACE OPTIONAL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With most lapsed gardeners citing lack of space as the top reason they stopped, the small footprint of plant kits and hydroponic systems have a lot of appeal. Many work indoors, making it easier for apartment-dwellers to get in on the satisfaction of harvesting their own, home-grown salad. Most of our survey respondents already have their own outdoor space (68%), but some might still be excited about indoor options, given the time and effort it takes to garden outdoors (as well as the pests they have to battle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HOME GARDENING IS HERE TO STAY, NO GREEN THUMB NEEDED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With high interest from consumers and increasing options from new players in the category, more and more people may try their hand at growing lettuce, tomatoes, herbs, and more. Most people already buy plants, eat a lot of produce, and want to garden. But only a third have a “green thumb,” creating big opportunity for easy systems. There’s a high-potential target of folks who used to garden but stopped because it was too much work, they don’t have the space, or they gave up fighting animals that ate their plants. Companies in the micro-farming category already talk about how they make it easy, but could do more to emphasize the top purchase driver: the unbeatable fresh-picked taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/CF_GreenThumb_pullquote.png&quot; alt=&quot;CF_GreenThumb_pullquote.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/drDwtwScksw&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 17:26:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/drDwtwScksw/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/fresh-insights-into-the-growing-home-garden-trend/</guid>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/fresh-insights-into-the-growing-home-garden-trend/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hanging By A Thread</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A big lesson from history is how chance encounters lead to both magic and mayhem in ways that would have been impossible to predict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me show you three times history hung by a thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giuseppe Zangara was tiny, barely five feet tall. He stood on a chair outside a Miami political rally in 1933 because that was the only way he could aim his gun across the crowd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zangara fired five shots. One of them hit Chicago mayor Anton Cermak, who was shaking hands with Zagara’s intended target. Cermak died. The target – Franklin Roosevelt – was sworn in as president two weeks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within months of inauguration Roosevelt transformed the U.S. economy through the New Deal. John Nance Garner – who would have become president had Zangara hit his target – opposed most of the New Deal’s deficit spending. He almost certainly wouldn’t have enacted the same policies, some of which still shape today’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Captain William Turner invited his niece, actress Mercedes Desmore, to tour his massive ocean liner before it sailed from New York To Liverpool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ship’s crew, eager to leave on time, removed the gangway for departure while Desmore was still onboard. She was stuck on a ship about to begin a seven-day voyage. Her furious uncle made the crew re-dock the ship so she could get off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The redocking delayed the ship’s departure. No one could have known that six days later the delay would mean that Turner’s ship – the Lusitania – would sail into the path of a German submarine at the very moment its periscope could finally see through the day’s diminishing fog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lusitania was hit with a torpedo, killing 1,200 passengers and becoming the most important trigger to rally U.S. public support for entering World War I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had it sailed through the Celtic Sea half an hour earlier – had Desmore’s tour not caused a delay – the Lusitania would have been cloaked in heavy fog. The ship likely would have avoided attack. A country may have avoided a war that became the seed event for the rest of the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert E. Lee had one last shot to escape Ulysses Grant’s troops and regroup to gain the upper hand in the Civil War. His plan was bold but totally plausible. All he needed was food for his hungry troops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An order was put in to have rations delivered to a Virginia supply depot for Lee’s men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there was a communication error in Richmond, and the wagons delivered boxes of ammunition but not a morsel of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lee said the mishap “was fatal, and could not be retrieved.” His troops were starving. The Civil War ended two days later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History hangs by a thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can play this game all day. Every big event could have turned out differently if a few little puffs of nothingness went the other direction. It’s so easy to prove how fragile big events are to trivia and accident that you start to wonder what the point is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s even crazier when you realize that every modern event has its roots in big past events, some of which occurred decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a simple question like, “What caused the financial crisis?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked that most people point to things like lending standards and the Federal Reserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you keep digging into the roots of what happened you go down a rabbit hole that never ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the financial crisis you have to understand the mortgage market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What shaped the modern mortgage market? Well, you have to understand the 30-year decline in interest rates that preceded it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What caused falling interest rates? Well, you have to understand the inflation of the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What caused that inflation? Well, you have to understand the monetary system of the 1970s and the hangover effects of the Vietnam War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What caused the Vietnam War? Well, you have to understand the West’s fear of communism after World War II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What caused World War II? Well, you have to understand World War I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What caused World War I? Well, for the Americans’ participation, an actress toured her uncle’s boat and then …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s also a game you can play all day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And an endless number of modern innovations were born out of those freak events. The modern grocery store &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/when-the-magic-happens/&quot;&gt;was invented&lt;/a&gt; because food sellers were trying to survive the Great Depression. Penicillin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3673487/&quot;&gt;owes its existence&lt;/a&gt; to World War II. So do radar, jets, nuclear energy, rockets, and helicopters. mRNA vaccines will owe their existence to Covid-19. All of those big events could have turned out completely differently if a few minor accidents had gone a different way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much of history hangs by a thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finance professor Ellroy Dimson says, “risk means more things can happen than will happen.” An important point here is that if none of these big events occurred, something else just as wild and unpredictable could have taken their place. Even when some part of the outcome is the same, the context and little bits of trivia are different in a way that can totally change the final story. America may have joined World War I without the Lusitania’s sinking, but its participation could have been less, or later, or not as popular. That could have shifted how the interwar period in the 1920s and 1930s played out, which would have impacted how World War II occurred, which would have altered the course of the most promising inventions of the 20th century … on and on, endlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to keep two things in mind in a world that’s this fragile to chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is to base your predictions on how people behave vs. specific events. Predicting what the world will look like in, say, 2050, is just impossible. But predicting that people will still respond to greed, fear, opportunity, exploitation, risk, uncertainty, tribal affiliations and social persuasion in the same way is a bet I’d take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another – made so starkly in the last year and a half – is that no matter what the world looks like today, and what seems obvious today, everything can change tomorrow because of some tiny accident no one’s thinking about. Events, like money, compound. And the central feature of compounding is that it’s never intuitive how big something can grow from a small beginning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/E1JA_sUhrKY&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 16:23:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/E1JA_sUhrKY/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/thread/</guid>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/thread/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What We're Reading</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eriktorenberg.substack.com/p/truth-status-and-tribes&quot;&gt;Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I refer to “increasing status” in the positive sense: accomplishing something impressive or contributing to others in a way that increases their estimation of you. That’s the only way that works, anyway. Paraphrasing Taleb: anything done with explicit intent to improve one’s status likely *won’t *improve one’s status. After all, the most respected people achieved their status as a byproduct of doing something great, like pursuing ambition, honor, and integrity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theirrelevantinvestor.com/2021/07/29/something-you-cant-buy/&quot;&gt;Communication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Your truth and *the *truth are not always the same thing. *The *truth is a fact. Your truth is just an opinion. Nobody values somebody who is honest about their opinions if their opinions always suck. Knowing when to offer your truth and keep your mouth shut is a rare quality. The line between thoughtful dialogue and disrespectful disagreement is razor-thin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/u-s-population-growth-slows-birth-rate-decline-economic-risk-11627231536&quot;&gt;Different world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/Screen%20Shot%202021-08-05%20at%203.32.44%20PM-418748.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screen Shot 2021-08-05 at 3.32.44 PM-418748.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/poll/351932/americans-life-ratings-reach-record-high.aspx&quot;&gt;“Thriving” at a new record&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/hhnnjuv8m0iqxpykpnv-pq.png&quot; alt=&quot;hhnnjuv8m0iqxpykpnv-pq.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a good weekend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/N1v65fHyy78&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 18:28:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/N1v65fHyy78/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/what-were-reading-8521/</guid>
        
        <category>What We're Reading</category>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/what-were-reading-8521/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Other People’s Mistakes</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;George Carlin once &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8rh6qqsmxNs&amp;amp;ab_channel=Mentat99&quot;&gt;joked&lt;/a&gt; how easy it is to spot stupid people. “Carry a little pad and pencil around with you. You’ll wind up with 30 or 40 names by the end of the day. It doesn’t take long to spot one of them, does it? Takes about eight seconds.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most comedy it’s funny because it’s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Daniel Kahneman mentions a more important truth in his book, &lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt;: “It is easier to recognize other people’s mistakes than our own.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would add my own theory: It’s easier to blame other people’s mistakes on stupidity and greed than our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s because when you make a mistake, I judge it solely based on what I see. It’s quick and easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I make a mistake there’s a long and persuasive monologue in my head that justifies bad decisions and adds important context other people don’t see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone’s like that. It’s normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s a problem, because it makes it easy to underestimate your own flaws and become too cynical about others’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to stop myself whenever my explanation for other people’s behavior – financial or otherwise – is “well, they’re not very smart.” Or greedy. Or immoral. Yeah, sometimes it’s true. But probably less than we assume. More often there’s something else going on that you’re not seeing that makes the behavior more understandable, even if it’s still wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few things make it that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. When judging others’ poor behavior it’s easy to underestimate your own susceptibility to the power of incentives.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worst behavior resides in industries with the most extreme incentives. Finance, where scams are everywhere. High-end art, where counterfeits proliferate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s important to ask: Are immoral people attracted to industries where there are big rewards for bad behavior? Or do big rewards for bad behavior cause good people to slide into immorality, justifying their decisions along the way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think so often it’s the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It helps explain things like the 2008 financial crisis. Was it caused by greedy bankers? Maybe here and there. But the huge majority of it was good, honest people who wanted to do the right thing but whose definition of “the right thing” is instantly warped when they’re paid $8 million a year to sell subprime bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incentives are almost like a drug in their ability to cloud your judgment in a way you would have found unthinkable beforehand. They can get good people to justify all kinds of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t excuse bad behavior. But it’s hard to know what you’d be willing to do until you’re exposed to an extreme incentive, and that blindness makes it easy to criticize other people’s mistakes when you yourself may have been just as tempted if you were in their shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. It’s hard to tell the difference between boldness and recklessness, greed and ambition,&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;contrarian and wrong.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same traits needed to be hugely successful are often the same traits needed to spark a catastrophe. Not always, but a lot of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A low-probability bet that works makes you look like a genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A low-probability bet that fails makes you look like a … failure, maybe even an idiot, in the eyes of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the difference between the two may have been minuscule. It could have been the same person doing the exact same thing ending up on the fortune or unfortunate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/ironies-of-luck/&quot;&gt;side of luck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything worth pursuing has a less than 100% chance of working. And a lot of terrible ideas have at least some chance of working. So you can make good decisions that don’t work, bad ones that do, and everything in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hard thing is that when the probability isn’t easy to determine, the path of least resistance is to put your own failures in the “good bet that unfortunately didn’t work” category and other people’s failures in the “that was clearly a bad idea” one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When judging others you want a simple story – did it work or did it not? And when judging yourself you want a comforting story – “my actions were worthwhile and I’m a good person.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those are just the easy explanations, not necessarily the right ones. So you may not be as great, and other people may not be as bad, as it looks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Not all relevant information is visible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brother in law, a social worker, recently told me, “All behavior makes sense with enough information.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s such a good point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see someone doing something crazy and think, “Why in the world would you do that?” Then you sit down with them, hear about their life, and after a while you realize, “Ah, I kind of get it now.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone is a product of their own life experiences, few of which are visible or known to other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes sense to me might not make sense to you because you don’t know what kind of experiences have shaped me and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question, &lt;em&gt;“Why don’t you agree with me?”&lt;/em&gt; can have infinite answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes one side is selfish, or stupid, or blind, or uninformed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But usually a better question is, “&lt;em&gt;What have you experienced that I haven’t that would make you believe what you do? And would I think about the world like you do if I experienced what you have?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the question that contains the most answers of why people don’t agree with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s such a hard question to ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s uncomfortable to think that what you haven’t experienced might change what you believe because it’s admitting your own ignorance. It’s much easier to assume those who disagree with you aren’t thinking as hard as you are – especially when judging others’ mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/V1aX8Boeb44&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 16:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/V1aX8Boeb44/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/mistakes/</guid>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/mistakes/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What We're Reading</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/selling-your-used-car-you-could-turn-a-profit-11626606000?mod=itp_wsj&amp;amp;ru=yahoo&quot;&gt;Car prices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Historically, it has been cheaper to buy a used vehicle over a new one, and overall that remains the case. But for some used models—mostly those with low mileage and bought in the past year or two—the differential is closing quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For instance, the average price paid by a customer in June for a one-year-old vehicle was only about $80 less than the selling price of a brand-new vehicle, according to J.D. Power. That gap is typically closer to $5,000 or more, the firm’s data show.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“It just seems like we’re in fantasyland,” said New England auto dealer Abel Toll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/od/lpa/nsf50/vbush1945.htm&quot;&gt;Productivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our population increased from 75 million to 130 million between 1900 and 1940. In some countries comparable increases have been accompanied by famine. In this country the increase has been accompanied by more abundant food supply, better living, more leisure, longer life, and better health. This is, largely, the product of three factors - the free play of initiative of a vigorous people under democracy, the heritage of great national wealth, and the advance of science and its application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-07-20/stop-calling-professors-professor&quot;&gt;Titles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Why for instance should I be called “Professor Cowen,” but few people would address the person fixing their toilet as “Plumber Jones”?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;For a long time I have insisted that my graduate students call me “Tyler.” My goal has been to encourage them to think of themselves as peer researchers who might someday prove me wrong, rather than viewing me as an authority figure who is handing down truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/businessbarista/status/1421154233764691968?s=20&quot;&gt;Tokyo Olympic budgets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2013: bid projected $7.4 billion of costs&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;2019: official budget of $14.6 billion&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;2020: budget revised to $15.4 billion&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;2021: government auditors project total spending will be $28 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/buy-borrow-die-how-rich-americans-live-off-their-paper-wealth-11625909583&quot;&gt;Debt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Banks say their wealthy clients are borrowing more than ever before, often using loans backed by their portfolios of stocks and bonds. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/market-data/quotes/MS&quot;&gt;Morgan Stanley &lt;/a&gt;wealth-management clients have $68.1 billion worth of securities-based and other nonmortgage loans outstanding, more than double five years earlier. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/market-data/quotes/BAC&quot;&gt;Bank of America &lt;/a&gt;said it has $62.4 billion in securities-based loans, dwarfing its book of home-equity lines of credit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a good weekend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/96HPhxw1nlM&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 13:52:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/96HPhxw1nlM/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/what-were-reading-73121/</guid>
        
        <category>What We're Reading</category>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/what-were-reading-73121/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Highest Forms of Wealth</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Wealth is easy to measure but hard to value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When George Vanderbilt moved into Biltmore – the largest home in America at 178,000 square feet – one newspaper in 1899 wondered what the point was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goals of the country’s richest during the Gilded Age, it said, seemed to be “devoting themselves to pleasure regardless of expense.” But often they got the reverse: “Devotion to expense regardless of pleasure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George didn’t spend much time in the 250-room mansion which, by the time he died, had nearly bankrupted him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twenty years before Biltmore was constructed, the &lt;em&gt;New York Daily Tribune&lt;/em&gt; wrote that “The Vanderbilt money is certainly bringing no happiness to its present claimants.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That wasn’t closet jealousy. Armed with the world’s greatest fortune, the Vanderbilt family seemed &lt;a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3kwaQPj&quot;&gt;committed to proving the idea that money doesn’t buy happiness&lt;/a&gt;. They took it a step further, showing that when managed poorly money could in fact buy resentment, insecurity, and social anxiety. It could buy it in bulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/graphic-detail/2013/05/02/money-can-buy-happiness&quot;&gt;buys happiness&lt;/a&gt; in the same way drugs bring pleasure: Incredible if done right, dangerous if used to mask a weakness, and disastrous when no amount is enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest forms of wealth are measured differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few stick out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Controlling your time and the ability to wake up and say, “I can do whatever I want today.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five-year-old Franklin Roosevelt complained that his life was dictated by rules. So his mother gave him a day free of structure – he could do whatever he pleased. Sara Roosevelt wrote in her diary that day: “Quite of his own accord, he went contently back to his routine.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a difference between working hard because you want to and working hard because someone else told you you had to, and how to do it, and when to do it. Even if you’re doing the same work, the independence of doing it on your own terms changes everything in the same way that sleeping in a tent is fun when you’re camping but miserable when you’re homeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the highest form of wealth is controlling your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wealth can lead to time independence, but it’s never assured. It can be the opposite, as whatever created the wealth – whether a company or an inheritance – creates a claim on your time in equal proportion to its financial reward. A great number of CEOs fall into this category: They have an abundance of wealth and not a moment of free time or scheduling control even when it’s desired, which is its own form of poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charlie Munger summed it up: “I did not intend to get rich. I just wanted to get independent.” It’s a wonderful goal, and harder to measure than net worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. When money becomes like oxygen: so abundant relative to your needs that you don’t have to think about it despite it being a critical part of your life.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a scene in the documentary &lt;em&gt;The Queen of Versailles&lt;/em&gt; when the son of a man whose ability to make money was exceeded only by his desire to spend it, causing a family fortune to shrivel near the edge of bankruptcy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;On my wedding day my father gave a speech, and he looked at my wife and he said, “You will never have anything to worry about in your life.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But now we worry every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high form of wealth is avoiding that mess. And it isn’t necessarily tied to how much money you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep two things in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Desiring money beyond what you need to be happy is just an accounting hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How much money people need to be happy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/goalpost/&quot;&gt;is driven more by expectations&lt;/a&gt; than income.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thing I’ve noticed over the years is that some of the wealthiest people think about money all the time – which is obvious, because it’s causation. But it’s an important observation because most people, despite aspiring to become one of the wealthiest, actually want something different: the ability to not have to think about money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a different skill, but it’s powerful when you make it work. A person whose expectations relative to income are calibrated so they don’t even have to think about money has a higher form of wealth than someone with more money who’s constantly thinking about making the numbers work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. A career that allows for intellectual honesty.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This includes: Being able to say, “I don’t know” when you don’t know. Being able to speak critical truths about your industry without fear of retribution. The ability to make reasonable mistakes, and be open about them, without excessive worry. And not pretending to look busy to justify your salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are high-paying careers that allow all those things. But there are so many that don’t, and a lot of what people pass off as “hard work” and “grinding” is just finding ways to bury the truth. A job that lets you be open and honest pays a bonus that’s hard to measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/the-spectrum-of-financial-dependence-and-independence/&quot;&gt;The Spectrum of Financial Dependence and Independence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/gains/&quot;&gt;Wealth Is What You Don’t Spend&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/the-biggest-returns/&quot;&gt;The Biggest Returns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/KGi39gr1LsA&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2021 17:38:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/KGi39gr1LsA/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/the-highest-forms-of-wealth/</guid>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/the-highest-forms-of-wealth/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What We're Reading</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanityfair.com/news/2021/06/jeff-bezos-and-elon-musk-want-to-burn-their-cash-in-space&quot;&gt;$1 billion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Just think about it,” the luminary told me. “It’s nearly impossible to spend a billion dollars.” I laughed at the ridiculousness of this statement, but he went on, doing the math in front of me to make his point. “The most expensive Gulfstream jet in the world is $65 million; a couple of very fancy houses will cost you $20 million, $30 million total; many of the highest-end cars are only a few hundred thousand dollars each. You’ve done all that and you’ve still got around $900 million or so left to spend.” I responded, “Well, you could just give it away to people and organizations in need.” “Ahh, but you can’t,” the man said to me. “Are you just going to hand it to someone and hope they do the right thing with it? You have to build entire infrastructures to give the money away.” He went on to explain that you need to hire legions of people, often hundreds, including teams of lawyers and tax lawyers, finance experts, project managers, communications staffers, and so on, to manage the distribution of the money. “Just look at&lt;strong&gt;Warren Buffett.&lt;/strong&gt;Rather than figure out how to give his money away, he just gave it to the Gates Foundation to do it for him.” Then, the man explained, there is the “problem” that your billions will only grow, often quicker than you can give them away, with interest and rising investments. “Being a billionaire is a lot harder than it looks,” the man said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-07-09/real-estate-agents-eye-record-100-billion-as-home-sales-boom&quot;&gt;Fees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[Realtory] Commission revenue – the cut that brokers collect for helping buy and sell homes – is on track to surge 16% in 2021, surpassing $100 billion for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheStalwart/status/1414954284811227140?s=20&quot;&gt;Used cars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.collaborativefund.com/uploads/Screen%20Shot%202021-07-16%20at%209.09.27%20AM.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screen Shot 2021-07-16 at 9.09.27 AM.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.rwbaird.com/blogpost/1527/24-hours&quot;&gt;Time flies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They say the “days go slow but the years fly,” and as I sit here stewing in my worries, I can’t help but reflect on just how fast my life is going.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My 20s were a blur. I met my wife and we got married. As we entered our 30s, we knew we wanted to start a family. After that period of time, it seems like someone pushed fast forward.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If I could map my life from the moment my son was born to its end and compress it into one 24-hour period, it would probably look like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2021/07/15/science/jeff-bezos-oliver-daemen-space.html?smid=tw-nytimes&amp;amp;smtyp=cur&quot;&gt;Tuesday’s space flight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At 18, Mr. Daemen will be the youngest person ever to go to space. At 82, Ms. Funk, who goes by Wally, will be the oldest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a good weekend.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/1pWKcI8YRNo&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 12:06:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/1pWKcI8YRNo/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/what-were-reading-71621/</guid>
        
        <category>What We're Reading</category>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/what-were-reading-71621/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Too Smart</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“One of the most persistent fallacies is the reflexive association of wealth with wisdom,” Ed Borgato once &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/edborgato/status/793112820837601280&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wealth might be a sign of good decisions, but can those decisions be repeated? And do good decisions in one field translate to wisdom in other areas of life? Maybe, maybe not – that’s the best we can say. And there are times where exceptional wealth can prevent empathizing with ordinary people, making insight more precarious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar mistake, a bit harder to grasp, is the assumption that smart people have the right answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They may. But does intelligence in one field convert to others? Does being good at taking tests translate to, say, leading groups of people?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maybe&lt;/em&gt;. It’s never clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like wealth, there are situations where people become too smart for their own good, where intelligence is a liability and blocks good decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few causes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ability to create complex stories makes it easy to fool people, including yourself.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know people I would not want to debate with on the question, “What is 2 + 2?” because they could go down a rabbit hole that’s over my head and leave me either exhausted or convinced the answer may not be four.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dangerous thing is that those people can do the same things to themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Feynman said, “The first principle is that you must not fool yourself — and you are the easiest person to fool.” The smarter you are I think the truer that becomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re blessed with intelligence you’re cursed with the ability to use it to concoct intricate stories about why things happened – especially stories justifying why you made a mistake or why you’ll eventually be right in an area you’re wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big blowups in any field aren’t typically caused by a lack of smarts. The catastrophes are typically caused by extreme intelligence that causes people to believe their own dangerous stories – that you can predict with accuracy, use leverage because your prediction must be true, and ignore warning signs that would have been obvious to a normal person who’s less adept at mental gymnastics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s boring is often important and the smartest people are the least interested in what’s boring.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ninety percent of personal finance is just spend less than you make, diversify, and be patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you’re very intelligent that bores you to tears and feels like a waste of your potential. You want to spend your time on the 10% that’s mentally stimulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which isn’t necessarily bad. But if your focus on the exciting part of finance comes at the expense of attention to the 90% of the field that’s boring, it’s disastrous. Hedge funds blow up and Wall Street executives &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/the-psychology-of-money/&quot;&gt;go bankrupt&lt;/a&gt; doing things a less intelligent person would never consider. A similar thing happens in medicine, a field that attracts brilliant people who &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/investing-the-greatest-show-on-earth/&quot;&gt;may be more interested&lt;/a&gt; in exciting disease treatments than boring disease prevention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a sweet spot where you grasp the important stuff but you’re not smart enough to be bored with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intelligence can make it difficult to communicate with ordinary people, who may have the missing insight you’re looking for&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many academics have discovered something amazing, but wrote it in a paper so dense and complex that no one else can understand it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And how many ordinary people would be able to bring an academic’s discovery into the real world if they could understand what was written in those papers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has to be so many.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer scientist Edsger Dijkstra &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/EWD/transcriptions/EWD08xx/EWD898.html&quot;&gt;once wrote&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[Complexity has] a morbid attraction. When you give an academic audience a lecture that is crystal clear from alpha to omega, your audience feels cheated and leaves the lecture hall commenting to each other: “That was rather trivial, wasn’t it?” The sore truth is that complexity sells better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When complexity is the preferred language of very smart people, great ideas can become walled off from ordinary people. Most of the allure of the information age is that ideas can be shared among huge groups of people. But among the superintelligent, that’s often not the case – they’re speaking a different language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally someone like Richard Feynman comes along, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/story/&quot;&gt;whose storytelling skills&lt;/a&gt; equal his genius. But it’s rare. Communication and intelligence are not just separate skills; they can repel each other, and the smarter you become the more complex your communication and the smaller the audience you may be able to persuade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key, like so many things, is respecting balance and diverse views.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/collabfund/~4/mrBe28ukAZM&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;/&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jul 2021 16:21:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/collabfund/~3/mrBe28ukAZM/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/too-smart/</guid>
        
        
      <feedburner:origLink>http://www.collaborativefund.com/blog/too-smart/</feedburner:origLink></item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
