<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet  type="text/xsl" media="screen" href="/~files/feed-premium.xsl"?>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                             
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:feedpress="https://feed.press/xmlns" xmlns:podcast="https://podcastindex.org/namespace/1.0" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <feedpress:locale>en</feedpress:locale>
    <atom:link rel="self" href="http://feeds.dzone.com/home"/>
    <atom:link rel="hub" href="http://feedpress.superfeedr.com/"/>
    <title>DZone.com Feed</title>
    <link>http://dzone.com</link>
    <description>Recent posts on DZone.com</description>
    <item>
      <title>What Is CORS?</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/what-is-cors</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Cross-Origin Resource Sharing (CORS) is a mechanism that supports secure requests and data transfers from outside origins (domain, scheme, or port).</p>
<p>For example, <code>example.com</code> uses a text font that's hosted on <code>fonts.com</code>. When visiting, the user's browser will make a request for the font from <code>fonts.com</code>. Because <code>fonts.com</code> and <code>example.com</code> are two different origins, this is a cross-origin request. If <code>fonts.com</code> allows cross-origin resource sharing to <code>example.com</code>, then the browser will proceed with loading the font. Otherwise, the browser will cancel the request.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 12:21:58 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3285091</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16395657&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Advait Ruia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deploy IBM App Connect Enterprise Apps From CI/CD</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/deploying-ibm-app-connect-enterprise-applications</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>This post is about a repository I've shared on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/dalelane/app-connect-tekton-pipeline" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">dalelane/app-connect-tekton-pipeline</a>. It contains an example of how to use <a href="https://tekton.dev" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Tekton</a> to create a CI/CD pipeline that builds and deploys an <a href="https://www.ibm.com/docs/en/app-connect/containers_cd" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">App Connect Enterprise</a> application to <a href="https://www.ibm.com/cloud/openshift" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Red Hat OpenShift</a>.</p>
<p>The pipeline uses the <a href="https://www.ibm.com/docs/en/app-connect/containers_cd?topic=operator-from-openshift-web-console" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">IBM App Connect Operator</a> to easily build, deploy and manage your applications in containers. The pipeline runs on OpenShift to allow it to easily be integrated into an automated <a href="https://www.ibm.com/garage/method/practices/deliver/practice_continuous_delivery/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">continuous delivery workflow</a> without needing to build anything locally from a developer's workstation.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 22:15:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3285559</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn4.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16393826&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Dale Lane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ending the DevOps vs. Software Engineer Cold War</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/ending-the-devops-vs-software-engineer-cold-war</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p dir="ltr">If we were that metaphorical fly on the wall, following an all too common Slack conversation between a software engineer and DevOps engineers, it might go something like this:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Software Engineer:</strong> <em>This is gonna take forever.</em> “I need a new environment for my app.”</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 22:02:11 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3285682</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16393803&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Amit Eyal Govrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Daily 10 Tech Q&amp;amp;A With Bala</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/daily-10-tech-qampa-with-bala</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<article> 
 <p data-selectable-paragraph="">With the growing number of cyber security threats, it is essential for everyone to know, mitigate, monitor, and prevent attacks on your apps. I have started this technology series as a small contribution to sharing the knowledge of whatever I have gone through so far. I hope my efforts will be useful to many software engineering aspirants and professionals who wish to use this information in their day-to-day work.</p> 
 <h2><strong>1. What Are the Important Aspects to Consider in Order to Secure Your Applications?</strong></h2> 
 <section> 
  <br> 
  <ul> 
   <li data-selectable-paragraph=""><a href="https://dzone.com/articles/authentication-cluster">Authentication and authorization</a> ( if your authentication part is compromised, hackers can easily penetrate into a user app and do whatever they want, so it is important to safeguard your authentication mechanism to the app, API, or system.</li> 
   <li data-selectable-paragraph="">Logging:<a href="https://dzone.com/articles/application-logging-what-when"> Application logs</a> are essential and, more importantly, without which you won’t be able to identify any security incident; application-specific data is used for investigation. You should follow the best practices as much as you can to log the data.</li> 
   <li data-selectable-paragraph=""><a href="https://dzone.com/articles/what-is-encryption-and-how-does-it-work">Encryption </a>on data: There are multiple encryption algorithms that I will cover at the end of the video today; it is safe when you encrypt the data while transmitting from sender to receiver. Decryption is done at the receiver level to get the actual data.</li> 
  </ul> 
  <h2 data-selectable-paragraph=""><strong>2. Why Should You Use WAF Along With a Firewall?</strong></h2> 
  <p data-selectable-paragraph="">Firewalls are the first level of protection that permits or blocks network traffic based on IP addresses and port numbers. It can allow traffic to default ports http80 and https443.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 18:35:49 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3285173</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn4.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16391283&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Balaji Kesavan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PromCon EU 2022: All Things in the Prometheus Community</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/promcon-eu-2022-all-things-in-the-prometheus-commu</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<div> 
 <p>For two days last week, I was on-site at the <a href="https://promcon.io/2022-munich/schedule/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">PromCon EU 2022</a> event in Munich, Germany. This is a very well-organized community event focused on all things in the open-source Prometheus project, including, for example, PromQL and PromLens.</p> 
 <p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEj4_Xoac-OzJ-jDj_J3TboAC_R52LKfhFc8T5DFtpEYNLST4-EuAircIrcSnJcjl0RzS74V8aLMF39LhCcigwKifQSeDcXZGSSI0dNEXNhYGwk6QERwHI2IhX8Uj8MXfEqx94eiARh_m9lqHQXcRwO-LD2Uax4pn5gZrOw5yHc6EQHON-Un9PBW0bd8/s790/Screen%20Shot%202022-11-06%20at%2021.15.43.png"><img class="fr-fic fr-dib lazyload" data-image="true" data-new="false" data-sizeformatted="65.9 kB" data-mimetype="image/png" data-creationdate="1668619585431" data-creationdateformatted="11/16/2022 05:26 PM" data-type="temp" data-url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/storage/temp/16392098-1668619586296.png" data-modificationdate="null" data-size="65881" data-name="1668619586296.png" data-id="16392098" style="width: 415px;" data-src="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/storage/temp/16392098-1668619586296.png" alt="PromCon EU 2022"></a>This article will be a bit of an overview, rather than a review of each specific talk, covering what I saw and found interesting between the common discussions and chatting that happens between talks in the hallways. Often these overlapping session starting times prohibit one from seeing everything at a conference.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 18:19:19 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3286169</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16392130&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Eric D. Schabell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Use the NestJS Framework?</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/why-use-the-nestjs-framework</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>As a front-end developer, I would like to say that the <a href="https://docs.nestjs.com/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">NestJs</a> framework was the best choice to start touching the backend part of the applications. I always asked my tutor about design patterns, clean architecture, and microservices. He then showed me the link to the NestJs’s fully completed and very well-structured documentation. It was a good discovery for me to get lost on this page and learn about decorators, providers, dependency injection, testing, authentication, and more topics from different areas.</p>
<h2><strong>What Is NestJs?</strong></h2>
<p>First of all, what is this NestJs? It is an <strong>open-source</strong> Node.js framework for developing challenging backend systems that use the design paradigm <strong>convention over configuration</strong> that eliminates the need for explicit configuration by allowing developers to utilize common tools and code in a particular way.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 15:39:05 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3286159</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn3.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16392957&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Beste Bayhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modular Data Centers Are Better for the Environment</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/modular-data-centers-are-better-for-the-environmen</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://dzone.com/articles/what-emerging-technologies-make-data-centers-more">Data centers </a>are the secret behind robust, successful networks — and they use a lot of energy. With every day leading humans to a more developed and connected world, these data centers are becoming focal points of the sustainability conversation for the tech sector. One of the top solutions experts present is modular data centers. These centers seek to optimize operations and energy <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/iot-and-the-environment-a-greener-world">efficiency for a greener future</a>, but is the effort to make the shift worth it?</p>
<h2 dir="ltr">How Different Are Modular Data Centers?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Data centers are responsible for <a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/data-centres-and-data-transmission-networks">1% of the world’s electricity</a> demand. Though this doesn’t seem like a large number, it will only increase as technological needs increase. That translates to around 200 TWh of electricity, most of which runs on fossil fuels and isn’t optimized for current internet activity.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 15:25:49 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3284694</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16385962&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Emily Newton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What Is Roles-Based Access Control (RBAC)?</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/what-is-roles-based-access-control-rbac</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Role-based access control (RBAC) is a security approach that uses roles to define what a user is and isn’t allowed to do. In an RBAC system, users are assigned roles with varying permissions for different resources, including files, databases, and applications.</p>
<p>So, when a user tries to access a resource, the system will first find the roles associated with the user and then check if any of the roles have the appropriate permission. If so, the user is allowed to access the resource. If not, the user is denied access.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 14:49:08 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283117</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn3.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16392951&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Advait Ruia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Native Dependency Injection in Swift</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/native-dependency-injection-in-swift</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In this article, we are going to go through a couple of solutions to a common problem when developing mobile applications, and this is Dependency Injection.</p>
<p>We all saw a project that was calling singleton classes from any part of the code without any security when writing data to them, battling with race conditions, and coupling implementations to all these issues. You can also find many third-party libraries that can help to solve or at least manage these problems, but many times we don’t want or we can’t add extra dependencies; in this case, a good approach is to implement the solution that fits your needs in a basic but sufficient way and with native code.<br>To start with this, we will go through the problem first and see what would actually help us. Let’s say we have a class called AViewModel that needs to use ServiceA; the first thing to think of is to instantiate the service in the initializer or directly inside the class like this:</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 11:58:56 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283516</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn2.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16376161&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Felipe Ferrari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model Drift in Computer Vision Models: Understanding the Problem</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/model-drift-in-computer-vision-models-understandin</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<h2 dir="ltr">What Is a Computer Vision Model?</h2>
<p dir="ltr">Computer vision (CV) is a field within artificial intelligence and machine learning (ML) that involves computer programs interpreting the meaning of image and video inputs. A computer vision algorithm can analyze specific criteria in visual data and use its interpretations to implement predictive and decision-making tasks.</p>
<p>Modern computer vision models are highly sophisticated and cover many use cases to automate critical decision-making systems and enhance business efficiency. As a type of machine learning algorithm, computer vision models are challenging to deploy.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 11:17:03 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283644</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn4.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16383991&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Gilad David Maayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spring Boot for Cloud: Actuator</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/spring-boot-for-cloud-actuator</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>In previous articles, we talked about some features of Spring Boot that are very useful in the development phase of our system: we described simplified <a href="https://codingstrain.com/spring-boot-for-cloud-configuration-dependencies/" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="dependency management">dependency management</a> and <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/spring-boot-for-cloud-configuration-and-dependenci">API development</a>, for instance. In this article, we are going to cover functionalities that are related to a production environment.</p>
<p>When a <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/introducing-spring-boot">Spring Boot</a> application is finally in production, it needs all the tools to manage and monitor it. This is especially important in complex scenarios like those related to microservice systems. Spring Boot provides an effective solution to provide the required functionalities, the <em>Actuator</em>. The <em>Actuator</em> is a Spring Boot module with a set of features available as HTTP or <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/deep-dive-into-java-management-extensions-jmx">JMX&nbsp;</a>endpoints, or even with a remote SSH shell.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 01:47:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3284650</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16390075&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Mario Casari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spring Boot for Cloud: REST API Development</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/spring-boot-for-cloud-rest-api-development</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>There are two main ways by which microservice applications can interact with each other: REST services and messaging systems. The REST approach is the most common and will be treated in this article. We will see how Spring boot can make the development process of REST APIs fairly easy, with the use of a set of useful annotations and some implicit background behavior, like the serialization of<em>&nbsp;model&nbsp;</em>objects to JSON format.</p>
<p>Another important issue is related to the documentation and sharing of APIs, and we will see that these concerns are addressed effectively with a solution named <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/spring-boot-restful-api-documentation-with-swagger">Swagger</a>. Integrating Swagger with <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/introducing-spring-boot">Spring Boot</a> allows us to generate the documentation from the source code, as a Swagger JSON file, and even browse and manage all the exposed REST services with a web user interface.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 01:26:58 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3284649</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16390063&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Mario Casari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spring Boot for Cloud: Configuration and Dependencies</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/spring-boot-for-cloud-configuration-and-dependenci</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>The natural choice to implement a micro-service application in the realm of the <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/spring-basics">Spring framework</a> would be to use the <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/microservics-architecture-introduction-to-spring-c">Spring Cloud</a> set of modules. But those modules cannot work without a solid platform underneath. Spring Boot sits on top of the <em>Spring&nbsp;</em>framework and is an effective base for <em>Spring Cloud</em> libraries (from this consideration the title of this article "Spring Boot for Cloud" makes some sense). &nbsp;</p>
<p>Spring Boot has some features that can be of great help in reducing the complexity of micro-service architectures:</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 01:14:13 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3284648</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn4.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16383063&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Mario Casari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NoSQL Migration Essentials</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/refcardz/nosql-migration-essentials</link>
      <description><![CDATA[Need help with your NoSQL migration? Look no further than our "NoSQL Migration Essentials" Refcard. We walk through the primary steps for moving out of a relational database, plus important design principles to understand and consider in your migration process.<br><br>
Readers will review key concepts that range from denormalizing and modeling data to defining access patterns, designing primary keys and indexes, and creating an entity relationship diagram — all demonstrated with a simple site application example. As a bonus, readers can use the included JSON structure at the end to interact with a NoSQL playground.]]></description>
      <category>nosql</category>
      <category>data modeling</category>
      <category>database migration</category>
      <category>database architecture</category>
      <category>nosql database</category>
      <category>data access patterns</category>
      <category>denormalized data</category>
      <category>entity relationship</category>
      <category>normalized data</category>
      <category>data denormalization</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 19:18:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/refcardz/3146424</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=15012750&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Melissa Habit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integration Tests With Arquillian Extensions on the Payara Platform</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/integration-tests-with-arquillian-extensions-on-the-payara-platform</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Arquillian is one of the most classical integration test frameworks for <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/jvm-architecture-explained">JVM (Java Virtual Machine)</a>-based applications, currently maintained by Red Hat. Its main particularity consists in the fact that, in order to facilitate integration testing through the <code>maven</code> lifecycle, it allows the deployment of the tested applications on an embedded, managed, or remote <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/getting-started-with-jakarta-ee-9-hello-world">Jakarta EE</a>-compliant container, like Payara.</p>
<h2>From Manual To Automated Integration Testing</h2>
<p>Historically speaking, the <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/integration-testing-what-it-is-and-how-to-do-it-ri">integration testing process</a> used to be a highly manual activity, consisting of deploying the application on the application server before running the test cases. This is especially due to the utilization of building tools like <code>maven</code> which default lifecycle provisions the integration test phase, named <code>verify</code>, just before <code>install</code> and <code>deploy</code>. This means that in-container integration tests cannot be performed in an out-of-the-box manner with such tools, because they are run before the deployment phase, despite the fact that, in order to be run, they require applications to be deployed. So, we find ourselves in a kind of circular problem here: in order to test the application we need to deploy it first, and, in order to deploy it, we need to test it first. This is why integration tests were traditionally performed manually.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 19:05:26 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3285622</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn2.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16387058&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Duminil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The SQL Review Tool for Developers</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/the-sql-review-tool-for-developers</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p data-v-14b060bf="">Treat SQL as code ("<a data-v-14b060bf="" href="https://blog.devgenius.io/why-google-treats-sql-like-code-and-you-should-too-53f97925037e" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Why</a>?" you may ask), which means all the reasons why we review other codes need to apply to SQL scripts. They interact straight with databases, and databases are too important. No matter how database vendors promise their products are stable and robust, databases are still pretty fragile. Even if we disregard the accidental "DROP TABLE" fiasco, ordinary queries like "SELECT FROM" can also overwhelm a database and bring it down. Let’s face it: databases are delicate, yet very few users understand how to treat them properly — &nbsp;meaning we should discipline the users’ behavior to some degree.</p>
<p data-v-14b060bf="">Here’s where SQL review comes in. It is the practice of reviewing DDL and DML statements before applying them to the database. It is one of the most critical aspects of database schema management. In the past, DBAs were in charge of the database. They know the database best and, thus, should be the ones reviewing the SQL. This is reasonable, but there is a contradiction: developers (database users) cannot understand the many restrictions and want the most freedom. At the same time, DBAs insist that stability triumphs over everything.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 18:17:20 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283012</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16387026&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Cayden Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Easy and Effective Tips for Learning a New Programming Language</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/7-easy-yet-effective-tips-for-learning-a-new-progr</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p dir="ltr">One of the important skills that can boost your career is — &nbsp;coding.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Whether you are looking forward to getting a good position in the tech space or just want to create an app for fun, becoming a pro in coding will be the greatest asset to your professional and personal development.&nbsp;</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 17:54:18 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3285670</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn2.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16386738&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Hiren Dhaduk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Missing Link in Cybersecurity: Culture</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/the-missing-link-in-cybersecurity-culture</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p dir="ltr">Cybersecurity culture is vital to strengthening a business’s first line of defense: Employee security practices. Most<a href="https://dzone.com/articles/how-to-stop-external-cyber-attacks-amp-lateral-mov"> cyberattacks</a> on businesses today target employees first. By building a supportive workplace culture that motivates employees to improve their security awareness, businesses can reduce their <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/security-concerns-part-2">cyber risks</a>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">How can business leaders go about creating a cybersecurity culture on their teams? A few core principles offer a good place to start.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 17:41:36 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3285680</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn4.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16386912&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Zac Amos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Big Data and Cloud in Vertical Farming-Based IoT Solutions</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/big-data-amp-cloud-in-vertical-farming-based-iot-s</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: justify;">Vertical farming-based IoT solutions are one of the key emerging trends in the agriculture industry today. These solutions are not only providing accurate information on plant growth statistics but also making operations more sustainable. With these solutions, farmers can track energy usage and soil composition, verify air quality, temperature and moisture levels, etc. and<a href="https://dzone.com/articles/robotic-farmers-automate-plant-management">&nbsp;perform operations</a> in a more efficient manner.</p>
<p style="text-align: justify;">In addition to processing data at rest, the real-time processing of sensor data i.e., the ability to process data collected by various sensors as it arrives, would form the major building blocks of these kinds of solutions. However, traditional data processing systems fall behind in handling real-time data, unstructured data, and scaling on demand. This is the reason why the usage of big data on the cloud in IoT-based solutions is on the rise, as it would require querying continuous data streams and detecting conditions quickly within a small interval from the time of receiving it. While big data supports data storage and structured as well as <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/structured-vs-unstructured-data-getting-to-know-th">unstructured data processing</a>, whereas cloud services are used for cost-effective scalable infrastructure.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 16:37:05 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283643</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn2.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16386937&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Phani Krishna Kollapur Gandla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Ways To Separate Plain Text From HTML Using Java</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/three-ways-to-separate-plain-text-from-html-using</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>On each webpage we visit, we are confronted with a huge variety of multimedia content, all of which is put together and presented using <a href="https://dzone.com/refcardz/core-html">Hyper Text Markup Language (HTML)</a>. &nbsp;HTML is a basic programming language that many developers are familiar with, composed of elements that – when interpreted by a browser – typically form a coherent, organized, and intentional display with various customized elements. &nbsp;This code provides the framework for how we view images, videos, bodies of writing, hyperlinks, data entry fields, and anything else you can think of on a web page – and all that code is available for anyone to view with a simple right-click on any browser.</p>
<p>Given the immense volume of formatting elements present in any complex HTML string, the actual subject of the code - the text contents and file paths buried within those strings - can be a bit difficult to access independently of those formatting specifications. If, for example, we want to review web copy and subsequently edit or manipulate that text in a meaningful way, we’re going to have a difficult time copying and pasting that information from the displayed web page directly. We’ll just end up with a mess of inconsistently formatted text riddled with hyperlinks, logos, disjointed tabs and spaces, and more. &nbsp;This isn’t to say that it can’t be done. We can, of course, copy small snippets of text from any web page and reformat those snippets to resemble their original form in rich text editors like Microsoft Word. &nbsp;The issue is that this “point and click” approach chews up valuable time in our workday, and if we need to scale up our operation to include multiple websites and thousands of characters worth of text, we’ll be doing ourselves a big disservice in the long run by attempting to do so manually.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 16:15:41 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3284691</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn2.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16388832&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Brian O'Neill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Build Your Exchange Server Recovery Strategy to Overcome Ransomware Attacks</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/how-to-build-your-exchange-server-recovery-strateg</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Ransomware attacks on on-premises Exchange Servers are quite common as they store sensitive and confidential information and business data. The attackers often exploit vulnerabilities to gain access to the organization's network and steal or encrypt data for ransom. &nbsp;</p>
<p>Even if attackers do not succeed in encrypting the data, they may leave a backdoor or cause other damage that can leave your server unusable or cause permanent <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/dlp-what-is-it-and-why-you-need-it">data loss</a>. That's why it's important to have a <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/choosing-the-right-dr-strategy">disaster recovery plan</a> or recovery strategy ready to deal with such critical situations.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 12:44:48 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3284670</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16388665&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Shelly Bhardwaj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I Used Render To Scale My Microservices App With Ease</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/how-i-used-render-to-scale-my-microservices-app-wi</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p dir="ltr">As a software lead and feature developer, I witnessed a team learn an important lesson about resource scaling and the cloud. Spoiler alert: the lesson was that if you’re not careful, scaling can get expensive!</p>
<p>The team felt they had no choice but to keep increasing the number of instances for a given service that was under heavy load. When they finished scaling up, the number of instances was several times larger than the number of instances that were configured by default. What they didn’t realize at the time was that—despite the load returning back to a normal state—their extra instances remained in place.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 10:51:29 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283650</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16384200&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>John Vester</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scrum Tools and Practices to Enhance an Incomplete Framework</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/scrum-tools-and-practices-to-enhance-an-incomplete</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<h3>TL; DR: Scrum Tools, Part 1</h3>
<p>“The Scrum framework is purposefully incomplete, […].” (<a href="https://scrumguides.org/scrum-guide.html#scrum-definition" rel="noopener" target="_blank" title="Scrum Guide 2020 —&nbsp;Scrum Tools —&nbsp;Age-of-Product.com">Source</a>.) This half-sentence is probably one of the more often misinterpreted statements of the Scrum Guide. On the one side, it defines the necessity to enhance Scrum with other practices and tools. On the other side, it is the reason that so many attempts to practice Scrum are simply botched, resulting in ScrumBut versions of epic diversity. So, let’s look at proven Scrum tools and practices enhancing a purposefully incomplete framework without defying or negating its first principles.</p>
<p>Please note that the following Scrum tools and practices list is not complete. Please feel free to add more suggestions by commenting.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 04:09:54 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283633</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn3.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16385224&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Wolpers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GitOps Using Flux and Flagger</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/gitops-using-flux-and-flagger</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>GitOps as a practice has been in use since 2017 when Alexis Richardson coined the term. It transformed DevOps and automation. If you look at its core principles, it extends DevOps by treating Infrastructure as Code (IaC). Your deployment configuration is stored in a version control system (a.ka. Git), providing a single source of truth for both dev and ops.</p>
<p>As the framework’s adoption increased, <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/what-is-gitops-1" rel="nofollow" target="_blank">GitOps became the standard for continuous deployment</a> in the cloud native space. Many agile teams <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/3-steps-to-developing-a-successful-gitops-model">adopt GitOps</a> because of familiarity with git-based workflow for the release management of cloud-native workloads.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 03:29:55 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3275287</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn4.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16385182&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Sudhanshu Prajapati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top 7 Less Known Angular Features Every Developer Should Know</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/top-7-less-known-angular-features-for-developers</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Every developer knows that Angular is a powerful framework. However, there are some less-known features of Angular that every developer should know.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Angular is a JavaScript framework that is used for building web applications. It is one of the most popular frameworks and is used by many big companies. Angular has many features that make it a great choice for web development.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 20:13:07 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3284340</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn2.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16367817&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Akash Chauhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Top 10 MLOps Platforms to Manage and Optimize Machine Learning Lifecycle</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/top-10-mlops-platforms-to-manage-amp-optimize-mach</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Businesses continue transforming their operations to increase productivity and deliver memorable consumer experiences. This digital transition accelerates timeframes for interactions, transactions, and decisions. Additionally, it generates reams of data with brand-new insights into operations, clients, and competition. Machine learning helps companies in harnessing this data to gain a competitive advantage. ML (Machine Learning) models can detect patterns in massive amounts of data, allowing them to make faster, more accurate decisions on a larger scale than humans could. This enables humans and applications to take quick and intelligent action.</p>
<p>As more businesses experiment with data, they realize that developing a machine learning (ML) model is only one of many steps in the ML lifecycle.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 19:36:14 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3285491</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn3.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16385835&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Saikiran Bellamkonda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Run Your Executables in Azure Data Factory</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/run-your-executables-in-azure-data-factory</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p data-selectable-paragraph="">When migrating SQL Server from on-premises to the cloud, there is always an ask about how to migrate SSIS packages or other ETL jobs to the cloud. Azure Data Factory SSIS Integration Runtime (IR) offers to run SSIS packages in the cloud.</p>
<p data-selectable-paragraph="">However, in certain circumstances, those ETL jobs or SSIS packages run executables such as .EXE as a part of a workflow or ETL pipelines. It becomes more challenging if you are migrating SQL Server running on-premises to PaaS as there is no access to PaaS compute to run those executables.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 19:21:44 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3284299</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn3.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16385833&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Afzal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>API Authentication Using Azure AD in IBM API Connect</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/api-authentication-using-azure-ad-in-ibm-api-conne-2</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://dzone.com/articles/api-authentication-methods-an-overview"><span data-preserver-spaces="true">API authentication</span></a><span data-preserver-spaces="true">&nbsp;is necessary to secure API access from any unauthorized user. There are several ways to secure APIs.&nbsp;</span><a href="https://dzone.com/refcardz/oauth-patterns-and-anti-patterns"><span data-preserver-spaces="true">OAuth</span></a><span data-preserver-spaces="true">&nbsp;token validation is used to authenticate the user. One of the methods is to use Azure AD as an OAuth provider to secure an API invocation. The Azure AD provides an authentication token when the user sends a request to the login URL<span data-preserver-spaces="true">&nbsp;with a valid <code>client_id</code> and <code>client_secret</code> to the microsoftonline.com login.&nbsp;</span></span></p>
<h2 style="text-align: left;"><span data-preserver-spaces="true"><span data-preserver-spaces="true">Architecture</span></span></h2>
<p style="text-align: left;">The below sequence diagram shows the design of the OAuth authentication process when Azure AD is used as an OAuth provider to <a href="https://dzone.com/articles/four-most-used-rest-api-authentication-methods">authenticate REST API access</a> implemented in IBM API Connect. <span data-preserver-spaces="true"><img data-fr-image-pasted="true" alt="Azure AD authorization sequence diagram in IBM API Connect" class="fr-fic fr-dib lazyload" data-src="https://dz2cdn4.dzone.com/storage/temp/16361127-figure0.png" data-url="https://dz2cdn4.dzone.com/storage/temp/16361127-figure0.png"></span></p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 19:03:12 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283214</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn3.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16385828&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Abhinav Priyadarshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DDoS Attacks: A Threat to Corporate IT Security</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/ddos-attacks-a-threat-to-corporate-it-security</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<p>Next to ransomware, which has been at the heart of cybersecurity concerns in recent years, distributed denial of service (DDoS) attacks are an equally crucial cyber threat for companies. The figures speak for themselves: 5.4 million DDoS attacks were recorded worldwide in the first half of 2022.</p>
<p>They generally aim to make a data center inaccessible. The company's website and applications are suddenly blocked until the attack stops. These attacks should not be taken lightly, and it is crucial to guard against them to protect business activity.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 17:44:48 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283580</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn2.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16380660&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Usama Amin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Establishing Kubernetes Governance Strategy</title>
      <link>http://dzone.com/articles/establishing-kubernetes-governance-strategy</link>
      <description><![CDATA[<blockquote> 
 <p><strong>Decisions in a Cloud ecosystem are decentralized and fast-paced.</strong></p> 
</blockquote>
<p>Governance is all about bringing consistency and repeatability, ensuring quality never gets deprioritized. Mapping out a Kubernetes governance model helps in keeping the entire organization on track. Furthermore, policies proposed in the Kubernetes governance model are not meant to be limited to security baselines of resources and deployments.</p>]]></description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 17:31:40 GMT</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">http://dzone.com/articles/3283589</guid>
      <media:thumbnail url="https://dz2cdn1.dzone.com/thumbnail?fid=16380825&amp;w=600"/>
      <dc:creator>Komal J Prabhakar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
