<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rebased Blog</title>
    <description>Rebased Team writing about tech we use. Languages, frameworks, libraries, tools. Certified for 0% fluff.
</description>
    <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.rebased.pl/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 12:26:36 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 12:26:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rebased 💚 Shopify</title>
        <description>
          
            We’re excited to announce that the Rebased team has joined Shopify! We founded Rebased to bring our Ruby and JavaScript programming experience to support companies all over the world. And, today, we are proud to be able to bring our expertise to one of the leading technology companies in the...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/09/13/rebased-x-shopify.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/09/13/rebased-x-shopify.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Using SQLite on the bus</title>
        <description>
          
            Recently a friend asked me to find out a certain piece of data. Which bus route in Poznań is the longest? As I’m a massive ferroequinologist and public transport enthusiast, this question is right up my alley. However, this information is rarely accessible directly. Public transport planning is a complex...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/05/11/sqlite-on-a-bus.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/05/11/sqlite-on-a-bus.html</guid>
        
        <category>sql</category>
        
        <category>sqlite</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Turning on the lights without HTTP</title>
        <description>
          
            Turning on the lights used to require a walk to the wall switch; nowadays, various smart devices exist to relieve you of that inconvenience. In this post I make such a device, but avoid putting a HTTP server on it. Read on to see how and why. So this is...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/04/20/light-fixture-bluetooth.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/04/20/light-fixture-bluetooth.html</guid>
        
        <category>esp32</category>
        
        <category>embedded</category>
        
        <category>infrared</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ELI5: Bitfields</title>
        <description>
          
            What is this bitfield thing? An array of true/false values. Usually a fixed-size array, due to platform constraints. Also a very compact array – taking exactly one bit to store each element. In other words: a boolean vector or set. So does anyone use it? Plenty of usage around, many...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/04/06/eli5-bitfields.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/04/06/eli5-bitfields.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>When a decorator meets a descriptor</title>
        <description>
          
            The best thing about this job is moments like these. When the problem at hand allows you to delve even further into the recesses of the language you are currently using. Decorator According to the official documentation, the definition of a decorator is: A function returning another function, usually applied...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/30/when-a-decorator-meets-a-descriptor.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/30/when-a-decorator-meets-a-descriptor.html</guid>
        
        <category>python</category>
        
        <category>descriptor</category>
        
        <category>decorator</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SSH Keygen: a 2021 update</title>
        <description>
          
            Not long after the previous article on ssh-keygen, OpenSSH released a whole new version of SSH and related tools. This version came with many changes, the most notable one being the support of FIDO/U2F keys. In this post we summarize these changes, and try to explain some of the inner...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/23/ssh-keygen-2021.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/23/ssh-keygen-2021.html</guid>
        
        <category>ssh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A regular expression surprise in JavaScript</title>
        <description>
          
            One of the most known and agreed upon principles in software development is DRY - don’t repeat yourself. In this short post I’ll show you how applying DRY to regular expressions in JavaScript can be tricky. The examples will be written for Node.js, but the idea applies to other environments...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/16/a-regular-expression-surprise-in-javascript.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/16/a-regular-expression-surprise-in-javascript.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A valid method signature?</title>
        <description>
          
            Sometimes, even veterans can be stumped by their language of choice. And not even by the newest, latest additions, but the core language itself. This is such a story, about an obscure corner of Python. It starts with a legacy1 project Legacy as in ‘still not fully migrated from Python...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/09/a-valid-signature.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/09/a-valid-signature.html</guid>
        
        <category>python</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Redis rate limiter – part 2</title>
        <description>
          
            Welcome to part 2, where we’ll take a look at how to test the rate limiter. First of all we have to make a couple changes to the class we’ve created in part 1. The first change is to make the interval and timeout instance variables configurable during initialization. This...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/02/redis-rate-limiter-testing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/03/02/redis-rate-limiter-testing.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Redis rate limiter</title>
        <description>
          
            At Rebased we have an internal time tracking project called Harmonogram. Its backend is built in Ruby on Rails. It started as a playground for new hires to get used to company culture and conventions, but over time grew into a fully-functional tool. When I joined, the application was already...
          
        </description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/02/22/redis-rate-limiter.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.rebased.pl/2021/02/22/redis-rate-limiter.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
